This month I’d like to talk
about “Presenting Your Gifts to God.”
We certainly have every reason
to consider this topic.
Well, why is that?
It’s because Jehovah gives us so much.
James 1:17 says:
“Every good gift and every perfect present
“is from above,
coming down from the Father
of the celestial lights.”
For example, Jehovah allows us
to enjoy the gift of life,
even though our first parents
tried to take that from us.
He’s provided us with a variety of foods.
The environment
is just right to support life.
He’s given us his precious Word, the Bible,
so that we can come to know him
and his purposes.
And the greatest “perfect present”
Jehovah has given us
is the ransom.
Jehovah sacrificed a great deal
to arrange for Jesus to buy back for us
the hope of everlasting life.
This was at no obligation on Jehovah’s part.
It was totally a gift of love.
Please read with me 1 John 4:9:
“By this the love of God
was revealed in our case,
“that God sent his only-begotten Son
into the world
so that we might gain life through him.”
What a gift of love from Jehovah, our God!
What does that move us to do?
Maybe you’ve had the experience
of a close friend or family member
unexpectedly giving you a valuable gift.
Immediately, what are you thinking?
You are probably trying to think
of what you can give in return.
How much more so would we want
to ‘present our gifts to God’
so as to show our sincere appreciation
for all he’s done!
Let’s consider some possible gifts
that Jehovah would be pleased
to receive from us.
Many of you in our viewing audience
have been moved to give your life to Jehovah,
dedicating yourself to do his will.
That’s commendable!
That’s what Romans 12 urges us to do.
However, there are some of you listening
who have thought about this way
of giving back to Jehovah,
but you haven’t yet taken this vital step.
Notice the appeal the apostle Paul makes
at Romans 12:1:
“Therefore, I appeal to you
by the compassions of God, brothers,
“to present your bodies
as a living sacrifice,
“holy and acceptable to God,
a sacred service with your power of reason.”
Your life is precious.
Presenting your body, your whole soul, to God
is one of the best gifts you can give to him.