She thought that she could win,
but there was no way.
Next year,
I’ll be the fastest kid in the entire school!
That’s ‘cause I’m not in your school.
Oh, please!
Remember last time
when I beat you in front
of the whole congregation?
Caleb, do you remember this story?
Oh, yeah,
that’s the Tower of Babel.
That’s right!
Why were these people
trying to build this tower?
So they could live there?
Actually,
it was because they thought
they were awesome
and wanted to show off.
But what did Jehovah think of that?
Oh, he didn’t like it.
That’s right.
He even confused their languages
so they would stop bragging.
But at school everyone brags!
I know.
Lots of people brag.
I have bragged too.
But that’s wrong.
When we brag or show off,
it’s like we are building
a tower for ourselves,
just like the Tower of Babel.
If I wanted to,
I could set a new world record
—no problem!
If you say so.
But I’m better at basketball than you.
I was just messing around,
but they say I’m a natural.
The higher up we try to put ourselves,
the more dangerous it gets.
Do you know why?
Because we’ll eventually fall?
Whoa, whoa.
Whoa!
Ooph!
Yes!
Also, 1 Peter 5:5
means that Jehovah
doesn’t want us acting like
we are better than everyone else.
Humble people don’t need to brag,
because Jehovah will make them
feel good about themselves
on the inside.