Soccer was my reason for living.
I always dreamed of becoming
a professional soccer player.
I thought that happiness came from fame,
a good career,
money.
When I was six,
my parents signed me up for soccer.
I really loved playing soccer.
I spent all my time at the stadium,
even late into the night.
When I was 12,
I learned about Jehovah from my mom.
At that time,
she started studying the Bible.
And after about a year,
I began to preach from door to door.
When I was 17 years old,
I finished school
and I received an invitation
from the Dynamo Soccer Club in Kiev.
Oh, that was unforgettable!
Yes, my emotions were running high
because since childhood
I had always dreamed of playing for Dynamo.
From that moment on,
all my energy and all my time
were devoted to my career.
Every day we either trained or there was a game.
There was no time left for spiritual things.
Of course, being around people like that,
I became just like them.
I led an immoral lifestyle
because huge amounts of money
opened up many opportunities.
Going to nightclubs, the nightlife
—it was so immoral.
Everyone wants to be
your friend and to meet you.
And, of course, this was tempting.
I also invested huge sums
of money in real estate.
I wanted to create a foundation
for the future and wealth for myself,
my family, and my relatives
so that no one would be in need.
Yes, I was sure that this really was happiness.
This continued for nine years.
The turning point
was a conversation with management
when an issue came up,
and they hurled insults at me.
At that moment, I felt worthless,
like a disposable cup
that you use and then crush
and throw away.
Besides, a new generation
of soccer players was arriving
—many young guys.
I stopped being included in the starting lineup.
Also, the financial crisis began,
and real estate prices fell drastically.
I panicked; I didn’t know what to do.
And I started to think about the meaning of life:
‘What really is the meaning of life?
‘If it’s not a career, not money
—then what is it?’
And then I remembered everything that I learned
about Jehovah when I was a teenager.
I began to study
the Bible again along with my wife.
After a year, I started preaching again,
and in 2009,
I was baptized as one of Jehovah’s Witnesses.
And this brought me so much joy and satisfaction.
These feelings can’t be compared
to winning any medal or cup.
I realized that I couldn’t slave for two masters,
but I still had to play
two more years for Dynamo Kyiv.
Although it was a difficult time,
I took advantage of this opportunity,
and I am thankful to Jehovah that a good witness
was given about his name.
There were some soccer players
who showed interest in the truth.
In 2011 when my contract ended,
I finished my professional career.
First Timothy chapter 6
encourages us “to place [our] hope,
not on uncertain riches,
but on God,” and “to be rich in fine works.”
People ask me: “Do you regret it?”
“Maybe you’d like to come back;
do you miss soccer?”
And I honestly and sincerely say no.
I don’t miss it, and I don’t want to go back
because my relationship with Jehovah—
Well, it can’t be compared to anything.
Everything that this world offers is all short-lived,
and it’s only an illusion.
People see only one side of the picture
—the fame and the money.
The other side are
the injuries and disappointments.
It’s very hard psychologically and emotionally;
you have no freedom.
That’s why it’s better
to give the very best to the One
who appreciates it.
What you do for Jehovah
will always bring you happiness,
joy, and satisfaction.