Welcome to JW Broadcasting®
for December 2022!
On September 10th,
24 students reached a milestone
and graduated from the 152nd class of Gilead.
Many of the students
were initially invited to attend the school,
but they patiently waited
until COVID-19 restrictions eased.
Now, after five months of intensive study,
how will they apply their training?
How can they succeed in their assignments?
And how can they strengthen
their brothers and sisters?
These questions and more are answered
in Part 1 of this Gilead graduation program.
Well, this day has arrived for you students.
I see you there smiling
and looking forward to this program.
I’m sure it’s hard for you to believe
that we’ve actually gotten to graduation day.
But we also know that you’re very keen
and enthusiastic to get to your assignments,
whether you’re going back
to where you came from
or you’re going to a new assignment.
Over the last few months,
you’ve learned so much, haven’t you?
You’ve crammed that information
into your mind and heart,
and now you have that ready to implement it
when you go to your assignments.
But we need to be careful
not only to be enthusiastic,
keen, and zealous,
but also we need to be patient.
So we’d like to talk to you
for a few moments about this theme
“Be Enthusiastic but Be Patient” as well.
Why so?
Well, when you go to your assignments
with all this that you’ve learned,
you’re going to be tempted
to try and implement it everywhere.
But remember, you’re not going to change
the whole world in one day
or even the whole branch.
You see,
it’s so easy to become overwhelmed
if we try to take on too much
all at one time.
So that’s why it’s important
to be enthusiastic
but also patient.
Our Lord Jesus Christ
was an excellent example of this.
When Jesus came into the world,
the whole world needed to hear his message.
And yet, he had to wait some 30 years,
growing up according to Jehovah’s timetable,
before he started his ministry.
So that took patience on his part, didn’t it?
But what about when Jesus
started his ministry?
What was his focus?
You can imagine him looking around,
seeing all the things that needed to be done
in the world at that point.
But let’s turn in our Bibles.
If you turn with me, please,
to Matthew chapter 15
—Matthew 15:24,
and here Jesus said to his apostles:
“I was not sent to anyone
except to the lost sheep
of the house of Israel.”
That’s interesting.
Jesus here mentions
he had a specific, limited assignment.
What was the assignment?
To go “to the lost sheep
of the house of Israel.”
Now, if you turn back
just a couple of chapters,
in chapter 10 of Matthew,
you’ll notice in verses 5 and 6
that when Jesus sent out his apostles,
what did he say to them?
“Do not go off into the road of the nations,
“and do not enter any Samaritan city;
“but instead, go continually
to the lost sheep of the house of Israel.”
So as Jesus sent out his apostles
in this particular instance,
what was he reminding them of?
He was telling them
that they likewise had a limited assignment,
a specific assignment.
They weren’t supposed to try
and do everything all at once
—to go to the Samaritans and to the Gentiles.
They were to focus
just on “the lost sheep of the house of Israel.”
So when we think about this,
what do we learn from these two verses?
Well, first of all,
yes, the whole world
needed to hear the message.
But what did Jesus do,
and what did he expect of his apostles?
That they would recognize
that they had a specific assignment.
They weren’t to be overwhelmed
by trying to think of changing
the whole world at that point.
Jesus showed great trust in Jehovah.
He knew that Jehovah
would gradually expand the message
and the reach of the message.
And, of course, we realize
that at Pentecost there was an expansion
and then in 36 C.E., another expansion.
So, what does that mean for you?
You see, when you return to your assignment
or you go to the new one,
there’s going to be
an endless number of possibilities
where you can help others
—to stabilize and strengthen everyone.
But if you try to take everything on at once,
you’re going to wear yourself out
and probably wear out
a whole lot of other people as well.
You know the English idiom
“Don’t bite off more than you can chew.”
You see, gradually do the things
that Jehovah has assigned you to do.
If you try to be too broad in what you do,
you may end up not accomplishing much at all
except just wearing yourself out.
But be patient just as Jesus was,
and recognize that each one of you
will have a specific assignment.
And then try to work at that,
trusting that Jehovah will allow
your good example to benefit others,
and gradually the effects of your work
will spread to others.
Now, an example of this is
in the South Pacific,
if I could just tell you about that now.
When missionaries arrived
in the South Pacific—
Let’s take, for example,
you might end up in a country
that has 100 inhabited islands.
Now you’re a new missionary.
I remember the feeling.
And then you find out
there are only ten islands
that have Jehovah’s Witnesses on them
—ten islands that have
publishers and congregations.
So there are 90 that don’t.
So, what do you think
the normal enthusiastic response is?
“Oh, let’s get a boat.
We have to get a boat!
“We must visit all the 90 islands.
Oh, that needs to be done now, immediately!”
Well, usually you’re assigned
to one congregation
in one area.
Now, what’s the point?
What normally happens?
Well, you see, if you were to get a boat
(and there’s nothing wrong
with getting a boat
or visiting other islands)
and if that becomes your focus
and you neglect your assignment,
how can you follow up on all the interest
that you may find on those 90 islands?
It’s not just enough
to go and give them some magazines,
but you need to be there with them,
build them up,
and form congregations.
So normally what happens?
Well, it’s amazing to see
missionaries and others
who work in maybe larger city areas;
they work diligently at their assignments.
But then maybe others from different islands
come to visit that city
the missionaries are in,
and they get contacted.
They show an interest, they start to study,
and they return to their home islands.
And what happens?
Gradually, the work spreads out
to all these islands.
So, what’s the point?
Don’t feel
that you have to take on everything.
Focus as Jesus did
on the limited assignment you have.
But then along the way,
you may be surprised at what happens.
Now, that’s exactly what happened to Jesus.
Let’s go back to Matthew chapter 15.
Remember,
what was the assignment that Jesus had?
In verse 24,
he mentioned “Israel.”
Now, looking at this map, we see at that time
there was actually a border around that area
that we could say was his territory assignment.
But when Jesus said these words,
where was he?
Do you remember?
Let’s look in verse 21:
“Jesus now went into the region
of Tyre and Sidon.”
So when you look at the map,
where was Tyre and Sidon?
What do you notice?
You see, he wasn’t in his territory.
He was out among the Gentiles.
Why?
Well, when we look at the parallel account
that’s mentioned in Mark chapter 7,
it tells us that Jesus wanted
some time alone with his apostles,
some downtime
because there were so many crowds;
they were so busy.
Now, I’m sure all of us
can understand that feeling Jesus had.
So he took them out of that general area
to this territory
that was beyond what he
would normally preach in
to have some quiet time together.
But what happened?
Well, the account tells us
that there was a Syrophoenician woman,
perhaps (as the study notes help us to see)
from a Greek background
as far as her nationality went,
but maybe she was a citizen
or an inhabitant of that area,
the Syrophoenician area.
So this woman approached Jesus,
pleading with him.
Now, she didn’t look like a Jewish person.
She probably didn’t even speak Hebrew.
She certainly wasn’t in the category
of the lost ones of the house of Israel.
So Jesus,
initially when she started
to make these efforts to talk to him,
mentioned this to his apostles in verse 24:
‘That’s our assignment.’
But notice that this was a little different
in the sense that this woman
showed an appreciation for who Jesus was.
Notice in verse 22, she said:
“Have mercy on me, Lord, Son of David.”
Now, here’s a Gentile woman.
Should she really know who David was?
And by saying “Son of David,”
as the study note indicates,
perhaps she was showing faith
in the fact that Jesus is the Messiah.
So she wasn’t
your average Syrophoenician person.
What did Jesus do?
Well, he tested her a little.
He did emphasize
the fact that in a household
you first of all
feed the children, the family,
and then the little dogs get fed afterward.
And perhaps he was playing on words there.
It’s interesting.
We’re not sure
what language Jesus was speaking to her.
The Watchtower  did say that Jesus
perhaps did understand Greek
and use it at times.
Why, his apostles
obviously understood some Greek.
They wrote some of the books of the Bible
in Greek.
But whatever the case,
the record of this is written
—the inspired record—
in Greek,
and it uses this term “little dogs.”
Was that offensive?
No.
As it’s mentioned,
it was an affectionate term
like saying “puppies” or “pets.”
So whatever the case,
he must have looked very friendly,
perhaps had a smile on his face,
because she was not deterred.
What was Jesus’ reaction?
Well, he acknowledged
his territory, his assignment.
But then in verse 28, he said,
“O woman, great is your faith;
let it happen to you as you wish.”
Is this the only time
that Jesus did something like this
for a non-Jewish person?
Remember in John chapter 4,
not only do we have this case
of the Syrophoenician woman,
but in John chapter 4,
we’re told about the Samaritan woman.
This non-Jewish person was witnessed to,
and then even members of her village
accepted Jesus as the Messiah.
And then what about the Roman army officer
that Jesus was able to help?
And Jesus mentioned
that he hadn’t even seen
that type of faith in all of Israel.
So, what lesson do we learn from this?
Well, Jesus focused on his assignment.
He always acknowledged
what he was assigned to do.
But when opportunities came up along the way
to help those
who weren’t necessarily in his assignment,
he still gave them some help
because they were genuine persons
who needed help.
Yes, although Jesus realized
it wasn’t yet the time to expand the work,
he was willing to reach out
to these ones as well.
So, what’s the lesson for all of us?
Well, when you go to your assignments,
you will have specific assignments.
Now, if it’s in a Bethel or in the field,
you’ll know what your assignment is.
So don’t start looking
at all the other assignments that are around
and how you can help them
and what you need to do
and say, “Oh, why don’t they change?”
I mean, you’ve changed a lot
in the last few months;
but remember, they haven’t.
And they survived without you.
So, what’s the key?
Focus on your assignment.
Be zealous, be enthusiastic,
but also be patient.
Yes, have trust in Jehovah
that if you focus on your assignment,
you work hard,
you take up whatever opportunities
come your way along the way,
then you can be sure you will be blessed
because you’re enthusiastic but also patient.
Well, now with those thoughts in mind,
we have a very interesting program
ahead of us.
First up, we have Brother Kenneth Cook,
a member of the Governing Body.
And Brother Cook
is going to talk to you on the theme
“Follow the Steps That Lead to Blessings.”
Brother Cook, please.
To begin, I’d like to share
a personal experience with you.
When I was told that I was appointed to be
a member of the Governing Body,
one of the brothers who informed me said:
“With this assignment, you’ll experience
“a great increase in responsibility.
“But you’ll also see a corresponding increase
“in Jehovah’s spirit to help you.
It will not be too much for you.”
Well, those words were very,
very reassuring to me.
And the fact is that all of us
(no matter who we are)
serving Jehovah faithfully
must rely on his help
to succeed in serving him.
Now, how do we show this
and receive his help?
There are a number of ways.
We’re going to focus on three of them.
They are these: Follow direction, show faith,
and use common sense,
or the thinking ability,
that Jehovah has given to us.
So let’s consider the first step.
Sometimes all that’s required
to receive Jehovah’s blessing on our work
is to follow simple, clear direction.
Now, here’s a Bible example of that.
It’s found in Mark chapter 14
—Mark chapter 14.
Now, you’ll recall from this account
that God’s Son directed two of his disciples
to go into Jerusalem and to prepare a large,
furnished upper room for the Passover.
His directions were specific.
For instance, Jesus said that they would meet
‘a man carrying a large, earthenware jar,
and they were to follow him.’
And then starting in verse 14,
Jesus added this,
he said: “Wherever he goes inside,
say to the master of the house,
“‘The Teacher says: “Where is the guest room
“where I may eat
the Passover with my disciples?”’
“And he will show you a large upper room,
furnished and ready.
“Prepare it for us there.
“So the disciples went out,
and they entered the city
“and found it just as he said to them,
and they prepared for the Passover.”
So the directions were simple, right?
They were told where they should go,
who they should follow,
what they were to say,
and what they were to do.
And the two disciples promptly followed
that direction,
and of course, their obedience
brought many blessings, as we know.
Well, what practical lesson
can you draw from this?
The lesson: Sometimes all that is needed
in serving Jehovah
is to follow simple, clear direction.
You’ll have many opportunities to do so
in your assignments.
Follow clear direction,
and look for Jehovah’s blessing on it.
But now, on the other hand,
you might be asked to care for something
that’s far more involved than that.
For example, what if you’re asked
to assist someone
who’s known to be difficult to deal with?
Or you’re asked
to care for a work-related problem
that others have not been able to solve.
You’re the one selected
because you’ve had the training.
In such a case, what will help you?
Your strong faith—the next step.
The fact is that at times we need to show
added faith to fulfill our assignments.
True?
Consider the example of Ananias.
Now, he too was a man of faith,
but he faced a challenge
that required even more of him,
and we read about it in Acts chapter 9.
We’ll begin with verse 10
—Acts 9:10—
it says: “There was a disciple
named Ananias in Damascus,
“and the Lord said to him in a vision:
‘Ananias!’
“He said: ‘Here I am, Lord.’
“The Lord said to him:
‘Get up, go to the street called Straight,
“‘and look for a man named Saul, from Tarsus,
“‘at the house of Judas.
“‘For look! he is praying,
“‘and in a vision he has seen
a man named Ananias
“come in and lay his hands on him
so that he may recover sight.’
“But Ananias answered: ‘Lord,
“‘I have heard from many about this man,
“‘about all the harm he did
to your holy ones in Jerusalem.
“‘And here he has authority
from the chief priests
“to arrest all those calling on your name.’
“But the Lord said to him:
‘Go! because this man
“‘is a chosen vessel to me
to bear my name to the nations
“‘as well as to kings and the sons of Israel.
“‘For I will show him plainly how many things
he must suffer for my name.’”
Well, the direction was clear.
Where should Ananias go?
To the street called Straight.
Who was he looking for?
A man named Saul.
What house is he in?
The house of Judas.
Ananias was even told what Saul was doing.
He was praying.
Then Ananias was told what he should do.
He was to lay his hands on him
so that he would recover sight.
Simple, right?
Jesus would do the rest.
What a great example
of giving clear direction!
But here is where Ananias
needed to stir up more faith.
The man he was to visit
had severely persecuted
the holy ones in Jerusalem.
And speaking to the Lord, Ananias added
that this man
“has authority from the chief priests
to arrest all those calling on your name.”
Well, talk about stating
the obvious to Jesus.
The point is that Ananias had a moment
where he was overwhelmed
by the weight of the assignment.
That’s just what happened.
What would help him?
More faith.
And Jesus knew how to draw it up
in that dear man.
Look again at Jesus’ reply.
He simply restated his command: “Go.”
Then Jesus said that “this man
is a chosen vessel to me
“to bear my name to the nations
as well as to kings and the sons of Israel.”
Now, Jesus added something there, didn’t he?
He pointed to the future.
What was he doing?
He was helping Ananias to look ahead, see.
And doing this evidently prompted Ananias
to show even more faith,
which is what he needed.
How do we know this?
Well, look at what he said to Saul.
On meeting Saul, verse 17 tells us
that Ananias called him “brother.”
His initial hesitation had changed
into putting his full faith and trust
in Jesus’ direction.
Well, like Ananias,
as you face challenges in the future
(and they will come;
they come upon all of us),
have strong faith
that Jehovah sees what is needed,
and he and his dear Son will help you.
Keep the big picture in mind,
and look to the blessings ahead
for your hard work.
Jehovah will always bless
your strong faith in him.
Well, so far we’ve looked at the need
to follow clear direction
and to show strong faith.
Now we’re going to add another step:
Use common sense, or thinking ability.
Our Bible example—Elijah.
In this account,
Elijah has traveled to Zarephath,
a Phoenician coastal town.
What was his business there?
Well, the land was
in the grip of a long drought,
and Jehovah would help his prophet
by means of someone in that town.
Elijah was told: “Look!
I will command a widow there
to supply you with food.”
It appears that he gave no other details
about the widow than that.
So how would Elijah find her?
Would Elijah look for the wealthiest widow
to care for his needs?
Or would he use common sense
and thinking ability along with his faith?
Let’s see what Elijah does
at 1 Kings chapter 17.
And we’re going to read verse 10
—First Kings 17:10,
it says: “So he [Elijah]
rose up and went to Zarephath.
“When he came to the entrance of the city,
“there was a widow gathering pieces of wood.
“So he called to her and said:
‘Please, bring me a little water in a cup
so that I may drink.’”
So then what did Elijah do?
Evidently, he approached
the very first widow he met.
And she was not a wealthy widow,
but a poor one.
In fact, it says Elijah had not yet passed
beyond the entrance of the city.
What does this tell us about Elijah?
First, he showed no prejudice
in following through on Jehovah’s direction,
did he?
And second, he added thinking ability
to his obedience and faith.
How so?
Well, common sense would tell him
to show his faith
and start looking
with the very first widow he met.
Elijah obviously had confidence
that Jehovah would make his choice clear.
His obedience, faith, and good sense
were rewarded
because that widow was Jehovah’s choice.
Now, surely holy spirit guided Elijah,
but we can’t ignore
the faith and clear thinking ability
that Elijah developed
as he obediently did God’s will.
After all, prior to that widow,
Jehovah used birds
to carry food to his prophet.
Surely Jehovah
could use a poor widow as well.
What’s the lesson for you and for all of us?
Sometimes we’re given much to go on
when we receive an assignment
and, at other times, frankly,
maybe not so much.
In such a case,
our faith and clear thinking ability
remind us to trust in Jehovah
and to look for his guidance
as we go forward in doing his will.
Jehovah will always help you dear friends
at the right time.
So then, as our examples show, promptly obey,
show strong faith,
and use common sense and thinking ability
in our service to our dear heavenly Father.
Remembering such lessons will help you
as you support Jehovah’s work
in your respective branches.
Jehovah gives power beyond what is normal
to those who rely on him
and follow the steps that lead to blessings.
And we are confident
that this will always be true of you.
Thank you very much, Brother Cook.
You clearly helped us to see
the steps that are needed
for us to gain blessings.
Well, now our next speaker on the program
is Brother Jeffrey Winder,
who is a helper to the Personnel Committee.
And Brother Winder is going to discuss
with us this very interesting question,
“How Close Can You Be?”
How would you students answer this question:
Do you feel closer to Jehovah now
than you did
before your Gilead training began?
The answer is a resounding yes, isn’t it?
Maybe you can relate to these comments
of graduates of past classes of Gilead.
One brother said: “Absolutely, yes!
“I believe I now experience more fully
“what it means to walk with God
“and know and rely upon him
as a close Friend,
not merely someone
I turn and look up to in prayer.”
A sister said:
“Gilead definitely drew me closer to Jehovah.
“The way we studied the Scriptures
with intensity
truly made me feel like the Bible
was a letter Jehovah wrote to me.”
Another brother said:
“Jehovah communicated with such clarity,
“which made it real and personal.
“It made me feel closer to Jehovah
than ever before,
and that feeling will never be forgotten.”
Well, unquestionably,
your deep study of God’s Word during Gilead
drew you closer to Jehovah.
But here’s the question,
How close can you be?
How close
can your relationship with Jehovah get?
You saw it leap forward in five months
of deep Bible study, but is there a limit?
Is there more?
Will you ever get done?
Consider two points
that answer that question.
The first one is found
in the book of James chapter 4,
and let’s read together
the first part of verse 8.
And let’s read it with that question in mind:
Is there any limit to how close
our relationship with Jehovah could be?
James 4:8 says:
“Draw close to God,
and he will draw close to you.”
So is there any limit indicated here?
Well, it is true that in English
this phrase to “draw close to” someone
could be applied in a physical sense
—actually standing next to someone.
And in that case, there is a limit.
You can only stand so close to someone.
But that’s not really the sense of James 4:8,
is it?
Rather, it’s in this sense:
When we talk about our close friends,
we’re not talking about those
that are nearest in proximity.
We’re talking
about the depth of our relationship,
the closeness of our friendship.
And so then to “draw close to God” then means
to strengthen our relationship,
strengthen our friendship, with him.
And then looking at the verse,
does it appear that there’s any limit
to how close that relationship can get?
The implication is that as long
as we keep drawing close to Jehovah,
then he’ll keep drawing close to us.
And that takes us to our second point,
and that is the real life example
of God’s Son,
because Jesus drew close to Jehovah.
Clearly, he was taught by Jehovah.
Remember Isaiah 50:4,
regarding Jesus’ prehuman existence,
where he said:
“He awakens me morning by morning;
he awakens my ear
to listen like the taught ones.”
Does that sound a bit
like your Gilead training?
‘Morning by morning
Jehovah was awakening your ear.’
Yet, Jesus wasn’t instructed by Jehovah
for five months;
he was instructed for billions of years.
And during all that time,
his relationship with his Father
continued to grow and deepen.
So, then, we put it all together.
You saw your relationship with Jehovah
grow significantly
in five months of deep Bible study.
James 4:8 encourages us
to just keep drawing close to Jehovah.
And Jesus did so for billions of years,
and look at how close
his relationship with Jehovah is.
So, then, what’s the answer?
How close can you be to Jehovah?
The potential for your relationship
with Jehovah to deepen
is endless.
Well, that’s just wonderful to contemplate,
isn’t it?
But let’s make some application
because this really becomes
a very important overall lesson
that you take with you
from your Gilead experience:
That is how your deep Bible study
affected your relationship with Jehovah.
And one of the reasons
why this is such an important lesson
is because your success in your assignment
is directly connected to the depth
of your relationship with Jehovah.
Your success in your assignment
is directly connected to the depth
of your relationship with Jehovah.
Now, why can we say that?
It’s because of what takes place
when we draw close to Jehovah
through a study of his Word.
Turn with me, please,
to the book of Psalms,
and we’ll read the 25th Psalm
in verse 4
—Psalm 25:4.
It says:
“Make me know your ways, O Jehovah;
teach me your paths.”
This is what’s happening
when we study God’s Word, isn’t it?
We are coming to know Jehovah God’s ways.
The Watchtower  once said it this way.
It said: “As we get a deeper
and deeper understanding of God’s Word,
we become imbued
with God’s way of thinking.”
“We become imbued
The dictionary said that the word
“imbue implies the introduction of a quality
that fills and permeates the whole being,”
so like dyeing a garment or leavening bread.
But here we’re talking
about being imbued with God’s thinking,
that maybe God’s thinking
would fill and permeate our whole being.
Is that possible?
Think back to the example of Jesus.
As we discussed,
Jesus drew close to Jehovah.
He was taught by Jehovah
for billions of years.
And what was happening
during that whole time?
He was being imbued
with Jehovah God’s thinking.
And it so permeated him
that when he was on earth,
he could say at John 14:9:
“Whoever has seen me
has seen the Father also.”
So in other words,
everything that Jesus said,
everything that he did while on earth
in every situation,
well, we could imagine Jehovah
doing and saying those very things.
And that is why
the success of your assignment
is directly connected to the depth
of your relationship with Jehovah.
The more you draw close to Jehovah
through a study of his Word,
then the more you are imbued
with his thinking
and the more then you will do, or act,
and say things as Jehovah would.
And so how does this play out?
Well, in your assignment,
if you have the privilege
to contribute to significant decisions
that will affect others in your department
or at the branch or in the field even,
my, you want to be guided
by Jehovah’s thinking, don’t you?
You want to do things as he would do them.
Well, the closer you are to Jehovah,
the deeper that relationship is,
the more your decisions will mirror his.
But, of course, we know
strengthening and stabilizing others
isn’t always done
in big, grand gestures like that
—big decisions,
new organizational arrangements.
Quite often it’s the day-to-day interactions
with others
that really encourage them.
And isn’t it true that we learn so much
from those intimate conversations
that Jesus had with others,
or seemingly incidental interactions
that he had with others,
that the Bible records?
Well, you will strengthen others
in similar ways.
For example,
when you are guided
by Jehovah’s thinking in personal matters,
such as in your choice of dress and grooming,
well, others will certainly notice that
and that will strengthen their resolve
to make good decisions
in these personal areas.
When you are guided by Jehovah’s thinking
in the use of your time,
as busy as you will be
—when the friends see you in the ministry,
at the meetings,
working hard in your assignment—
they will take notice of that
and that will strengthen their resolve
to make good priorities in their life.
Every time you steer
a negative conversation to the positive,
every time you show
a willingness to do humble tasks,
every time you take the time
to get the other side of the story
before rendering judgment
—yes, in all these areas of your daily life,
you give evidence
that you have drawn close to Jehovah,
you have been imbued with his thinking,
and you are acting as Jehovah would.
And in that case,
you absolutely will strengthen and stabilize
your brothers!
Well, we love you
for your relationship with Jehovah.
And we encourage you
to take this lesson of Gilead with you
—the effect that your deep Bible study
had on your relationship with Jehovah—
and keep drawing close to him.
The potential is endless,
and this is what will ensure your success.
Well, may the rich blessing of Jehovah,
your Friend, be with you
as you use your Gilead training
in the assignments he has given you.
Well, I’m sure we all agree
that was a beautiful answer
to the question, “How Close Can You Be?”
And all of us feel close to Jehovah,
but what a wonderful encouragement
for us to draw ever closer to him!
The next brother, who’s going to give you
some words of encouragement,
has a very intriguing theme
“Buy a Field in Anathoth.”
Brother Gage Fleegle,
who’s a helper to the Service Committee,
is going to develop this theme
“Buy a Field in Anathoth.”
The year was 608 B.C.E.
The prophet Jeremiah
had already served
nearly 40 years faithfully,
and now he “was confined
in the Courtyard of the Guard” in Jerusalem.
Jerusalem’s walls
were being battered by the Babylonians.
In less than a year,
the entire city
would be completely destroyed.
Jeremiah had to weather the storm.
There was no way out.
There was no place for him to go.
He was under lockdown.
Well, have you ever felt like Jeremiah
—as if the world was caving in on you?
Maybe it was a serious health scare,
the health of a loved one,
the death of a loved one,
or maybe COVID-19
has made you feel boxed in.
Some of our brothers, just like Jeremiah,
have faced persecution or imprisonment,
and that might be our lot
before the end of this system of things.
Well, what will help you students
—in fact, all of us—
during these critical last days
when we face personal trials, or adversity?
I invite you to open to Jeremiah chapter 32.
Let’s consider a dramatic illustration
in the life of Jeremiah.
Now, Jeremiah is under lockdown.
Jeremiah chapter 32,
let’s read verses 6-8:
“Jeremiah said: ‘The word of Jehovah
has come to me, saying,
“‘“Here Hanamel the son of Shallum
your uncle will come to you and say:
“‘“‘Buy for yourself my field in Anathoth,
because you have the first right
to repurchase it.’”’”
Verse 8 says:
“Hanamel the son of my uncle came to me,
“just as Jehovah had said,
into the Courtyard of the Guard,
“and he said to me:
‘Please buy my field in Anathoth,
“‘in the land of Benjamin, for you
have the right to take possession of it
“‘and to repurchase it.
“Buy it for yourself.’
At that I knew that this was
by the word of Jehovah.”
What was Jehovah’s instruction to Jeremiah?
Buy a field.
Buy a field?
Right now, with the Babylonians
beating on the door?
Jeremiah might have thought,
‘I need an escape plan, not a field
—of all places, Anathoth?’
Where was Anathoth?
Well, Jeremiah knew exactly where it was
—just a few miles
north-northeast of Jerusalem.
He was born there into a priestly family.
Did he have pleasant memories of his past
in Anathoth as a youth?
Very likely.
But now that was a distant memory.
More recently, men of Anathoth,
possibly some of Jeremiah’s own relatives,
threatened to kill him
because of his prophesying.
Well, did Jeremiah obey
in spite of any personal feelings
he might have had?
Jeremiah always obeyed,
even previously when Jehovah told him
not to take a wife or to have children.
Well, what did he do in this situation?
Verses 9 and 10:
“So I bought the field in Anathoth
from Hanamel the son of my uncle.
“I weighed out the money to him,
seven shekels and ten silver pieces.
“Then I recorded it in a deed,
affixed the seal,
called in witnesses,
and weighed the money in the scales.”
Jeremiah could have worked
in the Legal Department.
Well, he carried out the legal transaction,
the legal requirements of the transaction.
He recorded the transaction in two deeds
—one sealed, one unsealed—
complete transparency in this situation.
Why did Jehovah ask Jeremiah
to buy a field in Anathoth?
Jeremiah already had complete faith that,
yes, Jehovah’s word would be restored
—when 70 years had transpired,
the Jews would return to their homeland.
But now Jehovah reinforced Jeremiah’s faith
by giving him something specific
to think about.
Jeremiah could imagine the time
when buying and selling
would again occur in Israel.
Well, was Jeremiah’s faith
well-placed in Jehovah’s promise?
Absolutely.
Ezra later documented
that 128 men of Anathoth
were among the first group
of those returning from Babylonian exile.
Jehovah’s word always comes true.
Well, how might we
—how might you—
“buy a field in Anathoth”?
Well, we’re not expecting you
to go out and purchase
a piece of property
in a place called Anathoth.
No.
We find a clue, though, in Hebrews chapter 11
—Hebrews 11:1:
“Faith is the assured expectation
of what is hoped for,
the evident demonstration
of realities that are not seen.”
The Simple English Bible
renders it this way:
“Faith is the title-deed
to the things we hope for.”
Now, most of us in special full-time service,
we don’t own property.
But we may have the title to a car.
What does that mean?
That means that car, that vehicle,
belongs to us personally.
Our faith is the “title-deed”
of good things to come,
a guarantee of future realities.
Jeremiah had a “title-deed.”
We have a “title-deed” of faith.
So how do we “buy a field in Anathoth”?
It’s not a type-antitype situation;
it’s just an illustration.
In the context of our discussion,
it means we exercise faith
in Jehovah’s promises.
When facing a trial,
we can search Jehovah’s Word
for promises regarding the future,
and that gives us strength
to keep on enduring.
For example,
if we’re facing a serious illness,
God’s Word promises:
“No resident will say: ‘I am sick.’”
If we’re grieving the death of a loved one,
the Bible assures us
there is going to be a resurrection.
The trial doesn’t disappear yet,
but exercising faith in Jehovah’s promises
helps us to endure.
Now, there’s something else that we can learn
from that dramatic illustration
in the life of Jeremiah.
Back in Jeremiah 32, notice,
please, verses 13 through 15.
Jeremiah was inspired to write, he said:
“I now commanded Baruch
in their presence, saying:
“‘This is what Jehovah of armies,
the God of Israel, says,
“‘“Take these deeds, this deed of purchase,
“‘“the sealed one
and the other deed left unsealed,
“‘“and put them into an earthenware vessel,
“‘so that they may be kept for a long time.”
“‘For this is what Jehovah of armies,
the God of Israel, says,
“Houses and fields and vineyards
will again be bought in this land.”’”
Jeremiah involved Baruch
in the legal proceedings
when he bought the field in Anathoth.
Jeremiah’s faith
influenced Baruch for the good.
We can almost hear
the confidence and conviction in his voice:
“This is what Jehovah of armies,
the God of Israel says.”
Jeremiah used that expression,
“Jehovah of armies,”
more than any other Bible writer.
It was like Jeremiah said:
‘Our God will certainly overturn
the Babylonians.
‘These promises are real;
you can take them to the bank!
They’re not counterfeit;
they’re completely true!’
What’s the lesson for us?
Our faith can strengthen fellow believers.
A sister named Joyce,
while she herself was fighting cancer,
made what she called shot-in-the-arm cards.
They were collections of Bible verses,
pictures from our publications,
quotes from theocratic songs
or Watchtower  articles,
and she would give them
to those in need of encouragement.
One of her favorites was Psalm 112:7, 8.
And there it says:
“He will not fear bad news.
“His heart is steadfast, trusting in Jehovah.
“His heart is unshakable; he is not afraid;
in the end he will look in triumph
on his adversaries.”
Sister Joyce had
a lot of bad news in her life,
but her faith in Jehovah’s promises
was powerful.
Sadly, Joyce lost her fight with cancer
a few years back,
but she “bought a field in Anathoth,”
and she will witness
the fulfillment of Jehovah’s promises.
Even now, she’s given us a shot in the arm
—encouragement from Jehovah’s Word—
and strengthened us with her faith.
And so, dear Gilead students,
what have we learned?
Faith is like
a “title-deed of things hoped for.”
Faith in Jehovah’s Word
helps us to endure trials and adversity.
Our faith can have
a powerful effect on those around us.
So when faced with persecution,
“buy a field in Anathoth.”
When faced with a grievous health problem,
When grieving the loss of a loved one,
“buy a field in Anathoth.”
And some day soon,
your faith will be rewarded.
You’ll walk in that field
when Jehovah’s word comes true.
Well, what a beautiful talk!
Now to be honest
(I don’t know if you are like me),
when I heard the theme
“Buy a Field in Anathoth,”
I thought,
‘Where on earth is he going to take us?’
I mean, to be quite honest.
Well, Brother Fleegle,
you took us to a very good spot
with the title deed and seeing
the connection there.
And in fact, that’s going to be
a little password.
We might say, “Buy a field in Anathoth.”
And if we say that to someone
and they looked amazed,
we’ll say, “Oh, you weren’t there
for the graduation program.”
Well, thank you very much.
Now, for you, dear students,
over the last few months,
you’ve drawn very close to the instructors,
and you’ve heard them day in, day out.
You’ve learned and experienced
a lot of things from them.
So the next two parts
are the opportunities
for two of these instructors
to give you
a few final words of encouragement.
So first of all,
we’re going to have Brother Trent Lippold
who’s going to talk to you,
and he has this interesting question:
“Distinguished—By What?”
He was a mighty man.
He felled the heroes of the enemy.
He slayed a giant.
He even killed a lion.
And his name was not David.
Who was he?
Open your Bibles with me, please,
to the book of 1 Chronicles chapter 11
—1 Chronicles 11:22:
“Benaiah the son of Jehoiada
“was a courageous man who performed
“many exploits in Kabzeel.
“He struck down
the two sons of Ariel of Moab,
“and he descended into a waterpit
on a snowy day and killed a lion.
“He also struck down an Egyptian man
of extraordinary size
“—five cubits tall.
“Though the Egyptian had a spear in his hand
“like the beam of loom workers,
“he went against him with a rod
“and snatched the spear away
from the Egyptian’s hand
and killed him with his own spear.”
He is Benaiah.
Look at all we learn about him
in these verses,
the qualities that Benaiah displayed.
It tells us in verse 22
that he “was a courageous man.”
He “performed many exploits in Kabzeel.”
Kabzeel—Kabzeel is a small place
on the very southern border of Judah.
It borders Edom in the middle of nowhere.
But Benaiah worked there.
He was happy to be there.
It may be that that was his home.
Or it may be that that was his assignment.
No matter,
as obscure a place as Kabzeel is,
that’s where he worked.
And the record says that he performed
many exploits courageously in Kabzeel.
He killed a lion—courage.
But do you notice
that “he descended into a waterpit . . .
and killed a lion”?
Courage.
He descended into a waterpit
with a lion.
There’s only one coming out,
and it was Benaiah.
“He descended into a waterpit
on a snowy day.”
He didn’t wait for the sun to shine.
He knew that was the day
—adverse conditions, no matter.
Benaiah went in, and he slayed the lion.
Look at verse 23,
some more amazing qualities.
He struck down the giant,
‘an Egyptian of extraordinary size.’
But notice this: “Though the Egyptian
had a spear in his hand
“like the beam of loom workers,
he [Benaiah]
went against him with a rod”—a rod, a stick.
He didn’t have the right equipment
—courage, adaptability, commitment.
And notice this.
What does he do?
It says: “He went against him with a rod
and snatched the spear away
from the Egyptian’s hand
and killed him with his own spear.”
Courage, commitment,
adaptability, resourcefulness
—these are admirable, beneficial qualities.
Are those the qualities
that distinguished Benaiah?
Not entirely.
There was one quality that exceeded these,
and that quality was loyalty
—tenacious adherence
to the person of Jehovah.
That’s what the Bible record reveals
about Benaiah:
personal loyalty to Jehovah.
There is a caution, though, with loyalty.
The demarcation
between loyalty to Jehovah
and loyalty to self
can often be blurry.
It hides under the inertia
of imperfection and selfishness.
That line of loyalty to Jehovah
versus loyalty to self
can become very difficult to see.
In fact, loyalty to self
can lie dormant within us
until the circumstances arise and change,
and then it can emerge.
And Benaiah and his contemporaries
provide for us a beautiful contrast
in loyalty to Jehovah and loyalty to self.
Think of Benaiah.
He lived in a very tumultuous time.
David was a fugitive with his mighty men.
One of them likely was Benaiah, among others.
These men were comrades in arms
running with David.
They were a band of brothers.
They were fiercely loyal to David
and, to be sure,
they were loyal to Jehovah as well.
For example, among these three mighty men
were three brothers, fleshly brothers.
They’re mentioned in verses 20 and 26:
Joab, Abishai, and Asahel.
Now consider when circumstances changed
for the mighty men,
when Saul died and David now became king,
in these changing circumstances,
what happened to the mighty men?
Here’s the contrast: Joab and Benaiah.
What happened to Joab?
Joab saw opportunity
in changing circumstances,
and his loyalty to Jehovah was eclipsed
by his loyalty to himself.
For instance,
it was Joab who took matters
into his own hands,
and he killed Abner
with whom David
had already concluded a covenant.
He took matters into his own hands.
Why?
He wanted Abner’s job.
His selfish ambitions got the better of him,
and they eclipsed his loyalty to Jehovah.
Joab was a courageous man.
He was resourceful.
He was adaptable.
Admirable qualities.
But in the absence
of deep personal loyalty to Jehovah,
they seem somehow tainted, don’t they?
But consider Benaiah
in the same circumstances.
Benaiah had no part in these kind
of intrigues like Joab and his brothers.
Benaiah was loyal to Jehovah,
and he was a loyal man
to Jehovah’s anointed one, David.
And look at what we find in verses 24 and 25,
verses 24 and 25: “These things
Benaiah the son of Jehoiada did,
“and he had a reputation
like that of the three mighty warriors.
“Although he was distinguished
even more than the thirty,
“he did not attain to the rank of the three.
However, David appointed him
over his own bodyguard.”
You see, in the same circumstances as Joab,
Benaiah’s tenacious adherence to Jehovah
—his deep personal loyalty to Jehovah—
safeguarded him in these circumstances.
What did David see in Benaiah?
David saw in Benaiah
what he himself exemplified,
and that was deep and strong personal loyalty
to Jehovah.
You can see that in this verse,
in verse 25, can’t you?
It says: “However, David appointed him
over his own bodyguard.”
David knew that to assign someone
to this very, very trusted position
(head of his own bodyguard),
the man in that position,
if he was loyal to Jehovah,
would be loyal to him.
And that’s what David saw in Benaiah.
Then came another time of change
decades later.
When David died and Solomon became king
—changed circumstances,
another time of opportunity—
how would Benaiah react?
The same way he always did:
deep personal loyalty to Jehovah.
And it was Solomon when he became king
who rewarded Benaiah.
The son of David, Solomon,
Jehovah’s anointed,
rewarded Benaiah for his loyalty.
Turn with me, please, to Proverbs 19:22.
You see, Solomon
knew something about loyalty.
He was the son of David.
And look at what he wrote about loyalty
at Proverbs 19:22.
Solomon said: “The desirable thing in a man
is his loyal love.”
His loyalty
—that’s what Jehovah looks for in us.
So Benaiah was indeed a mighty man,
and he had beautiful qualities.
Did they distinguish him?
Not entirely.
It was his deep personal loyalty to Jehovah
first and foremost that distinguished him.
And because of that deep personal loyalty
to Jehovah,
those qualities of Benaiah were beautiful.
So daily cultivate your loyalty to God
through prayer and study.
That’s been your training here.
Use your training to develop
your close personal loyalty to Jehovah.
That’s what Benaiah did.
Think of Benaiah’s training.
He was the son of Jehoiada.
Jehoiada was
one of the chief Levitical priests in Israel.
Benaiah was raised with scrolls,
not with swords.
Growing up as the son of a priest,
that was his training.
So like Benaiah,
be willing to do the work without the rank.
Remember, loyalty is tested
not when you are at ease.
Loyalty is tested under adversity.
So be careful in changing circumstances.
Guard your hearts.
Dear students,
you all have beautiful qualities.
We’ve seen them over the last five months.
But may loyalty,
may your deep personal loyalty to Jehovah,
distinguish you.
Thank you very much,
Brother Lippold, for that.
We all felt like we were students
in the Gilead classroom, didn’t we?
And certainly you helped us
to see the importance of loyalty.
Well, the next instructor, who’s also
a helper to the Teaching Committee,
Brother Mark Noumair,
is going to give this stirring encouragement
“March On With Jehovah!”
The young man received his assignment,
and it was not for the faint of heart.
He would have to tell
about the desolation of cherished cities,
the burning of Jehovah’s temple,
and the captivity of his people.
And for delivering these messages
(which they were not easy),
he would endure
scathing and murderous attempts on his life.
Now, on top of that,
he would experience
moments of discouragement,
isolation,
self-doubt.
When receiving his assignment,
this young man said:
‘Jehovah, I cannot do this.
I’m just a boy.’
The boy was from Anathoth,
and his name was Jeremiah.
But what would help him
be successful with this assignment?
It would be following and taking to heart
the very points that Brother Fleegle
brought out about faith.
He would need a deep, abiding faith
and trust in Jehovah.
And in addition to that,
he would need to learn how to march.
Jeremiah was ready to enter
the front lines of the battle
—the battle to defend pure worship
against those who hate it.
And like any good soldier,
one of the first things you learn
is how to march.
Now, marching is more challenging
than mere walking.
Marching requires determination.
It requires stamina, endurance,
and to keep moving forward
in a regular, steady step.
And as Jeremiah entered this battle,
he would need to learn how to march.
What would help him?
Recalling what was written in God’s Word
centuries before his time,
words recorded at Deuteronomy 31:6.
I want to read these words to you.
These words were so important to Jeremiah.
The context was when Moses was encouraging
confidence in Jehovah.
The nation of Israel was ready
to enter into the Promised Land.
They would face enemies.
They would face a fight, a battle.
But look at what Moses says
in verse 6 of Deuteronomy 31:
“Be courageous and strong.
“Do not be afraid
or struck with terror before them,
“for Jehovah your God
“is the one marching with you.
“[He’s marching with you.]
He will neither desert you nor abandon you.”
So how did Jehovah march alongside this boy?
At Jeremiah 1:8,
Jehovah tells Jeremiah:
“Do not be afraid
because of their appearance,
for ‘I am with you to save you.’”
Don’t be afraid.
In other words,
when a person marches with Jehovah,
you see, Jehovah marches with him,
boosting him along, making him strong.
It’s as if Jehovah told Jeremiah,
‘Don’t worry,
you just come and march with me.’
And for the next 67 years,
that’s exactly what Jeremiah did
in Jehovah’s strength.
Think about what happened
Jeremiah preached to hard-hearted people,
including wicked kings,
corrupt priests, apostates.
He did it, and as he marched,
he saw Jehovah march with him.
He was conscious of that fact.
Jehovah saved him
when imprisoned in a dungeon.
Jehovah supplied him
a daily ration of food during a famine.
Jehovah rescued him from a cistern.
You see, this was real.
This was tangible.
This was concrete.
It wasn’t made-up.
Jehovah was marching with him.
And as Jeremiah saw Jehovah’s support,
it strengthened him
and it gave him more confidence,
and Jehovah marched with him.
And then Jeremiah was ready
for the next trial.
Why do we bring this up?
Because your situation
is very similar to Jeremiah’s.
How so?
Along with your Gilead training,
you are being put on the front lines.
You’re going to be asked
to defend pure worship,
maybe like you never have before.
So we want you to stay in the battle.
We want you to keep marching.
For example, what if in your assignment,
opposition turns into outright persecution?
Or what if in your branch territory,
you face political upheaval or war?
What if you need
to risk your lives
to provide relief
like our brothers in and around Ukraine
are doing?
What if that happens?
Your brothers will be looking to you
as an example.
Will you be able to set that example?
Can you maintain that example?
Yes, you can.
Because when you march with Jehovah
—now listen carefully
when you march with Jehovah,
he does something very special for you
in moments of weakness.
Well, consider what happened to Jeremiah.
At one point,
it got so bad that he wanted to quit.
‘I’m quitting.’
Jeremiah 20:9:
‘I’m not going to mention Jehovah’s name.
‘I’m not going to talk about it anymore.
‘I’m discouraged.
I’m tired.
I’m exhausted.
I’m going to stop marching.’
He was losing his focus.
So how does Jehovah help him?
What did Jehovah do?
Did he say, ‘Well, Jeremiah, that’s it.
If you’re going to be exhausted,
I’ll find another prophet.’
No, Jehovah did not do that.
What did Jehovah do?
And this is a thought
we want you to take to heart,
Jeremiah 20:11.
How does Jehovah help him to keep marching?
“But Jehovah was with me
“[like a what, friend?
“like a brother?
No, no, no.]
like a fearsome warrior.”
So in what way
did Jehovah prove to be a fearsome warrior,
a mighty soldier,
standing right at Jeremiah’s side?
How did Jehovah do that?
Well, what happens in battle?
When a soldier sees
a fellow soldier stumble and fall,
what does he do?
He rushes to his side; he supports him;
he grabs him;
they go together;
he wraps his arm around him,
and they move to safety together.
This is what Jehovah did for Jeremiah.
In fact, Jeremiah tells us this
in chapter 20, and in verse 7.
What does Jeremiah say?
He experienced this.
He says:
“You used your strength against me,
and you prevailed.”
“You used your strength against me.”
What does that mean?
Jehovah used his strength
against Jeremiah’s weakness.
Seeing Jehovah do this for him
time and again, time and again,
enabled Jeremiah to accomplish
what he could have never accomplished
on his own.
This is the point we’re making for you.
All of these experiences
strengthen and transform
his natural shyness,
his feelings of inadequacy,
and his lack of confidence
into ironlike boldness.
Jehovah was with him
like a fearsome warrior.
Jehovah loved the commission
he gave Jeremiah.
He was working with Jeremiah
to fulfill this commission.
It was precious to Jehovah.
Just like your commission,
it’s precious to Jehovah.
So you can be assured
that Jehovah is going to do the same for you.
We want you to have that confidence.
In fact, one sister,
who not long ago graduated from Gilead,
experienced this firsthand.
Shortly after arriving in her assignment,
she was arrested.
Our sister was held captive
in a dungeonlike prison.
And during that time,
she was given meager rations of food
and was subjected
to painful, prolonged punishment.
How was she able to endure?
How could she stay strong?
How?
By marching with Jehovah.
And she never lost sight of the fact
that she was part of an army of marchers.
She was marching with the fearsome Warrior.
In fact, this is what she said:
“Thinking about my Gilead classmates
“and visualizing their faces gave me power.
“I kept their smiling faces in front of me.
“I imagined where each classmate sat
“—each row from left to right—
front to back.
“I recalled where they were from,
what work they did in their assignments.
“This made the time go by quickly,
and I felt no physical pain at all.
“I sang in my head Kingdom songs.
“The song I sang the most
was ‘Jehovah Is Your Name.’
“Another song that touched my heart deeply
“was song number 38,
‘He Will Make You Strong.’
“I made that song more personal
“by replacing the pronoun ‘you’ with ‘me.’
“This song helped me never to give up.
“I had no Bible.
“So each day, I meditated on Bible teachings
“such as everlasting life in Paradise
and a resurrection hope.
“These meditations gave me deep inner joy
“and a calm that cannot be described.
“At times, I thought about the possibility
of facing death,
but the fear of death did not consume me.”
Yes, she thought about the possibility
of facing death,
but the fear of death did not consume her.
The fearsome Warrior, Jehovah,
was marching with her.
No prison walls, no bars
can block Jehovah from marching with her.
And our sister was recently released
from prison.
So whatever your trials,
we don’t know
what trials you’re going to face.
You don’t know.
We don’t know.
But reflect on how Jehovah supports you.
Stay in the battle.
And when you reflect
on how Jehovah supports you,
it’s tangible, it’s real, it’s concrete.
Think about that.
Jehovah will never stop marching with you.
And remember, you are part of a large army.
You’re not alone.
Therefore, when you see
a fellow worshipper struggling,
don’t ignore them.
Help them not to fall behind.
Help them.
You’re part of an army.
You’ve been trained to do this.
That’s what school taught you:
not to be independent,
but to be interdependent,
not independen—interdependent
with your brothers and sisters.
That’s your job.
Be quick to help them back up.
Keep marching with Jehovah.
And although you don’t know
what challenges lie ahead,
you are prepared.
So with your marching orders in hand,
be courageous and strong,
knowing that each trial you face,
each trial you endure,
will make you stronger for the next one.
Be confident that you will always have
the fearsome Warrior,
the mighty Soldier marching by your side.
He’s there, Jehovah.
So now go
wherever the battle may take you.
Go,
and be determined to fulfill your commission
to support your brothers
as you march on with Jehovah.
What a powerful encouragement
—one that I’m sure you’ll remember
for many years to come!
And students, maybe I need to apologize.
I didn’t realize Anathoth
was going to be the buzz word.
You see, if I had realized that
in the beginning in my introduction,
I would have said,
“We need to follow the example of Jesus,
“who according to Matthew 16:14
people thought was Jeremiah,
who was from Anathoth.”
But anyway, you can take note of that.
But thank you again, Brother Noumair.
That was
a very encouraging and stimulating talk.
Although these talks
were directed to the Gilead graduates,
they contain
beneficial lessons for all of us.
We hope you enjoyed Part 1.
Parts 2 and 3 will be available on jw.org
later this month.
Our postcard is from the United States.
It’s a large territory encompassing
a variety of landscapes.
There are majestic mountains,
twisting ravines,
tropical islands,
and vast deserts.
Across this varied land
resides an even greater diversity of people.
To help all they can,
over 1.2 million publishers
preach in 114 languages!
Whether native speakers
or learners of a new language,
publishers try to reach the heart.
One of the largest language groups
in the United States is Haitian Creole.
There are approximately one million people
of Haitian descent in the branch territory
with over 10,000 publishers.
Haitians are a vibrant people as expressed
in their energetic dances,
their colorful clothing,
and their delicious food.
Just north of Miami, Florida,
there’s a community referred to
as “Little Haiti.”
It’s here where the 80 publishers
of the West Haitian Creole Congregation
search for lovers of truth.
They have witnessed
in parks and on street corners.
They have written letters and focused
on the family members
of their Bible students.
The congregation now
conducts on average 126 Bible studies!
With love, the brothers and sisters
of the West Haitian Creole Congregation
of Miami, Florida,
send their greetings
to the worldwide brotherhood!
From the World Headquarters
of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
this is JW Broadcasting!