What can you do on a social network?
You can connect with people;
(a lot  of people)
share your photos;
tell jokes;
post your thoughts on,
well, just about anything;
And see what all your friends are up to.
It’s pretty easy
—and that’s  the problem.
Sometimes it’s a little too  easy.
You see, a social network may look harmless,
but once you log in,
watch out!
It could be a dangerous place.
So if your parents
allow you to have an account,
you have to be smart,
social-network smart.
Follow the front-page rule.
Don’t post anything
that you wouldn’t want to see on the TV news
or the front page of the newspaper.
And that includes
personal information like
your phone number,
where you live,
and where you go to school.
Never tell people when you’re not home
or when you’re going on vacation.
It may seem harmless,
but that’s exactly the kind of information
thieves can use to break into your house
or even steal your identity!
Now let’s look at your reputation.
Your photos and comments say a lot about you.
So, if you’ve made a fool of yourself, ask,
‘Is this how I really want people to view me
—not just now but in the future,
like at a job interview?’
At Proverbs 22:1,
the Bible says a good reputation
is ‘worth more than silver and gold.’
Don’t let that Delete key fool you.
Posting something on any social network
is kind of like writing in permanent ink.
OK, so you’re careful
about what  you share.
Now think
about who  you’re sharing it with.
Who are your friends?
Some people have hundreds of online friends.
Some have thousands.
So you may think,
‘The more friends, the better, right?’
Actually, no!
That kind of thinking
can blow up in your face.
You see,
when you connect with online friends,
you are also indirectly connecting
with their  friends
And their friends’  friends.
That means
you may find yourself seeing posts
from people you don’t even know
—people whose morals and beliefs
may be different from yours.
They may use bad language
or post about things you know are wrong.
Those just aren’t the kind of friends
you want to hang around with
—not even online.
And there’s another danger.
At Psalm 26:4,
the Bible warns about people
“who hide what they are.”
They pretend to be someone they are not
and may seem super friendly,
but they can be dangerous.
So when it comes to friends,
you need to be picky.
The safest friends online
are ones you already know offline.
There’s one more thing to think about:
It has to do with your time.
Checking out the latest posts
can be addictive.
So let’s set some limits,
and don’t let your online  life
get in the way of your real  life.
You know,
connecting with others online
can be fun and safe
as long as you look out for all the dangers.
So the next time you log in, be smart,
social-network smart.