‎Many people believe that it doesn’t matter
‎which religion you choose,
‎that religions are like different roads that lead
‎to the same destination
‎—lasting blessings from God.
‎But can that be true?
‎Does God accept all forms of worship?
‎The Bible itself describes worship as two roads:
‎One is spacious
‎with many people on it.
‎The other is cramped
‎with only a few finding it.
‎Only the cramped road
‎represents acceptable worship,
‎leading to life
‎and blessings from God.
‎How can we tell if we are on the correct path?
‎Imagine that you’re lost.
‎You stop someone to ask for directions.
‎One person says to head east;
‎another says to go west.
‎Finally, someone with a map shows you
‎that the destination is actually north.
‎Which one would you believe?
‎The Bible is like that map,
‎leading us to blessings from God.
‎So why are there so many conflicting beliefs?
‎For example,
‎many religions teach that the human soul
‎lives eternally in a spiritual realm,
‎while others believe that they are reborn
‎in another body or form.
‎This is just one example
‎of the many religious beliefs
‎in conflict with one another.
‎Could all religions
‎really be teaching the truth?
‎According to the map,
‎the dead know nothing at all.
‎In due time, God will restore them to life
‎and righteous ones will live forever on earth.
‎If the Bible is clear on this teaching,
‎what about other matters,
‎such as our personal conduct?
‎We may belong to a religion,
‎but if our conduct offends God,
‎our worship may be futile.
‎The Bible teaches that many people today
‎would be “without self-control,
‎“fierce,
‎without love of goodness.”
‎However, it also says
‎that true worshippers of God
‎would be peaceable,
‎controlling their speech
‎and actions.
‎Rather than saying
‎there are many religions that please God,
‎the Bible says there is only one faith.
‎True worship leads a person
‎to a good relationship with God
‎and everlasting life.
‎You may wonder,
‎‘How can I recognize true worship?’
‎That question and others are answered
‎in lesson 10 of the brochure
‎Good News From God!
‎You can download a copy from jw.org.
‎Jehovah’s Witnesses
‎would be happy to study the Bible with you.
‎Fill in the online request for a Bible study,
‎and a Witness in your area
‎will call to discuss the Bible
‎at a time and place convenient for you.