Well, it’s finally happened.
You think you’ve found the person
of your dreams, and now . . .
You’re hopelessly in love!
Or are you?
How can you tell if it’s really love?
The key is:
You’ve got to learn
the differences between attraction,
infatuation,
and actual love.
Attraction is based on what you see.
You know, how a person looks and acts.
The problem is, what you see
isn’t always what you get.
So then,
what is infatuation?
Infatuation is not only about what you see;
it’s about how you feel.
You may have romantic feelings.
But those feelings can change . . .
and fast!
Infatuation may seem like love.
But because it’s based only
on how you feel at the moment, . . .
it can just fall apart.
So how do you know if it’s really love?
One that will last?
Real love grows
when two people are kind,
hard-working,
and share the same spiritual outlook.
At 1 Corinthians 13:5,
the Bible says that real love
‘doesn’t look for its own interests.’
For example,
that guy you like so much,
how does he handle money?
Does he have to drink alcohol
to have a good time?
What are his goals?
Is he really working toward them?
Or is he all talk and no action?
And what about that girl
you just can’t stop thinking about?
Who are her friends?
And how does she treat them?
How does she treat her family?
There’s a lot to learn about another person.
It takes time!
So before you get swept off your feet,
remember:
Attraction is based on what you see.
Infatuation is based on what you feel.
But real love . . .
is based on what you know.