January 21, 2017, became a special day
for deaf people in Japan.
Jehovah’s Witnesses released
the book of Matthew
in Japanese Sign Language.
What, though, was behind these smiles?
When I used to read the Japanese Bible,
I really didn’t understand it,
so I forced myself to read—not much of a joy.
Right, it was hard to understand
and explain to people.
The Bible, written in a language
we do not know, will not move our heart.
Having no sign-language Bible
was a huge disadvantage
when it came to cultivating a longing for God.
When making shepherding calls,
reasoning on a scripture
with a deaf person was difficult if that scripture
wasn’t translated into sign language.
There is a Bible in American Sign Language,
so I was envious and wanted to see the Bible
in Japanese Sign Language so much.
At last, approval was given for Bible translation
into Japanese Sign Language.
I noticed that the translation team
offered a prayer
before they started each day’s work.
Also, when faced
with difficult translation problems,
they relied on Jehovah’s holy spirit
through prayers
so that they could exercise good judgment.
It was impressive.
There are various processes
needed for God’s Word
to jump off the page
and reach the heart of deaf people.
They considered carefully
how to express scriptures
so that deaf people would understand.
Let’s take an example:
“the lilies of the field” at Matthew 6:28.
I wasn’t able to understand
Matthew chapter 6 until now.
I always thought,
‘“Birds of heaven” and “lilies of the field,”
What do they have to do
with “seeking first the Kingdom”?’
The translators individually read and research
the source text
to fully understand what they’ll translate.
Then the team meets to discuss the text
and explore ideas
for translating certain concepts.
After the translation is complete,
the assigned brother signs the translation
to prepare the prompt video.
Then studio recording takes place,
referencing the prompt video.
The recorded movie is carefully edited
and prepared for delivery.
In this case,
the signer pretends to be a flower
and weaves his own petals
and sews them on his face.
Then he asks,
“Flowers don’t do that, do they?”
God’s Word coming off the pages
has reached the heart of deaf people.
I understood for the first time
that Jehovah is kindly teaching us,
‘If you seek the Kingdom first,
I’ll give you everything you need.
Don’t worry.’
I was watching it
on the train on my way to work.
I thought, ‘Wow, this is so good!’
I was absorbed in the video,
and I missed my train station.
So I changed trains, but again,
I was watching the video
and missed my station again!
The book of Matthew is that interesting.
Humans have beneficial feelings
because we are created in God’s image.
But because of Satan’s system of things,
these feelings are driven away.
However, when you show God’s Word
to people or read it yourself,
innate beneficial feelings
well up in our hearts.
I strongly feel that God’s Word
has the power to do that.
Just like a child grows up
listening to what their father says,
I can be closer to my Father,
Jehovah, by watching him
speak to me
in my native tongue, sign language.
Comments from deaf brothers show
that the sign-language Bible
talks to their heart directly.
I imagine that Jehovah loves our brothers,
and his face is shining.
And the faces of our brothers
are also shining.
Now by means of having God’s living Word
in the language of their heart,
our deaf brothers and sisters
are seeing Jehovah’s face shining.