Many people equate drinking
with having a good time.
But at Proverbs 23:32,
the Bible says that alcohol
can ‘bite like a snake.’
Are there laws
on drinking alcohol where you live?
If so, you could be fined,
be sentenced to community service,
lose your freedom to drive,
or even go to jail.
Even if none of those things happen,
alcohol can lower your inhibitions
—and not in a good way.
Under the influence,
you could say or do things
you’ll later regret.
But what if you’re at a party
and unexpectedly find
that some are drinking
and heading for trouble?
What would you do?
The Bible says that an intelligent person
sees trouble coming and avoids it.
Stop and think.
What might happen if you stay?
How could you leave before trouble comes
without inviting ridicule?
Here’s a tip:
Make a plan with your parents
to call or text if you need to leave early.
How about this?
What would you do
if someone pressures you to drink?
At Romans 6:16, the Bible indicates
that when you let others
control your decisions,
you become their slave.
You could just follow along
and let your peers rule your life.
Or you could give a firm response
—perhaps something like,
“No thanks!” or “Sorry, I’m not into that!”
What if you’re out with friends
and realize the driver has been drinking?
According to the Bible,
the person who spends time with fools
“will fare badly.”
What could happen
if you let that person drive you home?
What other options do you have?
Try this:
Avoid situations
where you’ll be with a driver
who has a reputation
for drinking and driving.
Always have a Plan B for transportation.
Remember, you don’t have to drink
to have a good time,
and you don’t have to associate with people
who think that you do.
Have the courage to think past the drink.