Nearly all religions teach
that part of a person survives death.
But what does the Bible teach?
God created the first man, Adam,
from the dust.
He had the opportunity to live forever.
But when he deliberately disobeyed God,
he was told that he would return to the dust
—ceasing to exist.
What about others who died after Adam?
When Jesus was told
that his friend Lazarus died,
Jesus did not say
that Lazarus had gone to heaven.
Rather, he said:
“Our friend has fallen asleep.”
What did he mean?
Just as someone in a deep sleep
is inactive
and unaware of his surroundings,
the dead are not conscious
of anything at all.
Further, just as a person
can be awakened from a deep sleep,
the Bible shows that it is possible
to be awakened from death.
Jesus did just that
for his friend Lazarus.
Lazarus had been dead for four days.
If some part of Lazarus
had survived his death
and gone to heaven,
would Jesus take him out of heaven
and force him to live on earth again?
No.
Lazarus was asleep in the grave.
Jesus gave him back his life
and reunited him with his family.
The Bible promises a time
when many people
will be resurrected from the dead,
just as Lazarus was.
Jesus spoke of this wonderful hope
when he said:
“The one who exercises faith in me,
even though he dies,
will come to life.”
You may wonder:
‘Who will return to life?
And what does the resurrection
tell us about Jehovah God?’
Those questions are answered in lesson 6
of the brochure Good News From God!
You can download a copy from jw.org.
Jehovah’s Witnesses would be happy
to study the Bible with you.
Fill in the online request for a Bible study,
and a Witness in your area
will call to discuss the Bible
at a time and place convenient for you.