‎Many people believe that it doesn’t matter
多くの人は どんな宗教を選んでも
大した差はない と考えています
‎which religion you choose,
‎that religions are like different roads that lead
どの宗教も道は違っても
‎to the same destination
同じ目的地に向かっていると言うのです
‎—lasting blessings from God.
しかし，本当にそうでしょうか
‎But can that be true?
‎Does God accept all forms of worship?
どんな宗教でも神に受け入れられますか
‎The Bible itself describes worship as two roads:
聖書は宗教を2本の道に例えています
大勢の人が進んでいる広い道と
‎One is spacious
‎with many people on it.
‎The other is cramped
‎with only a few finding it.
少数の人が見いだしている狭い道です
狭い道だけが神に受け入れられる
宗教を表わしていて
‎Only the cramped road
‎represents acceptable worship,
それは命と神からの祝福に通じています
‎leading to life
‎and blessings from God.
‎How can we tell if we are on the correct path?
どうすれば自分が正しい道に
いるかどうかが分かるでしょうか
‎Imagine that you’re lost.
道に迷ったとしましょう
‎You stop someone to ask for directions.
人に道を尋ねます
ある人は東へ
‎One person says to head east;
別の人は西へ行くように と言います
‎another says to go west.
‎Finally, someone with a map shows you
でも 地図を持っている人が
北に行くべきだと教えてくれます
‎that the destination is actually north.
‎Which one would you believe?
あなたはだれの言うことを信じますか
‎The Bible is like that map,
聖書は地図のようなもので
‎leading us to blessings from God.
わたしたちを素晴らしい将来に導きます
では なぜこれほど多くの
異なる教えがあるのでしょうか
‎So why are there so many conflicting beliefs?
例えば 多くの宗教は人間の霊魂が
‎For example,
‎many religions teach that the human soul
死後の世界でずっと
生きると教えています
‎lives eternally in a spiritual realm,
しかし他の宗教は 生まれ変わって
‎while others believe that they are reborn
別の人間
‎in another body or form.
動物
植物になると教えています
‎This is just one example
これは 互いに食い違っている
教えの一例にすぎません
‎of the many religious beliefs
‎in conflict with one another.
すべての宗教が真理を教えていると
本当に言えるでしょうか
‎Could all religions
‎really be teaching the truth?
‎According to the map,
‎the dead know nothing at all.
聖書という地図には
死んだ者には何の
意識もないと書かれています
神はご予定の時に人々を生き返らせ
‎In due time, God will restore them to life
‎and righteous ones will live forever on earth.
義なる者たちは地上で
永遠に生きるのです
このように聖書の教えは明快です
‎If the Bible is clear on this teaching,
では わたしたちの生き方については
何を教えているでしょうか
‎what about other matters,
‎such as our personal conduct?
‎We may belong to a religion,
もし わたしたちが何かの
宗教に属していても
‎but if our conduct offends God,
‎our worship may be futile.
神に喜ばれない生き方をしているなら
その崇拝は無駄なものになります
‎The Bible teaches that many people today
聖書は 多くの人々が「自制心のない者
‎would be “without self-control,
‎“fierce,
粗暴な者 善良さを愛さない者」
になると予告していました
‎without love of goodness.”
しかし 神の真の崇拝者は
平和を求めます
‎However, it also says
‎that true worshippers of God
‎would be peaceable,
そして そのことを自分の言葉と
‎controlling their speech
行動によって示します
‎and actions.
神に喜ばれる宗教は
‎Rather than saying
‎there are many religions that please God,
幾つもあるわけではありません
‎the Bible says there is only one faith.
聖書によると 真の宗教は一つだけです
‎True worship leads a person
真の崇拝の道は神との良い関係と
‎to a good relationship with God
永遠の命に通じています
‎and everlasting life.
‎You may wonder,
では 真の宗教を
どのように見分けられますか
‎‘How can I recognize true worship?’
‎That question and others are answered
その質問の答えは
「神からの良い知らせ」という
冊子の第10課にあります
‎in lesson 10 of the brochure
‎Good News From God!
この冊子はjw.orgから
ダウンロードできます
‎You can download a copy from jw.org.
エホバの証人は 喜んで聖書を
学ぶお手伝いをいたします
‎Jehovah’s Witnesses
‎would be happy to study the Bible with you.
‎Fill in the online request for a Bible study,
jw.orgで聖書レッスンを
お申し込みください
‎and a Witness in your area
お近くのエホバの証人が
‎will call to discuss the Bible
ご都合のよい時間に
ご希望の場所へお伺いします
‎at a time and place convenient for you.