When you were younger,
your parents were probably the first ones
you ran to for advice.
But now you might feel
that your parents
just don’t understand you.
Deep down,
you still want to talk to them.
But what if you try,
and you feel
they just aren’t listening?
Well, you could raise your voice,
but shouting won’t make
your parents more receptive
and won’t show them
the respect they deserve.
You could give your parents
the silent treatment,
but the Bible suggests
at Proverbs 15:22
that things only get more frustrating
when you don’t talk.
So saying nothing
really gets you nowhere.
It’s smarter to just wait
for a better time to talk.
Or you might even write them
an honest but respectful letter
expressing how you feel.
But what if the situation is flipped?
Yeah, that’s right.
Your parents want to talk,
but you don’t.
Maybe you had a bad day at school.
It’s true that choosing to talk
when you don’t feel like it could mean
the conversation will be forced,
which makes everyone tense
and leads to poor communication.
But refusing to talk
means you’ll still be stressed,
and your parents might think
that the problem is bigger than it is,
or worse,
that you’re hiding something.
Instead, you could start off
talking with them
on a subject that isn’t as stressful
or even one that makes you happy.
That will ease the tension
or get rid of it all together.
The bottom line:
Your parents want to help you
and you can use their help.
So choose your words carefully,
deliver them respectfully,
and think of your parents as friends,
not enemies.
Because let’s face it,
you’ll need all the allies
you can get to cope
with the challenges that lie ahead.