Our world is filled with breathtaking beauty.
Why did God create the earth
in such a special way?
Even from space,
it stands alone as wonderfully unique.
God created the earth
with an abundance of water.
He placed it
at just the right distance from the sun
and set its rotation at just the right speed.
He gave it a moon
to stabilize the earth’s tilt,
contributing to consistent seasons.
And he created
an amazing variety of living creatures
to share the earth with.
Why did God put forth so much effort
to create this beautiful earth?
Because he wanted to give
the first human couple, Adam and Eve,
a wonderful home.
As long as they obeyed God,
they and their children would live forever
and expand the Paradise garden
to cover the entire globe.
This was God’s purpose for the earth.
So what happened?
Why isn’t the earth a paradise?
Sadly, Adam and Eve chose to disobey God.
They eventually grew old and died.
Paradise was lost.
But did this mean that God’s original purpose
for the earth had changed?
Imagine that a father decides to build
a beautiful home for his son.
He gives it to him as a gift.
But instead of being thankful,
the son neglects his father’s gift
and the house falls into disrepair.
What would a loving father do?
Would he destroy the house
and all his hard work?
No, he would patiently save it
for a family member who would appreciate it.
In a similar way,
although Adam rejected the gift,
the Bible tells us
that God didn’t change
his purpose for the earth.
His purpose still stands.
He wants to give this gift,
an earth-wide paradise,
to you to enjoy
in happiness and health forever!
You may wonder:
‘How will Paradise be restored?
And who will live there?’
Those questions are answered in lesson 5
of the brochure Good News From God!
You can download a copy from jw.org.
Jehovah’s Witnesses would be happy
to study the Bible with you.
Fill in the online request for a Bible study,
and a Witness in your area
will call to discuss the Bible
at a time and place convenient for you.