Do you think it’s about time
you had more freedom?
You may think you’re ready
to be treated as an adult,
but do your parents agree?
Have you proven to them
that you can handle more freedom?
You see, if you want more freedom,
you have to gain your parents’ trust.
Earning their trust takes time.
But every time
you prove yourself responsible,
you get one step closer to your goal.
Some ways you can show
you are trustworthy are:
diligently completing your chores,
especially without being reminded;
managing your time wisely
and being punctual;
taking care of your things;
showing that you can handle
money in a responsible way;
and following through
on the promises you make.
Of course, nobody’s perfect.
So if you make a mistake,
it’s not the end of the world.
Follow the Bible’s advice
at Hebrews 13:18
to conduct yourself
“honestly in all things.”
Tell the truth
and be straightforward.
If you admit your mistake
and apologize,
your parents will see
that you are willing
to take responsibility
for your actions,
and they’ll appreciate
your honesty.
But what if you feel
that despite your best efforts,
your parents still aren’t giving
you enough freedom?
Don’t just get annoyed
—talk to them!
Respectfully ask what they think
you need to do to earn their trust.
You may be surprised
to learn of some other areas
where you can show
you’re responsible.
At 2 Corinthians 13:5,
the Bible says:
“Keep proving what you . . . are.”
So you need to build up
a record of consistency.
That way you’ll prove
you’re worthy of trust.
Every step you take
brings you closer to your goal.
Of course, trust is much harder
to gain than it is to lose.
But the effort is worth it.
When your parents see you
working hard to earn their trust,
they will likely be happy
to give you more freedom,
and you’ll be another step closer
to becoming a responsible adult.