Growing up in the South
during the time of segregation
—blacks and whites—
we couldn’t mix.
And not only that, they had signs
to keep you knowing
where you were supposed to go.
I couldn’t understand
why we couldn’t get along.
Fifty cents.
Yes, Sir.
Thank you, Sir.
Grandma, he’s just a boy.
Why are you saying “Sir”?
Be quiet.
I want you to know your place.
I told her after we got back on the truck:
“You know what?
I’ll never hold my head down!”
My grandmother
knew I had a love for the Bible
because I would
always read the Bible as a kid.
But I couldn’t understand it.
I used to pray,
“What makes us so different?”
You know,
“Why can’t we live together?”
I met a group,
and this group was like
what I really wanted to be in.
They were about politics.
They said, “We’re fighting injustice.”
And when they said
that word “injustice,” it was like,
‘Yeah, this is what I want to be in, right?
‘To be part of something that can change
and make people united, right?’
That was my goal.
We started protesting about police brutality,
and I think that’s what a lot of people,
you know,
were focusing on.
I liked some of the things
that they were doing,
but they trained us every,
every day in military training.
We learned how to use weapons
and stuff like that.
And so I’m thinking:
‘This is not what I want to be in.
This is not what I joined.’
So I started going back to God again
—to reading the Bible—
because it was like
I’m not changing anything.
The Bible that I was reading
was the King James Version.
So I was reading it, reading it, reading it,
but I couldn’t understand it.
We went to Jamaica,
and we saw this Bible,
the New World Translation.
And I started reading it,
and it made so much sense!
And I could understand it,
and it wasn’t “thee” and “thou.”
I was like, ‘Wow!’
You know, like,
‘This is the one I want to get.’
One day, two women knocked on the door.
I didn’t know they were Jehovah’s Witnesses.
All I could see was that Bible.
And I said,
“Where did you get that Bible from?”
And they said,
“OK, we’ll bring you one.”
And they did.
So they brought me the Bible,
but I didn’t know I was going to have
a Bible study that came along with it.
The first time I went
to a convention of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
it was like ten thousand people.
When I went in there and I saw
all these different faces
and different colors,
it was like Jehovah showing me:
“Hey, Rafika, remember you were asking me
“about all different people
getting together and being one?
See, I’m not partial;
they do get along; we are unified.”
And it just made me feel so good inside.
Yes!
This is the organization
that I want to be in.
I just see people as people, you know,
and I can preach
and be friends with anybody.
Now that I know
what the Bible really teaches,
I have a wonderful life
because I know
that only God and his government
can bring about peace.
Just like how Jehovah
unified everybody,
I want everybody
to be unified
and come to know Jehovah,
just like I know him.
Jehovah answered my prayer.