Sometimes I get words
mixed up and backwards,
so it can be kind of challenging.
So do I like reading?
Not really.
I don’t know.
I find books not interesting and boring.
You know, I just get completely distracted.
I have to mentally prepare myself to read
because there are so many things
you could be doing.
I don’t enjoy reading,
but I do like reading the Bible.
For me,
it’s more than a book.
It’s definitely worth it.
Some people may say
it’s not relevant for today.
But when you do look into it,
there are things
you can learn from all the time.
It’s helped me to think before I speak.
I find that I’m actually more concerned
with other people
—their well-being, how they’re doing,
and looking out for them.
I think Bible reading
has made me a better person.
It gives me a little push for the day.
My favorite book in the Bible
would probably be the Psalms
because it’s easy
for me to understand
and it’s really interesting to me.
The young people,
they can go through jw.org
and get the Bible
—several different copies of the Bible—
right there.
We’ll type in the certain—
that certain scripture
and there’ll be articles about it.
Another thing I’m loving is the new videos
—an introduction to this book of the Bible.
It just takes two or three minutes
and you can understand
what you’re about to read
—that book—
and that makes a huge difference.
I go by topics or what interests me.
I look for something that’s interesting,
that’s very—
that touches me directly;
it just becomes an enjoyable process.
It’s very, very relevant,
and it’s very important.
And you can find happiness.
I mean, who doesn’t want that?