Hello, everyone!
I bring you warm greetings
from the Governing Body
and the United States Bethel family.
We want you to know
that we love you all very much,
we’re concerned about you,
and we pray for you each and every day.
We know that more and more
of you are being affected
by the coronavirus pandemic.
You can’t go to work.
You can’t go to school.
You can’t go to the Kingdom Hall
or preach from house to house.
Some of you have lost your jobs,
and you have no idea how
you are going to be able to feed your family.
Others have family members who live far away.
There’s no one else in the house.
They’re worried about them.
And sadly, some are mourning
the loss of loved ones
who have been victims of the disease.
We want you to know
that our hearts ache for you.
We’re so sorry for your loss.
Now, these are very stressful times,
but it’s important to remember one thing:
No friend of Jehovah
is ever truly alone.
Through his holy spirit, Jehovah can help us;
he can sustain us
even if there’s no one else in the house.
Another way Jehovah is helping us
is by means of caring shepherds.
And this is in line
with the promise that he himself made.
We’re going to read Jeremiah 23:4,
and you’ll see how this prophecy
is being fulfilled today.
I’m just going to read a part of it.
Here’s the promise Jehovah made:
that he was
going to “raise up . . . shepherds
who will really shepherd them.”
And then at the end it says:
“None [of them] will be missing.”
Well, can you see how that promise
is being fulfilled today in the elders?
Just think of all the work
our elders are doing
to make sure that we don’t miss out
on spiritual food, for example.
They are arranging for us
to tie in to congregation meetings,
they set up shepherding calls
using videoconferencing,
they arrange for meetings for field service,
and they make sure
we have telephone territory
and letter-writing territory.
Of course, these shepherds
are also concerned
about your physical well-being.
So from time to time,
they may also check in on us
to make sure that we have basic food items,
medications, and other necessary things.
If they do that, don’t be shy:
Let the elders know your needs.
They may also provide practical suggestions
on how you can protect your health.
Now, as you can imagine,
when the pandemic broke out,
the elders had a lot of questions.
They’d never dealt with this before.
And suddenly, they needed to do all kinds
of things that they hadn’t done before:
set up videoconferencing accounts,
learn how to use new apps like Skype®
and Zoom—what’s that?—
and become familiar with how
to organize
an entire congregation meeting online.
It’s been a huge task for our brothers,
and we want to commend them
for the excellent job they’re doing.
The elders had a lot of questions,
but through his organization,
Jehovah provided the direction they needed.
And an experience
from Canada will bring this out.
Let’s watch a video
in which Brother Warren Shewfelt,
a member of the Canada Branch Committee,
explains what happened in Canada.
In the face of the coronavirus threat,
a body of elders near the Canada branch
recently met to determine
how to go forward with congregation meetings.
They had so many questions
about how to balance
the spiritual needs of the brothers
with government regulations on gatherings.
They prayed to Jehovah for guidance.
But as their meeting went on,
it still wasn’t clear to them how to proceed.
And then one of the brothers
noticed on his electronic device
a letter from the branch
with instructions to the elders.
As they read through it,
it answered all their questions
and even some they hadn’t anticipated.
They viewed this
as Jehovah’s answer to their prayers,
but now they had
less than 24 hours to prepare
their first-ever congregation meeting
by videoconference.
Prayerfully, they followed
the instructions step-by-step,
and the next evening,
the whole congregation gathered
for a meeting by videoconference.
The attendance was well over 100 percent,
and one of the families who were
in attendance wrote to the elders:
“We are so grateful for all the effort
“to provide this
much needed spiritual food live.
“It was exactly what we needed.
Thank you.”
What an encouraging experience that was!
Thanks, Warren.
We really appreciate it.
And, you know, it reminds me
of what the prophet Isaiah foretold
at Isaiah 65:24:
“Even before they call . . . , I will answer;
while they are yet speaking, I will hear.”
When we think of caring elders,
our circuit overseers come to mind
because they’re often a vital link
between the branch
and the congregation when disaster strikes.
That reminds me of an experience
my wife and I had back in 2010.
I was assigned to do
a shepherding visit to Haiti
about 10 days after a tremendous earthquake
took hundreds of thousands of lives.
And sadly, 154 of our brothers
also lost their lives.
Well, I met with the traveling overseers
in the country,
and I learned that some of them
had lost members of their own family.
But they were at the forefront
of the rescue effort,
so they hadn’t had time
to mourn their own loss.
They were still looking
for survivors of the quake.
So, what did Jehovah say?
“I will raise up . . .
shepherds who will really shepherd them.
None [of them] will be missing.”
And those shepherds in Haiti
were going to make sure
that none of their brothers
and sisters were missing.
Do you know that our fine traveling overseers
are continuing to serve congregations
as best they can during this pandemic?
How is that possible?
In this encouraging video report,
Brother Paul Echon,
who is a member
of the Philippines Branch Committee,
tells how even remote congregations
are being cared for.
This is interesting.
Let’s watch.
A circuit overseer in the Philippines
wrote regarding his experience
using the videoconferencing app Zoom
to visit two
of the remotest congregations in his circuit.
Normal travel to these islands by small boat
may take between five to eight hours,
depending on sea conditions
and the size of waves from the Pacific Ocean.
Because of the COVID-19 pandemic,
travel restrictions to Patnanungan
and Jomalig islands were implemented.
The circuit overseer and his wife
prayed fervently to Jehovah,
asking for a possible means
to still visit the congregations
the last two weeks of March.
Just days later, they received
a letter from the branch office
about alternative ways
of making congregation visits.
This included
the possibility of virtual visits
with the use of online conferencing tools.
The circuit overseer
immediately informed the elders,
and they excitedly tested
their newfound means of communication.
The visits were a success!
The brothers and sisters were so thankful
and really felt Jehovah’s love for them.
Reflecting on his experience,
the circuit overseer said:
“It is obvious that no coronavirus
“can prevent our Almighty God, Jehovah,
“from providing encouragement
to his servants today.
“We are determined more than ever
to help and encourage
“the brothers to continue trusting
in Jehovah completely,
“as mentioned at Psalm 91:2, which says:
‘You are my refuge and my stronghold.’”
What did we read at Jeremiah 23:4?
“None [of them] will be missing.”
Jehovah knows where all his sheep are,
and he arranges for them to be cared for.
Thanks, Paul.
And please give our warm love and greetings
to our brothers in the Philippines.
We love them all very much.
So, what do we want to take away
from this brief discussion?
Two points: First, we believe that Jehovah
will continue to guide his organization
every step of the way.
And it’s been faith-strengthening
to see how, at times,
the organization has been
one or even two steps ahead
of the authorities
in giving direction to protect the flock.
So that’s the first point:
Jehovah will continue
to direct the organization.
Second, what is one of the means
by which he will do that?
By providing loving shepherds
to carry out that direction.
And over them is the One who said:
“I am the fine shepherd;
“the fine shepherd surrenders his life
in behalf of the sheep.”
Brothers and sisters,
take good care of yourselves.
Don’t take chances.
Obey the instructions
of “the superior authorities.”
We at Bethel are extremely conscientious
about following
the guidelines we’ve received.
So if the authorities tell you
to stay home, stay home.
Practice social distancing.
Now, keep up-to-date with the news,
but don’t obsess.
Don’t watch it too much.
It can be just too discouraging.
Now, what season are we in?
Memorial season.
So, what should be the real focus
of our thoughts at this time?
The incredible gift of the ransom,
the love of Jehovah God,
the love of Christ Jesus.
Those things should be
the object of our thoughts.
And when you feel alone or stressed-out,
repeat to yourself the heart-cheering words
that we find at Hebrews 13:5:
“I will never leave you,
and I will never abandon you.”
Be assured of our warm love and prayers.
From the World Headquarters
of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
this is JW Broadcasting®.