Please watch the following video
that contains heartfelt comments
from persecuted brothers
and sisters in Russia,
and see why we have no reason
to fear persecution.
I was horrified when several masked officers
broke down two doors and burst into the home
where the meeting was being held.
Everything happened at once
—loud sounds, noise,
the order:
“Everyone sit on the floor!”
I was overcome with fear when they put me
in handcuffs, placed me in the police van,
and took me to jail.
I was afraid
because I didn’t know how long
I would be there and what was awaiting me.
When I was being interrogated,
I was afraid that I might be unfaithful
to Jehovah and let my brothers down.
After being detained, I was mostly afraid
about what I would face in prison
—whom I would encounter, how to act,
how others would treat me—
the unknown.
When one of the officers
began to describe
how bad life is behind bars,
I imagined that behind the officer
stood an angel just like the one
who supported Daniel in the illustration.
This helped me to calm down
and not to panic or be afraid.
That’s how Jehovah supported me.
At the first court appearance,
when I was brought out,
the brothers’ feelings
impelled them to show support somehow,
and they began applauding.
How that encouraged me
that they were with me!
Fervent and sincere prayers to Jehovah
helped me to cope with these fears.
Isaiah 30:15
gave me much support.
I realized that tranquility
and trust in Jehovah
are now the most important things.
Understanding this
made things much easier for me.
We took the elevator down to the first floor,
the doors opened,
and there stood a large crowd
of our brothers and sisters
—and they all began clapping.
When I saw that, my emotions just welled up,
and I got a lump in my throat.
I felt as if I had wings;
I felt the “great cloud of witnesses.”
I prayed to Jehovah
for calmness, courage, and wisdom
and that he help me
not to bring reproach on his holy name.
Almost immediately,
“the peace of God” came over me,
and I was calm.
The unpleasant sensations did not go away,
but I was no longer afraid.
While overcoming our fear,
my wife and I tried to go out
in service every day.
When you don’t concentrate on yourself
but focus on helping others, fear disappears.
Something that helped me
to cope with my fears
is hope,
looking at the situation
through Jehovah’s eyes,
seeing what will happen next
that this is not the end of the situation,
but only a difficult phase
through which you can pass.
I was helped to cope with my fear
by the words of the song:
“Take one day at a time;
“leave tomorrow until tomorrow;
peace is what I find.”
I understood that it was important
to solve problems as they came up
and not to be troubled
by what might never happen.
Fear is interesting;
that is, in principle, fear can be
inside a person, and if someone is afraid,
that is not shameful.
But the question is,
Can you overcome this fear?
Can you get the fear under your control?
Can you overcome this surge of negativity?
And when my heart persuaded me to get scared,
then I started to pray.
I prayed to Jehovah to give me courage
and not be afraid of anyone or anything.
I still say to myself,
‘Feliks, do not fear anybody
or anything except Jehovah!’
Dear brothers and sisters,
I really appreciate your support.
I’m very happy for all your letters,
for all your thoughts, for all your prayers.
I really appreciate it a lot.
I try to do my best,
and I try to serve Jehovah
in the best way that I can.
I will do that forever!