On behalf of the Governing Body,
we warmly commend you for your desire
to expand your service to Jehovah
and your interest
in submitting an application
to serve as a temporary volunteer
or as a member
of the Worldwide Order
of Special Full-Time Servants
of Jehovah’s Witnesses.
By making yourself available
to serve in this unique way,
you imitate the faithful prophet Isaiah,
who said at Isaiah 6:8:
“Here I am! Send me!”
Submitting your application
may open a door of opportunity
to serve Jehovah and his organization
in a variety of ways.
Of course, there’s a place
for everyone in Jehovah’s service.
Whether we’re working hard
as a congregation publisher,
a regular pioneer, a Bethelite,
or on a theocratic construction project,
we have the satisfaction of knowing
that Jehovah treasures what we’re doing
because of our heartfelt love for him.
Hebrews 6:10 says:
“God is not unrighteous
so as to forget your work
“and the love you showed
for his name by ministering
and continuing to minister
to the holy ones.”
Before submitting an application
for expanded theocratic service,
it’s important to consider prayerfully
how you’ll respond
to the questions on the application.
Hebrews 13:18 says:
“We wish to conduct ourselves
honestly in all things.”
So you should be honest
in answering the questions
on the application,
especially those that have to do
with your physical health
and spiritual health.
The work being done at Bethel
and on theocratic construction projects
requires good physical,
emotional, and mental health.
However, you may have
a chronic health problem
that requires the regular attention
of a physician
or must be treated with medication.
If you have
a significant limitation in this way,
it would be better for you
to continue your faithful service
in the field
with your local congregation
and, if possible,
in the regular pioneer service.
If you’re not sure
whether your health situation
would prevent you
from submitting an application,
the elders
in your congregation can help you.
They can review with you
the specific application questions
that deal with health matters
so that you personally may determine
whether or not you should apply.
Regardless of where we’re serving,
we need Jehovah’s blessing
to be successful.
Psalm 127:1 says:
“Unless Jehovah builds the house,
“it is in vain
that its builders work hard on it.
“Unless Jehovah guards the city,
it is in vain that the guard stays awake.”
But as the account
in Joshua chapter 7 vividly testifies,
it’s possible for Jehovah
to withhold his blessing.
Do you remember what happened
when Achan stole from the things
that were supposed
to be dedicated to Jehovah?
Israel lost God’s backing.
Our service to Jehovah is important.
We cannot afford
to lose Jehovah’s blessing.
For this reason,
the spiritual qualifications
for expanded service are high.
It’s expected that all of those
offering themselves to serve at Bethel
or in other theocratic assignments
have a clean conscience before Jehovah,
having left behind all unclean practices
or immoral conduct.
For instance,
those who have viewed pornography
in the past year should not apply.
Also, if you realize
that you may have become involved
in unclean conduct
with someone
of the opposite sex or the same sex,
Jehovah very considerately explains
what we should do
in James 5:14, 15:
“Is there anyone
[spiritually] sick among you?
“Let him call the elders
of the congregation to him,
“and let them pray over him,
“applying oil to him
in the name of Jehovah.
“And the prayer of faith
will make the sick one well,
“and Jehovah will raise him up.
Also, if he has committed sins,
he will be forgiven.”
How reassuring!
If you have a heavy conscience
because of something you’ve done,
you should get help to strengthen
your relationship with Jehovah.
You can later submit an application
with a clean conscience,
confident that Jehovah
will bless your efforts.
So don’t hesitate to speak
with one of the elders
in your congregation if you need help.
They love you
and want you to progress and qualify
for special privileges
of service in Jehovah’s organization.
We’ve spoken frankly to you
because we want you
to make a success
of your service to Jehovah.
We also want to reassure you
that your assistance
is very much needed.
So if you enjoy good health,
both spiritually and physically,
and want to apply
for expanded theocratic service
on a temporary or full-time basis,
ask your elders for an application
to serve as a temporary volunteer
or as a member of the Worldwide Order
of Special Full-Time Servants
of Jehovah’s Witnesses.
After completing the application,
return it to your elders.
Then continue to allow Jehovah
to direct your steps
wherever you may serve.
We love you
for the willing spirit you show.
Please be assured
of our prayers in your behalf
as you continue
to reach out in Jehovah’s service.