Our convention program contains
over 100 audio and video productions,
including the one we just enjoyed.
These videos are made
at various locations around the world.
We have the privilege of supporting this
and other aspects of the Kingdom work.
For your convenience,
donations can be made online
at donate.jw.org.
As we saw,
the prophet Daniel maintained his faith
despite tests and infirmities.
How can we do the same?
What strength can we gain
from the prophetic visions given to Daniel?
Please pay close attention
to Brother Stephen Lett of the Governing Body
as he answers those questions
in the final talk
of this convention, entitled
“Become Powerful by Your Faith!”
A building constructed
with steel-reinforced concrete
can withstand powerful earthquakes.
A tree with strong, deep roots
can remain standing
in the face of many powerful storms.
An athlete made powerful by rigorous training
can successfully complete a decathlon
—a ten-event athletic contest.
Well, just as a building, a tree,
and an athlete can be powerful,
we as Jehovah’s people
can be powerful by means of our faith.
And we will discuss during this talk
how faith
—a product of holy spirit,
the most powerful force in the universe—
can reinforce, or fortify, us
for any (and I mean any)
test, trial, or temptation
that comes our way.
Now, even though
we may not feel powerful physically
or emotionally,
our faith can make us powerful spiritually.
And spiritual power is much more valuable
than physical or emotional power.
With spiritual power, we can be like Abraham.
Please go to Romans chapter 4,
and notice what was said about Abraham,
beginning in verse number 18:
“Although beyond hope, yet based on hope,
“he had faith that he would become
the father of many nations
“according to what had been said:
‘So your offspring will be.’
“And although he did not grow weak in faith,
“he considered his own body,
now as good as dead
“(since he was about 100 years old),
“as well as the deadness
of the womb of Sarah.
“But because of the promise of God,
“he did not waver in a lack of faith;
“but he [now notice]
“became powerful by his faith,
“giving God glory and being fully convinced
“that what He [Jehovah] had promised
He [Jehovah] was also able to do.”
Even though almost 100 years old
—and Abraham likely
would have been frail physically
and emotionally weak at times—
his faith made him powerful.
In fact, his faith made him so powerful
that he believed this extraordinary promise
with all his heart
—that his almost 90-year-old wife, Sarah,
would give birth to a son
and that it would definitely come true.
And even though that promise
was unbelievable from a human standpoint,
he had no doubt whatsoever.
Well, likewise, if our faith
makes us powerful,
we will fully believe
all of Jehovah’s promises
no matter how extraordinary they may seem.
We will do so without doubting whatsoever.
But now think about this comparison
to Abraham:
An older, frail,
chronically ill servant of Jehovah
may seem weak,
but outward appearance can be very deceptive.
If that one has been empowered by faith,
then he is truly strong, just like Abraham.
And this wonderful convention
was designed to fortify our faith
so that it will empower us to be so strong
that we’ll be able to endure
whatever test, trial, and temptation
comes against us.
And there will actually be no breaking point
to our integrity.
But now let’s talk about how each day
of our convention
and our outstanding drama
have strengthened our faith.
First, let’s talk about Friday.
The day’s theme was a quote from Luke 17:5:
“Give us more faith.”
Now, these were the humble words
of Jesus’ apostles
who recognized their need for more faith,
and they were humbly pleading for such.
Well, we feel the same way, don’t we?
We know we need more faith,
and we humbly ask Jehovah for it.
But now the question is,
Will Jehovah answer our pleas for more faith?
Yes, he will.
And Friday revealed
some of the ways Jehovah answers
our humble plea for more faith.
As illuminated on Friday,
Jehovah gives us faith
primarily by means of two books
—the Bible and the book of creation.
The first symposium showed
how the Bible builds faith
in God’s existence;
it builds faith in itself,
that it’s the Word of God;
it builds faith in God’s moral standards;
and it builds faith in God’s love for us.
But now we ask that first part,
How does the Bible build faith
in God’s existence?
Well, for one thing, within its pages,
it gives us common sense,
reasoning from scriptures
such as Hebrews 3:4.
And do you know what that says?
It says: “Of course,
“every house is constructed by someone,
but the one
who constructed all things is God.”
Now, you could never convince
any sane person
that a beautiful house
designed and built itself.
Even more so,
it should not be possible
to convince any rational person
that all the beautiful creations around us
just designed and built themselves
or that they’re the product of blind chance.
Where there is design,
there is always a designer.
Now let’s illustrate this:
How many times
would you have to throw
black paint from a can
onto a white ceiling
until you produced
a perfect map of New York City,
until the paint particles scattered
accurately identifying all of the streets,
the highways, the tunnels, the bridges,
the overpasses, and the landmarks
and correctly named each one?
Well, you could do that
for billions of times,
and never would you produce
a perfect map of New York City.
Now to add a little humor:
Let’s say you tried doing this
for 100 billion years, and you get excited.
You finally got a city map.
But, oh, no!
It’s not New York City;
it’s Warwick, New York.
Now you’ve got to start all over,
going for that map of New York City.
I had to give you a little humor.
But think of this: One living human cell
is much more complex,
intricately designed,
than a map of New York City.
And one human body
is made up of about 100 trillion
of such amazing cells
all working together harmoniously.
Well, in the second part,
how does the Bible build faith in itself
—that it is the Word of God?
Well, for one thing,
everything the Bible recommends
works and brings superior results
—how to raise children,
how to have a happy marriage, and so forth.
Think about it:
Humans simply aren’t smart enough
to recommend only what works,
and their advice is constantly being revised
and updated, isn’t it?
Though written hundreds,
thousands, of years ago,
the Bible has never needed to be revised.
Yet, everything it recommends works.
It has to be from a higher source
than humans.
Well, in the third part, how does the Bible
build faith in God’s moral standards?
Well, it tells us what they are.
It encourages us to obey them,
and when we do,
it protects us physically,
emotionally, and spiritually.
We get happiness;
we get a good conscience;
we experience the benefits.
Thus, we don’t have to learn
the painful process
of trial and error.
There’s a saying
that “experience is the best teacher”
—completely wrong.
Experience is a school of hard knocks.
Jehovah is the best Teacher.
“Jehovah is . . . making
the inexperienced one wise,”
according to Psalm 19:7.
Well, in the fourth part, how does the Bible
build faith in God’s love for us?
The most powerful way is,
it explains how Jehovah gave
his firstborn Son to die for us
so that we could have everlasting life.
Now think about it:
What do most people give away
if they give something away?
Something they don’t need
or at least something they can do without.
But Jehovah gave at great cost,
great pain to himself.
Evolution teaches
that our ancestors were apes.
How could we feel happy and feel loved
thinking that an ape was our father?
But our real Father, Jehovah,
is the personification of love.
But now, on Friday afternoon,
we had our second symposium,
which opened the book of creation.
And peering into this book
can empower our faith.
First, let’s talk about that first talk
that dealt with the stars.
Isaiah 40:26 tells us
that Jehovah created all of them
and ‘he calls all of them by name.’
Now let’s ponder this for a moment:
How long would it take you
to name just the stars
in the Milky Way galaxy
if you named one every second?
Joseph, Paul, Rachel, Sarah.
Well, scientists estimate
that there are perhaps 400 billion stars
just in the Milky Way galaxy.
So if you named one a second,
it would take you 400 billion seconds.
Now, how long is that?
Twelve thousand six hundred
and eighty four years
—more than twice the time that has passed
since the creation of Adam.
And then you could go to the next galaxy.
And scientists estimate
that there may be two trillion galaxies
in the universe.
That’s five times the number of galaxies
as our individual stars in the Milky Way.
Now, if you ponder that,
it will really give you a headache.
Yet, Jehovah created, sustains,
and calls every one of them by name.
And the talk made the point
that if Jehovah can do that,
he will have no problem
remembering and recreating
all those sleeping in the memorial tombs.
The second talk examined
the page in the book of creation
about the oceans.
How powerful they are!
But the One who made them
is vastly more powerful.
And our powerful God
definitely can protect us now
and right through the great tribulation.
The third talk examined
the page in creation about the forests,
and it was discussed how forests
have the amazing ability
to repair and renew themselves.
And the point was made that the One
who has the wisdom to create such forests
surely knows how to undo all the damage
that man has done to the planet Earth.
The fourth talk focused on wind and water,
and it talked about how Jehovah
has in the past used wind and water
—and especially water in the form of hail—
to defeat his enemies and deliver his people.
Well, he will use them again at Armageddon.
The fifth talk took a glimpse
into the fascinating world of sea creatures,
and we looked at the largest animal alive
on earth today
—the blue whale.
And what an appetite
that blue whale has!
It can eat, according to the video,
tons of food every day.
Yet, Jehovah feeds it.
Now, if he can do that,
can he not feed and care for us,
if we continue to seek first the Kingdom?
Well, our faith was strengthened
that he can and he will.
The last talk examined our amazing bodies.
As discussed, it’s miraculous
how our bodies heal
and repair themselves when damaged.
Now think of this:
If you damage, scrape, or dent your car,
does it heal itself?
Hardly!
What if every time we bruised, scraped,
or damaged our body
it just stayed that way?
In a short time,
we’d get to looking pretty rough.
But the God who made our bodies
in this miraculous way
certainly can heal all infirmities,
reverse aging,
and prevent sickness in his new world.
And he has promised to do that.
Well, the third symposium
went back to our main book that builds faith
—the Bible.
And we discussed those
who acquired strong faith,
and we discussed how they did it.
And even though their contemporaries
were faithless,
they developed this faith.
Well, our faith was empowered
as we discussed Abel, Enoch, Noah,
Moses, and Jesus’ disciples,
and we became more determined than ever
to imitate these faithful ones
and not their faithless contemporaries.
And we know we can be successful
because we have the same Father, Helper,
Supplier of holy spirit as they had.
Yes, our three symposiums on Friday
clearly showed us
that Jehovah answers our pleas for more faith
by means of two books
—the Bible and the book of creation.
But regarding our drama, we ask,
How did Jehovah answer
Daniel’s pleas for more faith?
Well, one way was
he gave Daniel his written Word.
In the drama, if you recall,
Daniel’s father gave him a scroll
that he regularly referred to.
Did you recognize that scroll?
The scroll depicted in the drama
is known today as Psalm 27.
When enemies tried to discredit Daniel,
we saw him reflect on Psalm 27:11, 12,
which says in part:
“Do not hand me over to my adversaries,
“for false witnesses
have risen up against me,
and they threaten me with violence.”
When he was threatened with execution,
we saw him reflect
on Psalm 27:7-9,
which says in part:
“You are my helper;
“do not forsake me or leave me,
my God of salvation.”
How those verses
would have bolstered Daniel’s faith!
Of course, we cannot say for sure
that Daniel reflected
on those specific verses,
but the Bible does reveal that Daniel’s faith
indeed was strengthened by the Scriptures.
And we know that Daniel
was a keen student of Bible prophecy.
He even said of himself at Daniel 9:2:
“I, Daniel, discerned by the books
[that is, the sacred books]
the number of years.”
And then he talks about the desolation
(restoration) of Jerusalem
—“namely, 70 years.”
But now we ask, Will Jehovah answer
our pleas for more faith?
Most definitely he will.
And one outstanding way he has done this
is by providing us with Bible prophecy.
Prophecies in the book of Daniel alone
have helped millions
to build rock-solid faith.
For example, the fulfilled prophecies
regarding the king of the north
and the king of the south
have been very faith-strengthening.
In fact, let’s review the video on this topic
that appeared in Brother Kenneth Cook’s
May broadcast.
Enjoy this powerful video.
Daniel received a prophecy
about the coming of two rivals:
“the king of the north”
and “the king of the south.”
How has it been fulfilled?
In the late 1800’s, the German Empire
became the king of the north.
That government brought
its “power and . . . heart
“against the king of the south
with a large army.”
In fact, its navy was
the second largest on earth.
Who became the king of the south?
The alliance between Britain
and the United States.
He fought during World War I
“with an exceedingly large
and mighty army.”
He “swept away” and “humbled”
the king of the north.
But that was not the end
of the king of the north.
He turned his attention to and then hurled
“denunciations against the holy covenant.”
He removed “the constant feature”
by limiting the freedom of God’s people
to preach,
imprisoning many,
and even killing hundreds
of God’s anointed ones
and their fellow workers.
After Germany was defeated in World War II,
the Soviet Union
became the king of the north.
It worked with the king of the south
to “put in place the disgusting thing
that causes desolation”
—the United Nations.
Beginning in the early 1900’s,
the Soviet government tried to eliminate
religion in the lands under its control,
fulfilling the words
that he would “show no regard
for the God of his fathers.”
He gave glory, not to the God of heaven,
but “to the god of fortresses.”
As prophesied,
he used this military might
against the king of the south
by engaging “with him in a pushing.”
Anglo-America competed
with the Soviet Union
for world domination,
fighting in and supporting wars
and political struggles around the globe.
After the Soviet Union collapsed in 1991,
it was unclear who would fill the role
of the king of the north.
For a time, God’s people there
had been able to preach
and worship peacefully.
But in recent years, Russia and its allies
have pushed back at the king of the south.
Both kings have accused each other
of destructive cyber and economic attacks.
But the king of the north has not limited
his attacks to the king of the south.
As foretold, he also entered
“into the land of the Decoration”
—our realm of spiritual activity.
Today, Russian authorities continue
to attack true worship.
We expect such persecution,
but we also expect it to end.
Our King, Jesus Christ,
is more powerful than any human government.
Soon he will destroy
not only the kings of the north and the south
but all of his enemies,
and he will deliver God’s loyal people.
What a powerful video!
Has the unerring accuracy of those prophecies
strengthened your faith?
We’re confident that it has.
And we’re absolutely convinced
that the rest of that prophecy,
including our deliverance,
will be fulfilled.
Christ soon will defend God’s people
and bring an end
to this entire wicked system.
May all of us continue to study
these and other prophecies.
If we do, our faith
in our wise, our all-powerful,
our loving Father
will definitely be strengthened.
But now let’s move to Saturday’s program,
which had the theme taken from Jude 3:
“Put up a hard fight for the faith.”
The symposium
“Successful Fighters for the Faith”
showed that many who do not have a spouse
and many whose spouse
is not yet serving Jehovah
are winning their fight for the faith.
And we warmly commend
you dear, beloved ones.
The baptism discourse
encouraged new disciples
to continue strengthening their faith,
and we warmly welcome
all newly baptized ones.
Jehovah loves you very much.
The Governing Body loves you very much.
Your brothers and sisters love you very much.
And we’re so happy to have you join us
in our united family
of intense fighters for the faith.
The two afternoon symposiums
helped us to analyze
how we can show our faith
by giving of our time,
energy, and material things
to advance the Kingdom work
and to help others.
And we discussed some specific things
that we may be able to do.
For example, learn a new language,
move and serve where the need is greater,
apply for the School
for Kingdom Evangelizers,
assist with a building project,
and “set something aside” for Jehovah’s work.
The talk “Put Up a Hard Fight for the Faith!”
reminded us that as is true in all fights
—in our fight—
we have enemies.
For one thing, we must reject apostate lies
and the false stories of other opposers,
which are designed to sow doubt
and weaken faith.
Satan is very skilled
at using innuendo, half-truths, and lies.
So it’s not surprising that the news media
—which is often manipulated by apostates,
clergymen, and other opposers—
likewise often employs innuendo,
half-truths, and lies
against Jehovah’s organization.
Think about this:
Faith is a product of holy spirit.
It’s a provision from Jehovah
to strengthen us,
whereas doubt
is a tool of the Devil designed to weaken us.
Do you recall how Satan approached Eve?
“Is it really so
that God said you must not eat
from every tree of the garden?”
‘Is that really so?’
Why did he present it that way?
To plant doubt
and ‘shipwreck her faith,’ and he succeeded.
Well, likewise, if we’re not careful,
doubt can shipwreck our faith.
But strong faith
keeps doubt out of our hearts and minds.
But now, in talking just a little bit more
about apostates,
what if an apostate knocked
at your front door and said,
“I’d like to come into your home,
I’d like to sit down with you,
and I’d like to teach you
some apostate ideas”?
Why, you would immediately
get rid of him, wouldn’t you?
You would send him down the highway.
But now think of this:
What if that same apostate
tries to come into your home
by means of the television
or computer?
Well, hopefully, we reject him
just as decisively.
Second John 10 says:
“If anyone comes to you
and does not bring this teaching,
[never] receive him into your homes”
—that would mean not through the front door,
not through the television, or computer.
Sadly, though, some have reasoned foolishly:
‘If I listen to this apostate
on television or the computer
‘or perhaps read his book,
‘I’ll recognize how wrong he is.
‘It’ll build up my faith.
‘And if I ever encounter this teaching
in the ministry,
I’ll better be able to refute it.’
Well, that is foolish thinking indeed.
That would be like reasoning,
‘If I eat stinky, rotten, food
from a garbage can,
‘it will really help me in the future
to recognize bad food.’
That’s not very good reasoning, is it?
Rather than feed our minds
poisonous, apostate ideas,
we read God’s Word daily
and strengthen and safeguard our faith.
But now we ask, How did Daniel
put up a hard fight for the faith?
Well, for one thing, he resisted pressure
to compromise.
But can you imagine the pressure
he must have faced
when offered the king’s delicacies and wine?
How was he able to refuse?
Well, for the answer,
let’s go to Daniel chapter 1, please,
and let’s read verse number 8.
Daniel 1:8: “But Daniel
“resolved in his heart
“that he would not defile himself
with the king’s delicacies
“or with the wine he drank.
“So he asked the principal court official
for permission
not to defile himself in this way.”
So notice, in advance,
Daniel “resolved in his heart”
the course he was going to take.
And he did so because he was fully convinced
that whatever Jehovah had commanded
was for his good.
Well, like Daniel, we must put up
a hard fight for the faith.
Are you facing pressure right now
—at school, at work, or even at home—
to compromise?
If so, please don’t give up
and don’t give in.
Reflect on Daniel’s example,
and fight for your faith.
Be resolved to obey Jehovah because doing so
is always the right thing,
and if you do, you will have no regrets.
Pressure was also put on Daniel
by means of threats.
But can you imagine how Daniel felt
when he became aware
that his next prayer
could lead to his execution?
What helped him to stay loyal?
Well, let’s go to Daniel chapter 6
and get some help with that question.
Daniel chapter 6
and, please, let’s read together
verse number 10:
“But as soon as Daniel knew
“that the decree had been signed,
“he went to his house,
“which had the windows of his roof chamber
open toward Jerusalem.
“And three times a day
he got down on his knees
“and prayed and offered praise
before his God,
“[now notice] as he had regularly done
prior to this.”
So Daniel knew what was right,
and he didn’t hesitate to do it,
and he was consistent in his worship.
Daniel 6:16 tells us
that Daniel
was “continually serving” his God.
And The Watchtower  explains
that the original Bible word
translated “continually serving”
basically means to “move in a circle,”
which suggests continuity.
And how well that describes
Daniel’s unbroken worship!
See, there’s no end to a circle.
It’s unbroken, is it not?
Please watch the following dramatization
that depicts a brother
who faces a threat of being arrested.
But by reflecting on Daniel’s example,
he is helped to continue serving Jehovah
with constancy
in the face
of this intimidating circumstance.
It’s still chaos in many parts of the city,
with armed soldiers detaining and arresting
those not pledging support
of the new government.
Are we still going to the meeting tonight?
I wanted to do what was best
for my wife and daughter.
But a few of the elders
have already been arrested.
What if I was arrested?
What would happen to my family?
You’re not going home to pray, are you?
I pray at my window three times a day,
every day.
If I even appear to compromise,
what would they think?
I know Jehovah.
And if I trust him,
he’ll reward me.
I don’t know how,
but he will.
Pray that I keep my faith
—that we all keep our faith—
no matter how this ends.
The Scriptures are clear.
We must continue to meet together,
even in small groups if necessary.
Let’s just pray that whatever happens,
we have the strength to endure it.
Dear Jehovah God, please . . .
Eventually, I was arrested.
We miss you so much,
but we’re very proud of you.
We know whatever the outcome of your trial,
you’ll maintain your faith,
and so will we.
Were you scared?
I was very scared,
but Jehovah helps us when we’re scared.
I knew I would be OK
and that Jehovah
would take care of my family.
As was true of the brother in our video,
we will be persecuted.
Second Timothy 3:12 says:
“All those desiring to live
with godly devotion
“in association with Christ Jesus
will also be persecuted.”
It didn’t say maybe, good chance, probably
—‘will be persecuted.’
It’s guaranteed.
But like our brother in the video,
when persecuted,
let’s reflect on Daniel’s example
and let’s fight for our faith.
And then let’s pray,
confident that our God
is always mightier than our enemies.
Let’s be like young David
when he went out to meet Goliath.
Now, David saw the big picture, didn’t he?
Sure, he saw how big Goliath was,
but in the big picture,
he saw how puny Goliath was
compared to his almighty God, Jehovah.
In a unique way, Daniel also experienced
how mighty Jehovah is
when he was thrown into the lions’ pit.
Jehovah sent an angel
to shut the mouths of those lions.
Now, think about it: Those lions
obviously were very hungry
because a little bit later
when people were thrown in there,
they were consumed
before they hit the bottom of the pit.
So they were very hungry,
and Daniel would have looked
like a tasty morsel.
But no matter how hard they tried,
those lions couldn’t get their mouths open
to harm Daniel.
Daniel also set a good example
in remaining hopeful despite old age
and infirmities.
But can you imagine how Daniel felt
when he was almost 100 years old
and many Jews left
for their beloved homeland, Judah,
and he was unable to go with them?
But what helped him to keep his hope alive?
Well, let’s go to Daniel chapter 10, please.
Let’s see one thing that helped Daniel.
In Daniel chapter 10 and beginning
in verse 18, Daniel says:
“The one who looked like a man
touched me again
“and strengthened me.
“Then he said: ‘Do not be afraid,
O very precious man.
“‘May you have peace.
“Be strong, yes, be strong.’
“As he spoke with me I was strengthened
“and I said: ‘Let my lord speak,
for you have strengthened me.’”
So through an angel, Jehovah reassured Daniel
that he was precious
and still very useful to Him.
Well, Daniel accepted
the encouragement, didn’t he?
And thereafter, Jehovah
gave him a thrilling prophecy
about the king of the north
and the king of the south, which he recorded
for our benefit.
Although old and infirm, this precious man
was still very useful to Jehovah.
Please watch the following dramatization
in which an older brother who feels helpless
reflects on how the angel reassured Daniel.
It all went by so quickly
—pioneering,
foreign language,
circuit work.
There was even a time
that I was the one encouraging older ones.
I miss those days so much.
But now I’m the one in a nursing home.
Sometimes I feel like I have
nothing left to offer.
O Daniel,
you very precious man.
I have been sent to you.
Do not be afraid, Daniel.
Your words have been heard
from the first day you gave your heart
to understanding.
I have no strength.
There’s no breath left in me.
Do not be afraid, O very precious man.
May you have peace.
Be strong.
Be strong!
Happy is the one who keeps in expectation.
Go on to the end.
You will rest, but you will stand up
for your lot at the end of the days.
Hey, just checking on you.
Do you have a minute?
There’s something I’ve been wanting
to share with you.
OK, sure.
Yes, Jehovah does remember me,
and I still have much to offer.
That was a very touching video indeed!
But now we ask, Do you have infirmities
that keep you from doing
what you would like to do?
If so, reflect on Daniel’s example
and accept Jehovah’s reassurance.
And remember that what you used to do
is still viewed as valuable to Jehovah.
He will not forget it.
And your present acts of faithfulness,
even if small,
are very precious to him.
We entreat all of you:
Whether young or old,
like Daniel, do not stop
putting up a hard fight for the faith.
But now let’s talk about today’s program,
which has the theme taken from Matthew 21:21:
“If you have faith . . . , it will happen.”
In the morning, we enjoyed
the faith-strengthening symposium
“Imitate Women of Strong Faith!”
And in each of the eight parts,
the exemplary women of faith
who were discussed
faced mountainlike obstacles.
Sarah had to leave a comfortable lifestyle
for a nomadic lifestyle,
and for many years, she suffered barrenness.
Rahab had to take decisive action
—risk her life—
to protect the Israelite spies
and take a stand with God’s people.
Thereafter, she had to give up
an immoral lifestyle.
Hannah continued to serve Jehovah
while enduring many years of barrenness
and harassment from Peninnah.
The captive Israelite girl
was forcibly separated from her family
by Syrian marauders
but nevertheless continued
to fearlessly witness
to others about Jehovah.
Mary accepted the difficult assignment
of giving birth to, caring for,
and training God’s Son.
The Phoenician woman
courageously and persistently
sought help from Jesus
for her demon-possessed daughter.
And she got that help, didn’t she?
Martha, after the painful loss
of her brother to the enemy death,
maintained faith in Jesus’ ability
to raise the dead.
The two modern-day examples
that we discussed in the last talk,
Sisters Ishii and Toom,
both steadfastly refused to compromise
despite being imprisoned for many years
simply because they were
Jehovah’s Witnesses.
Yes, each one of these dear sisters faced
mountainlike obstacles
but Jehovah rewarded their faith.
Their faith moved them
to expect good things from Jehovah,
and Jehovah never ever let them down.
Well, what good things
do we expect from Jehovah
if we maintain strong faith?
Let’s talk about some of the events
that we expect to unfold in the near future.
Now, for one thing, the final part
of Nebuchadnezzar’s image dream
discussed in Daniel chapter 2
will be fulfilled.
As represented by the four upper parts
of that image,
four world powers have come and gone,
just as prophesied.
Today, the Anglo-American World Power,
symbolized by the feet of iron and clay,
is dominating.
And more than ever,
we see this last world power
living up to being a noncohesive mixture
of iron and clay.
And just as iron mixed with clay
is weaker than solid iron,
so too the Anglo-American World Power
is weaker
than the ironlike Roman Empire
from which it emerged.
The ability of the Anglo-American World Power
to act with ironlike strength
is weakened by claylike elements,
such as people rising up
to claim their rights
through insurrection,
civil rights campaigns,
and independence movements.
As Daniel foretold in chapter 2, verse 42:
“The kingdom will be partly strong
and partly fragile.”
And we see that is
more and more evident today than ever.
But despite the weakened condition
of this final world power,
it will not simply disintegrate
into self-destruction.
Go to Daniel chapter 2,
and let’s notice how it comes to its end.
It’s a very familiar scripture here
—Daniel 2:44:
“In the days of those kings the God of heaven
“will set up a kingdom
that will never be destroyed.
“And this kingdom will not be passed on
to any other people.
“It will crush and put an end
to all these kingdoms,
“and it alone will stand forever,
“just as you saw that out of the mountain
a stone was cut not by hands
“[that is, not by human hands,
but by Jehovah’s hands],
“and that it crushed the iron, the copper,
“the clay, the silver, and the gold.
“The Grand God has made known to the king
what will happen in the future.
“The dream is true,
and its interpretation is trustworthy.”
This scripture describes how God’s Kingdom,
represented by that stone,
will crush all human governments
at Armageddon.
And interestingly, at Daniel 2:34,
it tells us that ‘the stone [God’s Kingdom]
‘will strike the image
[representing human governments]
in the feet of iron and clay,’
clearly identifying that Armageddon will come
during the time
of the Anglo-American World Power
—the final human world power.
And like Daniel, we have strong faith
in the last sentence of verse 45, which says:
“The dream is true, and its interpretation
is trustworthy.”
There’s no doubt about it:
God’s Kingdom will destroy
all human governments at Armageddon
during the time
of the Anglo-American World Power.
But now, just as the final part
of the image dream
will soon be fulfilled,
the final part of Daniel’s vision
in chapter 7
will soon be fulfilled.
Now, in chapter 7,
Daniel describes four wild beasts,
which symbolize four world powers
that have come and gone.
And appropriately,
they’re described as wild beasts
because they haven’t ruled kindly
but, rather, in a harsh, beastly way.
Now, those four world powers
are Babylon, Medo-Persia, Greece, and Rome
—the very same four world powers
represented by the four upper metal parts
of the image dream we discussed previously.
But in verse 8, Daniel describes a horn
that grew out of the head
of that fourth beast—out of Rome;
that horn had eyes; that horn had a mouth;
that mouth spoke arrogantly.
Well, this arrogant horn symbolizes
the Anglo-American World Power
—again, the last world power.
Now, what was foretold to happen next?
We’ll go to Daniel chapter 7, please.
Let’s see what happens next.
Daniel chapter 7,
and please let’s begin in verse number 26:
“But the Court sat,
“and they took away his rulership
[that is, that horn’s rulership],
“in order to annihilate him
and to destroy him completely.
“And the kingdom and the rulership
and the grandeur
“of the kingdoms under all the heavens
“were given to the people
“who are the holy ones of the Supreme One.
“Their kingdom is an everlasting kingdom,
and all rulerships will serve and obey them.”
The rulership of this arrogant horn
is taken away,
and it is annihilated and destroyed
and replaced by God’s Kingdom.
So just as described
in the imagery in this vision,
we see that God’s Kingdom
destroys all human governments
during the time
of the Anglo-American World Power
and then takes over rulership of the earth.
How exciting that event,
which will take place
in the near future, will be!
But think about it: Every preceding part
of that prophecy has come true.
So we have complete confidence, strong faith,
that the final part of it
will also come true.
Now, there are many other prophecies
in the book of Daniel
that we didn’t have time to discuss
that have come true in amazing detail.
But the fulfillment of so many prophecies
totally convinces us
that we are deep, deep
in “the time of the end.”
Very soon, we’re going to witness
the fulfillment of Daniel 12:1,
which talks about ‘Michael the great prince
standing up.’
“And there will occur
a time of [great] distress.”
But God’s “people will escape,
everyone who is found
written down in the book.”
In the video near the beginning of this talk,
we saw Michael, the glorified Jesus Christ,
depicted as coming with the angels
to rescue Jehovah’s people
and destroy this wicked system.
But now, if you notice carefully
in that video,
the wicked were actually shooting
their weapons
into the sky at Michael.
Now, that’s laughable
—isn’t it?—
because mankind’s most powerful weapons
are like wet firecrackers
compared to Michael’s mighty power.
In fact, in the video,
Michael was depicted as coming
with no defensive equipment,
such as a breastplate or shield.
He doesn’t need it.
He was depicted only with a sword
—an offensive weapon.
Now, sometimes in our illustrations,
he’s depicted with a bow and arrow
—again, only an offensive weapon.
But his offensive weapons are powerful
—much, much more powerful
than needed to do the job
of rescuing Jehovah’s people
and sweeping out of existence
Satan’s entire wicked system.
But then after Armageddon,
the glorious Thousand Year Reign
of Christ Jesus will begin.
And during that marvelous time,
the last verse
of the book of Daniel will be fulfilled.
Now let’s read it.
The last verse of this book, chapter 12,
and let’s read verse 13.
And here’s what was said to Daniel:
“But as for you, go on to the end.
“You will rest, but you will stand up
for your lot at the end of the days.”
Yes, Daniel served Jehovah faithfully
until the end of his life.
He went “to the end,” didn’t he?
Now he’s resting in death,
but soon he “will stand up”
in the resurrection
during Christ’s Millennial Reign
“for [his] lot”—his place in the new world.
But we ask, Did Daniel have faith
in that promise
that Jehovah gave him through the angel?
For a certainty, he did!
He had already demonstrated
faith for decades.
He remained clean when tempted to eat food
that would defile him.
He was diligent in prayer,
even when praying meant
that he would be executed.
He never stopped building his faith
through Bible study.
So we can be sure
he believed with all his heart
that promise Jehovah gave him
through the angel
—that he would stand up in the resurrection
and take his place in the new world.
But now we ask,
How can we maintain our faith
as Daniel did?
Well, by staying morally
and spiritually clean,
not allowing anything to corrupt our faith;
by praying constantly
with full confidence that Jehovah
will answer our prayers;
and by listening to Jehovah
by diligent study of his Word.
Jehovah wants us to have faith
that he is our Rewarder.
Hebrews 11:6 says:
“Whoever approaches God must believe
that he is [that he’s really there]
“and that he becomes the rewarder
of those earnestly seeking him.”
Think about our two brothers
shown earlier in this talk:
the Christian father and the sick brother.
The Christian father ended up behind bars,
and our sick brother
was not miraculously healed.
So was their faith in vain?
For a certainty, no!
Will Jehovah reward them?
For a certainty, yes!
If you are facing a similar situation,
will Jehovah reward you?
Most definitely yes!
Please watch the following video
which features the song that we will sing
to conclude our convention.
Enjoy this video.
Why should I fear the lion?
Why should I fear any foe?
With Jehovah by my side,
I will not run and hide.
My God is with me; this I know.
With eyes of faith,
I see beyond the darkness.
there’s nothing more to fear.
With Jehovah, I am strong,
Determined to go on,
Knowing that my God is always near—
With eyes of faith.
Those faithful ones before us
Lived their lives in loyalty.
By their faith they endured.
Their future is assured.
They’ll stand again for all to see.
With eyes of faith,
I see beyond the darkness.
there’s nothing more to fear.
With Jehovah, I am strong,
Determined to go on,
Knowing that my God is always near—
With eyes of faith.
With eyes of faith, I can move a mountain.
With eyes of faith, my hope is sure.
Where would I be
Without the faith that helps me see
Beyond the trials I endure?
I see the wondrous future
God has in store for me.
I need to be strong.
I know it won’t be long
Till Jehovah claims his victory.
With eyes of faith,
I see beyond the darkness.
there’s nothing more to fear.
With Jehovah, I am strong,
Determined to go on,
Knowing that my God is always near—
With eyes of faith,
With eyes of faith.
What a powerfully motivating video!
And we look forward to singing that song
to conclude our convention.
Dear brothers and sisters,
faithful children,
cherished interested ones,
there’s no doubt that right now
we face powerful enemies.
For one thing, we have a powerful enemy
inside our bodies
—inherited sin.
It wages an intense war
against our desire to do what is right.
Secondly, we have the formidable foes:
Satan and his demons.
Satan is described as a devouring lion,
a cunning serpent,
a fierce dragon,
a sneaky birdcatcher,
and he’s given other evil descriptions.
Ephesians 6:12 says:
“We have a struggle
[the footnote, literally “a wrestling”]
. . . against the wicked spirit forces
in the heavenly places.”
And as mentioned in our publications,
there may be tens of thousands
of these powerful, evil spirit creatures
in the invisible realm
waging war against us.
Thirdly, we have this wicked world
all around us
that is trying to assimilate us
into joining them in ungodly conduct.
And looking at the ratio,
we as Jehovah’s people
are outnumbered by people of the world
by about 900 to 1.
But despite the power
of those three great enemies,
our faith—this product
of Jehovah’s invincible holy spirit—
makes us stronger and stronger individually
than all of those three enemies combined.
In the near future,
another powerful enemy will come against us.
This formidable foe
is a coalition of nations
called Gog in Ezekiel chapter 38.
And Ezekiel chapter 38 says
that Gog will come with “a great assembly,
a vast army.”
“Like clouds covering the land,”
they will come against God’s people.
Now, this could be
a very intimidating situation.
But dear brothers and sisters,
your faith will make you stronger than Gog
and will keep you strong
until Jehovah miraculously intervenes
at Armageddon.
And if you think about it,
Armageddon really is a rescue operation.
He will intervene,
and he will sweep attacking Gog away forever
with a “broom of annihilation.”
In the past, faith has helped God’s people
to overcome the most powerful obstacles,
and that same product of holy spirit
will help us do the same.
Yes, throughout the centuries,
just like today,
God’s servants, such as Daniel,
have been made powerful,
not by natural strength, but through faith.
So dear brothers and sisters,
faithful children,
cherished interested ones,
pray earnestly for faith.
Put up a hard fight to maintain your faith.
And trust with all your heart
that if you have faith,
maintain your faith, and walk by faith,
you definitely will see
all of Jehovah’s promises fulfilled.
Thank you, Brother Lett.
Your talk and this entire convention
have strengthened our faith
and prepared us for future events.
All in attendance will be pleased to know
that Parts I and II of the drama
Daniel: A Lifetime of Faith
are available now for download on jw.org
and in the JW Library® app.
This convention is further proof that Jehovah
and his Son, Jesus Christ,
provide abundantly for our spiritual needs
despite difficult world conditions.
How we rejoice to be in their loving care!
And on behalf of the Governing Body
and all the hardworking members
of our Bethel families
and translation offices around the world,
we thank you for watching
the 2021 regional convention program.
We love you.
May your love and faith remain strong,
and may your hope remain bright.
From the World Headquarters
of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
this is JW Broadcasting®.
Let’s conclude now by singing a song
that expresses the power
that faith has in our lives.
Please join in singing the original song
“With Eyes of Faith,”
which we heard sung
during the concluding talk.
After the song,
you may have your concluding prayer
at your individual locations.
Now we invite all to sing out
along with the Watchtower chorus
“With Eyes of Faith.”