After watching the 2020 regional convention
in her native language of Chichewa,
16-year-old Lisa from Malawi stated:
“With this convention, I saw
how Jehovah fulfilled his promise
“at Hebrews 13:5:
‘I will never leave you,
and I will never abandon you.’”
Many have made
similar appreciative comments
after watching the convention
in their language.
You have made kind donations online
at donate.jw.org
and by other means.
Thank you for these donations
that support
our extensive translation efforts.
Earlier in our program,
we discussed five peace wreckers
that we should “put away.”
But what can we do
if peace has been disturbed?
Can it be restored, and if so, how?
We invite you to pay careful attention
to the following four-part symposium.
Brother John Ekrann, a helper
to the Coordinators’ Committee,
will start us off with the talk
“‘Seek Peace and Pursue It’ . . .
By Not Quickly Taking Offense.”
The title of this series of four talks
is “Seek Peace and Pursue It,”
and it’s based on 1 Peter 3:11.
Let’s read that together
—1 Peter 3:11:
“Let him turn away from what is bad
and do what is good;
let him seek peace and pursue it.”
Yes, we have to pursue peace,
and pursuit requires effort.
Have you ever had to chase a piece
of paper that was in your hands
and got blown away by the wind,
and just once you get to it,
the wind blows it away again and again?
It can really take quite some effort
to retrieve and get that paper
back in your hands.
Just standing there and watching
the paper blow farther and farther away
is not going to get it back.
Well, peace can be a lot like that paper.
At some point, it can get blown away,
and we have to then chase,
or pursue, it to get that peace back again.
This series of talks will help us
to pursue peace in four ways:
by not quickly taking offense,
by apologizing,
by forgiving freely,
and by using our gift of speech wisely.
Let’s consider our first way to pursue peace:
Avoid quickly taking offense.
Now, because we are imperfect,
we might misjudge others
and quickly take offense.
Notice that we say quickly take offense.
That’s an important word.
We need to avoid jumping
to conclusions quickly
before we actually have the facts.
Even faithful men like Jesus’ apostles
have taken offense too quickly.
You may recall the time that Jesus
and his apostles
were looking for lodging
in a Samaritan village.
Now, the Samaritans in that village
rudely denied them lodging.
At Luke 9:54-56,
the apostles—James and John—
say to Jesus:
“Lord, do you want us to call fire down
from heaven and annihilate them?”
But Jesus rebukes them for their
rash and rather violent suggestion.
Think of the serious consequences
had Jesus yielded to the violent temper
of James and John.
The Samaritans could have become
prejudiced against the Kingdom message.
Instead, Jesus pursues a peaceful solution.
The account says
‘they simply went to a different village.’
Now, does this mean we’re saying
we can never take offense?
No, you may have a legitimate
“cause for complaint.”
The key point is that we should not
quickly draw conclusions
before we hear all the facts.
Proverbs 18:13 says:
“When anyone replies to a matter
before he hears the facts,
it is foolish and humiliating.”
In the following dramatization,
note what helps one sister
to overlook an offense.
And I expected more from you.
Haley, what are you talking about?
Gossiping about my posts!
Are you that lonely
that you’ve got nothing better to do?
Haley,
wait, please!
I don’t know what’s happening.
Did you talk to Emily about my posts?
Yes, we did . . .
So you gossiped about me.
No, I would . . .
I looked up to you!
I would never . . .
You’re supposed to be the mature one,
and you’re just like Emily,
busy running your mouth.
Haley!
Look, I can see you’re upset,
but trust me,
this is a huge misunderstanding.
I love you.
I would never ever say anything
behind your back.
So please calm down.
Sometimes I just feel so alone
—between Nana and work—
and then knowing all of you
are talking about me.
I promise, that’s not what happened.
You’re just really tired and overwhelmed.
So why don’t we
just slow things down a little.
You know, meetings
always make me feel better,
even on my worst days.
Why don’t we go inside,
clean up a little,
and enjoy the program together.
Then afterward, we can all talk.
I promise, it’ll be OK.
Haley really was upset.
She had already concluded that she
was being gossiped about by everyone.
If we find ourselves
like Haley feeling offended,
how can we avoid quickly taking offense?
Well, we must stop and think.
Let’s read Ecclesiastes 7:9
for some very good advice
in these situations
—Ecclesiastes 7:9:
“Do not be quick to take offense,
for the taking of offense lodges
in the bosom of fools.”
Like Celia said in the parking lot to Haley,
“Please calm down.”
So in those situations,
you need to think about what you know
and, just as important, what you don’t know.
Now, you know what you were told happened,
but what was really said?
In the video,
Haley quickly believed what she was told.
She did not even ask Celia
what she really said.
Or you may know what was said,
but do you know what was
really meant by it?
Haley asked,
“Did you talk about . . . my posts?”
And Celia said, “Yes.”
And immediately, Haley assumed the worst.
Or perhaps we misjudged
the person who hurt us.
Haley misjudged Celia
on the spot by saying,
‘You’re just as bad as Emily.’
She had not even heard from Celia yet.
Haley said to Celia
that she was the mature one,
the one she looked up to,
yet she was quick to believe
the worst about her.
Haley had not stopped
and really thought about what
she was thinking and saying.
Perhaps she was having a hard day.
Well, Celia really set a fine example for us.
Even though Haley spoke harshly to her,
Celia was calm and listened to Haley.
As Haley explained how
she was feeling lonely,
dealing and caring for her grandmother,
you can see the love and concern
that Celia had for Haley,
even though just moments before
she had spoken really harshly to her.
Well, besides taking time
to think things through,
we also need to remember
that it is Jehovah’s opinion of us
that matters the most.
Now, that’s an important point,
especially when we deal
with misunderstandings
or false accusations.
Think about it:
Jehovah is an eyewitness to everything.
To illustrate that, I want you to imagine
you had a traffic accident.
Now, you were just sitting at the stop sign,
but another car ran straight into you.
The police come,
and the person that ran into you
says that you ran into them,
and the police believe them.
You take the matter to court.
The judge listens as the other person
says that you ran into them;
however, before you can say anything,
the judge says:
“No, that is not what happened.
“I was there walking on the sidewalk
across the street that day,
and I saw the whole thing.”
Well, it’s extremely unlikely
that you can go to court and expect
the judge for your case
to have been an eyewitness.
This does illustrate, though,
the peace of mind that we can have
knowing that Jehovah is an eyewitness
to all that happens.
So when falsely accused
or when we have a misunderstanding
that we cannot seem to clear up,
it is of great comfort for us to know
that Jehovah was there that day
and saw the whole thing.
We don’t need to take offense
at every negative thing
that is said or done around us
or feel we have to defend ourselves
as being right on every occasion.
We would surely wear out emotionally
and probably not have very many friends.
We should be willing
to overlook minor transgressions.
Let’s look at Proverbs 19:11
—Proverbs 19:11.
What can help us?
“The insight of a man
certainly slows down his anger,
and it is beauty on his part
to overlook an offense.”
So can you “overlook an offense”?
As the proverb said,
that ‘is beauty on our part.’
If not and you have
a serious cause for complaint,
handle matters
according to Jehovah’s direction.
Show insight.
Slow down any anger.
Think carefully, and listen patiently
to make sure you clearly have all the facts
before you become offended
or take action.
Remember that piece of paper
that you had in your hands
and got blown away by the wind?
What if it was a hundred-dollar bill?
Well, you would make every effort
to pursue it and get it back
because it’s valuable.
Our peace with our brothers
is far more valuable than paper money.
When our peace
with our brothers or sisters
is blown away
by misunderstandings, mistakes, or sin,
then we should pursue peace
and try hard to get it back.
Yes, we glorify God and promote peace
when we avoid quickly taking offense.
Brother Ralph Walls,
a helper to the Personnel Committee,
will now present the next talk
of this symposium,
“‘Seek Peace and Pursue It’
. . . By Apologizing.”
“I am so sorry.”
“It’s my fault, please forgive me.”
No matter how we phrase it,
it can be difficult to apologize.
Why is that so challenging?
There are many reasons:
We may fear confrontation,
blame, or rejection.
Perhaps we feel embarrassed,
and we’re too proud to apologize.
We may reason, ‘Apologizing will not undo
the blunder I’ve already made.’
And it may even be that we are angry.
This is such a matter of concern
that “in July 2000,
“the California State Legislature
in the United States
“passed a bill designed
to relieve people of liability
“if they express sympathy to an individual
who was injured in an accident
“in which they
themselves were involved. . . .
“It was noted that . . . people
often hesitate to extend an apology
“[out of concern that]
it could be construed in court
as an admission of guilt.”
The Bible provides an account
of a faithful servant,
the apostle Paul,
who was a good example
of one who apologized.
The account is
in the book of Acts chapter 23.
The setting: A Roman military officer
wanted to know why Paul
was being accused by the Jews.
So he brought Paul
to the Jewish chief priests
and commanded the Sanhedrin,
the high court, to assemble.
As we read Acts 23:1-5 together,
we can’t help but be impressed
by Paul’s boldness
as he stands for what is right.
But at the same time,
please take note of his humility.
Acts 23:1: “Looking intently
at the Sanhedrin,
“Paul said: ‘Men, brothers,
“‘I have behaved before God
“with a perfectly clear conscience
down to this day.’
“At this the high priest Ananias
“ordered those standing by him
to strike him on the mouth.
“Then Paul said to him:
“‘God is going to strike you,
you whitewashed wall.
“‘Do you sit to judge me according to the Law
“‘and at the same time violate the Law
“by commanding me to be struck?’
“Those standing by said:
“‘Are you insulting the high priest of God?’
“And Paul said: ‘Brothers,
“‘I did not know he was high priest.
“‘For it is written,
“You must not speak injuriously
of a ruler of your people.”’”
Paul immediately admitted his error.
What he had said,
that the one appointed as judge
should not resort to violence, was right.
Yet, he apologized.
In the following dramatization,
we will see an older sister
applying the inspired words of Titus 2:3-5
in order to advise younger sisters
“to be sound in mind.”
We will also observe
how one of the younger sisters
avoids further problems
and pursues peace
by humbly apologizing.
I don’t know how this happened
but, Haley, I’m sorry.
It hurts me to see you so upset.
I can’t believe you two.
First,
what you heard
was not what I said.
Well, I thought that was how you felt.
And even if I got that part wrong,
all this drama?
Now stop!
Come on, girls.
Haley, come closer.
“Love is patient and kind.”
It’s not jealous.
It doesn’t become provoked,
even when things become difficult.
So, what are we going to do?
I just thought if—
No,
I’m sorry, Haley.
I’m sorry.
I shouldn’t have judged you so harshly.
I shouldn’t have judged you at all.
And I’m sorry for dragging you into this
by twisting what you said.
It’s OK; things happen.
I’ve been on both ends.
I should never have spoken
that way to you, Celia
—I mean, to either of you.
I’ve got to get home to Nana.
I’ll call you tomorrow.
Bye.
The older sister apologized,
even though she was not in the wrong.
She also urged
the two younger sisters to make peace.
It takes courage, humility,
and determination to apologize.
It’s interesting to note what’s stated
at Philippians 2:3:
“Do nothing out of contentiousness
or out of egotism,
but with humility
consider others superior to you.”
That means our determined effort
is not to win an argument,
which could be contentious,
nor do we want to start a discussion
with the primary thought being
that we are in the right.
That could mean
that we are self-concerned, or egotistical.
Rather, in harmony
with the principle of that scripture
we want to act with humility.
Our aim should be to pursue peace.
Even if we think the other person
is being unreasonable,
we apologize.
Why is it so important to do so?
Because that is what makes
our worship to Jehovah acceptable.
At Matthew chapter 5,
verses 23, 24,
Jesus makes it very clear:
“If, then, you are bringing
your gift to the altar
“and there you remember
that your brother has something against you,
“leave your gift there
in front of the altar,
“and go away.
“First make your peace with your brother,
and then come back and offer your gift.”
“One Bible scholar
describes the scene this way:
“‘The worshipper has entered the Temple;
“‘he has passed through [a] series of courts,
“‘the Court of the Gentiles,
“‘the Court of the Women,
the Court of the Men.
“‘Beyond that there lay
the Court of the Priests
“‘into which the layman could not go.
“‘The worshipper is standing at the rail,
“ready to hand over
his [living animal] to the priest.’ . . .
“At that [critical] moment,
the worshipper remembers
that his brother has something against him.”
What is he to do?
“Leave your gift there
in front of the altar,”
Jesus explains, “and go away.”
What does Jesus say is more important
than offering up a sacrifice?
‘First, make peace with your brother.
‘Then when you have come back,
offer up your gift.’
The expression rendered “make your peace”
means “to reconcile.”
Jesus’ words teach a crucial lesson:
Reconciliation, or peace,
comes before sacrifice.
The way we treat fellow worshippers
has a direct bearing
on our relationship with God.
First John 4:20 pointedly says:
“For the one who does not love his brother,
whom he has seen,
cannot love God,
whom he has not seen.”
If we find ourselves in a situation
where we have offended a fellow worshipper,
we want to apply Jesus’ counsel.
We want to take the initiative
to approach our brother or sister.
We may need
to acknowledge their hurt feelings.
We may also need to ask,
“What can I do to make amends?”
Often a sincere apology
is all that is needed.
Although our worship today
no longer includes animal sacrifices,
what Jesus was teaching
emphasizes that there is a connection
between peace with our brother
and acceptable worship to God.
When two humans are at odds,
there may be a measure
of blame on both sides,
since both are imperfect and prone to error.
This usually calls for mutual concessions.
Even if only the one apologizing is right,
the issue is not so much
who is right and who is wrong
but who will take the initiative
to make peace.
When the apostle Paul heard
that the Christians in Corinth
were taking fellow servants of God
to secular courts over personal differences,
he said:
“Why [do you] not
rather let [yourself] be wronged?
Why do you not
rather let [yourself] be defrauded?”
The principle is clear.
Peace among fellow believers
is more important than proving
who is right and who is wrong.
Keeping this in mind makes it easier
to apologize for a wrong
that someone thinks
we’ve committed against him or her.
A heartfelt apology can open the way
to a constructive conversation.
It can minimize problems
and restore peace.
Brother Leonard Myers,
a helper to the Writing Committee,
will now present
the next talk of this symposium,
“‘Seek Peace and Pursue It’ . . .
By Forgiving Freely.”
It’s a simple fact
that to be at peace with others,
we must be willing to forgive.
Please notice two examples:
A father and his teenage daughter
didn’t get along.
Minor disagreements often developed
into shouting matches.
Finally, the tension got so bad
that the daughter was asked
to leave the house.
Eventually, she recognized
that she was at fault
and asked for her father’s forgiveness.
But instead of overlooking her mistakes,
her father rejected her efforts.
He was unwilling to extend forgiveness
to his own daughter.
Now, let’s contrast that
with another example.
A blameless man was condemned to die
for a crime he didn’t commit.
Shortly before he died,
the innocent man stated:
“Father, forgive them,
for they do not know what they are doing.”
Those words of Jesus
are recorded at Luke 23:34,
and he may have been referring
to the Roman soldiers
who drove the nails into his hands and feet
and who didn’t know who he really was.
Or Jesus may have had in mind
some in the crowd
who demanded his execution
but would later exercise faith in him.
The point is that Jesus
was willing to forgive freely.
How do we measure up
with regard to forgiveness?
Are we like Jesus,
willing to forgive others freely?
Or at times, do we tend to be more
like the man who was unwilling to forgive?
Granting forgiveness isn’t always easy.
Imperfection exerts
a powerful influence over us,
sometimes robbing us of compassion.
When someone hurts us,
we may become resentful, or hold a grudge.
And perhaps some of us
were taught not to forgive others.
Little wonder that cultivating
a peaceful, forgiving spirit
can be difficult.
Still, the Bible encourages us
to forgive freely.
Let’s consider another example
of forgiveness in the man Job.
Now, we’re familiar with his trials:
loss of his possessions and ten children,
a loathsome disease,
and his wife told him to curse God and die.
Three companions heard
about Job’s calamities,
and they agreed to go comfort him.
Job 2:13 states that when they arrived,
“they sat . . . with him
for seven days and seven nights,”
but they didn’t say “a word to him.”
Now, maybe that was a good thing
because when they finally opened
their mouths,
they deeply hurt Job
with their baseless accusations.
But notice something interesting
about this account.
Please turn with me to Job chapter 42.
At the end of Job’s trials, Jehovah asked Job
to do something
regarding these false accusers.
Notice Jehovah’s words there at Job 42,
the B  portion of verse 8:
“And my servant Job will pray for you.
“I will surely accept his request
not to deal with you
according to your foolishness.”
Did you notice
that after all the false accusations,
Jehovah asked Job to pray
for the men who had tormented him?
Now, would Job tell Jehovah,
“Jehovah, after what they said to me,
I’m not going to forgive them”?
Would Job be resentful?
Notice the latter portion of verse 9:
“And Jehovah accepted Job’s prayer.”
Job followed Jehovah’s instructions.
What was the result
of Job’s integrity and his forgiving spirit?
Verse 10:
“After Job had prayed for his companions,
“Jehovah removed Job’s tribulation
and restored his prosperity.
Jehovah gave him double what he had before.”
The account goes on to say
that Job had ten more children.
He lived for 140 more years,
and verse 17 states:
“Finally Job died,
after a long and satisfying life.”
Job was blessed for his forgiving spirit,
and he set a good example for us
to forgive freely.
In the following dramatization
with Celia and Haley,
notice why Haley finally decides
to forgive freely.
Hey, it’s me.
I’ve been thinking of you.
Great broadcast.
How did you like the new original song?
Give us a call.
I wish she’d give it a rest.
Sorry?
Oh, nothing.
Sorry, it’s just Emily
for the millionth time.
What’s the problem, love?
There’s no problem.
It’s just . . .
. . . difficult to let her back in?
Not that simple?
Not that simple.
You want to forgive . . .
. . . but not get burned again.
Keep in mind
that a chance to forgive
is a chance to imitate Jehovah.
We wouldn’t want to miss that opportunity.
I never thought about it like that.
Think back to a time
when you wanted forgiveness
—when it meant everything.
How did it feel?
. . . just like your Nana does as well.
She really deeply cares about you.
You feel awful
that you’ve let everyone down.
You’re very precious.
Thank you.
Then they forgive you,
and suddenly everything is OK.
Emily, sorry I haven’t been back to you.
Have plans for tomorrow?
What good reasoning on the part of Celia!
Did you notice the expression
that really touched Haley’s heart?
“A chance to forgive
is a chance to imitate Jehovah.
We wouldn’t want to miss that opportunity.”
So when we’ve been wronged,
we don’t want to miss the opportunity
to imitate Jehovah by forgiving freely.
Please notice how this is highlighted
at Colossians 3:13.
When we considered Job’s example,
remember that Jehovah
instructed him to pray for his companions.
And that helped Job
display a forgiving spirit.
Well, notice here what Jehovah
instructs us to do at Colossians 3:13:
“Continue putting up with one another
“and forgiving one another freely
“even if anyone has a cause for complaint
against another.
“Just as Jehovah freely forgave you,
you must also do the same.”
The Greek verb used here for “freely forgive”
is related to a word often rendered
“undeserved kindness” or “favor.”
When used in the sense of forgiving,
this verb conveys the idea of doing so
freely, generously
—just as when you, out of generosity,
give a gift to someone.
Jehovah requires that we
freely forgive others in imitation of him.
Did you notice the end of the verse?
“You must  also do the same.”
Now, if the offense is minor,
it’s best to overlook it.
First Corinthians 13:5 states
that love “does not keep account
of the injury.”
And Proverbs 19:11 tells us
that “it is beauty . . .
to overlook an offense.”
However, if we feel that we need to talk
to our brother or sister
about an offense that was committed
against us,
what’s the best way to handle that?
First, we should ask Jehovah in prayer
for his guidance.
Then with the brother’s good qualities
in mind,
graciously tell him
that we want to make peace.
Listen carefully and empathetically.
We shouldn’t interrupt, even if we
don’t agree with everything being said.
It may be that his viewpoint is wrong,
but it is his viewpoint.
Then when it’s our turn to speak,
we want to be gracious.
Tell the brother
what we appreciate about him;
apologize for any part that we played
in the misunderstanding.
If our humble efforts result in good,
thank Jehovah.
If they don’t,
keep asking Jehovah for guidance
while we look for another opportunity
to make peace.
When we truly forgive,
we make a heartfelt decision
to let go of resentment.
And what peace that can bring us!
Now, forgiving doesn’t mean
that we approve of a wrong action,
consider it unimportant,
or pretend it didn’t happen.
Also, if we’ve been treated unjustly
and have a cause for complaint,
we do what we can to pursue peace
and resolve the matter.
And then we confidently leave it
in Jehovah’s hands.
Brothers and sisters, what will you
take away from this consideration?
I’m sure you’ll agree that it can be
a challenge at times to forgive.
But rather than be like the man
we spoke of earlier
who refused to forgive his own daughter,
may we follow the examples of Jehovah,
Jesus, Job, and Haley
by forgiving freely, generously.
Remember, a chance to forgive
is a chance to imitate Jehovah,
and we wouldn’t want to miss
that opportunity.
May all of us pursue peace
by being willing to forgive freely.
Brother Gerrit Lösch,
a member of the Governing Body,
will now present the final talk
of this symposium,
“‘Seek Peace and Pursue It’ . . .
By Using Our Gift of Speech Wisely.”
Why is it challenging
to use our gift of speech wisely?
Because something powerful
constantly works against us.
What is it?
Imperfection.
The tongue is powerful.
It can do much good,
but because of imperfection,
it can also cause much harm.
This thought is well expressed
in the Bible book of Proverbs.
For example, Proverbs 12:18 says:
“Thoughtless speech
is like the stabs of a sword,
but the tongue of the wise is a healing.”
And Proverbs 18:21 states:
“Death and life
are in the power of the tongue;
those who love to use it
will eat its fruitage.”
Words have power,
so we need to be careful about what we say
and how we say it.
Perhaps you can recall
when someone spoke unkindly to you
and hurt you deeply.
On the other hand, thoughtful speech
can mend an aching heart
and heal friendships.
Because of imperfection,
we all have difficulty
controlling our tongue.
This was true
even of the first-century disciple James.
He humbly acknowledged the challenge
that all humans face
in the third chapter of his inspired letter.
Notice how James described this
at James 3:3-6, 8:
“If we put bridles in the mouths of horses
“to make them obey us,
“we guide also the whole body.
“Look also at ships: Although they are so big
“and are driven by strong winds,
“they are steered by a very small rudder
“wherever the man at the helm
is inclined to go.
“So, too, the tongue
is a small part of the body,
“and yet it makes great brags.
“See how small a fire it takes
“to set a great forest ablaze!
“The tongue is also a fire.
“The tongue represents a world
of unrighteousness
“among our body members,
for it defiles
“all the body
and sets the whole course of life on fire,
and it is set on fire by Gehenna.”
And verse 8:
“But no human can tame the tongue.
“It is unruly and injurious,
full of deadly poison.”
In addition to inherited imperfection,
our upbringing could also be a factor.
The Watchtower  of September 15, 2006,
page 21, paragraph 6 states:
“In addition to human imperfection,
“family environment plays a role
in the misuse of the tongue.
“Some people were raised in homes
“where parents were ‘not open
to any agreement, . . .
without self-control, fierce.’”
Despite such challenges,
it is possible for each one of us
to “seek peace and pursue it.”
Jesus set a good example
in using the gift of speech wisely.
He used his speech to encourage
and comfort others.
While on earth, he applied to himself
the words
found at Isaiah 61:1,
which states the following:
“The spirit of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah
is upon me,
“because Jehovah anointed me
to declare good news to the meek.
“He sent me to bind up the brokenhearted,
“to proclaim liberty to the captives
and the wide opening of the eyes
to the prisoners.”
As recorded at Matthew 12:20,
Matthew applies the words
of Isaiah 42:1-3 to Jesus.
At Matthew 12:20, he stated:
“No bruised reed will he crush,
“and no smoldering wick will he extinguish,
until he brings justice with success.”
We learn an important lesson
from such verses.
Jesus recognized that the tongue has power
—power to harm and power to heal.
The Watchtower  of February 15, 2015,
page 13, and paragraph 11, thus stated
that “Jesus showed discernment
in all he said and did.”
Can we imitate Jesus more closely?
If so, what will you do
the next time an opportunity arises
for you to use your gift of speech wisely?
In the following dramatization,
notice how the wise use of the tongue
helps to heal.
I just need a bit of help.
What do you think I should do
for my winter collection?
Well, I don’t know,
but I love what you did with your new stuff,
especially
this set.
Oh, thanks.
You’ve all given me so many great ideas.
Yeah, but you make them.
Yeah.
OK, girls.
You love it.
Oh, this is my song.
Mine too.
“You have a treasured place
“in Jehovah’s house;
“He’ll help you out [out].
And you have . . .”
Oh, I sing like a crow.
No, stop!
I’ll tell you who else thinks it’s her song,
but you’d better have earplugs handy
—Veronica.
Oh, my goodness!
She’s in love with her own voice.
Ever sit near her at the hall?
It’s like she’s the only one that can sing.
And she’s such a diva.
My first thought:
‘Oh, no! Here we go again!
I’ve seen this movie before.’
You don’t think she’s showing off?
Is this just about Haley?
It seems it’s all about Haley.
Is there just a little bit of envy in there?
I’ve lived it.
If it’s a case of her being more careful
how she comes across,
that’s another matter.
What did she suggest?
That I should tell her
that she needs to stop.
Can you believe that?
Especially as a pioneer,
what kind of example is she setting?
How quickly it snowballs out of control!
That’s not what I am saying at all.
You are such . . .
Wow! I can’t believe you.
Are you that lonely
that you’ve got nothing better to do?
Haley!
How difficult it can be to unravel!
I’m sorry.
I shouldn’t have judged you so harshly.
I shouldn’t have judged you at all.
A chance to forgive
is a chance to imitate Jehovah.
Think back to a time
when you wanted forgiveness.
Has anyone ever tried talking to her
about her singing?
You know what I love about Veronica?
She’s probably the most hospitable person
I know.
It’s always open house at her place.
And can she cook!
Have you tried her curry?
I haven’t tried it yet.
Yeah, it’s so good.
It’s so good.
I really look forward to that.
It’s really good.
OK, I’ll ask her.
She does these curry nights.
Oh, you’re going to love it.
We should use our gift of speech
to honor God and to benefit others.
And if somebody gets angry at us,
our mild reply can diffuse the situation.
As Proverbs 15:1 says:
“A mild answer turns away rage,
but a harsh word stirs up anger.”
We can also use our gift of speech
to console and encourage others.
First Thessalonians 5:11, 14 states:
“Therefore, keep encouraging one another
and building one another up,
“just as you are in fact doing. . . .
“On the other hand, we urge you, brothers,
“to warn the disorderly, speak consolingly
“to those who are depressed,
support the weak, be patient toward all.”
Yes, even faithful servants of Jehovah
may at times struggle with depression.
How can we help such ones?
Offer specific, genuine commendation
to help them see their own value
in Jehovah’s eyes.
Share with them the powerful words
of Bible texts
showing that Jehovah
truly cares about and loves those
who “are broken at heart”
and “crushed in spirit.”
We can also use the power of our tongue
to provide much needed encouragement
to others.
Has a fellow believer lost
a loved one in death?
Sympathetic words
expressing our care and concern
can comfort a grieving heart.
Is an elderly brother or sister
feeling unneeded?
A thoughtful tongue can reassure older ones
that they are valued and appreciated.
Is someone struggling with a chronic illness?
Kind words shared on the phone or in person
can do much to lift the spirits
of one who is sick.
How pleased our Creator must be
when we use the power of speech
to utter sayings
that are “good for building up”!
We may not be able to fix their problems,
but we can let them know that we love them
and we care about them.
For example, you can arrange
to spend time with him or her.
Additionally, we can use God’s Word
to strengthen them.
Or you may notice
that someone in the congregation
is discouraged or depressed.
You could read an encouraging Bible verse
and even offer to say a prayer.
Reassure such ones
that their brothers and sisters
in the congregation love them.
And speak in a way that shows
that you really mean and believe
what you say.
This symposium has given each one of us
much to think about, has it not?
We have been reminded
that seeking peace is not always easy.
We have also learned
that the pursuit of peace
requires effort.
In what specific ways are you resolved
to “seek peace and pursue it”
in the days ahead?
May we all continue to pursue peace
(1) by not quickly taking offense,
(2) by apologizing,
(3) by forgiving freely,
and (4) by using our gift of speech wisely
to encourage and comfort others.
And may Jehovah, “the God of peace,”
bless you abundantly for doing so!
Thank you, brothers, for reminding us
that the peace we enjoy
does not happen by chance.
It requires continuous effort on our part,
but we can succeed with Jehovah’s help.
We have now come
to the concluding talk of this session.
True Christians come from a variety
of backgrounds and cultures.
Individual consciences differ.
How can we remain united
despite these differences?
Please give your attention
to Brother David Splane,
a member of the Governing Body,
as he delivers the talk entitled
“Safeguard Our ‘Uniting Bond of Peace’!”
When we think of unity,
the words of Psalm 133:1 may come to mind.
Let’s read them.
Now, the words
aren’t going to be on the screen,
so let’s look them up in the Bible.
I’ll give you a moment.
That’s Psalm 133
and verse 1.
It says: “Look!
“How good and how pleasant it is
for brothers to dwell together in unity!”
Well, we certainly agree
with these words of David.
Now, speaking of David,
he knew the value of unity.
And we may remember
that he didn’t always get
to experience it in his own life.
The beginning and the end
of his reign were marked by civil war
—the very opposite of unity.
But you’d think it would have been easy
for the Israelites to remain united.
After all, they came from the same roots;
they were all children of Abraham;
they spoke a common language—Hebrew;
and they came
from a similar social background.
Their ancestors had all been slaves in Egypt.
So there was no basis
for anybody to brag about his heritage.
Still, the Israelites
found reasons to hate one another.
Israel’s first king was from Benjamin.
Its second king was from Judah.
That was reason enough
to start a war in Israel.
Let’s fast-forward now to the first century.
Unity is so important
that it was on Jesus’ mind
on the night before he died.
You remember that he prayed to his Father
that his disciples ‘might be one
just as he and the Father are one.’
Now, that could have been a challenge.
Why do we say that?
From a human standpoint,
there was no reason
for Jesus’ disciples to be united.
Unlike the Israelites,
they did not have a common ancestor,
they did not have a common mother tongue,
and they came
from a variety of social backgrounds.
Think of it: The first Christians
were Jews or Jewish proselytes.
Growing up, they were taught
that Gentiles were unclean,
and they wouldn’t even
enter the home of a Gentile,
let alone preach to one.
As for Gentile Christians,
they came “from every nation under heaven.”
Most of them knew nothing
of the Hebrew language
or the Hebrew Scriptures.
They’d worshipped false gods.
Some had been highly educated at Athens,
Alexandria, or some other
center of worldly wisdom.
Others had little formal education.
Yet, when they accepted the truth,
Christians became united
and at peace with one another.
The apostle Paul wanted to help them
to safeguard that bond of peace.
Now, that’s the theme
of our discussion this morning.
And we’re going to look at his words
recorded at Ephesians 4:3-6,
and we’re going
to focus in on a particular expression
in these verses.
This is Ephesians chapter 4.
I’ll give you a moment.
Ephesians chapter 4
and we’re going to read verses 3-6.
Now, Paul is interested in unity here,
so let’s see how he frames his discussion.
He says: “Earnestly endeavoring
“[so an effort is involved,
earnestly endeavoring]
“to maintain the oneness of the spirit
“in the uniting bond of peace.
“One body there is, and one spirit,
“just as you were called
to the one hope of your calling;
“[and then he emphasizes]
one Lord, one faith,
“one baptism; one God
and Father of all.”
Now, let’s go back to verse 3
and look at the expression
“the uniting bond of peace.”
So our discussion
is “Safeguard Our ‘Uniting Bond of Peace’!”
Now, the Study Bible
has an interesting note on that expression.
It tells us that the word
translated “uniting bond”
can also be translated “ligament”
—ligament.
And it is translated
“ligament” in other verses.
Now, we know what a ligament is.
It’s a band of strong tissue
that holds our bones together.
So when we talk
about the uniting bond of peace,
we mean that peace is the ligament.
It’s the tissue
that holds God’s people together.
That was true in the first century
and is true today.
Like the early Christians,
we come from different backgrounds;
we speak different languages.
Yet, Jehovah has shown us
how to remain united
and at peace.
Now, let’s explain
what we mean by being united.
To be united doesn’t mean
that we all have to like the same things
or we all have
to think the same on every subject.
There’s room
for a variety of tastes and opinions.
There’s variety on this convention program.
We don’t all wear the same style of suit
or have the same color of tie.
What about you?
What’s your favorite color?
your favorite food?
your favorite pet?
In Jehovah’s organization,
there are dog lovers and cat lovers.
And not everyone
likes the same breed of dog or cat.
Have you ever visited someone
who has a pet
that he thinks is just adorable?
You take one look at the animal,
and you wonder
how anyone could love a face like that.
Yet, he does.
People are different,
and their pets are grateful for that.
The variety we find among God’s people today
will continue on into the new world.
Jehovah loves variety.
How many colors are there?
How many species of plants,
birds, and animals are there?
Among God’s creation,
we find the simple and the complex,
the plain and the fancy,
the sweet and the sour,
the rough and the smooth.
There’s great variety among people.
Even in the new world,
perfect humans won’t have
the same personality,
talents, and abilities.
You’ve always wanted to play the violin?
Don’t think that when you’re perfect,
you’ll just be able
to pick up a violin and play.
And there’s no guarantee
you’ll be able to play in our orchestra.
Now, one way to maintain unity
is to respect the conscience of others.
This is very important
because very often when unity is disturbed,
it’s because we don’t respect
the ability of other brothers and sisters
to decide things for themselves.
Now, what do we mean by the conscience?
Let’s be simple.
It’s the faculty
that helps us determine right from wrong.
I’m going to repeat that.
The conscience is the faculty
to determine right from wrong.
Now, let’s consider
how our upbringing and our culture
can help shape
our personal view of right and wrong.
In some cultures, there are large families.
Conversation around the dinner table is loud.
You can hardly hear yourself think.
The children tease one another
and don’t hesitate
to ask each other personal questions.
The girls borrow each other’s clothes,
sometimes without asking.
Some people would say that’s wrong,
but the girls see nothing wrong with it,
and neither do their parents.
In other cultures, family members
are polite and courteous,
but they don’t talk much
about their plans or their feelings.
The parents don’t often talk about their past
because they value their privacy.
Now, some who were raised that way
tend to be rather strict
with themselves and others.
They have definite views of right and wrong.
Borrow their clothes without asking
and they’ll say: “That’s stealing.
I’m calling the elders.”
There are no gray areas with them.
Now, there are lots of exceptions,
and we’re not saying that everyone
in a certain culture fits the bill.
But you get the idea.
Now, what do you suppose happens
when a publisher from one culture
moves into a congregation
where the other culture predominates?
If he doesn’t adjust
his way of viewing others,
he’ll be miserable.
Is one way right and the other wrong?
No.
Members of both cultures
could learn from one another.
Speaking of culture, we might ask ourselves,
‘How do I feel about brothers and sisters
who come from cultures
that are very different from my own?’
They may speak with an accent.
Their style of dress may be different.
Their manners and food
may not be what we’re used to.
Suppose that an elder
is younger than we are
or from a different race.
Will we accept his counsel?
Will we ask him for counsel?
Or will we look for an elder who’s older
and from a similar background?
Will we celebrate our differences,
or will we allow them to disturb our unity?
So that’s one thing.
But let’s talk about our personal history.
Our personal history
can also affect our view of right and wrong.
Some grew up in a household
where alcohol was a problem.
Home was not a happy place.
And as adults, they stay
as far away from alcohol as they can,
and they take a dim view
of anyone who uses it,
even in moderation.
To them, it’s just plain wrong to drink.
Others have only good memories
of their childhood home.
At supper time,
there was always wine on the table,
but nobody ever abused it.
A person who left behind an immoral lifestyle
might be extremely sensitive
about choices of clothing.
He may be troubled by a clothing style
that other brothers and sisters
find totally acceptable.
If they’re not careful,
those who tend to be strict with themselves
could impose their conscience on others.
Now let’s consider a familiar scenario.
Four publishers
are working rural territory in a car group.
Now, each home is separated from the next
by many miles or kilometers.
At the first call, the driver
and her companion get out
and the other sisters stay in the car.
They have no choice.
There’s no place to go.
Now, the householder has many questions,
and a Bible study has started.
It’s noon when the two publishers
return to the car
—all smiles.
You know what’s coming next, don’t you?
One of the sisters in the back seat says,
“Well, the two of us
can’t count any time this morning.”
What’s she done?
She’s spoken for herself
and for her companion.
And unintentionally, she’s imposed
her own conscience on her friend.
Now, if she doesn’t want
to count any time, that’s her business.
It would be best
if she kept her business to herself.
If you’ve ever visited a foreign country
and gone on a guided tour,
probably one of the things
the tour guide wanted to show you
was the architecture inside a church.
Now, some brothers
have no problem entering a church
if it’s part of a tour because to them
it’s no different from visiting a museum.
Others who were
strong supporters of false religion
couldn’t enter a church for any reason,
not even to attend a wedding or a funeral.
To them, it’s just plain wrong.
Consciences can differ in this respect,
and we have to respect that;
we have to acknowledge that.
And we’re going to expand
on that idea in a moment.
Well, we’ve hardly scratched the surface
when it comes to describing
the variety of personalities
and viewpoints in Jehovah’s organization.
So here’s the question:
How can we maintain our unity?
Remember what Paul said?
“Earnestly endeavoring to maintain”
—maintain this perfect bond of unity.
It means that we have to put forth effort
to maintain that unity.
Well, first of all,
it’ll help a lot to get well-acquainted
with brothers and sisters
who think differently from us.
Get to know their background.
That’ll help you not to overreact
when they take a position
that you don’t agree with.
It’ll help us not to judge them.
Now, Paul wrote very plainly on that subject
in the words found at Romans 14:4
—simple statement but very powerful.
Let’s check it out together
at Romans chapter 14
(I’ll give you a moment)
and verse 4.
Paul writes: “Who are you
“to judge the servant of another?
“To his own master he stands or falls.
“Indeed, he will be made to stand,
for Jehovah can make him stand.”
Now let’s go back
and look at that first sentence again:
“Who are you to judge
the servant of another?”
We know what a judge does.
He declares someone guilty or not guilty.
That’s not our job.
Jehovah is the Judge.
If each of us concentrates
on his own thinking and his own conscience,
the peace and unity
of the congregation will be preserved.
Well, we all want to be balanced
when we determine
what is right and what is wrong.
We want to have a balanced view of things
—a good conscience.
So how can we be balanced
when determining
whether something is right or wrong?
Now, in some cases, it’s easy;
the Bible tells us.
But in other cases, there’s no clear answer.
Let’s consider a scenario
we touched on earlier
—the matter of entering a church.
Now, that may not be
a problem where you live,
but in some places, it’s a real issue.
And remember, these talks
are for our worldwide brotherhood.
So we’re going to consider a subject
that will be a real problem
for many to overcome,
and we hope that they will benefit from it.
So here’s the scenario:
Two different sisters are married
to men who are not in the truth.
Now, in both cases,
the husband’s mother has died.
The funeral will be in a church.
One sister decides to go;
the other decides against it.
The sister who decides to attend
has considered that in that church,
there will just be a talk by a clergyman.
There will be no congregation singing,
congregation prayers, or religious gestures.
She was never very religious anyway,
so none of that would mean anything to her.
And her husband and his family will be happy
if she just sits quietly until it’s over.
Now, the second sister
has a different set of circumstances.
The service in that church
involves participation by the congregation.
She used to be
an active member of that church,
and she’s afraid
she’ll do something she’ll regret.
Her husband’s family
get very emotional at funerals,
and they’re likely to make a scene
if she doesn’t participate.
So she respectfully tells her husband
that her attendance
could cause him embarrassment
and declines to attend.
You can see that each situation is different.
Now we’re going to discuss four questions
that we might ask ourselves
when we’re called upon
to make any difficult decision.
And I will repeat the question
because if you’re taking notes,
you may want to at least
write the question down.
These are very, very good questions
that we can ask ourselves
before we make a difficult decision.
Are you ready?
Here’s number one:
What will make Jehovah happy?
I’ll repeat that.
And that should be our main concern,
to please Jehovah.
Well, how do we know
what will make Jehovah happy?
We identify the Bible principles
that have a bearing on the situation.
One way we can do that
is by checking the Index
or the Research Guide.
What are some Scriptural principles
a sister who’s married to an unbeliever
might consider when deciding
whether to attend a funeral in a church?
Can you think of some?
What about 1 Peter 3:1?
“Wives, be in subjection to your husbands.”
Jehovah is pleased when
a Christian woman respects her husband,
whether he’s in the truth or not.
But a wife’s subjection is relative.
She’s dedicated to Jehovah,
not to her husband.
So that’s 1 Peter 3:1.
What about Isaiah 52:11?
“Touch nothing unclean! . . .
Keep yourselves clean.”
Under the Mosaic Law,
if someone so much as
touched something unclean,
he became unclean.
Many brothers and sisters
would find it very hard to sit quietly
while a clergyman told lies
about the condition of the dead.
To them, it would be
touching something unclean.
Others might compare that
to a young person in school
sitting quietly while his teacher
tells lies about the origin of life.
If someone does decide
to attend a funeral in a church,
he or she should be absolutely determined
not to participate in any religious ritual,
whether singing hymns
or so much as saying “amen”
to a prayer that the clergyman offers.
Remember, the goal is to please Jehovah.
So the first point was,
What makes Jehovah happy?
Number two—number two:
How might my choice affect others?
Have you got that?
How might my choice
affect others?
We would never want to stumble anyone.
Even in a family matter,
such as attending a wedding
or a funeral in a church
(which we may consider as a personal matter),
we need to weigh the effect our decision
could have on others.
It could affect them in one of two ways.
Now, the first is the obvious way.
In some areas, if a Witness
even entered a church,
his brothers and sisters
would lose respect for him.
But there’s a second way
the Witness could stumble someone.
He might be able to attend the funeral
and make no compromise.
But suppose a new brother decided
to follow his example
when a family member died.
The new brother could give in
to family pressure
and participate in idolatry.
How tragic is that!
The apostle Paul never worshipped idols.
So when meat that had been offered to an idol
went up for sale in a meat market,
it probably didn’t bother
Paul’s conscience to buy it
because he knew that an idol is nothing.
But some of his brothers had worshipped
those very idols
before coming into the truth.
They could have felt guilty
about eating that meat.
To them, it would be
like having a communion meal with an idol.
The feelings of his brothers
were important to Paul.
He was willing to sacrifice his own rights
for the sake of his brothers.
We’d never want to take the unloving view
that if our brother
is stumbled by what we do,
it’s too bad for him.
On the other hand,
if we’re the type of person
who is often stumbled by what others do,
we need to ask Jehovah
to help us gain a more balanced viewpoint.
So far, we’ve discussed
the need to make Jehovah happy
and to consider the feelings of our brothers.
What’s next?
Number three: Have I asked for counsel?
You got that?
Have I asked for counsel?
Now, maybe the elders haven’t dealt
with the exact situation we’re facing,
but they know a lot of people.
They may know someone
who has dealt with the situation before
and saw how he handled it.
Or they may know about the effect
the decision had on others.
For example, they might know
how the congregation reacted
the last time someone attended a wedding
or a funeral in a church.
Another situation where brothers often ask
for the help of the elders
involves the use of blood fractions.
Should we accept them or not?
The Governing Body has refused
to impose its conscience on the brotherhood.
But what do we know?
We know that the Bible says
to “abstain . . . from blood.”
But as you divide it into fractions
and the fractions get tinier and tinier,
at what point does blood stop being blood?
Each one will have to decide that
for himself.
Now, some might say,
“Well, if it’s a really,
really tiny fraction,
it doesn’t bother me to take it.”
But others will say:
“It doesn’t matter to me.
If it’s from blood, I don’t want it.”
And their conscience
also has to be respected.
Now let’s illustrate:
Air is made up of nitrogen
and oxygen,
and together they make up 99 percent of air.
That leaves 1 percent.
The 1 percent is made up
of a variety of gases:
carbon dioxide, hydrogen, neon
—small fractions.
When it comes to small fractions,
elders need to be careful, though,
not to insert their personal opinion
into the discussion,
such as by saying
“I wouldn’t take any of it.”
They should simply help the publisher
to reason on the basic principles
and let him make up his own mind.
So where are we?
We make Jehovah happy.
We consider the feelings
of our brothers and sisters.
We ask for counsel.
Number four:
Did I take the time
—did I take the time—
to meditate prayerfully
before making my decision?
Did I take the time to meditate prayerfully
Your goal is to make Jehovah happy.
So you wouldn’t want
to make your decision hastily
and then ask Jehovah to bless it.
We should ask Jehovah for guidance first
rather than asking him to bless a decision
we’ve already made.
Have you ever heard someone say,
“That doesn’t bother my conscience”?
We might ask:
‘How did he come to that conclusion?
‘Did he follow the four steps
we just mentioned?
‘Did he do research to learn
what makes Jehovah happy?
‘Did he think
about how others might be affected?
‘Did he ask for counsel?
‘And did he meditate prayerfully
on his decision?
Or is he just following his feelings?’
Following your feelings isn’t the same
as following a Bible-trained conscience.
I’m going to repeat that.
Following your feelings is not the same
as following a Bible-trained conscience.
Our conscience needs to be trained
in harmony with Scriptural principles.
Now, Paul’s conscience
didn’t bother him a bit
when he was persecuting Christians.
He thought he was doing Jehovah a favor.
But when he realized
how Jehovah felt about it,
he knew he had to change.
We have to be sure that we’re really getting
Jehovah’s thinking on matters.
Remember Jeremiah 17:9
—simple expression but so true.
Jeremiah chapter 17
and verse 9 says:
“The heart is more treacherous
“than anything else and is desperate.
Who can know it?”
‘The heart is treacherous.’
We might allow our emotions
to get the better of us.
For example, when a family member
is disfellowshipped,
if the person is living outside the home,
we know that we should limit our association
to necessary family business.
Now, if the family was never very close,
that might not be a problem.
But suppose family ties are really strong;
that can be a challenge.
If we allow ourselves to be ruled by emotion
rather than by Scriptural principles,
we could stretch the meaning
of necessary family business
to include almost any activity.
The heart is treacherous.
Asking ourselves
the four questions we just mentioned
can help us to make decisions
based on godly principles
rather than simply relying on our feelings.
Now let’s see how mature Christians
can apply these principles
and how the elders can help.
The following video interviews
are about weddings and funerals
—a touchy subject
in many cultures, as you will see.
In Japan,
religious rituals are associated
with each stage of life
and with each season of the year.
As Jehovah’s Witnesses,
we want to keep the cleanliness and unity
of the congregation.
In this regard,
one of the most delicate areas
is the decision on whether to attend
a non-Witness funeral or not.
The first thing we must consider
regarding funerals is not to be involved
in religious rituals and acts of worship
that are condemned by the Bible.
In harmony with the principle
at 2 Corinthians 6:14,
we need to keep completely separate
from pagan acts of worship.
Next, even if we don’t participate
in the worship of other religions,
we need to consider if our decisions
could stumble someone in the congregation.
When we consider the Bible principle
at Luke 17:2,
we do not want our decisions to hinder
the faith of someone in the congregation.
The third point to think about
is our conscience.
We need to seriously think
about the Bible principle
at Galatians 6:5, where it says
that each must “carry his own load.”
This Bible principle also applies
when elders want to support others.
Of course, those in the congregation
can ask the elders for support
in issues related to funerals.
However, in matters of conscience,
elders cannot force decisions on others.
So it would be wrong to make
some kind of rule regarding attending
non-Witness funerals.
If each person can make
decisions based on Bible principles,
we can have a truly peaceful
and free atmosphere
where each individual’s
differing situation is respected.
This would really contribute
to the unity of the congregation.
And all can maintain a clean conscience
and serve happily before Jehovah.
In my culture,
specifically the Namibian Oshiwambo
culture,
like in many African cultures,
there are many spiritistic customs
related to weddings
that are included in wedding celebrations.
Unfortunately, my family is not in the truth.
So obviously, for Ben and I,
that was one of the main concerns.
They don’t understand our worship of Jehovah,
and they don’t understand
that we apply Bible principles
and not the traditions of men.
We got engaged before the pandemic,
but obviously, now that our wedding
was to be over videoconferencing,
it meant that we didn’t have control
over many things.
We tried to imagine situations
that could stumble our brothers or disrupt
the unity in the congregation.
We had to, in advance,
think of Bible principles
that would apply in our case,
but particularly what we also found helpful
was speaking to a mature elder.
He gave us a principle at Proverbs 14:15.
He told us to be very careful
when people say,
“I will do this” or “I won’t do this”
at your wedding.
Basically, it was up to us to make sure
that the proceedings
or things that happen at our wedding
would be in order and in harmony
with Bible principles.
Another principle that came to mind was
1 Corinthians 10:23.
So obviously, we knew
that we had the right to do many things,
but we were also very conscious
of how our brothers would view our wedding.
We didn’t want anybody to be at our wedding
and feel embarrassed
or even stumbled to be there.
Now looking back at our wedding,
we look back with fond memories.
So applying Bible principles
didn’t restrict our fun.
Also, it contributed to the unity
among our brothers
because all of us
—those present, those who were invited—
were able to enjoy the wedding.
You’re not worried about thinking,
‘Oh, did that thing offend anybody?’
So you’re able to enjoy the day
without any bad memories.
As you can see,
our brothers in many countries
are faced with very difficult decisions
where weddings and funerals are concerned.
The guidance the elders
can provide is invaluable.
Now, sometimes medical doctors
complain that their Witness patients
are inconsistent
because they don’t all have the same view
of certain medical treatments.
One Witness patient
accepts certain fractions or therapies,
so the doctor figures he knows
what Jehovah’s Witnesses believe.
But then the next patient comes along,
and he rejects them all.
The doctor is confused.
Those doctors don’t understand
the role of the conscience.
We shouldn’t worry
when medical professionals
don’t understand our differing viewpoints,
because we should be glad
that we serve a God
who dignifies us
with the freedom to make many
of our own decisions.
Now, the apostle Paul
mentioned four qualities
that will help us to maintain
the uniting bond of peace.
And we’re going to find those qualities
at Ephesians chapter 4,
and we’re going to zero in on verse 2.
Let’s turn to Ephesians chapter 4,
and we’re going to look at verse 2.
Now, we read verses 3-6 earlier,
and you know that Paul
was concerned about unity.
Unity is what he had on his mind,
and now he is telling us
that these four qualities
are going to help us to maintain our unity.
“Earnestly endeavoring”
—remember when he said
“earnestly endeavoring
to maintain the oneness of the spirit”?
It’s the work that we need
to put into promoting unity.
Verse 2 says:
“With all humility and mildness,
“with patience,
putting up with one another in love.”
Isn’t that beautiful?
You notice the qualities:
humility, mildness,
patience, and love?
When we’re humble,
we recognize that our opinion
isn’t always the right one.
Humility will also prevent us
from trying to impose
our conscience on others
as if Jehovah had appointed us to judge them.
What about mildness?
Mildness will help us to think
about the effect our words might have
on our brothers and sisters.
We would never want to hurt them,
even when we strongly disagree with them.
And we should give them
the benefit of the doubt.
If someone says something
that makes you mad,
pray before you speak.
Pray before you speak.
“Love covers a multitude of sins,”
which contributes
to the peace of the congregation.
And we deeply appreciate it
when our brothers are patient with us.
In turn, we need to be patient with them
because we’re all
at different stages of spiritual growth,
and we have to acknowledge that.
Well, we’ve talked
about making Jehovah happy
with our decisions.
We can also please Jehovah
when we work hard
to promote peace in the congregation,
and sometimes it does take
an earnest endeavor.
Sometimes we have to work hard
at ensuring
that the congregation is at peace.
What about the elders?
The elders take the lead
in working together in unity.
They should always speak with a united voice.
If they don’t, their congregation
will sense that they’re divided,
and this will make
the brothers and sisters uneasy.
Any difference of opinion
should be worked out in private,
while showing deep respect for one another.
Just because someone disagrees with us
doesn’t make him a bad person.
We have to understand that,
and his difference of opinion
may search us through.
It may be something
that we need to think about and consider.
And we always consider
that the other person may be right.
What about us publishers?
If we’re having a hard time
getting along with someone,
rather than asking Jehovah to change him,
we should ask Jehovah to mold us,
like the Great Potter he is.
We should ask him to show us
why he drew that person to the congregation.
Remember what Jesus said?
‘No one comes to him
unless the Father draws him.’
What does Jehovah see in that person
that we aren’t seeing?
We each have a responsibility to contribute
to the peace and unity of the congregation.
May Jehovah bless us
as we work toward that goal.
Thank you, Brother Splane,
for that motivating talk!
We are determined to do our part
to safeguard our “uniting bond of peace.”
This session has provided
such practical lessons!
What can we look forward to
in the next session?
The theme scripture will be Romans 15:13,
which says in part:
“May the God who gives hope
fill you with all joy and peace.”
The program will feature
a seven-part symposium
with Bible examples of those who sowed
and reaped peace.
We will also want to invite
as many as possible
to enjoy the public Bible discourse entitled
“Friendship With God—How Possible?”
Now let’s sing together song number 113,
which draws attention to what it means
to have godly peace.
The song is entitled
“Our Possession of Peace.”
After the song, you may have
your local concluding prayer.
Again, that’s song number 113.