We are overjoyed that you are
among the millions around the world
who are viewing this convention.
An infirm Bible student named Joyce,
who lives in Southeast Asia,
expressed her appreciation
for these arrangements by saying:
“With the convention being streamed online,
“I don’t have to miss a single talk!
“I can watch the program
with the rest of the brotherhood worldwide.
I am so thankful to Jehovah
for this arrangement.”
Perhaps you can relate to her expressions.
Thank you for the generous donations
you have made online
at donate.jw.org and by other means,
which help make
these streaming services possible.
During these critical last days,
many families lack the affection
that Jehovah designed us to give and receive.
However, God’s Word contains principles
that, when followed, lead to peace.
We’re sure you will enjoy
the fine talks and dramatizations
in this next symposium.
Brother Joel Dellinger,
a helper to the Service Committee,
will deliver the first talk,
“Follow the Road Map to Family Peace
—Show Love and Respect.”
Family peace is precious.
It’s even as the Bible proverb says:
“Better is a piece of dry bread
where there is peace
than a house full of feasting
along with quarreling.”
But what exactly is family peace?
Someone might say, “As long as we’re not
arguing, our family is at peace.”
But is that real peace?
We might think of two countries
that were fighting
but have now agreed to a cease-fire.
Does the cease-fire mean that they’ve become
real friends who love one another?
No.
We know that genuine peace takes more work.
That’s true in the family as well.
Our heavenly Father knows
that the most satisfying family peace
involves more than an absence of arguing.
It involves a family’s well-being and unity.
Is such peace in a family today
really possible?
Although none of us have a perfect family,
the answer is yes.
While it requires work
—perhaps breaking bad habits
that disrupt peace and adopting
new ones that promote it—
those efforts are worth it.
In this symposium,
we’ll see how Bible principles
can guide families to peace,
just as a road map
guides travelers to a beautiful destination.
In each of the talks,
we invite you husbands, fathers,
wives, mothers, children, teenagers
to be the traveler who studies the map
and then goes in the right direction.
The focus of our first talk
is showing love and respect.
Why would you say these two qualities
are so important to family peace?
Well, it’s simple:
because family members
who love and respect one another
feel secure and appreciated.
As a result, our relationships
are warm, close, and peaceful.
Of course, showing love and respect
can be a challenge these days.
In the following dramatization notice why.
Irene.
Aww,
you look so handsome there.
Oh, you look beautiful.
Those came out so nice.
Look at you.
Crazy, right?
That’s the day!
Look at us.
You’re so surprised.
I just knew you were going to do it.
Sorry, Olivia.
Are you OK?
Yeah, it’s OK, Sue.
I’m so sorry.
No worries.
Um, I’m all moved in.
That was the last box.
Dad, are those the wedding photos?
Yeah.
Let me see.
Look it. Here’s . . .
Oh, you all look beautiful.
That dress looks so nice.
You look so good.
Aww, look at you.
Aww, that suits you.
Very nice, you guys.
Yeah, it all came together.
It really did.
Yeah.
Olivia?
I know this is all new, baby.
Be patient.
Can I cut in?
Yeah, sure.
Thanks.
What’s wrong?
Where’s the desk?
We had to get rid of it.
This one is better for everyone.
You mean it’s better for him!
For Max?
What are you saying?
What do you care?
Don’t talk to me like that. Get back here!
Hey, Olivia, what do you think
about the desk?
Come here, sweetie. Come here.
So you never forget that I love you.
I hope you like it.
Today, every family
faces challenges of some sort.
So let’s consult our road map together
in the Bible at Romans 12:10.
Would you read it with me, please?
That’s Romans 12:10:
“In brotherly love
“have tender affection for one another.
In showing honor to one another,
take the lead.”
Now, what’s the point?
Regardless of the role we play in the family,
each of us needs to treat our family members
with love and respect.
We need to “take the lead,”
or initiative, to do so.
To help us, let’s consider four good habits
that all of us should work
to develop more fully.
Habit number one:
Regularly express tender affection.
When conveyed with sincerity,
expressions of affection
are like sunshine and water to plants.
They help everyone
in the family grow and thrive.
In the video we just watched,
did you note how Olivia
cherished her father’s gift (that green desk)
and his tender words?
He told her,
“So you never forget that I love you.”
We also saw warm affection
as the newly blended family
of Max and Irene looked at wedding photos.
That was encouraging.
Well, here’s a question: How are we doing
in expressing tender affection in our family?
If that’s not one of our strengths,
we might relate to a husband
who mustered up the courage
to say “I love you” to his wife.
It brought her to tears—tears of joy.
And she said this, “I love you too,
but this is the first time in 25 years
you’ve said it like that.”
Well, what’s the point?
We don’t want to wait that long, of course,
but even an awkward attempt
at expressing affection in our family
is an act of love,
and it can do so much good.
That’s a habit we all want to cultivate.
Let’s consider a second habit:
Be kind in your actions,
tone of voice, and choice of words.
In the video, we recall Irene’s reassurance
to her daughter, Olivia.
She said: “I know this is all new, baby.
Be patient.”
Mom was kind
in what she said and how she said it.
A little later, though, Olivia was upset.
While we know she was hurt,
her speech and actions were not so kind,
were they?
During the pandemic,
all of us have been under tremendous stress,
and likely we didn’t always treat others
in our family as kindly
as we would have liked.
Well, that’s in the past.
But what can we all do now?
We can pray to Jehovah
to help us “take the lead”
in showing kindness.
For example,
every day greeting one another kindly,
every day saying “please” and “thank you,”
sharing little gifts,
making time to talk, really listening
—all of these are acts of kindness.
That’s a good habit we all want to cultivate.
What’s habit number three?
Be quick to apologize and forgive freely.
In the video, Olivia’s new stepsister, Sue,
apologized after she bumped into Olivia
with a box by mistake.
That apology promoted peace.
When you and I realize we’ve hurt someone
even unintentionally, what should we do?
We should make amends quickly.
A mother named Marina said this:
“We try to set a good example
for our children
“in forgiving others
. . . and not getting offended.
“When I am wrong, I apologize to my children.
I want them to learn to do the same
in their dealings with others.”
That’s a good habit, wouldn’t you agree?
Well, let’s consider one more,
a fourth habit:
Help your family members feel respected.
An article in the Awake!  magazine
once made this insightful comment:
“Respect is in the eye of the beholder.”
What does that mean?
Even if we think
we’re showing respect in the family,
good questions to ask ourselves are:
‘Do my family members
feel that I respect them?
‘Is there more I can do to help my mate,
my children, or my parents
feel loved and respected?’
Brothers and sisters, when we fulfill
our God-given role in the family
by developing good habits such as these,
we show respect both for Jehovah
and for all of our family members.
Now, let’s think about Olivia and her mom.
In the next video,
note how peace can be restored
by showing love and respect.
It’s OK, Mom.
You didn’t know.
Dad did that for her just before he died.
Anything I can do to help?
Romans 12:10:
“In showing honor to one another,
take the lead.”
Olivia?
I made your favorite tonight.
Thank you.
I wanted to tell you
that I didn’t handle that so well today.
You had good reason
to be upset about the desk.
Mom, you didn’t know.
It’s just one of those things
that Dad did just for me.
I know he’s my stepdad now, but
I just wish he would have checked first.
It wasn’t Max.
It was me.
I wanted to surprise Max
with a place for him to do his work.
So he didn’t make you get rid of the desk?
No.
I just thought you both didn’t care.
I will never ever stop caring about you.
What a beautiful outcome!
The well-being and unity
of the family were restored.
The mom, Irene,
applied the principle at Romans 12:10.
She ‘took the lead,’ or the initiative,
to talk kindly with her daughter.
Though Olivia was upset,
she too showed love and respect
by being willing to listen to her mom.
As a result,
the misunderstanding was cleared up,
and Irene used the opportunity to reassure
her precious daughter of her love,
saying, “I will never ever
stop caring about you.”
And how our hearts were touched
to see their warm embrace!
When we “take the lead”
in applying Bible principles,
we promote genuine family peace.
So may all of us be determined
to keep showing our family
that we truly love and respect them
in word and action.
Now please listen as Brother Robert Luccioni,
a helper to the Publishing Committee,
considers the next talk
of this symposium, with the theme
“Follow the Road Map to Family Peace
—Improve Communication.”
Our previous talk reminded us
that it’s possible
for a family to enjoy peace,
but it takes work.
Let’s look at one more step
that can help us stay on the road to peace,
and that is good communication.
A family promotes peace
when all the family members communicate
in an open, calm, and honest manner.
But how does communication help with peace?
Well, a pattern of good communication
keeps a family close.
It helps us to identify and address problems
before these reach a point
that they take peace away.
Now, that may seem obvious.
But isn’t it true that we may find
that between work and school,
the meetings and ministry,
and recreation and just life in general
it’s hard to find time
to communicate as a family?
Is that a challenge in your family?
In the following dramatization,
notice what habits
hinder family communication.
Hey, Steve.
Yeah, I’m sorry I was late to the meeting.
I should have been there
to help out with my assignment.
Yeah, we got delayed.
We’re late!
Let’s go, kids!
We’re coming! Sorry!
Yeah, the family is fine.
Everybody is adjusting really well.
Anyone seen my glasses?
Anyone?
I mean, we might be a little out of sync,
but I don’t know
—every family has their issues, right?
You going outside in those?
Mm-hmm.
Hey, well, thanks for understanding.
All right.
OK. Take care.
All right, bye-bye.
Did you notice some habits
that hinder family communication?
In the case of this family, it seems like
technology is stifling their communication.
And they obviously have some things
they need to communicate about
—punctuality, dress and grooming—
but it’s not happening.
Now, while the scenes of them
all looking at their devices
and ignoring one another
may have been a bit humorous,
did it remind you of your family at times?
What a good reminder
for us not to let the use of technology
rob our family of our time and attention!
So how can we develop habits
that promote good communication?
Let’s consider the second Bible principle
of this symposium.
Let’s turn together, please,
to Ephesians chapter 5.
And let’s read verses 15 and 16
—Ephesians 5:15, 16:
“So keep strict watch that how you
“walk is not as unwise but as wise persons,
“making the best use of your time,
because the days are wicked.”
Now, let’s look at two ways
that this Bible principle can help us.
The first is by making time
to have meaningful communication.
Did you notice there in verse 16
it says “making the best use of your time”?
Now, the study note for this phrase indicates
the need to ‘buy out the time’
for important things
from other pursuits.
So how can this apply
to family communication?
Well, this could include
having a plan, or a routine,
for when we spend time together
as a family each day.
And during those times,
we may choose to limit
our use of technology so that it
does not interfere with communication;
perhaps it’s in the evening
or at a specific mealtime.
One brother named Aaron stated,
“We have our evening meal together,
“which allows us time to talk
and hear what’s important
to each member of the family.”
He says: “My wife and I
have arranged our schedules
“so we take the boys
to school and pick them up.
This allows us to spend more time with them.”
And then he says,
“My wife and I regularly take walks
and freely talk about our concerns.”
What’s the point?
Well, they’re making good use of their time.
However, to do this, they’ve had to buy
that time out from other pursuits.
But they have a plan; they have a routine.
So, what plan, or routine,
does your family have
for meaningful communication each day?
If you don’t have one, can you start now?
Let’s look at the second way
that this Bible principle can help us.
And that is by determining when and how
to deal with problems when they do arise.
You notice verse 15 in Ephesians chapter 5
says that we should ‘walk as wise persons.’
It means we need
to choose our paths carefully,
knowing when to go, when to stop,
when to take another route.
Well, how can that help us
when problems arise?
Well, a wise person
generally knows when is and when is not
a good time to address a problem.
For example, we all can attest
that when emotions are high,
it’s probably not the best time
to bring up an issue.
One father states:
“Sometimes we need to wait
and let things cool.
“Often a night’s rest
with prayer makes a big difference
when we address the issue the next morning.”
That’s a wise person.
A wise person also listens.
James 1:19 reminds us to “be quick to listen,
slow to speak, [and] slow to anger.”
Thus, we can go to Jehovah in prayer
and ask him to help us to really listen,
to stay calm, to stay humble.
One sister named Dawn states,
“When there are problems,
the first thing I do
is ask Jehovah in prayer to help us
resolve the problem calmly.”
Then she says, “Then we talk
with the family member privately
and really try to listen
to their side of the issue.”
That’s a wise person.
A wise person will also consider the approach
and the words that he or she uses.
For example, rather than telling
our family member that they have a problem,
can we turn it around so that it’s something
that we all need to work on together?
Do you reassure your family members
that you really love them
and you want to understand
their side of the issue or the problem?
See, now, doing this,
we’re not attacking the family member
but, rather,
showing that we’re all in this together.
So we see benefits of this Bible principle
in communication in our family, don’t we?
You notice the two points:
(1) making the best use of our time
and (2) walking as wise persons.
Now, communication will always be
a work in progress,
but it’s worth the effort,
as it will go a long way
to bringing peace to your family.
Let’s watch more of our dramatization
and notice the benefits of developing habits
that promote good communication.
I don’t know.
What do you think?
We all have to work on it.
I know I need to.
Why don’t we approach it that way
with the kids
—just be open with them?
That sounds like a good idea.
OK. So Irene and I have been talking about
communication
in our family.
We wanted to talk
about our phones and other devices.
You’re not talking about me, are you?
You can’t do that.
No, no.
I know that we can all be
more balanced, but . . .
I need it.
You’re joking, right? You mean them.
You can’t take them away.
I haven’t done anything bad.
I have responsibilities.
Hold on.
You’re always on your phone too.
That’s true.
It’s OK.
Let’s just talk about it, all right?
Sue,
can you read Ephesians 5:15, 16
for us, please?
“So keep strict watch that how you walk
“is not as unwise but as wise persons,
making the best use of your time,
because the days are wicked.”
So
how do you think we’re doing
with our phones and other devices?
It isn’t that what you’re doing
on your devices is wrong.
Exactly.
But could it be taking time away
from more important things
—like talking to each other,
and in that way affecting even
how we’re talking to each other?
Yeah, I think it’d be smart
to have some boundaries then.
Yeah, OK.
OK.
Let’s talk about how we can do that.
Hey!
Hey, Olivia.
Hey.
Evidently, I haven’t figured out
how to talk to her about her clothes yet.
Hmm.
I need your help.
I got this one.
I know,
but it’s all about good spiritual judgment.
Do you think that these trends reflect
Jehovah’s view of “respectable dress”?
I know that you’ll do the right thing.
OK.
Hey, Gabe, can you take us?
Yeah, of course.
Mm-hmm.
While we’re all here,
I know we all have
different views on punctuality,
but
I really need your help
so that I can take care
of some of my responsibilities.
You think we can meet in the middle?
OK.
Yeah.
All right. Great.
Now, this symposium has been discussing
four Bible principles
that can guide families to peace.
Brother Dellinger considered the first one
at Romans 12:10.
And in this part, we considered
Ephesians chapter 5,
verses 15, 16.
Now, did we see how this scripture
helped our family in the video?
Well, we saw that they knew down deep
that they were not making
the best use of their time,
so they made changes.
They saw that they needed to set boundaries
so that they could improve
their communication.
We also saw how the family
—the parents—acted as wise persons.
How?
Well, by determining when and how
to address the problems
that needed to be addressed,
such as the use of technology,
dress and grooming,
and punctuality.
Well, can this Bible principle
help your family
—help my family—to improve communication?
Would this be a good scripture to include
in your next family worship?
Now, it takes time to learn how
to communicate well as a family.
But it is worth the effort.
Why?
Well, if we strive to communicate
well each day,
then communication will come more readily
when there are problems.
So be determined to look for ways
to improve communication in your family.
And by taking this initiative
and sticking with it,
you will be following the road map
to family peace.
Please listen now to Brother David Splane,
a member of the Governing Body,
as he considers the next talk
of this symposium,
“Follow the Road Map to Family Peace
—Work as a Team.”
Jehovah intended married couples
to work together.
That’s why Jesus used the expression we find
at Matthew 19:6.
Let’s read this from the Bible
—Matthew 19.
And I’ll give you a moment.
Matthew chapter 19
—now, we’re going to read verse 6.
Now, first of all, Jesus quotes
from Genesis 2:24.
Speaking of married couples, he says:
“So that they are no longer two,
but one flesh.”
Now, you remember, Jehovah
made that comment in the garden of Eden.
But now Jesus adds something
that isn’t in Genesis.
He says: “Therefore, what God has yoked
“[yoked] together,
let no man put apart.”
When we think of a yoke,
we may think of a team of horses
plowing a field or pulling a heavy wagon.
Well, if they pull together,
they can be a powerful force.
The same is true
when family members work together.
Mom, Dad
—you have excellent reasons to work together.
When you work together,
you contribute to the peace of the family.
And think of the effect
it has on the children.
By working together, you’re teaching
that fine young son of yours
how to be a caring husband and father,
and your beautiful daughter how to be
a supportive wife and mother.
But what happens when teammates
begin pulling in opposite directions
or when one puts on the brakes?
Let’s watch a video.
Now, here’s the setup.
For a long time, a sister raised
her two children as a single parent,
and she did a great job of it.
Then she married a very kind brother.
The family has a new head.
Let’s see how well the sister
is adapting to her new role.
The last few weeks of family worship
have been nice,
right?
Yeah.
All these things we ask and pray
in Jesus’ name, Amen.
Amen.
OK, this week . . .
We are in chapter 5.
Yep, that’s right.
And last week, Gabe read, so this week . . .
It’s Sue’s turn.
That’s right.
OK, the point here is
that when it comes . . .
Honey, maybe an illustration would be better.
Um, OK.
It’s like a bird . . .
Well, hopefully I was able to clear that up
for you a little bit, Olivia.
Yeah. Thank you.
Well, actually, Max, that’s not true.
We had an updated understanding
in the recent Watchtower.
Thanks.
I think they went really well, right?
Um, actually . . .
Hey.
Maybe we can talk about it later.
OK.
The sister isn’t a bad person.
But we can ask:
What is she teaching her daughter
about the wife’s role in the family?
And what is her son learning
about taking the lead
as the man of the house?
He hasn’t had a man
in his life for a long time.
Now there is one.
It’s safe to say that the kids
will stand a better chance
of having a successful marriage themselves
when they see their parents pulling together.
A little later, we’ll see how
the husband handles the situation,
and we brothers
are going to want to pay attention.
This is a classic.
Family life is more pleasant when Dad, Mom,
and the kids work together as a team.
The family head is the captain.
He needs to make sure that everyone knows
what goals the family is working toward
and how each one can contribute
toward achieving those goals.
When it’s your family’s turn
to help clean the Kingdom Hall
or a convention venue, for example,
don’t leave the kids at home.
They’re part of the team.
Don’t go there with half the team.
Let them experience the joy
that comes from serving others.
Let them work along with you.
If you’re assigned to clean the restrooms,
don’t complain about it—a very fine example.
Your children will learn that when
there’s work to be done, we just do it.
We aren’t picky about what we will
and will not do.
And we don’t feel
that some jobs are beneath us.
Now, this is in line with Paul’s counsel
found at Philippians 2:3, 4.
Let’s look that up.
It’s good exercise
—Philippians chapter 2,
verses 3, 4.
Now, we’re thinking about the family
as a team here.
It says: “Do nothing out of contentiousness
“or out of egotism,
“but with humility consider
others superior to you,
“as you look out
not only for your own interests,
but also for the interests of others.”
When there’s work to be done,
someone has to do it.
Do I think that I’m so special
that someone else has to look after it?
Some families volunteer
to help with Kingdom Hall maintenance.
When the kids are old enough,
they can work on other projects
like working on an Assembly Hall.
They have a ball!
The friendships that you
and your young people will forge
can last a lifetime.
And here’s a bonus: When the young people
go to a circuit assembly
or a regional convention,
they’ll have good friends to associate with
—both young and old—
people they’ve been working with.
What about working around the house?
Some parents feel that the children
shouldn’t have to help out at all
because they have their schoolwork to do.
But their schoolwork is something
they do for themselves.
How are they contributing
to the welfare of the family?
How are they learning
to serve others unselfishly?
It’s good for a child to feel that he has
an important role in the household
and that people are counting on him.
Think what that does for his self-respect.
A father named Steven said,
“When nothing is expected of them,
“children learn that they
are here to be served,
“and they grow up with a distorted view
of what life will require of them.”
We might ask, Would a young person
with that attitude
even be able to keep a job?
When some in the world lose their job,
they remain unemployed for a long time.
They can’t pay the bills.
Yet, there are job opportunities
all around them,
but they consider those jobs beneath them.
And what’s one of the most annoying traits
an employee can have?
Ask any boss.
When the worker is asked to do something,
he replies,
“That’s not my job.”
Teach your child that anything
that needs to be done
is his job if he’s old enough
and capable of doing it.
How early should parents
start to assign chores to their children?
Some experts have found that children who are
three years old or even younger
can be taught to help out.
They can learn to pick up their toys,
clean up spills, sort laundry.
Older children can vacuum,
wash the car, prepare a meal.
I’m happy to say that many young brothers
here at Bethel
are excellent cooks,
which is often the result
of fine parental training.
Do you remember the video where Caleb
is taught to clean his room
and put away his toys?
That video was a game changer
for many children.
They want to be just like Caleb.
And now when you enter their room,
you can find the bed.
When problems arise,
attack the problem, not each other.
It’s not ‘How can I win?’
but ‘How can we win?’
You’ll see an excellent example of that
in the follow-up video.
Let’s watch.
Hey!
Want some tea?
Sure!
Hey, babe,
you and me, we’re a team, right?
Yeah, of course!
When I read this, I thought about us.
“So that they are no longer two,
but one flesh.”
I know that before, you had to shoulder
everything yourself for so long.
Mm-hmm.
And you did great.
You’ve been raising two beautiful,
spiritual kids on your own.
But now you have me.
Yeah, I do.
So do you think
sometimes we’re not a team?
Well, it’s just that sometimes
during family worship . . .
I get excited, and I jump in. I know!
I’m just so used to doing it
after all these years.
I know you’re not trying to take over.
And listen, I love the way you teach.
I see how you can reach the kids
in ways that I can’t.
Just let me guide it,
and I’ll make sure you can do that.
Thanks, honey. Thanks for your patience.
No, thank you for your patience.
I’m a work in progress,
but we make a great team.
Why don’t we look at what we’re going
to cover before our next family worship?
That sounds great.
Wasn’t that a fine example
of how to attack a problem and not your mate?
No arguments, no raised voices,
no accusations
—the husband had empathy for his wife.
He didn’t question her motives.
He realized that as a single parent,
she’d been taking the lead for a long time.
And notice how she responded
to her husband’s kind counsel.
No doubt it’s going to be easy
for the kids to respect their stepfather,
and they’re going to learn
how a husband and wife
should treat each other
and how they should pull together.
Sometime soon, you might want
to consider these questions:
In what aspects of our marriage
do we work well as a team?
And then, how can we improve?
It pleases Jehovah
when family members work together as a team.
That promotes peace in the family.
And our God is a “God of peace.”
Now Brother John Ekrann
will consider the final talk
of this symposium,
“Follow the Road Map to Family Peace
—Worship Jehovah Together.”
Jehovah wants your family
to be happy and peaceful.
But Jehovah does more than simply say,
“I hope you have a peaceful family life.”
He explains exactly how we
can get our family there.
I want you to imagine Jehovah
laying out a map in front of you
and saying: “See these landmarks?
“Look for them on the road to peace.
And if you see them,
you’re going in the right direction.”
So far in this symposium, we’ve passed
the landmarks of showing love and respect,
improving communication,
and working together as a team.
The last landmark
we’ll consider in this symposium
is worshipping together as a family.
Worshipping together as a family
promotes peace and brings his blessing.
Even if not all in your family
are worshippers of Jehovah,
you can promote peace
by maintaining a very good spiritual routine.
In the following dramatization,
notice some common obstacles
to worshipping Jehovah as a family.
Hi.
Hey, babe.
So, what’s for family worship this week?
I think I got some good ideas.
Yeah?
Mm-hmm.
Thank you for reading that.
Um.
Let’s just go ahead and ask the question.
We’ll just do that.
So paragraphs 13 and 14:
“How can we be generous?”
Anybody?
Now, the footnote that we just read
really helps us to appreciate
the definition of that quality.
Without the definition, we’re left to wonder
exactly what it is
and how it connects to the other things
that we’ve discussed this evening.
Gabe, can you go ahead
and read the next one for us?
Mm-hmm.
Thank you.
The Bible contains many examples
of submissive individuals.
So are there examples?
Sue.
Yeah.
That’s right.
When we talk about examples,
where do we start?
There are examples in the past;
there are even examples presently.
And we could even be examples.
That’s—that’s the power of them.
Let’s keep going.
That was a lot of reading.
I know, right?
I want to enjoy family worship, but
I feel like the things that we are covering
are just really not what I need right now.
Yeah.
You know, I just don’t know
if this is what they need right now.
Hmm.
We’ll keep working on it.
I think we’d all agree that family worship
was difficult to watch.
It was uncomfortable for everyone.
Clearly, Max and Irene had some obstacles
they needed to overcome
to really worshipping Jehovah as a family.
To start and keep a good habit going
requires determination and resolve.
So that’s where you need
to start for your family.
You need to resolve
that you’re going
to worship Jehovah as a family.
Notice the resolve in Joshua’s words
at Joshua 24:15.
That’s Joshua 24:15:
“Now if it seems bad to you to serve Jehovah,
“choose for yourselves today
whom you will serve,
“whether the gods that your forefathers
served on the other side of the River
“or the gods of the Amorites
in whose land you are dwelling.
“But as for me and my household,
we will serve Jehovah.”
Yes, worship of Jehovah as a family
needs to be at the very center
of your family life.
Now, weekly family worship
is not all that’s involved
in worshipping together as a family.
Let’s consider five ways
we can worship Jehovah together as a family.
(1) Prayer.
Parents, do not underestimate the impact
that your prayers have on your children.
When a child hears their parents
pour out their hearts to Jehovah,
that tells them that Jehovah
is very real to their parents.
I can recall growing up listening
to my father’s prayers.
Now, when I was young,
I thought his prayers were very long.
But as I grew older and really
listened carefully to what he was saying,
I could see how much of a close relationship
he had with Jehovah.
(2) Discuss the daily text.
It’s an excellent habit
and a very spiritual way to start the day.
(3) Attend meetings.
Now, we’re not just making sure our family
is there at the meetings
but that they’re involved and engaged.
And work hard to prepare
so that all family members
can have a meaningful comment
at the meetings.
(4) Share in the ministry regularly
as a family.
Now, sharing in the ministry together
as a family
draws us closer to our family members.
When we hear them speak about the truth,
we listen to their phone calls,
or we read their letters,
we can feel their faith.
I loved going in the ministry with my mother
and listening to her skillfully use the Bible
to answer questions.
And (5) have a consistent,
enjoyable,
and meaningful Family Worship program.
Let’s consider what that means
—first of all, consistent.
In the video, Max was trying to have
the family worship consistently each week.
Is your family worship consistent each week?
Is your family worship enjoyable?
In the video, the kids were bored.
They were looking at their phones
and checking the time.
And week after week
of kind of a question-and-answer style
led to the young people
giving sort of one-word answers.
It did not look enjoyable.
Now, would your family
describe family worship as enjoyable?
How about meaningful?
What Max was using for material
was material that he thought was meaningful.
But did it look like it
was meaningful to the family?
Does your family worship use material
that is meaningful to your family?
Now, after reviewing these five points,
we don’t want you to be discouraged
if it’s a struggle
to maintain a good routine.
Life in this system has many challenges,
trials, and unexpected events.
So stay positive.
And when your good routine
breaks down from time to time,
consider what adjustments you can make
to be successful and get
your spiritual routine back on track.
Regularly ask Jehovah for his help,
and don’t give up.
Now, as you watch
the following dramatization,
notice how Max and Irene
and the family worked together
to make family worship successful.
March 15, 2014, Watchtower,
“Family Worship
—Can you Make It More Enjoyable?”:
“The worship of Jehovah
should not be boring. . . .
Address the needs of each family member.”
Babe, what do our kids need?
What’s actually going on in their lives?
Family worship needs to include that.
Yeah, maybe we need to pay more attention
to what’s going on with them.
Talk to them; listen to them.
I’m going to send you a link
to a great Watchtower  article.
I can’t wait to read it.
Max and I changed our approach.
We found out what mattered to our kids
—like friends,
. . . adjusting to a blended family,
. . . dating.
So we turned things around
and used family worship
to focus on what our kids really needed
and to prepare ourselves
for possible future trials.
Good night, y’all.
Good night.
Um,
family worship was—was cool.
It was.
I’m glad you liked it.
Thank you.
Good night, y’all.
Night.
Good night.
Hey! Guess what?
What?
I applied to Bethel.
You did?
Yep.
That’s really exciting.
I’m proud of you.
Thanks.
Aww, congratulations.
Thank you.
Hey, it’s selfie time, everybody.
Come on, let’s get together.
All right. On three
we’re going to say Bethel, OK?
All right.
One, two, three.
Bethel!
We’ve come a long way.
And through it all,
Jehovah has taught us to love
and he’s given our family
peace.
We can see that Max and Irene analyzed
what was wrong with family worship
and decided to change their approach.
Let’s examine how they did that
and what it means for us.
What did they do to make their
family worship more meaningful?
Well, Max and Irene had to ask themselves
what was going on in their kids’ lives.
What topics could they
discuss at family worship
that would truly be useful to their kids?
Did you smile when you saw Max
almost drop the glass
when his daughter talked about dating?
But what a difference their efforts to listen
and really understand what was happening
with the kids made in the family worship!
How did Max and Irene
make family worship more enjoyable?
Did you see how the family
was reacting at family worship now?
What a difference!
The kids were smiling.
They looked engaged in the discussion
and touched by what they were discussing.
So do what you can
to make sure that your family
feels relaxed and happy
and that your family worship reflects
the kind of happy
and joyful God that Jehovah is.
Remember, your family will often remember
more about how they felt
during family worship
than maybe the exact details
of what they learned.
Keep worshipping Jehovah as a family.
Make your family worship consistent,
enjoyable, and meaningful.
And work together to overcome obstacles,
just like Max and Irene and the kids
all worked together to solve problems
and create a very peaceful family life.
It was really beautiful to see how far
they had come by applying Bible principles.
In review, this symposium has taught us
that Bible principles can be used
as a road map to family peace.
Work hard to show love and respect,
to improve communication,
to work together as a team,
and to worship Jehovah together.
And please be patient with one another
as you form habits that lead to peace.
With Jehovah’s help, you and your family
will enjoy peace that only he can provide.
Thank you, brothers.
We benefited from thinking
about how we can apply
the Bible principles you shared
and from the practical lessons
in the dramatizations.
All of us long to see true peace on earth.
How will that be accomplished?
And how can we prove
that we honor and support
Jehovah’s appointed King, Christ Jesus?
Let’s listen as Brother Mark Noumair,
a helper to the Teaching Committee,
provides these answers and more in the talk,
“Loyally Support the ‘Prince of Peace.’”
Imagine the scene: It’s nighttime.
You’re in the garden of Gethsemane
with your close friends and beloved Teacher.
Suddenly, you hear a crowd coming.
They’re being led by a man you know,
Judas Iscariot.
He approaches Jesus
and kisses him on the cheek.
He then steps aside
as men move in to arrest Jesus.
Your emotions churn inside you.
Your Master and Lord is being arrested
—the Son of God.
How can this be happening?
What do you do?
Before you can even decide what to do,
Peter draws his sword
and chops off the ear
of the slave of the high priest.
Then Jesus says to Peter:
“Return your sword to its place,
for all those who take up the sword
will perish by the sword.”
And then you watch the unbelievable,
as Jesus heals the man’s ear.
Peter must have thought
that it was a great and noble thing
to fight on behalf of the Son of God.
But Jesus didn’t think so.
With six words
—“return your sword to its place”—
Jesus taught his disciples
an important lesson.
This was not their fight;
nor was it the time to fight.
So in this talk,
we’re going to focus our attention
on an insidious way
that any of us, like Peter,
can become inadvertently involved
in this world’s conflicts
without even realizing it.
And we will talk about how we
can avoid making that serious mistake.
But first,
let’s discuss why Jesus
did not ask his Father
to send “12 legions of angels”
to help him when being arrested.
It has to do with Jesus’ name.
So please open your Bible
to Isaiah chapter 9,
and let’s read verse 6
—Isaiah 9:6.
Now, we know Jesus has many titles,
but in this verse,
we’re going to focus on just one.
Verse 6:
“For a child has been born to us,
“a son has been given to us;
“and the rulership will rest on his shoulder.
“His name will be called Wonderful Counselor,
“Mighty God, Eternal Father,
Prince of Peace.”
Why is Jesus called “Prince of Peace”?
Well, consider what Jehovah’s angel
declared to the shepherds in the field
at Jesus’ birth at Luke 2:14.
They said:
“Glory in the heights above to God,
and on earth peace among men of goodwill.”
How appropriate for the angels to announce
that at the birth
of the destined Prince of Peace,
there would be divine peace
for those who have God’s goodwill!
But when will this become a reality?
It didn’t happen when Jesus was on earth,
and we certainly don’t see peace today.
Instead of peace, what do we see?
We see the nations that are locked
in hostilities and aggression
in a competition for world dominance.
We see global violence and bloodshed.
But please don’t lose heart.
Because we don’t see peace now
does not mean it’s not coming.
Isaiah 9:6
—it’s not just wishful thinking.
It’s a promise from Almighty God,
and Jehovah cannot lie.
All his prophecies come true.
In fact,
let’s read the last portion of verse 7
in Isaiah chapter 9.
The last verse
(the last portion of verse 7) says:
“The zeal of Jehovah of armies will do this.”
What does that mean?
It means that Jehovah
does nothing in a half-hearted way.
He’s zealous to bring peace, and he will.
We can be sure
that whatever Jehovah promises,
he will fully accomplish.
So how will peace come to the earth?
Did the Prince of Peace give us a clue?
Yes, he did.
In fact, the key to everlasting peace
is on the lips of millions of people
throughout the world.
They know it by heart.
But let’s read it at Matthew 6:9, 10
—Matthew 6:9.
What a beautiful thought for us!
This is how everlasting peace
is going to come through.
It depends on the fulfillment
of these verses.
Verse 9:
“You must pray, then, this way:
‘Our Father in the heavens,
let your name [the name Jehovah]
be sanctified.’”
The emphasis that we place
on the name of God
is not merely a matter
of religious knowledge.
Everyone must know God’s name
and treat it as something holy and respected.
It has to be something sacred.
It must be cleared of all the reproach
that has been heaped upon it.
In fact, the well-being
of the entire universe and its inhabitants
depends upon the sanctification
of Jehovah’s name.
Now, let’s look at verse 10:
“Let your Kingdom come.
Let your will take place,
as in heaven, also on earth.”
God’s Kingdom
—two words but so important.
is the most powerful government
humanity will ever see.
There is no nation or empire
that can withstand
the might of God’s Kingdom.
And any nation who thinks
they can block the coming of God’s Kingdom
is like an ant who plants itself firmly
on the railroad track
and with his hand raised defiantly
shouts to the oncoming locomotive:
“Stop! You can’t run over me.”
Well, God’s heavenly government has the power
to destroy all present-day violent regimes.
They’re like ants to Jehovah.
And he will eliminate their ability
to wage war, to foment conflict,
and to shed blood.
So, yes, Matthew 6:9, 10
—it’s that valuable and important
for lasting peace.
God’s Kingdom is the only road
to lasting peace.
And in his role as King,
Revelation 19:15 describes Jesus
as ‘striking the nations with an iron rod.’
Soon, Jehovah will give
the command to his Son,
and he will destroy
all the things that disrupt peace.
Gone will be the terror
that we have grown accustomed to living with
day in and day out.
So, what will happen next?
This is what will happen
—Psalm 37:10, 11.
Let’s open our Bibles here
to Psalm 37:10, 11,
and just allow this prophecy to absorb
and to thrill our minds and our hearts
and give us a hope for the future.
Verse 10 of Psalm 37:
“Just a little while longer,
“and the wicked will be no more
[a little while longer];
you will look at where they were,
and they will not be there.”
“Just a little while longer.”
It’s just like children saying
to their parents
when going on a trip
“Are we there yet?”
and the parents say
“Just a little while longer.”
And that brings comfort to them,
and it’s the same with us.
So imagine that!
This means you go into the streets,
you’re looking for a wicked person,
and you will not be able to find even one.
“The wicked will be no more.”
“But the meek will possess the earth.”
That’s what we’re speaking about in verse 11.
Let’s read that:
“But the meek will possess the earth,
and they will find exquisite delight
in the abundance of peace.”
We love reading that.
Men will be at peace.
They will be at peace with themselves,
with their neighbors, with their God.
How does that sound to you?
Meditate on that.
Can you see yourself there
in a peaceful new world
where the only news to tune into
is regarding who’s getting resurrected today
or which new person you will be assigned
to teach about Jehovah?
Can you imagine the joy
of studying with a person,
not just from a different culture,
but from a different time period,
seeing things through their eyes
as they come to love Jehovah as you do?
Well, soon the Prince of Peace
will turn this world
into one of sheer delight
—no more borders,
no more threats, no more worries—
just an abundance of peace
with your brothers and sisters.
Do you want to be there?
Me too.
So how can we show our loyal support
for the Prince of Peace?
Please watch the following video,
and notice the different ways
we can do this right now.
“I am no part of the world.”
But is the world a part of me?
I’m pressured every day
to get involved in political issues
that affect me socially,
. . . environmentally,
. . . and economically.
That pressure could rob me
of my peace of mind
. . . and influence how I think.
I could take sides in my heart,
even if I’m not aware of it.
But I know that Jehovah
will care for all of mankind’s concerns
. . . by means of his Kingdom
ruled by his Son, Jesus Christ.
I show my support for him
in my prayers,
. . . in how I think and feel,
. . . and by teaching others
what the Kingdom will do for mankind.
I know there are millions
of brothers and sisters
all over the world
. . . who loyally support
the “Prince of Peace”
just like me, because I
. . . I
. . . I am no part of the world.
So, what takes away the peace
in the country where you live?
in your community?
in your town? in your society?
Most likely,
it’s the hot-button social issues.
Did you notice
how our two brothers and sister
showed their loyal support
for the Prince of Peace?
What issues affected them?
Unfair tax hikes, blatant injustice,
a disregard of the environment
—all things in themselves seemed
like noble causes worthy to get involved.
‘How can they get away with this?
It’s not right.
We should do something.’
Does that sound familiar?
We may not have a literal sword in our hand,
but we all have our Peterlike moments.
And if we’re not careful,
issues that are close to our heart
can charge our emotions
and we can lose our spiritual balance.
So, what can help us
when we see things that are wrong?
Remember what the Prince of Peace
said to Peter
in that highly charged moment:
“Return your sword to its place.”
In other words, this is not your fight.
So, what do we do?
We do something far better than fight.
We preach.
Each time that we share the Kingdom news,
we proclaim our support for Jesus’ rule.
But here’s the thing:
If we truly believe
in the good news of the Kingdom,
we will not do anything
that hinders our ability to tell it.
Once again, it’s so important
that if we truly believe
in the good news of the Kingdom,
we will not do anything
that hinders our ability to tell it.
Why?
Well, let’s find out.
Let’s open up to Peter’s words himself
at 1 Peter 2:12
—1 Peter 2:12.
Peter helps us here with why we need
to maintain our conduct properly.
First Peter 2:12:
“Maintain your conduct fine
among the nations,
“so that when they accuse you
of being wrongdoers,
“they may be eyewitnesses
of your fine works
and, as a result,
glorify God in the day of his inspection.”
So Peter had to learn this.
But do we see the connection?
Our actions and words
are directly linked to Jehovah.
When people see us,
they see a people that worships Jehovah.
And when people hear us,
they hear a people that worships Jehovah.
Imagine how our freeness of speech
to speak about God’s Kingdom
would be hindered if we were to voice
a position for a political issue!
And it can happen so easily.
It can happen at work, at school,
with relatives, and so forth.
Satan sets the trap masterfully.
He’s just waiting.
If he could only make us
“chop off the ear” of anything in this world
that causes hurt and indignation in our heart
or if he can hook our heartstrings
by getting us emotionally charged,
he can then step back and reel us in.
The new world, our hope for true peace,
all starts to fade into the background.
Don’t give him that chance!
Be determined to do
what Titus 3:1, 2 tells us.
Let’s read that
—Titus chapter 3,
verses 1 and 2.
Here is the Scriptural admonition:
“Continue reminding them to be in subjection
“and to be obedient
to governments and authorities,
“to be ready for every good work,
“to speak injuriously of no one,
not to be quarrelsome,
but to be reasonable,
displaying all mildness toward all men.”
‘Be in subjection
and be obedient
to governments and authorities.’
Well, now let’s break that down.
In practical terms, what does it mean?
It means to obey the laws of the land
and pay taxes,
to not speak negatively
about the superior authorities,
and to be careful not to take sides
on political issues
(not even in our hearts).
Do you remember
that expression from the video?
“I am no part of the world.
But is the world a part of me?”
Of course,
when we find ourselves
between Caesar’s law and God’s law,
we know what to do.
We apply Acts 5:29
and “obey God as ruler rather than men.”
We know that.
But like Jesus, who healed the ear
of the armed guard Malchus,
we’re determined to react with mildness
when provoked by an injustice
or cruelty in this world.
In conclusion,
we have the indescribable privilege
to honor the Prince of Peace.
And how reassuring it is to know
that Jesus understands our feelings!
He understands our emotions
when we see things that we know are wrong.
He knows these things hurt our heart.
We just want to make things right.
But remember the critical lesson
he taught his apostles
in the garden of Gethsemane:
This is not your fight.
Rather, Jehovah, the King of Eternity,
and Jesus, the Prince of Peace,
are telling us:
“This is our fight. Leave it in our hands.”
Soon, the prophecy at Isaiah 9:6, 7
will be fulfilled completely.
In the meantime,
keep preaching about the Kingdom.
Avoid saying or doing anything
that suggests taking sides
on a political issue.
Don’t allow yourself to “chop off the ear”
of the injustices and the causes of conflict
of this old world.
Peter tried that, but it didn’t work.
He learned a big lesson
that day in the garden,
and he never forgot it.
May we never forget it either.
Now is the time to show
your active and loyal support
for the Prince of Peace
as we echo Peter’s words at 2 Peter 3:14
and “do [our] utmost to be found finally
by [Jehovah and the Prince of Peace]
spotless and unblemished and in peace.”
Thank you, Brother Noumair,
for strengthening our determination
to give our undivided support
to God’s appointed King, Christ Jesus.
This brings us
to the final talk of today’s session.
Jesus promised to give his followers peace.
Why is the peace that Jesus gives
far superior
to any peace that this world promises?
And how can we safeguard the gift of peace
that Jesus has given us?
Please follow along
as Brother Anthony Morris,
a member of the Governing Body,
delivers the talk,
“Do Not Be Misled by Imitation Peace!”
Jesus taught us that Satan
is “the father of the lie.”
We recall that he deceived Eve,
a perfect woman.
He lied about our precious Jehovah.
Now, you’re familiar (many of you)
with Revelation chapter 12.
I invite you to find that
—Revelation chapter 12.
And in this chapter, verses 7 and 8,
it addressed the fact
that “war broke out in heaven.”
But notice
that after he’s kicked out of heaven,
in verse 9 we read:
“So down the great dragon was hurled,
“the original serpent,
the one called Devil and Satan,
“who is misleading
the entire inhabited earth;
“he was hurled down to the earth,
and his angels
were hurled down with him.”
Now, I read it that way specifically,
but what it doesn’t say is
(in the middle part of verse 9):
“Satan, who is [trying to mislead]
the entire inhabited earth.”
No, he “is  misleading
That’s crucial to understand
when we think about the theme of this talk,
not to be misled by imitation peace,
because as “the ruler of the world,”
that’s what he’s out to do—mislead.
In fact, it’s an interesting point
here in 2 Corinthians chapter 11
to appreciate
how he goes about misleading,
or at least it’s addressed here
to serve as a good warning for us.
And an interesting point with the revision
of the New World Translation
(for those of you in the truth before 2013
when it was revised, you’ll remember this)
in verse 14 of 2 Corinthians chapter 11:
“And no wonder,
for Satan himself keeps disguising himself
as an angel of light.”
Now, the New World Translation
used to say before the revision
“[transforms] himself
into an angel of light.”
Well, the very English word “metamorphosis,”
like for a caterpillar transforming
into a beautiful butterfly,
that’s where it comes from,
the Greek language.
And that word was not in verse 14.
No, because Satan can’t transform himself
into “an angel of light”
(so it’s an improved translation),
but he does disguise.
He’s a masquerader.
And he does that with the subject of peace.
His world offers a sort of peace,
but it’s imitation peace.
Now, Jesus is distinguished,
though, with the peace that he gives.
And if you’ll follow along here
in John chapter 14,
he himself explains it to us.
And we treasure the Gospel accounts,
verse 27: “I leave you peace;
“I give you my peace.
“I do not give it to you
the way the world gives it.
Do not let your hearts be troubled
nor let them shrink out of fear.”
So Jesus gives us his peace, see.
And the peace that Jesus gives us,
it’s this inner calm once you know
the truth and Jesus gives us the peace.
We have this confidence that he loves us
and Jehovah loves us,
so that we enjoy a good,
peaceful relationship with them
and a good conscience.
And we look forward to the Kingdom
removing all war and death.
Now, a point to make here:
Satan wants us to trade
the peace that Jesus gives
for his imitation peace
that he has advertised in the world.
Now, in this talk,
we will consider
three forms of imitation peace
and why the peace
that Jesus gives is superior.
The first one has to do with material things
—how they’ll not bring true peace.
And to help us with that,
turn to Matthew chapter 4,
and we’ll be referring to this chapter
throughout this particular talk
about not being misled by imitation peace.
And this one
is connected with material things
—how they don’t bring true peace—
in the example Jesus sets forth here.
So in Matthew chapter 4:
“Then Jesus was led by the spirit
“up into the wilderness
to be tempted by the Devil.
“After he had fasted
for 40 days and 40 nights,
“he felt hungry.
“And the Tempter approached and said to him:
“‘If you are a son of God,
tell these stones to become loaves of bread.’
“But he answered: ‘It is written:
“‘“Man must live, not on bread alone,
but on every word that comes
from Jehovah’s mouth.”’”
Isn’t that a beautiful rebuttal?
See, Jesus refused to trade
his peace for material things
(in this case, bread),
even though he was hungry.
So serving Jehovah was more important to him
than material things, see.
In the world, they have this thinking,
‘Well, you need
a certain amount of money to retire,’
and they’re constantly
focused on material things
—not Jesus, see.
It’s superior peace from Jehovah God.
So it’s only temporary anyway,
the material benefits that people seek
and pursue throughout their lives.
Now we can enjoy true contentment
because Jehovah God is going to care for us.
We know that many have
personal experiences to prove that.
Now, in the following video,
see what a brother learned
about the so-called peace
that the world promises.
As a family, we were doing
very well spiritually.
We did family worship, went preaching,
and went to the meetings together.
After some time, we began
to encounter financial problems.
At times, we did not even have money
to buy food
for each day.
Many people in our area
were going to South Africa
to provide basic needs for their families.
So I decided to go as well,
leaving behind my wife
to take care of our seven children.
This affected me spiritually
because I did not know the language,
I was unable to preach,
and I did not benefit from the meetings.
Being so far from my family
caused me to neglect
my responsibility as a family head.
As a result, my family grew weak spiritually
and we all missed each other very much.
I realized that I had made
a wrong decision going abroad.
My conscience started to trouble me greatly.
Then I remembered the example of Baruch
found at Jeremiah 45:5.
Baruch may have wanted
to pursue material riches as I had.
When he was helped, he returned.
I decided then to put Jehovah in first place
instead of searching for material things.
So I started to make changes to go home
and help my family spiritually.
When I left South Africa
and reached the border of Malawi
(after leaving my family
for about six months),
I felt great happiness in my heart,
and I am still happy till now.
Studying the Bible has helped me.
We still encounter financial problems,
but I remember that in Satan’s world,
there is nowhere we can go
and have no problems.
Now I serve as an elder.
My family is progressing spiritually.
And this makes me very happy,
because my relationship
with Jehovah is strong.
Yes, he learned a hard lesson.
He goes to South Africa
—meetings interrupted and no field service.
And then he remembers Baruch,
secretary for Jeremiah.
And he returns to be with his family,
putting the Kingdom first,
and we appreciate him
being truthful and sharing that experience.
That’s imitation peace,
going after material things.
Now this next one, it’s quite interesting.
So pay close attention
because there may be some
listening who need this counsel.
Satan’s world says that we
can ignore Bible standards
and that we might need
to ignore some of them to gain peace of mind.
Here are two examples
that we’re going to analyze in this talk.
A person may reason
that marrying an unbeliever
or obtaining an unscriptural divorce
will make life easier.
And they start reasoning this way,
‘I just want to get married,
and he’s an unbeliever,
but he’s a nice person.’
Things like that go on
with the treacherous heart.
Again, we go to the example
of our Lord and Master, Jesus.
We’re going to read verses 5-7 of Matthew 4:
“Then the Devil took him
along into the holy city,
“and he stationed him
on the battlement of the temple
“and said to him:
“‘If you are a son of God,
throw yourself down,
“‘for it is written:
“‘“He will give his angels
a command concerning you,”
“‘and, “They will carry you on their hands,
“so that you may not strike
your foot against a stone.”’
“Jesus said to him: ‘Again, it is written:
“You must not put Jehovah
your God to the test.”’”
See, Jesus made that very clear.
He was going to be obedient to his Father
and wasn’t going to worry about being testy
with such an experience
as the Devil proposed there.
So obedience
—Jesus twice (in a moment we’ll read
another one) said: “It is written.”
He sticks with the Scriptures
—Jehovah’s thinking—
and he refused to disobey Jehovah.
Now here’s the question,
Why is the peace that Jesus gives
superior to the pursuit
of unscriptural solutions to our problems?
Let that sink in.
Why is the peace that Jesus gives
superior to the pursuit
of unscriptural solutions to our problems?
For example, marrying an unbeliever
—that will likely bring
(and it has happened time after time)
that person greater pain
than the longing
they felt when they were single.
I’ve personally seen that
all too many times in various congregations
that I’ve had the privilege to serve in.
You see, the other one
is an unscriptural divorce.
It often leads to immoral conduct.
It certainly leads to a troubled conscience,
emotional damage
and, of course, a loss of privileges.
Now, this is very important to keep in mind.
It’s true that with two imperfect individuals
married to each other,
well, there are going to be difficulties
and there are going to be challenges.
But stop and think about this:
When you’re having difficulties,
don’t forget that marriage
is a sacred arrangement.
The world totally has forgotten that.
So Jehovah will strengthen
both to make a success.
You have to keep that in mind:
Jehovah will strengthen and help
so that you can succeed
because this is his sacred arrangement.
And the Devil has been attacking
the family arrangement
all through the last days of this system,
and he’s intensifying it
as he gets closer
to being thrown into the abyss.
Now, in the following video,
notice the results
of pursuing imitation peace.
Newly married life came with a lot
of unexpected challenges.
You dream about the way
your marriage will go,
but then the reality is quite different.
All we ever did was argue,
or we wouldn’t speak to one another.
We never ever went to the elders.
We just didn’t want to bother them.
We just felt, you know,
we needed to figure it out ourselves.
We decided that if the house sold,
then we would separate.
The separation wasn’t a good thing,
because in some respects
it made things worse.
It did have an impact on the boys.
They started acting out.
They got into some trouble
with the police one time.
And there was a loneliness
because you’ve gotten married,
and now you don’t have that,
and you’re by yourself.
And the same old routine
went on where you’re
cooking and cleaning
and doing laundry and working.
I felt sick to my stomach.
I had a hard time getting up every morning
and facing the world.
At that point, I felt that I needed
to have the elders help out a little bit.
I did pray for Jehovah’s help to direct me,
and I kept wondering
why Jehovah wasn’t really
answering my prayers.
But I kind of realize now
that it was because we were separated.
The expectations of the separation
were not at all what I was thinking.
I reflected on the marriage vows.
One of the things I thought about
was a sister in our congregation.
She was married to an unbeliever,
and then she learned the truth.
And he was so violent.
He would beat her; he would burn her books;
he would burn her clothes.
He did not allow her children
to attend the meetings.
And I thought about the problems
that Darrel and I had.
And I thought:
‘Well, Darrel is a kind person.
He’s never done that.’
And I thought:
‘You know, this is something
‘that we need to really work on.
‘We need to really put forth the effort
‘to start applying Bible principles
‘to put Jehovah first in our life
so that we can bring our marriage
back in union with Jehovah.’
I realized that it wasn’t what I wanted,
but it was what Jehovah wanted.
There was just no other choice.
Jehovah wasn’t going to bless us
unless we got back together.
When we got back together,
our marriage was still a work in progress.
You can’t have
a perfect marriage in this world,
but you can sure make it better
when you put Jehovah first.
We enjoyed the feelings
we had toward each other.
I felt closer to Debbie.
Debbie and I
have been married now for 48 years.
Separation does not make
anything better at all.
If you even have an inkling of love
for one another,
you want to work on that,
and you want to make it bloom
so that Jehovah can bless it.
The blessings have been endless.
Our children are all doing
fantastic in the truth.
Jehovah said:
“Taste and see that [He] is good.”
So we’ve got to do that.
We really appreciated this couple sharing
their experience with the brotherhood.
He learned, you know.
They were always arguing,
and that’s all they
did was argue, argue, argue.
It affected their children.
They decided to separate
and finally have peace.
‘I don’t have to be around her,’
or ‘I don’t have to be around him.’
But then he realized
his relationship with Jehovah
was being interfered with here,
and he went to the elders.
His prayers were affected.
The things he noticed
—he was honest about that.
And our precious sister
was so nice to honestly explain.
She said what she learned
was that ‘this is not about me;
it’s about Jehovah.’
When you finally come to that realization,
Jehovah will strengthen you
to enjoy peace with your marriage partner.
Now, the next one, I never tire of speaking
about these particular couple of verses
or reading about it or hearing
another brother give a talk about it.
See, here’s what’s coming soon.
Turn with me to 1 Thessalonians chapter 5.
And many of you are going, ‘Oh, yeah, I know
what he’s going to read about.’
And this is one of the prophecies
that is yet to be fulfilled.
So it’s just invigorating
to know that soon
here’s what’s going to happen
—1 Thessalonians chapter 5,
verses 2 and 3:
“For you yourselves know very well
“that Jehovah’s day
is coming exactly as a thief in the night.
“Whenever it is that they are saying,
“‘Peace and security!’
“then sudden destruction
is to be instantly on them,
“just like birth pains on a pregnant woman,
and they will by no means escape.”
Yes, see, “Jehovah’s day”
—this has to do with the day
of the outbreak of the great tribulation
when Babylon the Great is destroyed
and Armageddon finishes it off.
In this context, that’s “Jehovah’s day.”
And what happens before then
is this proclamation, “peace and security!”
Will religious leaders be involved?
Well, they’re part of Satan’s system;
that’s very possible.
We’ll have to wait and see.
Will it be one announcement
or a series of announcements?
That we don’t know.
But this is coming.
And those who are staying close to Jehovah
and enjoying the peace
from him and his Son, Jesus,
will not be deceived
by this imitation proclamation of peace
—imitation peace.
And again, back in Matthew chapter 4,
we’re going to see how Jesus handled
this type of test from the Devil
and what we learn from it here
in verses 8-11 of Matthew chapter 4.
“Again the Devil took him [in verse 8]
“along to an unusually high mountain
“and showed him all the kingdoms
of the world and their glory.
“And he said to him:
“‘All these things I will give you
“if you fall down
and do an act of worship to me.’
“Then Jesus said to him [without hesitation]:
“‘Go away, Satan!
“‘For it is written:
“It is Jehovah your God you must worship,
and it is to him alone
you must render sacred service.”’
“Then the Devil left him,
and look! angels came
and began to minister to him.”
Right away, a third time: “It is written.”
Jesus was having nothing to do
with this offer of the kingdoms
—this imitation peace.
‘You’ll have all the glory and rule.’
And it’s always boggled my mind
that this one who knew
Jesus in his prehuman existence
would have the audacity to try to get Jesus
to bow down and worship him.
It shows you that he’s obviously insane.
Now, he wouldn’t allow it either
when they tried to make him an earthly king.
Jesus wasn’t having any part of that.
They were thinking he could bring them peace.
But Jesus said there’s no peace
except by Jehovah’s way.
And the peace from God’s Kingdom
is so superior
to anything they could try to come up with
—their imitation peace.
Here’s why.
Think about this:
Jesus will remove the Devil.
Jesus will remove human rulership.
Jesus will remove sin.
So the earth’s peace
will never again be disturbed.
And I appreciate very much
that he’s going to get rid of all problems,
and that includes undoing all causes of pain
—and not just physical pain,
emotional pain as well.
It’s wonderful to look forward to that time
with that beautiful peace
from our precious Father,
Jehovah, and his Son, Jesus.
Now, in the following video,
see what convinced this sister
not to believe the world’s promises of peace.
My father always taught me
that we needed God in our life
in order for there to be peace.
And he always wanted to know,
Can Christians go to war?
How is this consistent
with the Gospel of Jesus Christ?
But the pastor could never give us an answer,
and so I thought I’d have to look
to politics to find it.
A lot of peace movements
were being formed at that time,
so I joined one of them.
We decided where
the protest marches would be
and which pamphlets we would use.
But after the protests were over,
everyone was so excited
and they all started applauding
and cheering for the leaders.
I thought:
‘That’s not what I wanted.
‘I don’t want to honor people.
‘I want to have world peace.
And that still hasn’t happened yet.’
Then I started to feel very alone,
and it made me feel unsafe in this world.
With no peace in sight,
I thought,
‘What is the purpose of life?’
While visiting friends for coffee,
I saw a man I’d never met before.
My friends told me he wanted
to talk to us about the Bible.
So I asked him:
“Sir, what do you think?
Can Christians join the military?”
And the man said,
“No, that’s not allowed
because the Bible says
you should ‘love your [enemy].’”
It made me think
about what my father always said
—that we need God to bring peace.
Then a really nice lady came to my door,
and she had an orange book in her hand.
And it said:
True Peace and Security.
After reading it, I thought:
‘This is it!
This is the organization
that truly wants peace.’
So I went to those involved
in the peace movement.
I told them that I believe
that God will change this world
into a beautiful earth
where there’ll be true peace.
They all looked at me
like I had lost my mind.
I was so happy with my new life.
I felt like I was part of a family
who truly cared about one another
and really wanted peace with each other.
Isaiah 14:7 had a major impact on my life
because there God promises
a calm and peaceful world.
Wasn’t that nice how she learned?
She’d looked to politics and protests
for world peace.
Obviously, she was sincere.
But she learned that’s all imitation peace.
True peace and security
comes from Jehovah God.
So wrapping it up with these
three different types
of imitation peace
that we’ve emphasized,
we want to encourage you
in these last minutes
to safeguard the peace
that Jesus has given you.
In John chapter 14
(you know this,
but I want you to really focus
on a particular point), in verse 6:
“Jesus said to him:
“‘I am the way and the truth and the life.
No one comes to the Father
except through me.’”
Isn’t that beautiful?
Particularly we want to emphasize
Jesus is “the truth.”
We can trust all of his promises.
He is “the truth.”
He’s going to give us peace
—already has—
and will to a greater extent in the future.
Yes, our Master is “the truth.”
And he gave the early Christians that peace.
The things that they were able to deal
with are just mind-boggling.
As we read the apostle Paul’s experiences
and Peter’s and others’
—the persecution they endured—
they did it,
enduring with joy.
It’s amazing!
It can only be
a supernatural provision of peace.
And just remember,
Jesus will likewise give you
the peace you need now
to keep doing Jehovah’s will
and to make Him happy.
So, brothers, please,
safeguard the gift of peace
that Jesus has given you.
Satan uses this world
to offer you promises of imitation peace.
Do not be misled!
No, rather, “Let the peace of the Christ
rule in your hearts.”
“And show yourselves thankful.”
Yes, through his Son,
Jehovah will bless us all with peace forever!
Thank you, Brother Morris,
for strengthening our trust in Jesus’ promise
to give us peace now and during the events
that will shortly take place.
The second session of our convention
has truly helped us
to see how Jehovah blesses us with peace.
What can we look forward to
in the next session?
The scripture theme will be
from 2 Peter 3:14:
“Be found . . . spotless and unblemished
and in peace.”
The program will begin with a symposium
that will help prepare us
to share the “good news of peace”
at every opportunity.
Young ones can look forward
to a special talk just for them
given by a member of the Governing Body.
We’ll also see how brothers and sisters
are maintaining their peace
even when suffering from illness,
economic problems,
natural disasters, and other difficulties.
And of course, our next session
includes the baptism talk,
after which those who have been approved
will be baptized locally.
We have much to look forward to!
To conclude today’s session,
let’s sing song number 112, entitled
“Jehovah, God of Peace.”
Again, that’s song number 112.
After the song concludes,
you may have your own closing prayer.