We extend a warm welcome to all.
Today’s session will begin
with a music-video presentation
that will remind us of the many blessings
in store for Jehovah’s servants
and motivate us to share
these precious truths with others.
Please enjoy.
During this session and the next,
we will enjoy the talks and videos
under the Saturday heading on your program.
The scripture theme for these two sessions
is taken from 2 Peter 3:14,
where we are admonished
“to be found . . . spotless
and unblemished and in peace.”
These sessions will highlight
what we can individually do
to ‘pursue peace with others.’
To begin,
please join in singing song number 58,
“Searching for Friends of Peace.”
That’s song number 58.
As Jehovah’s people,
we are proud to witness
about “the God of peace”
and to proclaim his Kingdom.
How can we give an effective witness
and help interested ones to progress?
Our first symposium for this session
will address these questions.
Brother Kenneth Flodin,
a helper to the Teaching Committee,
will deliver the first talk of the symposium,
“Be Ready to Share ‘the Good News of Peace’
—Maintain Your Zeal.”
This symposium is
about sharing “the good news of peace.”
What a privilege it is to help humble people
find peace with Jehovah!
At Ephesians 6:15,
in describing
a Christian’s “complete suit of armor,”
it mentions our feet.
Now, back at that time,
thinking of Roman soldiers,
Paul knew that often they marched
for hundreds of miles on Roman highways,
crisscrossing the empire.
So at Ephesians 6:15, he said this:
“Having your feet shod in readiness
[in readiness] to declare
the good news of peace”
—yes, ready to share “the good news of peace”
on every suitable occasion.
In this symposium, we’ll discuss five ways
to remain ready to preach and teach.
We’d first like to discuss
why it’s important to maintain your zeal.
Now, as an analogy,
zeal has often been linked to fire.
We even use the expression
—don’t we?—
“He has a fiery zeal for his beliefs.”
But what does “a fiery zeal” indicate?
Please find Romans 1:14, 15,
and here it does not
actually use the word “zeal,”
but the sense of the word is evident.
You say: “We’re on fire,”
“We’re stoked up,” “We are ready.”
Did you find it?
Romans 1:14, 15:
“Both to Greeks and to foreigners,
both to wise and to senseless ones,
“I am a debtor; so I am eager
“[you see, ready with fiery zeal, eager]
to declare the good news.”
Zealous evangelizers are eager to declare
the good news—they’re “on fire.”
They want others to find peace with Jehovah.
But is there something
that can dampen that flame,
something that could even extinguish
the eager desire
—the readiness—
to find those who
even unknowingly yearn for peace?
Yes,
it can be difficult
to remain eager with fiery zeal
when we face such problems as
an unresponsive territory,
criticism, or outright opposition to the work
—and then there are
the pressures of daily life.
Those issues can also be likened to a fire,
to destructive fires like the wildfires
that have plagued the western part
of the United States year after year.
Those problems can threaten
our zeal and enthusiasm.
So, what can we do?
Well, there’s an English expression
that originates with firefighters.
The expression is “Fight fire with fire.”
In the path of a raging wildfire,
one technique is to ignite a controlled fire.
That controlled fire
consumes combustible materials.
So when the wildfire advances to that point,
there’s no fuel left
and the wildfire goes out.
Fight fire with fire.
Keep your zeal for the ministry
burning brightly.
And now please find 1 Timothy 4:16.
If our zeal fades—the flame smolders—
we might miss out on opportunities
to help others to gain life,
a life of peace with God.
Look at 1 Timothy 4:16 with me.
It says: “Pay constant attention
to yourself and to your teaching”
—you see, the flame, the temperature.
‘Pay attention to your zeal and teaching.’
It says: “Persevere in these things,
“for by doing this
you will save both yourself
and those who listen to you.”
Yes, share “the good news
of peace” with zeal.
Now, in the following video,
note how a couple realized
that the flame had gone out.
They still had some glowing embers left,
but they now find a way to fan the coals
and regain their fiery zeal.
I don’t remember when our routine service day
became so,
well,
routine.
Our zeal wasn’t what it used to be.
And we were finally starting to notice.
Not everyone wants to listen.
We just didn’t want to be the reason.
It didn’t take much research to find
great ideas
and set a few simple goals,
like working with those
who encourage us.
With Ryota and Ami, we’re always talking
about how we can reach the heart.
We got back to basics:
Be friendly,
listen,
let the conversation progress naturally,
try to share an appealing Scriptural thought,
and keep trying.
Our zeal
can attract an honest person
to the truth.
In the video, what wildfires, or problems,
did the couple face that sucked the oxygen
out of their ministry?
Well, of the four we mentioned earlier,
it seems the couple’s zeal was waning
because of seemingly unresponsive territory.
And as tired as the husband looked
in that first scene,
the pressures of daily life
might have been having a toll on him.
So how did they come to realize
that they needed
to fight fire with fire?
Do you remember their kitchen-table talk?
The husband mused
that “not everyone wants to listen.”
But then he added,
“We just didn’t want to be the reason,”
you see, the reason for them not listening.
They decided to fight fire with fire.
They reignited their own
controlled fire of zeal
to counteract the problems
they were succumbing to.
Well, what were some
of the techniques they used?
The first was to pray to Jehovah.
Could it be that the husband borrowed
the words of Romans 12:11 in his prayer?
Yes, he may well have asked
Jehovah to help them
as a couple to “be aglow with the spirit.”
Remember he said earlier,
“I don’t remember when
our routine service day
became so, well, routine.”
Fight the wildfire by, again,
becoming “aglow with the spirit.”
Ensure that any lack of response
is not due to our lackluster approach.
Well, what else did you notice
they did to rekindle their zeal?
They did some research,
looking for suggestions
to invigorate their ministry.
Yes, and regular Bible study
helps us to remember
why we endure in the disciple-making work.
For example, review Jesus’ attitude
toward the ministry.
The apostles’ bold witnessing
despite fiery opposition
and the disposition of Paul,
Aquila and Priscilla, Stephen,
and other Bible characters
—these can infuse us with similar zeal.
Next, keep your ministry fresh.
Well, what does that mean?
Instead of having a number
of phone calls that go unanswered,
which is similar to having no one at home
when in the door-to-door work,
change the time of day for witnessing
to when more people are home.
Participate in various forms of the ministry.
You know, ironically,
the pandemic more or less forced some of us
who were staunch door-to-door Witnesses
to branch out.
We tried phone witnessing and letter writing.
And now we have
a variety of preaching activities,
and this can keep us
more fully engaged and enthused.
And did you notice what the couple
in the video set as a goal?
Periodically, they decided in advance
to share in the ministry
with someone specific.
And then they determined
to talk about encouraging subjects
when in between calls,
whether in phone witnessing
or in the public ministry.
Jehovah values our work in the ministry
regardless of the response we receive.
Hebrews 6:10—are you familiar with that?
Of course you are.
It does not say
that Jehovah does not forget
the number of return visits you make.
It does not say he does not forget
how many Bible studies you conduct.
No, it says he does not
“forget your work [your effort]
and the love you showed for his name.”
Our zeal for the ministry demonstrates
that we have a deep love
for Jehovah and Jesus.
If (like the couple in the video)
you detect that your
routine of service is becoming, well,
very routine, then fight fire with fire.
Maintain that fiery zeal.
Be ready to share “the good news of peace.”
Brother Robert Ciranko,
a helper to the Writing Committee,
will now present
the next talk of this symposium,
“Be Ready to Share ‘the Good News of Peace’
—Prepare Well.”
What would you think and how would you feel
if I showed up to give this talk
but had done nothing to prepare
what to say to you
—if I had not bothered
to study the outline I was given,
could not remember the theme,
had no idea what the main points are,
and would have to guess
at what scriptures to use to support them,
and then, as I spoke,
I would ramble incoherently?
I’d make a very bad impression.
I know how I would feel.
I would be a nervous wreck,
and you would wonder why
I did not think enough of you
to put all the time and effort
that was necessary
into preparing the talk so that you could get
the most benefit from it.
Can you see where I’m going with this?
Could the same things be said
if you engaged in the ministry
without first preparing what to say?
If you did not review the sample
conversations that had been provided,
could not think of how
to start a conversation,
and did not know
what scripture to share,
how nervous would you be?
And what would the householder
think of you?
It would likely be a very short,
uncomfortable conversation.
And the other person may not care
to have you call again.
We should take some time
to prepare well before we preach.
Why?
Because we have the best message ever
—“the good news of peace”
to share with people—
and we should do our best so that they
will want to listen to what we have to say.
Jesus helped his disciples
to prepare for the ministry.
Luke chapter 10 reports that before
sending out 70 disciples to preach,
he shared with them a pleasant way
to greet each householder,
he told them what to talk about
(the Kingdom of God),
and he told them how to respond
to the varied reactions
they would get in their territory.
As a result,
because the disciples
were fully prepared for the ministry,
they enjoyed some thrilling experiences.
When we are prepared,
we are more poised and enthusiastic
and can truly enjoy the ministry.
As you watch the following video,
notice the good results of preparing well.
We’d made some good changes,
but we weren’t done.
I asked Yuri what she planned to talk about.
That started the usual scramble.
Then we got it—the sample conversation.
That’ll do.
But for that to work,
I had to remember the scripture.
We were both a little forgetful that morning.
Yeah, we needed to prepare better.
We’d been relying on our experience
and not enough on Jehovah.
So first we prepared our hearts.
Then we prepared our minds
and found new ways
to use our preaching tools.
Even a little preparation for initial calls
and our returns visits
went a long way.
The husband said,
“Yeah, we needed to prepare better.”
Have you ever thought that
about your ministry?
Like the couple in the video,
we can first prepare
our heart and our mind
and then see how best to use
our preaching tools.
Our goal should be the same
as that of the apostle Paul.
At 1 Corinthians 9:23,
he wrote that he wanted
to “do all things for the sake
of the good news,
in order to share it with others.”
So let’s think about some specific things
that we can do to prepare well,
beginning with what we can say
on the initial call,
whether that is done
in person or over the telephone.
Each issue of the
Christian Life and Ministry—Meeting Workbook
provides us with sample conversations
that give us some helpful ideas.
Of course, you may modify the samples
or use something entirely different.
Perhaps a subject from a previous month
or a different scripture would have
wider appeal in your territory.
Your opening words may be
the most important part of the presentation,
so think it through.
If the introduction
does not arouse interest,
the other person may terminate
the conversation
before we can give a witness.
We will be more effective if we
carefully prepare
the first sentence or two that we will say
after giving a customary greeting.
We might say,
“Many people are concerned about . . . ”
or “I would like
to get your opinion on . . . ”
or say something else.
Then pick a topic that is of local interest
and ask a well-worded viewpoint question
that would draw the person
into the conversation.
Now, what about preparing
for our return visits?
That actually begins
on the initial call by leaving a question
for the person to think about
until you call again.
That is how the sample initial calls
and return visits
are set up in the Meeting Workbook.
By leaving a thought-provoking question
at the end of every visit,
we can keep the chain of conversations
going as long as possible.
We can illustrate it this way:
Imagine a freight train
with an engine at the front,
a caboose at the rear,
and many cars in between.
What keeps all of those cars
moving together down the train track?
There is a device called a coupler
at the back of each train car
that latches onto the coupler
at the front of the car behind it.
By being coupled, or linked, together,
the cars all run as a unit along the track.
So the question that we leave
with a householder at the end of one visit
is what we can latch onto at the beginning
of our next visit
so that we can keep the train of thought
going from one conversation to the next.
For example, on the initial call
you could ask,
“Why is there so much suffering
in the world?”
After discussing that, raise the question,
“How does God feel about our suffering?”
But don’t answer the question
until your next visit.
After answering that question
on the first return visit,
leave the person with this question,
“What will God do to end our suffering?”
This will be discussed on your next visit.
It is also important to have an objective
in mind for each return visit.
Before making the call,
think about what you want to accomplish
on that call.
If you raised a question the last time,
you’re objective will surely include
answering that question from the Bible.
Of course,
the ultimate objective is to try to start
a Bible study
in the Enjoy Life Forever!  brochure.
Now, what about preparing
for the Bible studies that we conduct?
Even if we know the material very well,
we should prepare for each study session
with our student in mind.
That means thinking about and anticipating
the views and needs of that individual.
What points might he struggle
to understand or accept?
It also means getting familiar
with the lesson
to be covered
in our interactive Bible course.
Read the lesson carefully,
look up the “read” scriptures
to see how they apply,
watch the videos that will be shown
during the lesson,
and review the items
in the “Explore” section
so that you will know which of those
will be especially helpful to your student.
Then you will be well-prepared
to conduct the study.
Since it is ‘God who makes
the seed of truth grow’ in a person’s heart,
we should ask for Jehovah’s blessing
on our preparation for the study
so that we can best help
the student spiritually.
And we will be more effective
in our ministry
if we stay up-to-date
with the latest material
and features found
on jw.org and on JW Library®.
So learn how to navigate the website
and the app.
Two very helpful features on the website
are “Bible Questions Answered”
under the Bible Teachings tab
and “Frequently Asked Questions”
under the About Us tab.
They can also be found
on the app under “Article Series.”
The apostle Paul described himself
at 1 Corinthians 3:10
“as a skilled master builder.”
That is because he was engaging
in a spiritual construction work
to build Christian disciples.
And we are doing the same sort of work
when we engage in the ministry.
But to build effectively,
we must learn to use our tools well.
We especially need to develop skill
in using our principal tool, God’s Word,
as well as learn how to make effective use
of the publications
in our Teaching Toolbox.
A builder who prepares
before starting to work
avoids mistakes and frustration.
Remember what the brother said
at the end of the video?
‘Even a little preparation goes a long way.’
And that is what will help you
to do your best in the ministry.
Just as Paul recommended
at 2 Timothy 2:15
—please follow along in your Bible,
if you will—
it’s 2 Timothy 2:15:
“Do your utmost to present
yourself approved to God,
“a workman with nothing to be ashamed of,
handling the word of the truth aright.”
Then you will experience great joy
in the spiritual building work
that is taking place now
because you will be ready
and well-prepared to share
“the good news of peace.”
Brother Anthony Morris,
a member of the Governing Body,
will now present the next talk
of the symposium,
“Be Ready to Share ‘the Good News of Peace’
—Take the Initiative.”
For this part of the symposium,
“Share ‘the Good News of Peace,’”
we’re going to discuss
the need to take the initiative.
Now, we’re going to look
at why we should take the initiative,
how to take the initiative,
and then a concluding thought
about who’s helping
in directing us in our preaching work.
Now, first of all, why take the initiative?
Well, think about it.
One thing about being Jehovah’s Witnesses
is that we’re never off duty.
We never stop being
one of Jehovah’s Witnesses
—wherever we are or whatever we’re doing.
So it isn’t just when we’re out
in the formal preaching work
with a congregation group
—we are one of Jehovah’s Witnesses
all the time.
There’s no such thing as being off duty
when we’re one of Jehovah’s Witnesses.
Now, to give you an idea of how
significant this is
with informal witnessing,
I will tell you a statistic:
A survey was taken some years ago
(and you’d be surprised, possibly),
and one group
of over 200 baptized Witnesses,
now notice, over 40 percent
had been contacted by informal witnessing.
Isn’t that amazing?
So the door-to-door work is crucial.
Of course, during COVID-19
that’s been inhibited
—letter writing has its place
and also phone witnessing.
But the point is, there are other times
when we can do some witnessing informally.
Now, let’s examine how to do it?
And the best example
of how to do informal witnessing
is, of course, Christ Jesus.
And there’s an account that all of us
are familiar with in the Bible book of John.
So please find John chapter 4,
and we’re going to take a look
at how Jesus took the initiative
and then imitate him
—do just as he did.
Now notice here in John chapter 4
(we get the context),
they’ve been traveling through Samaria.
And then verse 6, we’ll read:
“In fact, Jacob’s well was there.
“Now Jesus, tired out as he was
from the journey,
“was sitting at the well.
It was about the sixth hour.”
Now, that’s interesting, is it not?
Jesus was tired.
He was a perfect man, but human,
and his journey tired him out.
And he’s there
about noon sitting at the well.
And now notice what happens in verse 7:
“A woman of Samaria came to draw water.
Jesus said to her: ‘Give me a drink.’”
Real simple—“Give me a drink.”
Well, what do we learn from this?
As you noticed, Jesus was tired.
We get tired
because of being imperfect.
If a perfect man gets tired out,
certainly we get tired.
Sometimes you may feel:
‘Well, you know, maybe I could witness
‘to this person
—take the initiative.
But I just don’t feel like it.
I’m tired.’
Not with Jesus.
See, to imitate Jesus,
even in the case when you’re tired,
you’re thinking of others.
You want to take the opportunity
to start a conversation.
That’s the initial goal.
Now, notice something else here
that we learn in the 9th verse
of John chapter 4:
“So the Samaritan woman said to him:
“‘How is it that you, despite being a Jew,
ask me for a drink even though
I am a Samaritan woman?’”
And then we learn more here in parentheses:
“For Jews have no dealings
with the Samaritans.”
And it went both ways.
That’s the way prejudice was
—“no dealings”—
and on top of that, she’s a woman.
And women were not treated very nicely
during that period in man’s history.
So she’s a Samaritan, she’s a woman,
and Jesus asks her for a drink.
He starts a conversation with her.
Now, these are the things we learn from this:
He didn’t make any assumptions about her
and obviously knew that she was a woman
and a Samaritan traveling
through Samaria at that time.
And he didn’t refuse
to speak to her
because of that.
So the lesson for us is:
Don’t judge people by what you see,
based on their culture
or color of their skin.
This world is filled with judges.
We’re Jehovah’s Witnesses.
We don’t do that.
We leave the judging
to Jehovah and Jesus Christ.
And don’t judge
whether you think they’ll converse with you.
That’s wrong.
Jesus didn’t do that,
and he set the perfect example for us.
Go ahead, and if you’re
a little nervous about it,
then we beg Jehovah for his spirit to help us
and to give us the courage to witness
about his beautiful name and purposes.
Now, he also teaches us
something else interesting here.
And this is where in taking the initiative,
you start a conversation;
you don’t rush into things.
Now notice, we read verse 9,
and then they had
this conversation take place
through these following verses here.
We get to verse 24 where he mentions
that ‘God is a Spirit, and you
must worship him with spirit and truth.’
And now here’s what happens
after they had this fine conversation
and after he simply asked for a drink.
Notice verse 25:
“The woman said to him:
“‘I know that Messiah is coming,
who is called Christ.
Whenever that one comes,
he will declare all things to us openly.’”
She spoke out of her heart.
Now notice verse 26:
“Jesus said to her: ‘I am he,
the one speaking to you.’”
My, what a moment!
And she’s blessed
with having the Messiah himself speak to her.
However, give it some thought.
What if Jesus, rather than saying:
“Give me a drink,”
started off with saying:
‘I am the Messiah.
Give me a drink.’
Hmm, I don’t know.
Because Jesus had Jehovah’s spirit
and heavenly wisdom,
he entered the conversation first.
So that’s what we want
to keep in mind and try to do ourselves
—to have a conversation.
It might just be speaking from your heart
and trying to engage the person.
For example, you could be
in the doctor’s office waiting room.
So you speak from your heart,
and you notice the person is looking at you:
“Boy, I look forward to the day
when I’ll never be sick again.”
Well, they could look at you and think,
‘Well, this guy is crazy.’
Or they could say: “Well, that would be nice.
What makes you believe
that’s going to happen for you?”
Either way, you’re starting
to take the initiative
to start a conversation,
and leave the rest to Jehovah.
He’s the one
that gets the credit for the results.
Now, next, we have a video here.
Now, as you watch the following video,
notice how a sister
finds an effective way
to witness informally.
They seemed nice.
I knew what Yuri was thinking.
I wanted to start a conversation,
but I didn’t want to bother them either.
And when an opportunity came,
I just froze.
Then I was in a rush to give a witness.
It felt forced.
It helped to hear that we’d all been there.
Our past experiences were similar.
Whenever we didn’t put pressure on ourselves
and just looked for something in common
to talk about,
we could usually find a moment
when we could say something about the Bible.
She was curious why we were dressed up.
It turns out that she’d never talked
to Jehovah’s Witnesses before.
So we appreciated
how she took the initiative.
Of course, you see the contrast there
that at one point she froze.
So it is stressful—no doubt about it.
We’re only human.
But then she rushed
into things running after her with the tract.
See, give it some thought.
Try to have a conversation,
then let the spirit move it,
and that would be imitating Jesus.
Then this can move
to getting into the spiritual purpose
of initiating the conversation.
So a good example,
give it a try, brothers and sisters,
and let Jehovah bless your efforts.
Now, to conclude,
I want to share this beautiful thought
when it comes to this work we’re engaging in
and sharing “the good news of peace”
by taking the initiative.
Never forget this, and you know it,
but it’s a good reminder
—Revelation chapter 14.
And here in Revelation
(familiar to most of you listening),
and verse 6, let’s read it:
“And I saw another angel flying in midheaven,
“and he had everlasting good news to declare
“to those who dwell on the earth, to every
nation and tribe and tongue and people.”
Now, this is profound, obviously,
an “angel flying in midheaven.”
The footnote helps us;
it’s overhead
—where the birds fly.
You know, you see them.
See, another ‘angel in midheaven,’
that’s how close they are.
And this is something
you want to meditate on.
Personally, when I was in the traveling work,
sometimes I’d be working with one
of the brothers or one of the sisters,
and they had opposition
in some of the territories we’d work.
And I could tell they’re feeling the stress,
and I know it was because of the reaction
of some of these householders.
So, what I used to enjoy doing
(and they appreciated it
after they realized what I was doing),
we’d be walking along
and then I would just stop and I’d look up.
And I’d say, “Do you see him?”
And they’d say, “Who?”
“He’s right up there above the trees.”
And they’d look at me like,
‘Our circuit overseer has lost it.’
But I said, “See,”
and I would tell them
about Revelation 14:6.
When we’re in the preaching work,
whether it’s informal or formal door-to-door,
the angels are the real reapers.
At least one is nearby.
What a profound thought!
They are the real harvesters.
They are the ones directing us
to the “rightly disposed” people.
Don’t ever forget that.
When it comes to being ready
to share “the good news of peace,”
you go ahead and take the initiative
to start conversations.
You’ll have valuable opportunities
to share “the good news of peace.”
Now, Brother Gary Breaux,
a helper to the Service Committee,
will now present the next talk
of this symposium,
“Be Ready to Share ‘the Good News of Peace’
—Follow Up on Interest.”
To encourage us to promptly follow up
on interest that we find
in the field ministry,
Paul likens our work to a plant
that grows from a little seed.
Now, what’s vital for a planted seed to grow?
One authority says:
“Of all the factors
that determine seed germination,
water is the first and most important.”
And another reference says:
“Until seeds have sprouted,
keep the seed bed moist,
never allowing it to dry out.”
So, what will happen
to a seed that is not watered?
Nothing!
It will lay dormant.
See, regular watering
is vital for a seed to sprout,
to take root
and, in fact, continue to grow.
Now, with these facts in mind,
Paul’s words at 1 Corinthians 3:6
show that more is required
than simply planting a seed of truth.
Let’s note his words.
It’s at 1 Corinthians 3:6.
It says:
“I planted, Apollos watered,
but God kept making it grow.”
So all credit goes to Jehovah God
for making the spiritual seed grow,
but he allows us
to have a role in the process.
Did you notice
the important role Apollos played?
He did the watering.
In a regular way,
he helped keep
the spiritual soil of the individual moist,
never allowing it to dry out.
Many people who show interest
in the Kingdom message today
are searching for the truth about God.
In order to teach them progressively,
we must return again and again.
This requires good preparation
and organization on our part.
By promptly making return visits,
we demonstrate
a sincere concern for the individual,
wanting to help them grow spiritually
and develop a relationship with Jehovah.
In the following video,
notice how a sister follows up
on interest shown.
Ami left a great question for her next visit.
Return visit! Mrs. Iwata!
I told her I’d visit this morning.
I just didn’t schedule the time.
I could at least stop by on the way back.
I missed her again.
If I didn’t try something different,
I was just going to keep missing her.
First, I wanted her
to know I hadn’t forgotten her.
Dear Mrs. Iwata,
I hope you’re doing well.
I promise to come by early next week.
By the way, your flowers are so beautiful!
Then I made a plan for my service day.
Following through is just too important
to leave to chance.
As you plan your share in the ministry,
follow the good example
of the sister in the video
and schedule time
to make regular return visits.
Doing so is just as important
as other aspects of our ministry.
These regular visits with interested people
are vital links in the chain
leading to a Bible study.
In our ministry,
we often compliment the householder
for the beautiful flowers or plants
in their yard,
just like the sister did in the video.
But how did they get that way?
Well, the householder
probably watered them on set days
or even used an automatic sprinkler timer
to schedule regular watering cycles.
See, to have healthy and vibrant plants,
watering cannot be left to chance.
Well, how can we apply that to our ministry?
Before leaving a person
that has shown interest,
endeavor to set
the proper time to water.
The water of truth will come on.
See?
Perhaps ask, “On what day or hour
would you like for me to return
to continue our discussion
or to answer the question?”
See, this consideration
really dignifies the person,
allowing them to share
in setting the appointment.
It’s important that we be willing
to water an interested person
at the most convenient time for them.
Then, just like setting a timer,
put that appointment
where you’ll remember it.
The sister in the video
put it in her electronic calendar
so she could be reminded later.
If you promise someone that you’ll return,
then keep your promise.
Remember Jesus’ simple statement
recorded at Matthew 5:37:
“Just let your word ‘Yes’ mean yes.”
If they’re truly interested,
they may go to great efforts
to keep the appointment.
How disappointed they would be
if we didn’t show up!
Following through is just too important
to leave to chance.
Because of the busy lives
that people have today,
it may be hard
to find the person at home again,
even if you set an appointment.
So it’s a good idea to try
and obtain his contact information,
maybe his phone number.
Some publishers anticipate this challenge
and simply ask, “Do you text?”
By simply texting,
you may be able to keep in touch
and cultivate the interest further.
And if you can’t get his contact information
and the person isn’t home
at the agreed-upon time,
you might leave a brief note,
just as the sister did in the video.
And this will assure the householder
that you haven’t forgotten them.
The disciple-making work
requires patience and persistence.
In this regard, note what
Ecclesiastes 11:6 says.
Ecclesiastes 11:6
—it says:
“Sow your seed in the morning
“and do not let your hand rest
until the evening;
“for you do not know
which will have success,
“whether this one or that one,
or whether they will both do well.”
When it comes to planting literal seed,
we don’t know when and where it will sprout.
Many factors are beyond our control.
Something similar can be said
of the disciple-making work.
We need to be patient and positive
because we don’t know who will respond.
Last and of utmost importance:
Even if the return visit is brief,
share a Scriptural thought.
The spiritual content of our conversation
is what makes our visit different
from any others that they may have.
See, they have neighbors,
friends, workmates,
or relatives that check in on them.
But for them to grow spiritually,
the water of truth from God’s Word
must be dispensed.
See, conveying
just a brief Scriptural thought
may provide just enough
to keep their spiritual soil moist.
The work involved of following up interest
is a very important assignment
that Jehovah has given to each of us.
With this in mind,
let’s return to Paul’s illustration
and see how Jehovah views us.
It’s back at 1 Corinthians chapter 3,
and verse 9.
It says:
“For we are God’s fellow workers.
You are God’s field under cultivation,
God’s building.”
It’s an honor to be one
of “God’s fellow workers.”
It enables us to show our love
for him and for our neighbors.
It brings us great joy
to share “the good news of peace”
by following up on interest shown.
And we can be assured
that those who respond favorably
will forever appreciate our diligent efforts
when they recall how we promptly followed up
when they showed interest.
Brother William Malenfant,
a helper to the Teaching Committee,
will now present
the final talk of this symposium,
“Be Ready to Share ‘the Good News of Peace’
—Help Students Grow to Maturity.”
Basic Bible teachings are wonderful.
Usually,
it’s the fundamental doctrines of the Bible
—basic teachings—
that draw people to the truth.
However, learning basic Bible teachings
is just the beginning
of knowledge about Jehovah.
At Hebrews 6:1,
the apostle Paul exhorts
all students of God’s Word
to progress beyond basic teachings.
This is what is stated at Hebrews 6:1:
“Therefore, now that we have moved beyond
“the primary doctrine about the Christ,
let us press on to maturity.”
Isn’t that what we want to achieve
with our Bible students,
to help them move beyond the primary doctrine
and progress to Christian maturity?
It comes about in degrees
as students acquire
an increased level of knowledge
and appreciation for the truth.
Bible students must learn to love God
and his standards and appreciate
that all of his ways and requirements
are expressions of his love for us.
When Bible students experience the good
that comes from obeying Jehovah
and following his ways,
their love for him will deepen.
As you watch the following video,
please note how a sister helps her student
to make progress toward maturity.
Mrs. Iwata was doing great.
We were already on Lesson 10.
I really hoped she’d come to a meeting soon.
We talked about Hebrews 10:24, 25
and watched the video.
Did I miss something?
I guess I did.
I was too focused
on our progress with the lessons
instead of her progress and what she needed.
Mr. Iwata said going to meetings
would dishonor the family.
He wanted her to quit the study.
She didn’t want to quit,
but whenever she tried to talk about it,
they argued.
We showed her where to look for help
and made time during our studies
to talk about it more.
And we all prayed for Jehovah
to bless her efforts.
We did our best
to share the good news of peace,
and Jehovah did the rest.
As we saw, the student took an important step
toward Christian maturity
when she began to attend meetings.
As you study with your student
lessons 7 to 11
of the Enjoy Life Forever!  book,
please be sure to highlight
Jehovah’s appealing qualities
that are set forth in those lessons.
For example, lesson 7
of the Enjoy Life Forever!  book
describes Jehovah’s loving ways.
We want to help our students to understand
that Jehovah
really does love them as individuals
and wants them to achieve everlasting life.
The apostle John highlights Jehovah’s love
at 1 John 4:9
by pointing out
that Jehovah sent Jesus to earth
to take our place in death
and thus pay for our inherited sins
and our personal sins.
Yes, out of love,
Jehovah provided a way for us
to enjoy an approved standing with him.
This is one of Jehovah’s loving ways.
Lesson 8 shows us
how to become Jehovah’s friend.
This is likely something that most people
have never even thought of.
Can you imagine the privilege
of becoming God’s friend?
Help your students to see how their obedience
and exclusive devotion to Jehovah
pave the way to friendship with him.
Proverbs 3:5, 6
tells us specifically
what Jehovah wants us to do.
Proverbs 3:5, 6 says:
“Trust in Jehovah
“with all your heart,
“and do not rely on your own understanding.
“In all your ways take notice of him,
and he will make your paths straight.”
We show our trust in Jehovah
by doing what he tells us to do
and thereby become his friends.
Jehovah takes good care of his friends,
and he is always loyal to them.
Lesson 9 highlights the power of prayer.
Teach your Bible students
how to pray to Jehovah.
In addition to prayer,
regular Bible reading is also necessary
to make spiritual progress.
Psalm, the first Psalm,
verses 2 and 3, encourages Bible reading.
Let’s look it up together.
That’s Psalm, the first Psalm,
and we’re going to read verses 2 and 3.
It’s speaking about a man of God
who takes delight in God’s Word.
It says: “But his delight
“is in the law of Jehovah,
“[well, the law of Jehovah
is found in the Bible,
“and it says,] and he reads His law
“in an undertone day and night.
“He will be like a tree planted
by streams of water,
“a tree that produces fruit in its season,
“the foliage of which does not wither.
And everything he does will succeed.”
Yes, “everything he does” as a Christian,
leading a Christian life, “will succeed.”
Reading God’s Word
and then putting it into practice
brings Jehovah’s blessing.
Now, if you have a student
who feels limited in his learning ability,
perhaps because of a lack of education,
please encourage him
to go to Jehovah in prayer
and persist in asking him
for help to understand his Word.
James 1:5
assures us that Jehovah is ready and willing
to help those
who ‘keep on asking’ him for help.
Lesson 10 gives this direction:
As soon as possible,
invite Bible students
to attend congregation meetings.
What your student hears and observes
at Christian meetings
can touch his heart
and will help him to progress.
So when you show your student the video
What Happens at a Kingdom Hall?,
that would be a good time
to warmly invite him
to attend meetings.
Also, be sure to invite
a variety of publishers
to accompany you on the study.
In that way, your student will get acquainted
with others in the congregation,
and he will likely feel more at home
when he attends our meetings.
Lesson 11: In this lesson,
we are encouraged to teach our students
how to do personal study
using jw.org and JW Library®.
Show your student how to use these tools.
If you feel a bit unsure
about teaching someone
to make use
of their electronic device for research,
don’t hesitate to ask
for help from the congregation.
There are many
who would be delighted to assist you.
The blessings that we receive
when we teach someone the truth
is described by the apostle John
at 3 John 4, where it states:
“No greater joy do I have than this:
“that I should hear that my children
go on walking in the truth.”
Yes, John is speaking
of his spiritual children.
That same joy can be ours.
What has this symposium
brought to our attention?
It has helped us to see how we can maintain
our zeal for the preaching work.
It has instructed us to prepare well
to share the truth with others.
It showed us how to take the initiative
to give an informal witness,
to follow up on interest,
and to help Bible students
grow to maturity.
If we do the best we can in the ministry,
whether people respond or not,
we will enjoy the peace
that comes from knowing
that we are pleasing Jehovah.
Hebrews 13:15, 16
tells us how to bring pleasure
to Jehovah God,
and that’s certainly something we want to do.
That’s Hebrews 13:15, 16; it reads:
“Through him [that is, through Jesus]
“let us always offer to God
a sacrifice of praise,
“that is, the fruit of our lips
“that make public declaration to his name.
“Moreover, do not forget to do good
“and to share what you have with others,
for God is well-pleased
with such sacrifices.”
Your readiness to share
“the good news of peace” with others
is just such a sacrifice.
And you can rest assured
that Jehovah is thoroughly pleased
with your loving and faithful service to him.
Thank you, brothers,
for helping us to be ready
to share “the good news of peace” effectively
at every opportunity.
Jehovah’s organization continues to grow,
and there is plenty of work to do.
Young people in particular
have many opportunities
to expand their service.
How can a career in full-time service
lead to rich blessings now and in the future?
What are some common obstacles
to pursuing full-time service,
and how can they be overcome?
We encourage young ones
to give special attention to the next talk.
Brother Mark Sanderson,
a member of the Governing Body,
will develop the theme
“Young People
—Choose a Path That Leads to Peace!”
An 18-year-old brother
was trying to decide
what he wanted to do after high school.
He was raised in the truth, and in his heart,
he wanted to be a pioneer.
But he also had a scholarship
to go to university
and some other grants,
and he had been accepted to attend.
He had many questions
(how was he going to support himself?)
and much pressure from his teachers
and counselors to go to university.
What decision would he make?
Well, maybe many of you young ones
who are listening to this talk right now
are facing that same decision,
or maybe you will be in a year or two.
What path will you take?
Well, now, here’s what we know:
Jehovah wants you to have,
not just a good life,
not just an average life,
but he wants you to have an awesome,
wonderful life
—both now during your youth
and really for your entire life.
That’s why the Bible says
at Ecclesiastes 11:9:
“Rejoice, young man, while you are young,
and let your heart be glad
in the days of your youth.”
Well, many young people
have found real joy and peace
by choosing a career
in the full-time service.
But now, when we say full-time service,
what are we talking about?
Well, full-time service
is not just one thing.
It actually includes many things.
It includes pioneering,
maybe in your home congregation
or maybe in another area
or maybe in another city, state,
province or even in another country.
It might mean assisting
with theocratic construction projects,
maybe building Kingdom Halls
or Assembly Halls
or building remote translation offices
or even working at building
at Bethel facilities.
And it also could mean
submitting an application
for Bethel service and becoming a Bethelite.
Really, there are
so many wonderful opportunities
that are available for you young ones
in full-time service.
But now, here’s a question:
What challenges could prevent you
from starting or continuing
on the path of full-time service?
And more important,
how can you overcome those challenges?
Well, let’s talk about three obstacles.
Here’s the first one:
It’s financial concerns.
How am I going to support myself?
Well, let’s look at something that Jesus said
at Matthew chapter 6
and verse 33
—Matthew 6:33.
Jesus said: “Keep on, then,
seeking first the Kingdom
“and his righteousness,
and all these other things
will be added to you.”
Well, now, OK.
It says “all these other things.”
What other things?
What is Jesus talking about here?
Well, to find out,
why don’t we go back up to verse 25?
And let’s read a little bit more
of what Jesus
was talking about when he said
those famous words
—verse 25:
“On this account I say to you:
“Stop being anxious about your lives
“as to what you will eat
or what you will drink,
“or about your bodies
as to what you will wear.
“Does not life mean more than food
and the body than clothing?”
Now (after identifying)—
Now, we know what Jesus is talking about:
He’s talking about our necessities
—food, shelter, clothing.
But now, look at the illustrations
Jesus goes on to give now,
beginning here in verse 26:
“Observe intently the birds of heaven;
“they do not sow seed or reap
or gather into storehouses,
“yet your heavenly Father feeds them.
“Are you not worth more than they are?
“Who of you by being anxious
can add one cubit to his life span?
“Also, why are you anxious about clothing?
“Take a lesson from the lilies of the field,
“how they grow;
they do not toil, nor do they spin;
“but I tell you that not even Solomon
“in all his glory was arrayed
as one of these.
“Now if this is how God clothes
the vegetation of the field
“that is here today and tomorrow
is thrown into the oven,
“will he not much rather clothe you,
“you with little faith?
“So never be anxious and say,
‘What are we to eat?’
“or, ‘What are we to drink?’
or, ‘What are we to wear?’
“For all these are the things
the nations are eagerly pursuing.
“Your heavenly Father knows
that you need all these things.”
Well, do you get the sense of this?
Jesus was trying to reason
that just as Jehovah provides
for all of his creation,
he can provide for you too.
We just need to develop our faith
that Jehovah will provide the things we need
if we put his service first.
Well, does that mean
that Jehovah is just going to drop
into our lap everything that we need?
Well, no.
Jehovah expects
that we’re going to use the things
that he’s given us
to be able to support ourselves.
So it’s very wise when you’re young
to plan ahead so that you can obtain
the skills you need
to be able to support yourself.
Now, in some lands,
it may be that as you’re growing up,
you can learn a trade from your father
or from your mother
or maybe even from another relative.
In other lands, you might be able
while you’re still in high school
to take some vocational courses
that would help you to learn
a skill or learn a trade.
But here’s the point: We need to plan.
So ask yourself, ‘What abilities and skills
do I have that I could use
to support myself?’
A sister named Kelly
had a very clear goal in mind
of becoming a pioneer.
So, what did she do?
Well, this is what she says:
“I had to choose something
that would allow me
to support myself in my ministry.”
Kelly enrolled in a vocational program
in her high school,
and that helped her
to achieve her primary goal.
Here’s what she said:
“The full-time ministry
was what I wanted to do.
Everything else was secondary.”
Well, how does Kelly feel now
about the decision that she made?
She says: “I feel my decision
was the best one that I could have made.”
You young brothers and sisters,
you can overcome that challenge
just by planning ahead
and making sure
that you have practical skills
you can use to support yourself.
Here’s the second obstacle:
pressure from others.
‘My relatives want me
to focus on making money.’
Well, if that’s the case,
explain your spiritual goals
in a calm, respectful way.
Colossians 4:6 says:
“Let your words always be gracious,
seasoned with salt.”
Well, we all know
when we eat food with no salt,
it doesn’t taste very good, does it?
We put a little salt on it
—now it becomes delicious.
So make sure that when you
speak to your relatives,
you put a little salt on those words
so that you can reason with them
and help them to see the wisdom
of the decision that you want to make.
Well, it could be
that your relatives will not agree with you.
But let’s look at something that Jesus said
here at Luke 7:35.
Jesus said: “All the same,
“wisdom is proved righteous
“[or, now, if you look at the footnote,
it says, ‘or “is vindicated”’]
by all its children.”
Well, now, what’s the point?
Well, sometimes when people make a decision,
we’re not sure if it
was the right one or not.
But when the decision works out well,
when it leads to success,
when people see how happy you are
and how successful you are
—the joy, the satisfaction you have—
well, then, what happens?
Well, maybe your relatives will see
that your decision has been vindicated.
It’s been “proved righteous”
by the way things have turned out.
Here’s obstacle number three:
unexpected challenges.
‘I thought it was going
to be easier than this.’
Well, those unexpected challenges
can be many.
It could be just trying
to get used to new roommates,
dealing with personality challenges,
or even just coping with homesickness.
Here’s the point: Don’t give up!
Notice what James said here
in James chapter 1
—James chapter 1
and verse 4.
Now, you notice as you look at verse 2,
James is talking about trials,
and he’s talking about how trials
can have a positive effect on us.
But now look what he says in verse 4:
“But let endurance complete its work,
“so that you may be complete
and sound in all respects,
not lacking in anything.”
What’s James trying to say?
What’s his point?
Well, have you ever heard the expression
“No pain, no gain”?
Well, if you want to reach
a certain fitness goal
or if you want to be very good
at playing a certain sport,
no doubt you’re going to have
some aching muscles.
And no doubt you’re going to have
some hurt pride along the way too.
Maybe you won’t be very good
when you first start.
But what do you do?
If you want to become good,
if you want to reach your goal,
you can’t give up.
You have to keep trying.
Well, the same could be said
about reaching our spiritual goals.
You see, James mentions
that trials often reveal our weaknesses.
Maybe it’s some aspect of our personality
that needs improvement.
Or maybe it’s something
in our relationship with Jehovah.
Maybe we need greater faith;
maybe we need greater trust.
If we endure even during periods of trial
and when we refuse to give up,
we become stronger.
We become stronger in our spirituality
and our relationship with Jehovah
—our love for him,
our faith in him, our trust in him
just continues to grow.
As James says there in verse 4,
we become “complete
and sound in all respects,
not lacking in anything.”
So when those trials come
—and they will come—
don’t look for a quick way out.
Endure, keep going, don’t give up!
Seek advice from brothers and sisters
who have successfully coped
with similar challenges,
and you too will be successful.
In the following video,
notice how some full-time servants
have found real peace
despite those three obstacles:
financial concerns,
pressure from others,
and unexpected challenges.
I prayed to Jehovah,
“If it is your will, I would be happy
to enter pioneer service.”
But I had to work really hard
to provide for the needs of my family
because my father had died
when he was 45 years old.
The elder that I talked to
gave me advice not to be picky
about what kind of job I could get.
He reminded me of Matthew 6:33,
and told me
not to be overly anxious.
Because of our good communication
within the family,
we were able to find solutions.
My other siblings realized
that they also shared
responsibility in providing
for the needs of the family.
After one year of pioneering,
I was encouraged to apply for Bethel service,
and now I am in Bethel.
I feel that Jehovah really cares for me,
loves me,
and appreciates all my efforts.
Because they love me, my cousins
pressured me to choose a secular career.
If I went against
their wishes, it would hurt them
and put a strain on our relationship.
I was really anxious.
I wanted to show my trust
in Jehovah by pioneering
and give him an opportunity to show me
that I can be happy in his service.
I tried to express my appreciation
for my cousins by what
I said and did
and showed them love.
They’ve realized
that I have changed for the better.
I show more concern for others now.
Now they understand that we have been
learning good things and that we have
a happier and more meaningful life.
I wanted to try serving
where the need was greater.
When I first arrived,
I thought it was so cool being there.
I had expected the poverty,
but when I saw it,
it hit home more than what I had expected.
So then I started to feel really homesick.
But my brothers and sisters—
I’d go to the Kingdom Hall and they
were able to cope with the challenges
that they were facing because they had
Jehovah in their life.
So their example really helped me to see
that my circumstances
don’t need to change
for my attitude to change.
Proverbs 15:15 stood out to me,
which is about having “a cheerful heart”
and being able to have “a continual feast”
no matter what my circumstances are.
And I found an article about that scripture.
And so from there, I decided to ask myself,
‘How can I use my situation
and what I’m learning to help others?’
And I got to start helping
with a foreign-language group there.
That whole experience
just made my love for people grow so much
and definitely changed my life.
Some of your non-Witness family members
might offer you secular or financial advice.
We know they mean well
and they feel that they’re giving you
the best advice
because they love you.
But, young brothers and sisters,
we are convinced that the blessings
of full-time service
far outweigh any challenges
that might go along with it.
Just think of the experiences
that we heard in the video.
Harley’s choices allowed him to go to Bethel
and helped him to feel
that Jehovah really loved him.
Anjil’s choices took courage,
but those choices helped him
to be more concerned about other people
and helped his relatives to see
that he had made a good decision.
And Carlee did not give up
when the trials came.
Instead, she learned
to love other people even more
and became a more powerful, strong Christian.
Brothers and sisters, why are we so convinced
that full-time service
will lead you young ones
to a wonderful life?
Well, it’s because that’s the decision
that so many of us made when we were young.
Do you remember
that 18-year-old young brother
who was trying to decide which path to take?
Well, that was me some years ago.
I’m so glad
that with the help of Jehovah and my parents
and other mature friends in the congregation,
I made the decision
just like so many other brothers
and sisters around the world
to turn down that scholarship,
to give up university,
and to go directly
into the full-time service.
That is a decision
that I have never regretted;
that is a decision that I will never regret.
Young people, Jehovah loves you.
He wants you to have
a wonderful, awesome life.
Choose the path
of full-time service if you can.
You will never regret it.
It will put you on a path
that leads to joy and peace
with our marvelous, wonderful God, Jehovah.
Thank you, Brother Sanderson,
for the warm encouragement
to pursue full-time service
from an early age.
Now we invite all to join
in singing song number 135,
“Jehovah’s Warm Appeal: ‘Be Wise, My Son.’”
That’s song number 135.