Welcome back, brothers and sisters,
for the second session
of the 2022 “Pursue Peace”! Convention
of Jehovah’s Witnesses.
This session corresponds
to the Friday afternoon section
on your program,
and it will continue
to develop the Scriptural theme
from Psalm 29:11:
“Jehovah will bless his people with peace.”
Let’s begin with a music-video presentation.
As Jehovah’s people,
we love to tell others
about our God and our hope.
The following video
features brothers and sisters
sharing “the good news of peace”
around the globe.
We’ll also see the work done
at various Bethel facilities
in support of this worldwide preaching work.
Enjoy!
Jehovah’s promises of peace
bring us great delight.
When we think about
what life will be like in God’s new world,
it fills our hearts
with appreciation and love for Jehovah.
Let’s express those feelings
as we sing song number 144,
entitled “Keep Your Eyes on the Prize!”
That’s song number 144.
The Bible book of Isaiah
contains many promises for the future.
Do you take time to contemplate
what that future will be like?
The following five-part symposium
will help us to picture
that wonderful time yet ahead.
We will also learn how Jehovah
is fulfilling his promise
to care for his servants even now.
Brother Samuel Herd,
a member of the Governing Body,
will present the first talk,
entitled “Take Delight
in God’s Promises of Peace
—‘My Servants Will Eat . . .
My Servants Will Drink.’”
In his Word, Jehovah has promised
to bring peace to his loyal servants.
As we’ve learned, that peace
is more than the absence of conflict.
It involves our overall well-being,
including our health and security.
God’s heartwarming promises
fill us with appreciation and hope.
In the Bible in the 145th Psalm,
it tells us in verses 15 and 16:
“All eyes look hopefully to you;
“you give them their food in its season.
“You open your hand and satisfy the desire
of every living thing.”
In this symposium, we will consider the past,
present, and future fulfillment
of several Bible prophecies of peace
that are found in the book of Isaiah.
Jehovah promises to provide an abundance
of both literal food and spiritual food.
When the Israelites loyally served Jehovah,
they experienced the blessings foretold
at Isaiah 49:10.
Today, Jehovah’s servants are experiencing
the fulfillment of Isaiah 65:13, 14.
There you’ll find it to say:
“Therefore this is what
the Sovereign Lord Jehovah says:
“‘Look!
“‘My servants will eat,
but you will go hungry.
“‘Look! My servants will drink,
“‘but you will go thirsty.
“‘Look! My servants will rejoice,
“‘but you will suffer shame.
“‘Look! My servants will shout joyfully
“‘because of the good condition of the heart,
“‘but you will cry out
because of the pain of heart
and you will wail
because of a broken spirit.’”
Although we may at times
experience literal hunger,
we enjoy an abundance
of satisfying spiritual food.
In the future,
Jehovah will
completely eliminate literal hunger.
As you watch the following video,
think about the blessings we enjoy now
and the ones we will enjoy in the future.
Through Isaiah,
Jehovah promised to feed his servants
physically
and spiritually.
Today, Jehovah invites us to a banquet
that is spiritually nourishing.
Bible-based videos and publications
draw us close to God
and satisfy our hunger for truth.
In the new world,
abundant, healthy food will be more
than a promise
—it will be a reality.
“There will be an abundance
of grain on the earth;
on the top of the mountains
it will overflow.”
What a blessing it is
to be among Jehovah’s people!
Spiritual provisions flow to us
like an ever-broadening
and ever-deepening river.
There’s not a grain of salt missing
nor a slice of bread
nor a pat of butter missing.
There is way too much to eat at one meal.
We have to come
to Jehovah’s table several times a week
to keep our spiritual fiber intact
and energy strong
for the work we engage in
—the Kingdom preaching.
We have an abundance of nourishing food
—Bible-based publications,
recordings and videos,
meetings and conventions,
website material.
Jehovah has not deviated from his promise.
Note this one, Psalm 72:16:
“There will be an abundance
of grain on the earth;
“on the top of the mountains
it will overflow.
“His fruit will flourish as in Lebanon,
“and in the cities people will blossom
like the vegetation of the earth.”
And then again, Isaiah 30:23:
“And he will give the rain
“for the seed you sow in the ground,
“and the bread that the ground produces
“will be abundant and rich.
“In that day your livestock will graze
in spacious pastures.”
Jehovah has placed
everything we need on the table.
We must willfully come to the table
and sit down and eat.
He doesn’t make us come
like some mothers may have
to demand a reluctant child
to come to the house
from playing and eat a meal.
Be sure to thank Jehovah
for the spiritual food he provides.
Psalm 100:2, 3 reminds us:
“Serve Jehovah with rejoicing.
“Come into his presence with joyful shouting.
“Know that Jehovah is God.
“He is the one who made us,
and we belong to him.
We are his people
and the sheep of his pasture.”
Show your appreciation.
How?
By studying diligently
and applying what you learn.
If you lack sufficient material things now,
take delight in meditating
on future Kingdom blessings.
Jehovah will surely fulfill his promises,
just as he has always done.
Isaiah 55:10, 11 reminds us:
“For just as the rain and the snow
“pour down from heaven
“and do not return there
“until they saturate the earth,
“making it produce and sprout,
“giving seed to the sower
and bread to the eater,
“so my word that goes out
of my mouth will be.
“It will not return to me without results,
“but it will certainly accomplish
“whatever is my delight,
“and it will have sure success
in what I send it to do.”
Brother Ronald Curzan,
a helper to the Teaching Committee,
will now present
the next talk of this symposium,
“Take Delight in God’s Promises of Peace
‘They Will Build Houses and . . .
Plant Vineyards.’”
“If it sounds too good to be true,
it probably is.”
This familiar saying might be true
with human promises,
but it’s certainly not true
with promises from Jehovah.
They always come true.
Just before his death at the age of 110,
Joshua reminded the Israelites
why Jehovah’s promises
can always be trusted.
He said: “Not one word
out of all the good promises
“that Jehovah your God
has spoken to you has failed.
They have all come true for you.”
Among all of Jehovah’s good promises
are the heartwarming restoration promises
given to the Jews returning
from exile in Babylon.
Since the land of Judah
had lain desolate for 70 years,
the Jews wouldn’t have expected brand
new homes waiting for them to occupy
or fields ready for them to harvest.
There would be much work
for them to do once they arrived.
There were many unknowns
about their future,
which could have caused some to worry,
or to be anxious.
Some family heads might have wondered:
‘Where will we live?
How will I feed my family
and keep them safe?’
Jehovah calmed their hearts
with the reassuring promises
recorded at Isaiah 65:21, 22.
Let’s read these together.
That’s Isaiah 65:21, 22,
and there it reads:
“They will build houses
and live in them,
“and they will plant vineyards
and eat their fruitage.
“They will not build
for someone else to inhabit,
“nor will they plant for others to eat.
“For the days of my people
will be like the days of a tree,
and the work of their hands
my chosen ones will enjoy to the full.”
These promises
must have strengthened the Jews.
Now, Jehovah didn’t say that ‘they might
build and live in their own homes,
and they might  enjoy the fruitage
from their own vineyards.’
No, he told his precious chosen ones
that they will  enjoy
these promises to the full.
Even though they
hadn’t been told every detail
and there were many unknowns
regarding their future,
they knew their God, Jehovah.
They knew that his promises
were for their good
and that they would all come true.
And those promises did come true.
Knowing that God fulfilled
all of his promises in the past
strengthens our trust and confidence
that all of his promises for the future,
like the ones that we read in Isaiah 65,
will all come true for our everlasting good.
What a joy it will be to build
and then live in our own home,
never having to worry that we will lose it
because of a natural disaster
or economic collapse!
Sadly, though, many of our
brothers and sisters today
do suffer the harsh realities
of living in this old system of things.
For example,
a sister in Poland named Gabriela
experienced great loss when her home
was nearly destroyed by a flood.
How did she maintain her joy?
Notice what she said:
“I don’t want to talk about what I lost
—those are just material things.
“Rather, I want to tell you
how much I gained.
“This experience reassured me
“that being a part of the Christian
congregation is a unique privilege
as well as a source of joy and happiness.”
So although she went through some
very difficult times, what did she gain?
Joy and happiness.
But what about a single sister
from Puerto Rico named Anel?
She endured a very difficult test
back in 2017 when Hurricane Maria
destroyed her home.
As a result of that storm, she lost her job.
But notice what she recalled:
“During those difficult days,
I felt anxious
“but I learned to trust in Jehovah
through prayer
and not let anxiety paralyze me.”
She also said:
“Following the direction of the organization
helped me to remain calm.
“I saw Jehovah’s hand
in the spiritual encouragement I received
“as well as the material assistance
provided by the brotherhood.
“Jehovah gave me much more than
I could even ask for, and my faith
was greatly strengthened.”
So she received assistance from Jehovah
—from his organization—
and she was greatly strengthened.
What about you?
Are you suffering some sort of storm
in your life,
perhaps from a natural disaster
or maybe a figurative one
caused by a health issue,
a family problem,
or some injustice?
During such times,
it’s normal to experience
feelings of anxiety,
worry about our future,
the safety of our family.
But don’t allow such feelings
to paralyze you.
Like Gabriela and Anel,
keep doing what you can
and continue trusting in Jehovah.
Also, continue to trust
in our loving brotherhood.
Our brothers and sisters are true friends
who are ready to show love
in our time of distress.
They will quickly come to our aid
by providing practical assistance
and relief provisions.
They will help us rebuild our home
and rebuild our life.
They will build us up and stabilize us
with words of encouragement.
When we put our complete trust in Jehovah
and his promises,
we receive the best protection possible.
Note what the psalmist wrote
at Psalm 91:1, 2.
Psalm 91:1, 2 says:
“Anyone dwelling in the secret place
“of the Most High will lodge
under the shadow of the Almighty.
“I will say to Jehovah:
“‘You are my refuge and my stronghold,
my God in whom I trust.’”
What a beautiful reminder
of protection from Jehovah!
But what is
“the secret place of the Most High”?
Well, it’s a figurative place
of spiritual security and protection.
Those who dwell, or lodge,
with God as his personal guests
and remain there are safe from anything
or anyone that threatens their faith
and their love for God.
We can be sure that Jehovah
will never abandon those who trust in him
—not now, not ever.
As you watch the following video,
envision the secure future that lies ahead
when we will enjoy complete security.
Do you long for a home of your own?
Jehovah promised the returning exiles
that they would build
and enjoy comfortable dwellings.
Jehovah likewise cares for us,
whether we lose our home
or we’re taken from it.
Above all,
true worship provides spiritual security
that is found nowhere else.
The spiritual home we have now
reminds us that Jehovah will give us
a physical place to call home
in the new world.
“They will build houses and live in them.”
What a beautiful video!
It helps us imagine
what we will experience
in the near future
when all of God’s promises
become a reality on a paradise earth
and when we truly are safe
and cared for in every way
—physically, spiritually, and emotionally.
Would you like to read another
comforting promise from Jehovah?
It’s found at Isaiah 65:23.
And there it says:
“They will not toil for nothing,
“nor will they bear children for distress,
“because they are the offspring
made up of those blessed by Jehovah,
and their descendants with them.”
This must have brought
great comfort to the Jews.
And how comforting it is for us today!
In the new world,
all families will experience
Jehovah’s blessing
and enjoy the results of their hard work.
In the meantime,
if you have lost your home or possessions
or if you experience loss in the future,
keep focusing on Jehovah’s good promises.
Strong faith can help you
to weather any storm
—literal or figurative.
Trust that Jehovah will hear
and respond to your needs,
even anticipating them.
He promises to “open [his] hand
and satisfy the [proper] desire
of every living thing.”
That promise includes you and your family.
Continue to take delight
in all of God’s promises,
knowing that “not one word
out of all the good promises
“that Jehovah your God has spoken
to you has failed.
They [will] all come true for you.”
Brother Leonard Myers,
a helper to the Writing Committee,
will now present the next talk
of this symposium,
“Take Delight in God’s Promises of Peace
—‘The Wolf and the Lamb
Will Feed Together.’”
As we continue our consideration
of the promises of peace
in Isaiah’s prophecies,
I’d like you to imagine
an Israelite living in Babylon.
Now, he’s just learned
that Jews can return to Jerusalem
and help to rebuild the temple.
So he must decide
if he and his family will leave Babylon
to make the long trip to his homeland.
What might he consider?
Well, after 70 years,
the land must have changed.
Fields would be overgrown with weeds.
Wolves, leopards, lions, and bears
must freely walk in the fields.
Snakes make their home there.
So he might ask himself:
‘Will my domestic animals
be killed by predators?
‘Will my small children be bitten by snakes?
And what about the danger of fierce men
attacking us on the journey home?’
Well, any such fears could be dispelled
by considering the prophecy at Isaiah 11:6-9.
Let’s read that together.
Isaiah chapter 11
—and notice this promise of peace—
starting in verse 6:
“The wolf will reside for a while
with the lamb,
“and with the young goat
the leopard will lie down,
“and the calf and the lion
and the fattened animal will all be together;
“and a little boy will lead them.
“The cow and the bear will feed together,
“and their young will lie down together.
“The lion will eat straw like the bull.
“The nursing child
will play over the lair of a cobra,
“and a weaned child will put his hand
over the den of a poisonous snake.
“They will not cause any harm or any ruin
“in all my holy mountain,
“because the earth will certainly be filled
with the knowledge of Jehovah
as the waters cover the sea.”
What a beautiful promise of peace!
Jews wouldn’t need to fear
wild animals or fierce men
on their journey home
or in their restored land.
With these poetic words,
Jehovah assured the exiles
that they and their livestock would be safe.
He would bless them with peace.
And did you notice, according to verse 7,
that the lion would symbolically eat straw,
illustrating that lions
wouldn’t kill the Jews’ cattle?
Faithful ones would have nothing to fear
from animal or human predators.
Do we see this prophecy
being fulfilled in our day?
Not with the literal animals,
but we do see a spiritual fulfillment.
Notice again, the end of verse 9.
It says: “The earth will certainly be filled
with the knowledge of Jehovah.”
Now, does the knowledge of Jehovah
change the behavior of animals?
No, but the knowledge of God
does change people.
In our day, the knowledge of Jehovah
helps people who are violent
to transform their personality
and become peaceable.
In harmony with Colossians 3:10,
these ones have ‘clothed themselves
with the new personality.’
They’ve stripped off
animalistic, violent tendencies
and transformed their lives
in harmony with what the Bible teaches.
They get along peaceably with others.
Perhaps you know someone
who made such changes.
Or perhaps you made these changes,
leaving behind a violent way of life.
Let me share with you such an experience.
A man named José
was trained in the martial arts
and in the use of weapons.
He had broken the law so many times
that he was brought to trial on 22 counts
and sentenced to 20 years in prison.
He was so violent
that even fellow inmates were afraid of him,
and he was kept in a high-security cell.
For seven years, his fleshly sister,
who was one of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
visited him.
But he always rejected the Bible’s message.
In time, though,
he accepted one of our publications,
and a Bible study was started.
Right away,
he made tremendous changes in his conduct.
One week later,
he gave a personal witness to 200 prisoners
and the following week to 600 more.
He even received permission
to visit the inmates in other prison blocks.
Well, because of the remarkable change
in his behavior,
his sentence was reduced to 15 years.
However, after serving just ten years,
he was released from prison.
José was eventually baptized
as one of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
truly a case
of ‘the wolf residing with the lamb.’
And what about the future fulfillment
of Isaiah 11:6-9?
In the earthly Paradise
that God has promised,
there will be delightful peace among humans
and between humans and animals.
Don’t you long for that time?
As you watch the following video,
notice the peace we enjoy
with fellow believers now
and just imagine the peace
that we’ll enjoy in Paradise.
How would you feel during a long journey
where you might meet
wild animals and criminals along the road?
Jehovah assured the returning exiles
that they would return
in safety and dwell in peace.
In the spiritual paradise we enjoy right now,
people who were once violent
have learned to be humble,
loving, and peaceable.
Imagine the peace
that will reign in God’s new world,
where we can wander this beautiful globe,
explore every corner,
and admire the handiwork of the true God
with no fear.
“‘They will do no harm nor cause any ruin
in all my holy mountain,’ says Jehovah.”
As the video showed,
people who were once violent
have learned to be
humble, loving, and peaceable.
And how did you feel
when you saw scenes in the video
of humans so close to wild animals?
Jehovah’s promise of peace among humans
and peace between humans and animals
is thrilling!
Please notice
what Isaiah further wrote about this peace
at Isaiah chapter 65.
Please turn there with me
—Isaiah 65.
Now, these are words similar to those
we read earlier in Isaiah chapter 11.
Isaiah 65:25:
“‘The wolf and the lamb will feed together,
“‘the lion will eat straw just like the bull,
“‘and the serpent’s food will be dust.
“‘They will do no harm nor cause any ruin
in all my holy mountain,’ says Jehovah.”
Skilled artists in the Art Department
at world headquarters
beautifully illustrate such scenes,
and the images can be found
in our publications.
But what Isaiah describes
is no artist’s rendition.
This will be real.
Think how you’ll feel
when you’re not afraid of wild animals
and the animals aren’t afraid of you.
As we look forward
to that future promise of peace,
what can we do now to pursue peace?
One thing is to contribute
to the peace of our spiritual paradise,
the secure,
spiritually prosperous environment
in which we worship Jehovah.
Jesus stated at Matthew 5:9:
“Happy are the peacemakers.”
A peacemaker is skilled
at restoring peace among brothers
when peace is disturbed.
But more important,
a peacemaker strives
to avoid disturbing peace in the first place.
Does “peacemaker” describe you?
Are you contributing
to our spiritual paradise in that way?
Something else we can do
as we await the future fulfillment
of the wolf and the lamb feeding together
is to meditate on what it will be like
to help resurrected ones who were violent
to become peaceable.
Imagine studying with a resurrected one
who had a violent background,
who perhaps experienced a violent death
because of a fierce personality.
How will you reason with the person
from God’s Word
to help him see the need to be a peacemaker?
What examples of such transformations
will you share?
And how will you explain
the prophecies of peace
at Isaiah chapter 11, verses 6 through 9
and chapter 65, verse 25?
We encourage all of you to think deeply
about how this promise of peace
was fulfilled for the ancient Jews,
how the promise is being fulfilled today,
and what life on earth will be like
when it’s fulfilled in the future.
May all of us take delight
in the peaceful promise
of the wolf and the lamb feeding together.
Brother James Mantz,
a helper to the Writing Committee,
will now present the next talk
of this symposium,
“Take Delight in God’s Promises of Peace
—‘No Resident Will Say: “I am Sick.”’”
Jehovah is the Great Healer.
Only he can make the promise:
“No resident will say, ‘I am sick.’”
Why can we be confident
that Jehovah is going to keep his promise
to bring an end to all sickness?
We find assurance
in the words of Isaiah 35:5, 6.
Please open your Bibles to that scripture.
Here we read a promise of healing
that Jehovah made to the nation of Israel.
This promise gives us hope
because it was actually fulfilled
on a small scale
more than 2,500 years ago.
Isaiah 35:5, 6 reads:
“At that time
the eyes of the blind will be opened,
“and the ears of the deaf will be unstopped.
“At that time
the lame will leap like the deer,
“and the tongue of the speechless
will shout for joy.
“For waters will burst forth
in the wilderness,
and streams in the desert plain.”
Isaiah recorded this promise 125 years
before the Babylonian army
destroyed Jerusalem.
It was fulfilled
after Jehovah freed the Israelites
from Babylonian captivity in 537 B.C.E.
and restored them
to their homeland in Israel.
But you may ask,
‘Were the blind, deaf, lame, and speechless
really healed at that time?’
To answer,
we need to apply a basic principle:
Jehovah restores what was lost.
During the 70 years of exile,
Jehovah did not punish the Israelites
by striking them with physical blindness,
deafness, lameness, and loss of speech.
Therefore,
their restoration would not require
the healing of their physical disabilities.
However,
these afflictions are a good description
of the self-inflicted spiritual sickness
that had caused the nation
to fall into apostasy
and lose Jehovah’s favor.
Jehovah saw their repentant attitude
and their desire to restore
true worship in Jerusalem.
He healed their spiritual sickness
by forgiving their sins
and restoring them to his favor.
In other words,
they came to their spiritual senses.
They regained their spiritual vision
and their ability to hear, obey,
and speak Jehovah’s word.
No longer spiritually lame,
they were energized
to carry on Jehovah’s pure worship.
Similarly today, we are eyewitnesses.
Yes, we are the beneficiaries
of a worldwide spiritual healing program.
Jehovah heals us spiritually by freeing us
from false religious teachings
and unclean practices.
He has brought us into a spiritual paradise,
where our spiritual strength
is renewed day by day.
In a spiritual sense,
the blind are learning to see
and the deaf are learning to hear.
But is spiritual healing the only part
of the fulfillment of Jehovah’s promise?
No.
Please open your Bibles to Isaiah 33:24.
As we read this verse,
pay attention to the latter part,
because it contains
the key to understanding
why physical healing
is included in God’s promise:
“No resident will say: ‘I am sick.’”
Isaiah 33:24 says:
“And no resident will say: ‘I am sick.’
The people dwelling in the land
will be pardoned for their error.”
Did you notice that the end of sickness
is related to our being pardoned
for our errors, or sins?
Clearly, that ties the fulfillment
to a spiritual healing.
However, our imperfect, sinful condition
is also the reason
that we get physically sick.
Therefore, in the new world,
on the basis of the healing power
of Jesus’ ransom sacrifice,
we will experience
a healing of our physical sicknesses.
Jehovah’s promise
that “no resident will say: ‘I am sick’”
will come true in the complete sense.
As you watch the following video,
think about the spiritual blessings
we enjoy now
and imagine what our lives
will be like in the future
when all our physical ailments
will be healed.
Clear instruction from Jehovah
draws us close to him
and maintains spiritual health.
While false teachings hold many
in the grip of spiritual darkness,
Jehovah offers true freedom.
The spiritual health we enjoy now
reminds us
that perfect physical and mental health
await us in Paradise.
Imagine waking every day
feeling clean,
healthy,
happy,
and full of the joy of life.
Jehovah promises:
“No resident will say: ‘I am sick.’”
How refreshing and heartwarming
to think of the global healing
that lies ahead!
We are confident
that this is going to happen.
Why?
Because we have already experienced
how Jehovah has healed us spiritually.
Keep in mind
the powerful statement from the video:
“The spiritual health we enjoy now
“reminds us that perfect physical
and mental health
await us in Paradise.”
We also learned from the video
that clear instruction from Jehovah
draws us close to him
and helps us to maintain
our spiritual health today.
What a blessing it is
to be taught by Jehovah!
We can show our appreciation
for this spiritual healing
by thanking Jehovah in prayer.
Psalm 40:5 mentions another way
we can thank the Great Healer
for all he has done and will do for us.
Let’s read it.
Psalm 40:5 says:
“How many things you have done,
O Jehovah my God,
“your wonderful works
and your thoughts toward us.
“None can compare to you;
“if I were to try to tell and speak of them,
they would be too numerous to recount!”
Our gratitude to Jehovah
will move us to tell others
about Jehovah’s wonderful works,
to speak of the many things he has done.
And we will never run out of good things
to say about our God.
Those who respond favorably
will come to know Jehovah
as their Great Healer
and enjoy his friendship forever.
Granted, today many of us are dealing
with serious health challenges.
But we do what we can to share with others
this good news about healing.
And we take delight in Jehovah’s promises,
which cannot fail.
When Jesus was on earth,
no sickness was beyond his ability to heal,
whether it was
physical, mental, or emotional.
In the new world,
such healings will take place
on a much grander scale
and the cures will be permanent.
Many of the great crowd
will go through the great tribulation
with serious, debilitating illnesses.
Our publications have said
that it seems reasonable
to expect that shortly after the destruction
of Satan’s system of things,
miracles like those
that Jesus performed while on earth
will no doubt take place on a global scale.
That will allow all survivors
of the great tribulation
to have a satisfying share
in transforming this earth
into a beautiful paradise.
And by the end of Jesus’ Thousand Year Reign,
they will reach the very fullness
of perfect human life.
As we enjoy the rich blessings
of our spiritual paradise now,
let’s keep in mind
that these spiritual blessings
are evidence that all the promises
of the Great Healer will come true.
We will forever take delight
in the complete fulfillment
of Jehovah’s promise
that “no resident will say: ‘I am sick.’”
Brother Gerrit Lösch,
a member of the Governing Body,
will now present
the final talk of this symposium,
“Take Delight in God’s Promises of Peace
—‘He Will Swallow Up Death Forever.’”
How wonderful and impressive
to realize that Jehovah promises
to raise people from the dead
and to end death permanently!
I invite you to read with me
that comforting promise
found in Isaiah chapter 25.
Regarding our God, Jehovah,
Isaiah 25:7, 8 says:
“He will do away with the shroud
“that is enveloping all the peoples
“and the covering that is woven
“over all the nations.
“He will swallow up death forever,
“and the Sovereign Lord Jehovah
will wipe away the tears from all faces.”
The Watchtower
of September 15, 2014,
page 25, said:
“Fittingly, the Bible refers
to inherited sin and death
“as ‘the shroud
that is enveloping all the peoples
“and the covering
that is woven over all the nations.’
“This suffocating covering, or shroud,
“this intricate webwork of condemnation,
entraps all people.”
But how do we know that Jehovah
can resurrect the dead?
Because he already brought his people
back to life figuratively in the past.
In 537 before our Common Era,
Jehovah, in effect,
raised the nation of Israel from the dead,
restoring the people who were held captive
in Babylon for 70 years to their homeland
and reestablishing pure worship.
In 1919,
Jehovah freed his modern-day people
from Babylon the Great,
the world empire of false religion,
revitalizing them for renewed activity.
Isaiah 26:19 prophesied this:
“Your dead will live.
“My corpses will rise up.
“Awake and shout joyfully,
“you residents in the dust!
“For your dew is as the dew
“of the morning, and the earth will let those
powerless in death come to life.”
When were God’s people held captive
by Babylon the Great?
That spiritual captivity lasted
from the second century
of our Common Era to 1919,
when anointed Christians were gathered
into the restored congregation.
God’s people were tested and refined
during the years following the establishment
of God’s Kingdom in the heavens in 1914.
Then, in 1919, Jesus appointed
“the faithful and discreet slave”
over God’s cleansed people
to give them spiritual
“food at the proper time.”
This was the year that God’s people
started to return
to their God-given spiritual estate.
It was also the time when they
were released from symbolic captivity
to Babylon the Great.
How happy we can be, though,
that after God’s people experienced
centuries of spiritual oppression,
we are living in the time when
“those having insight
will shine . . . brightly”
and many will “cleanse themselves”
as they “will be refined”!
We as God’s people
not only experience a spiritual restoration
and a spiritual paradise
but also will see the fulfillment
of Isaiah 25:8
when God “[swallows] up death forever.”
Yes, Jehovah will end death forever.
What a thrilling promise of peace!
Who of us have not lost a loved one
to some disease,
perhaps even from COVID-19
or an accident or a disaster?
God here promises
that death will be no more,
which suggests that the children who
might be born then will not have to face
the prospect of growing up and then
getting old, ending in death.
In addition to Isaiah’s prophecy,
Revelation 21:4 clearly states
a similar thought.
There we read that “death will be no more.”
As you watch the following video,
think about what Jehovah has already done
to show his love for us
and what he will do for us in the future.
Jehovah fulfilled his word to the exiles.
He restored that ruined nation
as if bringing it back to life.
In 1919,
Jehovah did something similar.
He released his modern-day people
from spiritual captivity
and energized them to preach.
Just as Jehovah raised his people
from figurative death,
so will he reverse
the effects of literal death.
Indeed, God “will swallow up death forever.”
Imagine living longer than any tree
because “death will be no more.”
How we delight in the many things
Jehovah gives us!
Today, we are privileged
to be among the only group of people
who worship Jehovah
in the elevated way that he approves,
as prophesied in Isaiah 2:2.
And think about the overwhelming joy
we will feel when Jehovah
resurrects our loved ones!
Thank Jehovah
for our precious resurrection hope.
First Thessalonians 4:13 says:
“Moreover, brothers,
“we do not want you to be ignorant
“about those who are sleeping in death,
“so that you may not sorrow
as the rest do who have no hope.”
Meditate on it to strengthen
your faith and courage.
Why is it important for us to do so?
Because the threat of death
is a powerful weapon.
Those under Satan’s control
use it to force people to betray
their friends
or to give up their convictions.
But that threat is powerless against us.
We know that if our enemies kill us,
Jehovah will restore us to life.
We are convinced that nothing
they can do can sever
our attachment to Jehovah.
What remarkable wisdom
Jehovah has shown
by giving us the resurrection hope!
By means of it, he disarms Satan
of one of his most effective weapons
and at the same time arms us
with unbreakable courage.
Remember that death is temporary
and that the life Jehovah
offers each of us will last forever.
In this symposium,
we have learned how Jehovah
fulfilled his promises in the past,
how he is fulfilling them today,
and how he will fulfill them in the future.
As we have seen,
God’s promises of peace include:
(1) nutritious spiritual
and physical food for all,
(2) adequate housing and satisfying work,
(3) freedom from the risk of violence,
(4) perfect physical health,
and (5) the elimination of death.
With Jehovah as our God and best Friend,
we will ‘delight
in the abundance of peace forever.’
Thank you, brothers.
Few things bring more joy to our heart
than meditating on
what Jehovah is doing for us now
and what he will do in the near future.
We have so many rich blessings
to look forward to.
How fitting it is
that we keep our focus
on pleasing our loving heavenly Father!
Thus we invite you to sing song number 35,
entitled “‘Make Sure
of the More Important Things’”
—song number 35.