Welcome to the fifth session
of our “Pursue Peace”! Convention,
which corresponds to the Sunday
morning session on your program.
Our music-video presentation
is about to begin.
As you watch,
please notice how pursuing peace
with God brings great happiness.
Please enjoy the presentation!
Greetings, brothers and sisters!
The scripture theme
for this session and the next
is taken from the inspired words
found at Romans 15:13,
which says in part:
“May the God who gives hope
fill you with all joy and peace.”
We invite all to sing song number 101,
“Working Together in Unity.”
Again, that’s song number 101.
At times, specific challenges
can make it difficult
for servants of Jehovah to pursue peace.
What are these challenges,
and how can we overcome them?
These questions will be answered
in a seven-part symposium.
We will consider
how we can imitate the examples
of those who reaped peace
after first sowing it.
To begin, let’s give our attention
to Brother William Turner,
a helper to the Service Committee,
as he presents the talk
“How They Sowed and Reaped Peace
—Joseph and His Brothers.”
The Bible contains
many fundamental principles
that a Christian
can use every day to guide his life.
For example,
at Proverbs 13:20, we’re told
that if we ‘walk with wise persons,
we will become wise.’
Proverbs 28:20 states
that if ‘we’re faithful,
we will receive many blessings.’
Likely you have Bible principles
that you live by as well.
However, as it pertains to pursuing peace,
there is one essential principle
that must be followed.
Let’s find out what it is.
Turn with me, please, to Galatians chapter 6,
and let’s read the words
of Galatians chapter 6,
verses 7, 8.
Here we read:
“Do not be misled:
“God is not one to be mocked.
“For whatever a person is sowing,
“this he will also reap;
“because the one sowing
with a view to his flesh
“will reap corruption from his flesh,
“but the one sowing with a view to the spirit
will reap everlasting life from the spirit.”
So the principle:
We reap what we sow.
You might think of a farmer;
he knows that he must plant
what he hopes to reap.
He also knows that he will not
reap fruitage right away,
but he trusts the results
will come in due time.
It is similar with the quality of peace.
The only way for us to reap peace
is to sow it.
And as we put in the work to achieve it,
we trust that in due time
we will reap the benefits.
In this symposium, we will consider Bible
and modern-day accounts
of how Jehovah’s people,
despite particular challenges,
have reaped peace after first sowing it.
Now, one particular challenge
to gaining peace
is problems within the family.
Because of imperfection,
it’s not uncommon to have disagreements,
even tension, from time to time.
And family members may hurt one another
in various ways.
And usually such offenses are minor,
and peace can quickly be sown and reaped.
But what if the offense is more serious?
A family member says or does something
that hurts us deeply.
Well, even then,
it still may be possible
to sow and reap peace.
We can prove this
by considering the Bible account
of Joseph and his brothers.
Now, we’re familiar with the story.
Out of envy,
Joseph’s brothers sold him into slavery.
And this was by no means a minor offense.
It began with Joseph being led to Egypt.
Sometime later, he was falsely accused
and thrown into prison.
So for 13 years,
Joseph suffered mistreatment
when he had done nothing to deserve it.
Now, it could have been very easy
for Joseph to feel
that if he ever saw his brothers again,
the best option for peace
would be not to have any dealings
with them at all.
Perhaps we might feel the same way as well.
But Joseph didn’t do that.
In fact, after some years passed,
both Joseph and his brothers sowed peace.
Now, note how this was done.
Turn with me, please, to the 105th Psalm,
and note the 19th verse of Psalm 105.
It says: “Until the time
that his word proved true,
“the saying of Jehovah
is what refined him.”
Joseph trusted in Jehovah to refine him,
to shape his thinking and godly qualities.
He refused to become bitter.
In fact, how interesting it is to note
that there is nothing
in the Scriptures to indicate
that Joseph ever told anyone,
not even Pharaoh,
that his brothers were the ones
who kidnapped him and sold him as a slave.
And how about Joseph’s brothers?
Years after they had mistreated him,
they met Joseph in Egypt.
When Joseph tested them
by giving the youngest brother, Benjamin,
significantly more attention
than he gave the others,
he saw that his brothers had changed.
They had let go of envy.
They showed genuine concern for their brother
and for their father, Jacob.
Joseph realized
that his brothers were repentant,
and he forgave them.
And because Joseph and his brothers
were willing to take steps to sow peace,
they reaped the benefits
and eventually were able to enjoy
a harmonious relationship.
Well, how can the example
of Joseph and his brothers
help us today?
In the following dramatization,
notice how a family member sows peace.
And every morning
—and I mean every morning—
there’s Jeremy singing
at the top of his lungs.
OK, I wasn’t the only one.
No, but you were the loudest.
Spoken like a true big brother.
I was always impressed
with how close you two were.
Hmm.
Well, it wasn’t always that way.
No.
I mean, it started out that way.
Nick and I—we weren’t just brothers;
we were friends.
But then the family business
ran into trouble,
and what started
as a small disagreement just exploded.
You don’t even understand at all
how our business works!
Instead of criticizing,
could you just once . . .
Jeremy!
Do you have any idea
what this is going to cost us?
I didn’t have a choice.
You went behind my back!
What’s your problem?
You!
You’re the problem.
We tried to work it out.
But things just got worse.
It was like a door
had slammed shut between us.
On the outside,
I acted like everything was fine.
But inside, I couldn’t let it go.
I felt like a total hypocrite,
and that had to change.
I needed a lot of help from Jehovah
to let go
—to move on—
and make things right with Nick.
It took a long time
for the wounds to heal . . .
. . . and for us to trust each other
the way we used to.
But we did.
I’m so grateful that we made peace
before the world turned upside down.
So how can you and I
imitate Joseph and his brothers?
Let’s discuss three steps.
The first step is found at Ephesians 4:32.
Let’s read that
—Ephesian 4:32:
“But become kind to one another,
“tenderly compassionate,
freely forgiving one another
“just as God also by Christ
freely forgave you.”
So first, we must be ready to forgive.
If we let grievances and resentment build up
and develop in our hearts,
it becomes even more difficult
to be forgiving.
Did you note in the video that what started
as a small disagreement
between Nick and Jeremy exploded
into something much bigger?
Why?
Jeremy could not let go
of his resentment toward his brother.
We must work to treat others
in a forgiving way,
just as Jehovah treats us.
The second step:
Don’t dwell on the offense.
Proverbs 17:9 says:
“The one who keeps harping on a matter
separates close friends.”
And isn’t that how Jeremy described
the relationship with his brother?
It was a door slammed shut between them.
It wasn’t until steps were taken to sow peace
—having that open, honest communication
with each other;
spending time together;
working with each other in the ministry—
only then did things start to improve.
And did you notice?
Everything did not go back
to normal right away.
It took time to reap peace,
time for those wounds to heal,
time to regain lost trust.
So we can’t look for miracles,
but we should look for progress.
Like the farmer, trust that in due time
we will see results from our efforts.
And here’s where
the all-important third step comes in:
Ask Jehovah in prayer
to help us to let go of resentment.
Remember Psalm 105:19.
It was “the saying of Jehovah”
that helped refine Joseph
to develop the qualities needed
not to become bitter
and to let go of any resentment.
In the video, Jeremy acknowledged
that he needed Jehovah’s help
to let go and to move on.
And Jehovah can do the same for us.
It’s not easy when we go through situations
that threaten the peace of our family.
But if we live by this fundamental principle
—we reap what we sow—
then we can be assured
that with a forgiving spirit,
looking for opportunities to sow peace,
and beseeching Jehovah for his help
our efforts will be blessed
and, in due time, we and our family
can reap the benefits
and enjoy true peace.
Brother Ronald Curzan,
a helper to the Teaching Committee,
will now present
the next talk of this symposium,
“How They Sowed and Reaped Peace
—The Gibeonites.”
There is a battle
that has lasted for centuries
and continues down to our day.
It’s a battle of wills
—the will of disobedient humans
who fight against Jehovah’s will.
Rather than submitting
or surrendering their will
to do Jehovah’s will, most humans refuse
to make peace with him,
becoming peacebreakers.
On the other hand,
millions throughout the centuries
have humbly submitted to Jehovah’s will,
making his will their will.
They are known as peacemakers.
By sowing peace with Jehovah,
they have reaped the benefits of having
a close, personal friendship with him
and the wonderful hope of living forever
in a peaceful new world.
Even so, we must admit
that it can be difficult at times to accept
and then follow Jehovah’s direction
or direction that we may receive
from his organization,
especially if we don’t understand
the reasons behind the direction
or it’s not what we might prefer.
What is needed to sow and reap peace?
Humility.
Humility is defined as a “lowliness of mind,
freedom from pride or arrogance.”
A humble person is not self-willed,
but they actively look for ways to sow peace
with Jehovah and others.
He’s known as a peacemaker.
What is the result of humility
and sowing peace?
Notice what Proverbs 22:4 says:
“The result of humility
and the fear of Jehovah
“is [reaping, notice] riches
and glory and life.”
Yes, everlasting life.
The Bible contains many fine examples
of those who sowed and reaped peace
by humbly submitting to Jehovah’s will.
Let’s consider the example of the Gibeonites.
The Gibeonites
—weren’t they enemies of the Israelites?
Yes.
So how did they humbly sow and reap peace
with Jehovah and with his people?
As you recall,
after Joshua led the Israelites
across the Jordan River
into the Promised Land,
Jehovah directed them to remove
the pagan Canaanite nations
who dwelled there.
This included the Gibeonites.
The account at Joshua chapter 9
informs us that the Gibeonites
were plainly told
that it was Jehovah’s will
that the Canaanites be annihilated.
Israel’s stunning victories
over Jericho and Ai
made it very clear that Jehovah
was fighting for his people,
and the Gibeonites did not want to be next.
But what could they do
if this was Jehovah’s will?
Well, they devised an interesting plan.
They sent representatives to seek peace
with the Israelites and thereby with Jehovah.
According to verse 11, they were instructed:
“We will be your servants;
now make a covenant with us.”
So this is what they were
to say as representatives.
Verse 4 says that the Gibeonites
“acted shrewdly”
by trying to trick the Israelites
with their worn-out clothing and provisions,
pretending that they had traveled
from a very distant land
but were actually just 20 miles (30 km) away.
Did their plan work?
Despite their deception,
yes, their plan was successful.
In fact, in verse 15,
Joshua made a covenant of peace
with the Gibeonites.
Evidently, this was in harmony
with Jehovah’s will
and reflected their humility
and desire to seek peace
with Him and his people.
They demonstrated
their humility and submission
to Jehovah’s will
and his representative, Joshua,
by following whatever direction
they received.
In fact, notice the direction at verse 27;
it says: “Joshua made them gatherers of wood
and drawers of water for the assembly
and for Jehovah’s altar.”
Although the Gibeonite men
were likely skilled warriors,
they were happy and content
to do whatever work
they were given to support pure worship.
Humbly following direction
saved their lives and brought them peace.
How can we imitate the Gibeonites?
By bringing our lives into harmony
with Jehovah’s will.
For some, this may require
making big changes,
adjusting their thinking,
giving up harmful practices,
and avoiding bad associates.
We can also imitate the Gibeonites
by being willing
to perform whatever assignments we are given
to humbly support pure worship.
So the lesson is clear.
Sowing and reaping peace
requires humbly following direction.
This lesson is highlighted
in the following dramatization.
Notice the benefits of submitting
to Jehovah’s direction.
You see,
the pandemic lasted longer
than any of us expected,
and all the conflicting news reports
just added to the stress.
Then my sister lost her job
and had to move in with us.
So, yeah, it was me
and Kelly, Nicole, and Dad.
Twenty seconds, Son
—twenty seconds.
I’ll see you later.
Yeah.
Uh, where’s your mask?
Don’t worry.
Here, you can use this one.
I won’t get near anyone.
Gary.
Listen!
Nobody at the warehouse is wearing masks.
And do you know how many people
have actually gotten sick?
Zero.
So far.
You saw the last Governing Body update.
We can’t let down our guard.
Not now.
Dad, I get it.
OK?
Look, I think it’s great that the brothers
are trying to keep us safe.
But . . .
But what?
Don’t you think that they’re,
you know, overreacting?
But, of course, it wasn’t
the brothers who had the problem.
It was me.
A week later, I found out that a friend
in our service group
was in the hospital with COVID-19.
He was young, and he had been taking
all the right precautions.
I had really let my guard down.
Now is not the time
to slacken our hand when it comes to safety.
Don’t let your guard down.
Don’t think the virus
can’t affect you or your family.
I saw how the organization
was really trying to protect us
and how much my decisions
were affecting others,
including the people I love the most.
As the pandemic dragged on,
I learned the importance
of being humble and obedient.
Following Jehovah’s direction
didn’t just help us stay safe,
it brought us peace.
What timely lessons,
especially with all that we are facing today!
Like Gary, there are times
that we may need
to adjust our thinking on matters
and put aside our personal opinions
and preferences
so we can loyally
and humbly follow Jehovah’s direction
or whatever direction we receive
from his representatives,
“the faithful and discreet slave.”
Gary learned an important lesson:
Humbly following direction
doesn’t just help our family stay safe,
it brings us happiness and peace
—a vital lesson for us today.
What can help us
to humbly follow direction now
as well as in the future?
Note what the apostle Paul said
at Ephesians 5:17;
he says: “Stop being unreasonable,
“but keep perceiving
what the will of Jehovah is.”
The Bible clearly shows
God’s thinking on matters.
But what if it’s not so clear to us
or we struggle to fully grasp
how it applies to us personally
or in a given situation?
What did Paul advise?
He said: “Keep perceiving
what the will of Jehovah is.”
How can we do that?
Well, just as a miner keeps digging
deep below the surface of the ground
to find precious gems,
we must look beyond the surface
of what we read in the Bible.
This requires that we keep digging deep,
carefully searching for gems
in the form of Bible principles.
Then we must prayerfully meditate
on what we find.
Then Jehovah’s precious thoughts
will become our thoughts.
Perceiving Jehovah’s thinking on matters
will help us to avoid getting
into a battle of wills,
so we can follow His direction
or whatever direction we receive
from the Governing Body.
Like the Gibeonites, may we be peacemakers
by continuing to sow peace
with Jehovah and his people.
As we humbly make Jehovah’s will our will,
we will joyfully reap abundant peace forever.
Brother Kenneth Flodin,
a helper to the Teaching Committee,
will now consider
the next talk of this symposium,
“How They Sowed and Reaped Peace
—Gideon.”
The man Gideon is
the Bible example we will consider.
But what is the challenge
this talk intends to address?
Are you ready for this?
Differences between fellow Christians.
You might think: ‘No, how can that be?
‘Jesus said the identifying mark
of his disciples
would be the “love among [themselves],”
not the differences.’
And that is true.
In our Christian brotherhood,
we feel the love.
Love is prominent.
It is dominant.
But as individuals,
we are drenched in imperfection.
Differences will inevitably erupt.
James 3:2 doesn’t mince any words.
It says: “We all [all] stumble many times.”
Not constantly, not every day
—but it acknowledges
that we make mistakes many times.
A brother or sister
may say something to hurt us.
Or maybe we push their emotional button
with words,
or they push ours.
Usually, it’s not intentional.
Often it’s a misunderstanding.
We or they say something in good faith.
One thinks it appropriate;
the other does not.
Or possibly what we said or did
was perceived in a way
that we could not even have imagined.
But it happened, and now we must
sow peace in order to reap peace.
And when we plant seeds,
some germinate much faster than others.
In the opening talk of this symposium,
it acknowledged that a farmer trusts
he will see results in due time.
If we find ourselves
at odds with a fellow Christian,
the Bible example of Gideon
can help us to sow and reap peace.
Now, Gideon was at war with the Midianites,
and he asked his fellow worshippers,
the Ephraimites,
to help chase them down
—Judges chapter 8.
They had tremendous success.
We say, “Great.”
But after the battle,
the Ephraimites were offended.
They tried to pick a fight with Gideon.
They felt that Gideon
did not call them into battle soon enough.
Judges 8:1:
“Then the men of Ephraim said to him:
‘What have you done to us?
“Why did you not call us when you went
to fight against Midian?’
And they quarreled bitterly with him.”
Well, these are all armed, fighting men.
If this difference of opinion
was allowed to escalate,
it could get out of hand very quickly.
In fact, in this case,
hand-to-hand combat might have ensued.
Instead, though,
how did Gideon sow peace with words?
Let’s read verses 2 and 3:
“He [Gideon] said to them:
“‘What have I done compared with you?
“‘Are not the gleanings of Ephraim
better than the grape harvest of Abiezer?
“‘It was into your hand that God
gave Midian’s princes Oreb and Zeeb,
“and what have I done compared with you?’
“[and notice]
When he spoke this way, they calmed down.”
Now, in this case,
the germination period was very short.
Gideon sowed peace with well-chosen words,
and he reaped peace in one conversation.
Now, in the following dramatization,
notice how a brother prevents the situation
from escalating into a confrontation.
And you know how Jehovah’s people are.
When there’s a need,
our brothers step up.
So even though we had
a lot of work to do back then,
we always had willing workers
—so many workers that some started to feel
like they were being overlooked.
Hey, Ray!
What’s up?
Hey, Matt,
I hear you’re organizing
the food distribution for our congregation.
Yeah, I’m trying my best.
Yeah, well, can I give you a hand?
My truck is all ready to go.
We actually just finished loading up
for the day, so I think we’re good.
But, wow, yeah,
thank you very much for offering.
OK.
When’s the next run?
You know what, Ray?
We’re about to pull out right now.
Is it OK if I call you back?
Yeah.
Yeah, sure.
Ray was such a hard worker,
more than most of us even realized.
He put his heart into every assignment.
Who was that?
But when I told him
we already had all the help we needed,
it didn’t go the way I hoped.
Ray, I think you’re muted.
So, what you’re saying is
you don’t think I’m qualified to help out.
No, no, we just—
We know how hard
you’re working caring for your mom.
We didn’t want to . . .
Isn’t Paul Thompson on your crew?
Yeah, but—
And Oliver Kagan?
Oliver’s my assistant, yes, but—
So how does this work, Matt?
I mean, you just use your friends,
and you shut the rest of us out.
Don’t you think I notice
how you brothers ignore me?
Ray, I owe you an apology.
I’m so sorry.
I should’ve spoken with you
about this right from the start.
You’re working so hard
taking care of your mom.
The last thing we wanted to do
was make things harder for you.
But even more than that,
we didn’t want to have to ask you
to do something
that would put you
or your mother at higher risk.
I know.
I worry about that too.
You know,
your mom
—we wouldn’t want anything to happen to her.
She’s one of our congregation treasures.
I know.
And you’re not so bad either.
Seriously, you’re such a good example.
Think how Jehovah must feel when he sees
all that you’re doing
for us and for your mom.
Thank you.
That means a lot to me.
If something comes up
that I can help with then
—even just a little—
and I can do it from home—
Well, that’s a good point.
Maybe I can get your thoughts
on something, if that’s OK?
Two good brothers
—but because of imperfection,
they were both looking
at the exact same situation
from two different perspectives.
Matt was well-intended
in what he did for Ray.
He realized he was caring
for his ailing mother;
he was trying to protect him.
But Ray was offended.
He even accused Matt of showing favoritism
to his friends and ignoring others.
Well, how did this calm down?
Well, first of all, thankfully,
Ray went directly to Matt
and expressed his feelings
between the two of them alone.
Well, how did that allow for a follow-up?
Well, Matt now had the opportunity
to absorb and understand Ray’s concerns.
What a blessing that was!
And so, what followed after that?
Well, you remember, when he grasped it,
Matt paused and apologized.
His words—like Gideon’s, well-spoken—
calmed Ray down.
It was a short germination period.
He sowed and reaped peace
in one conversation.
Well, how can we imitate Gideon
when there are future differences
with fellow worshippers?
Second Timothy 2:24
—(And you recall that when the men of Ephraim
confronted Gideon, they were confrontational.
They were upset;
they were rattling their sabers.)
but here, Paul, in effect,
summarizes for Christians Gideon’s demeanor.
Second Timothy 2:24:
“For a slave of the Lord
does not need to fight,
“[you see, with words or swords,
instead like Gideon, it says]
“but needs to be gentle toward all,
“qualified to teach, [and notice this]
showing restraint when wronged.”
That is not easy to do.
But “showing restraint when wronged”
is a means of sowing peace.
Now, if it’s just a minor offense,
we might ask ourselves,
‘Can I put up with this slight
to avoid a confrontation?’
But, of course, in the case with Ray,
he felt deeply hurt.
Matt realized the perspective was different.
But you remember, in hindsight,
Matt admitted,
‘I should have talked to you first.’
With those words, he planted seeds of peace.
Now, amazingly,
long before the first century,
Gideon manifested
what later became a Christian principle.
At Philippians 2:3, it says:
“With humility consider others
superior to you.”
Do you remember Gideon’s exact expression?
Twice he said:
“What have I done compared [to] you?”
His humility calmed
the Ephraimites down instantly.
So, what can we do?
Well, we can apologize
for our contribution to the difference,
even if the apology is done
on the other person’s terms.
We can pray for him.
We can give a sincere compliment;
do something kind for the person.
And if we have a discussion,
may our words be gracious
and the tone kindly.
Now, it would be nice if all the differences
between Christians
could have a short germination cycle.
But because of circumstances, personalities,
or the nature of the issue,
that’s not always possible.
But may we each
be determined to do our part to sow peace
and, like the farmer,
expect peace in due time.
And, oh,
how sweet restored peace truly is!
And now, Brother Robert Luccioni,
a helper to the Publishing Committee,
will give the next talk
of this symposium, entitled
“How They Sowed and Reaped Peace
—Abigail.”
Pursuing peace can be a challenge.
Because of our imperfections
and the complexities of life,
we have to work for peace,
even under normal conditions.
But pursuing peace
becomes a greater challenge
when it’s one-sided.
Difficulties arise in the family
and in the congregation
when one person pursues peace
but the other does not.
For example, in the congregation,
perhaps we have a friend
who has a problem with another friend
in the congregation
but does not do anything
to reconcile the situation,
or in the family, a Christian mate
may have difficulty pursuing peace
if his or her spouse
does not apply Bible principles.
Well, what do we do then?
Well, in those situations,
the Bible account of Abigail may be helpful.
I invite you to turn in your Bibles
to 1 Samuel chapter 25,
and here we’re introduced to Abigail
and her husband, Nabal.
And you notice here in verse 3,
Nabal is described as “harsh.”
In verse 25,
Abigail describes him as ‘senseless.’
In verse 17, his own worker
describes him as “worthless”
and says “no one can speak [with] him.”
Well, with a personality like that,
it’s not surprising
that he mistreats David’s young men.
And now David wants revenge.
How do you pursue peace
in a situation like that?
Well, what does Abigail do?
Well, think about it.
What she could have done.
See, Abigail could have done nothing.
It’s not hard to imagine that she had
a difficult life as well
living with this man.
She could have just stepped back
and let David come through
and do what he had in mind.
Or she could have gone out to David
and inflamed the situation,
maybe describing what a terrible man he is
and how he mistreats her as well.
See, either of these approaches
could have made her life easier,
but she didn’t do that.
Now, Abigail could not change
her husband’s ways,
but she did what she could
to defuse an escalating conflict.
In fact, notice her respectful,
well-chosen words.
Let’s go back to 1 Samuel 25,
and let’s read verses 27-31:
“Now let this gift that your servant girl
has brought to my lord
“be given to the young men
who are following my lord.
“Pardon, please, the transgression
of your servant girl,
“for Jehovah will without fail make
for my lord a lasting house,
“because my lord
is fighting the wars of Jehovah,
“and no evil has been found
in you all your days.
“When someone rises up to pursue you
and seeks your life,
“the life of my lord will be wrapped securely
“in the bag of life with Jehovah your God,
“but the lives of your enemies
“he will hurl away like stones from a sling.
“And when Jehovah has done for my lord
all the good things he has promised
“and he appoints you as leader over Israel,
“you will have no remorse
or regret in your heart
“for shedding blood without cause
“and for letting the hand
of my lord take revenge.
“When Jehovah confers good upon my lord,
remember your servant girl.”
Do you notice what Abigail does?
She comes in with a gift,
she bows down to David,
she takes the blame
for the situation herself,
and she reasons with him
using godly principles.
Abigail’s actions calm David
and avert a calamity.
She pursued peace.
But to do that, she had to look
beyond her own feelings
and consider what was best
for Jehovah’s name.
And that is not always easy to do.
But what was the result?
Because she sowed peace—she pursued peace—
she reaped peace.
How can we benefit from Abigail’s example?
Why is it important to do so now?
Let’s look at the following dramatization.
And later on,
when things got even more intense,
that’s when our peace
was really put to the test.
Yeah, but, Tim, you always
found a way to keep us positive.
Well, I learned a lot about that
from my better half.
Amy has always had a way
of bringing people together.
For example, just before the pandemic,
there were these two pioneer sisters
in our congregation.
Becky was energetic, industrious,
and fearless in her ministry,
and Lena was experienced, self-sacrificing,
and such a good Bible teacher.
But they didn’t exactly get along.
Are you ready to go?
Are you OK?
It’s just— It’s Becky.
She’s just such a phantom pioneer.
We never see her.
I’m sorry, but she just needs
to be more serious
about her ministry.
Well, she’s been doing
metro witnessing and . . .
I know, I know, and LDC too, right?
She does plumbing?
Concrete.
She does have a lot of energy!
Do you remember
when we used to be like that?
I don’t know that I was ever like Becky.
No, you weren’t.
You were Beckyer than Becky.
I couldn’t keep up with you
—those long service days
in your little red car.
That feels like a long time ago.
Yeah.
You know, Becky reminds me a lot of you
—I mean both of us—
twenty years ago.
She’s working so hard,
and she’s made
so many sacrifices
for the truth,
just like you have.
I think we should get together
—the three of us.
You should get to know her better.
The next week,
I had them both over to the house.
And the more those two
got to know each other,
the closer they became.
You know that proverb:
“The tongue of the wise is a healing”?
Amy taught me what that verse really means.
OK, everyone out!
When everything changed
and we suddenly
found ourselves locked up together,
I tried to show that same spirit
so that we could stay united.
And with Jehovah’s help,
we did.
Now, did you notice what our sister did
and did not do?
She could have done nothing.
She could have let Lena, her service partner,
cultivate those thoughts about Becky.
Or Amy could have poured fuel
on the situation,
maybe agreeing with Lena
or telling a few stories
about how Becky annoyed her as well.
But she did not do that.
See, Amy’s desire to sow peace
moved her to help Lena
see things from a different perspective.
And as a result, the congregation benefited
and reaped peace.
Notice how the apostle Paul explains
this approach that we should take
if you turn in your Bibles
to Romans 12:18
—Romans 12:18:
“If possible, as far as it depends on you,
be peaceable with all men.”
“As far as it depends on you”
—see, our congregations
and our families benefit
when we sow seeds of peace
before matters get out of hand.
It’s like seeing a small fire in our house.
What do we do?
Do we just ignore it—hope it goes away?
Do we fan the flames?
Do we put fuel on it?
No, we do something.
Why?
Because we know that if left unchecked,
that fire could destroy our home.
Well, it’s similar when we see problems
that develop
and peace being disrupted.
We do the same.
Why?
Because we know that if we don’t
do something and if it’s left unchecked,
that disturbance could destroy our family
and the congregation.
So the question is,
How do we sow seeds of peace?
Well, Abigail was a good example.
Did you notice what she did?
She considered how best
to approach the situation.
She was proactive.
She didn’t just hope
it would go away on its own.
She used respectful, soothing speech.
She was careful not to fan the flames
or add fuel to it
—all good steps we can take.
And we have other resources
to help us as well.
We can do research in the Bible
and in our publications
to see how others have sowed peace
in similar situations,
and we can also consult with the elders.
Now, we understand that this
is especially a challenge
if the situation is in the family,
as it was for Abigail.
That is not easy at all.
And in those situations,
try to focus on your mate’s good qualities,
not on his or her irritating traits.
But with all of this,
we have to be realistic.
Remember what the apostle Paul said there
as recorded in verse 18.
He said “if possible,
as far as it depends on you.”
So Paul is acknowledging
that peace with others
may not always be possible.
So, what do we do?
We have to do the best that we can,
and then we leave the rest
in Jehovah’s hands.
So may we be determined
to develop the practice
of pursuing peace now.
Whether we’re in the congregation
or in the family,
we can be confident that if we sow peace,
we will reap peace,
even if others don’t respond.
How?
Well, we’ll have peace with Jehovah,
peace with ourselves,
and the knowledge
that we did the right thing.
Additionally, when in the future
a force for peace is vitally needed,
we will be prepared to provide it.
Brother William Malenfant,
a helper to the Teaching Committee,
will now consider
the next talk of this symposium,
“How They Sowed and Reaped Peace
—Mephibosheth.”
Inherited imperfection
—we don’t like it, but we all have it.
And since imperfection means
that everyone is less than perfect,
we are bound to be treated unfairly at times,
even by fellow Christians.
In rare cases, one might become
the victim of slander
or even fraud.
Consider with me an account about slander
that occurred in the nation of Israel
in the days of King David.
It’s about a man named Mephibosheth
who was slandered by a man named Ziba.
Examining the way
that Mephibosheth handled this matter
can be of real help to us to sow peace
and to reap peace.
Jonathan was Mephibosheth’s father,
and King Saul was his grandfather.
When Jonathan and Saul died,
King David gave to Mephibosheth
all the land of his grandfather.
David assigned Ziba as a servant
to take care of the land
that he had given to Mephibosheth.
Sometime later, a rebellion
in David’s household
forced him to flee from Jerusalem,
and Ziba went out to meet David.
When David asked Ziba about Mephibosheth
and why he didn’t come with Ziba
to show his support for David,
Ziba slandered Mephibosheth,
saying that he was seeking the kingship
for himself.
Sad to say, David believed the slander
and gave Mephibosheth’s land to Ziba.
Sometime later, Mephibosheth
met with King David
and explained why he didn’t show up
to travel with him.
He told David that Ziba had lied about him.
Upon hearing
Mephibosheth’s side of the story,
David now decided
that he and Ziba should share the land.
Instead of complaining or seeking vengeance,
Mephibosheth displayed
the spiritual qualities of a peacemaker,
and he was willing to be wronged.
He said to David, as recorded
at 2 Samuel chapter 19
and verse 30,
these words:
“At this Mephibosheth said to the king:
“‘Let him take it all,
“‘now that my lord the king
has come to his house in peace.’”
Yes, Mephibosheth was more concerned
about David’s kingship
than he was about himself.
In the following dramatization,
notice how a brother reacts
to a perceived injustice
and thereafter
how he sows peace with his brothers.
The first time we met David,
we were in chains!
I’d seen a lot of things
during my time as a guard,
but nothing like the peace that you all had.
Prison chains may be strong,
but we all had something much stronger.
But we had to work for that peace.
Right, Phil?
That’s right.
See, there was a misunderstanding
that got blown all out of proportion.
And I didn’t handle it the best.
The more I tried to defend myself,
the worse it became.
Brothers, there must be some mistake.
This isn’t true.
You know me!
I wasn’t prepared
for how far it would go.
There’s one more announcement.
Brother Philip Kim
is no longer serving as an elder.
Well, that brings our meeting to a close.
Now we can stand.
The next few months were a real struggle.
But when more details came to light,
I thought I’d be reappointed,
but I wasn’t.
Phil!
I couldn’t understand why.
Phil, come on . . .
I felt bitterness growing inside.
Phil, you know . . .
Everything became about me
—how I felt, what I deserved.
It was like a fog that stopped me
from seeing what Jehovah deserved,
and I really needed his help.
I found comfort
in accounts of Jehovah’s servants
who were either misunderstood or misjudged
but maintained their loyalty to Him.
They helped me realize that it’s a privilege
just to be in Jehovah’s organization.
Being at peace with my brothers
was more important
than any appointed position.
Without peace, I don’t know
how we could’ve managed what was to come.
Is your arthritis bad today?
Then I’ll be your secretary
just like Baruch was to Jeremiah.
I don’t know what I’d do without you.
The question now for all of us is,
How can we imitate the example
of Mephibosheth?
First of all, if you are the victim
of minor gossip or rude treatment by someone,
why not choose to let it pass
and not make a big issue of it?
Isn’t that what 1 Peter 4:8 advises?
First Peter 4:8 reads:
“Above all things,
have intense love for one another.”
And then it tells us what our love can do.
It says:
“Because love covers a multitude of sins.”
Yes, love covers sins and imperfections
if we are willing
to let love have its way.
But what if you are the victim
of a more serious injustice?
For example, the brother in the video
felt that he was a victim of injustice
when he was deleted as an elder.
He tried to clarify matters,
but since he didn’t get the response
he was hoping for,
he became very upset.
He lost his peace, and he caused others
to lose their peaceful relationship with him.
To regain his peace,
the brother dug into the Scriptures,
looking for examples he could benefit from.
And he prayerfully looked to Jehovah
to help him.
He could see the importance of self-control
and being guided by God’s spirit.
As a result, he was able
to be at peace with himself
and sow peace with his brothers.
Now, think for a moment
about the unfair decision David made
when he told Mephibosheth
that he and Ziba were to share the land.
Ziba was the cause of the problem,
not Mephibosheth.
However, Mephibosheth
displayed the qualities of a spiritual man
by not looking out for his own interests,
by being patient,
and by not seeking vengeance.
Read with me
at 2 Samuel chapter 19,
verse 25 through verse 28
—2 Samuel 19:25-28; it reads:
“When he came to Jerusalem
“[that is, Mephibosheth went to Jerusalem]
“to meet the king,
“the king said to him: ‘Why did you not go
with me, Mephibosheth?’
“To this he said:
“‘My lord the king, my servant tricked me.
“‘For your servant had said,
“‘“Let me get my donkey saddled
“‘so that I may ride on it
and go with the king,”
“‘for your servant is crippled.
“‘But he slandered your servant
to my lord the king.
“‘However, my lord the king
is like an angel of the true God,
“‘so do whatever seems good to you.
“‘All the household of my father
“‘could have been doomed to death
by my lord the king,
“‘and yet you placed your servant
among those eating at your table.
“‘So what right do I have
to cry out further to the king?’”
It’s truly remarkable.
Mephibosheth was grateful for what he had,
and he was seeking nothing more.
He enjoyed peace of mind and heart.
If a matter involving slander
or fraud arises today,
a Christian may choose to follow
Jesus’ instructions
at Matthew 18:15-17.
However, if for some reason,
following that procedure
does not fully resolve the matter,
he or she may choose to pursue it no further
and suffer a loss
rather than disturb the peace
of the congregation.
We can leave any unresolved issues
with Jehovah,
knowing that he sees what we do
and what others do,
and he will carry out justice
at the right time.
For our own benefit,
we really must try to let go of resentment.
When we do, we benefit ourselves.
When we forgive, we forgive others
and Jehovah forgives us.
Now, that doesn’t mean
that we minimize or excuse
the wrong conduct of fellow believers.
No.
But it does mean that we imitate Mephibosheth
by letting go of resentment
and pursuing peace.
We draw closer to Jehovah
by following the advice at Psalm 55:22:
“Throw your burden on Jehovah,
“and he will sustain you.
Never will he allow
the righteous one to fall.”
And as Romans 15:13 assures us,
Jehovah will “fill you with all joy and peace
by your trusting in him.”
Brother Joel Dellinger,
a helper to the Service Committee,
will now consider
the next talk of this symposium,
“How They Sowed and Reaped Peace
—Paul and Barnabas.”
What’s the next challenge we’ll discuss?
It’s a disagreement between elders.
If you’re an elder,
have you experienced that?
Were voices raised?
Did tempers flare?
Has a friendship
with a fellow elder cooled off?
Though we rightly expect
appointed brothers to be exemplary,
the fact is that all of us, including elders,
are still imperfect.
Differences in backgrounds,
personalities, experiences, and opinions
can lead to disagreements.
And a disagreement, if not resolved,
can disrupt our peace and that of others.
In this talk, we’ll consider
how two elders in the first century,
Paul and Barnabas, sowed and reaped peace.
Let’s see how their example
can help appointed men today,
including all of you dear elders,
to resolve a disagreement.
Please open your Bible with me
to Acts chapter 15
and read together verses 36 to 39.
In the reading, please note the problem
that arose between Paul and Barnabas.
That’s Acts chapter 15,
beginning in verse 36:
“After some days, Paul said to Barnabas:
“‘Let us now return and visit the brothers
in every one of the cities
“where we proclaimed the word of Jehovah,
to see how they are.’
“Barnabas was determined
to take along John, who was called Mark.
“Paul, however, was not in favor
of taking him along with them,
“seeing that he had departed
from them in Pamphylia
“and had not gone with them to the work.
“At this there was a sharp burst of anger,
“so that they separated from each other;
and Barnabas took Mark along
and sailed away to Cyprus.”
What was the problem?
These two elders strongly disagreed
about whether to take Mark with them
on their next missionary tour.
Of course, expressing
a difference of opinion is not always wrong.
Verse 7 of this same chapter
reports that the apostles
and older men in Jerusalem
had an “intense discussion”
that led to a good outcome.
But in this case, what resulted?
Please look again at verse 39.
It would be nice to read,
“At this Paul and Barnabas prayed to Jehovah
and came to an agreement.”
Sadly, though,
their discussion on this occasion
led to a “sharp burst of anger,
so that they separated.”
As a result, their friendship
was affected by a temporary strain.
Why do we say “temporary”?
Because in time,
it appears that Paul and Barnabas
put this matter behind them.
A short time later
in Paul’s letter to the Galatians,
he wrote about Barnabas
and the activity they had enjoyed together.
And Paul did not bring up their dispute.
Also, when Paul later wrote
to the Colossians and then to Timothy,
Paul spoke well of Mark.
In fact, in Paul’s last inspired letter,
the second to Timothy, he wrote this:
“Bring Mark along with you,
for he is helpful to me in the ministry.”
Yes, it seems that Paul and Barnabas
resolved their disagreement.
Now, let’s think about that, brothers.
What made that possible?
It’s this: Long before their disagreement,
they had shared together
in an exciting ministry.
For years, they were united
in what the Bible calls a “bond of peace.”
So even though their friendship
experienced strain,
the bond between them was strong
—strong enough to withstand the stress.
Well, let’s bring this to our day.
In the following dramatization,
please notice how an elder sows peace.
But you know, there is more to the story.
Phil didn’t know just
how tense things were between Tim and I.
No idea.
We never talked,
I mean really talked, about it
until it was too late.
Look!
We need to talk.
I think we need to seriously reconsider
Phil’s qualifications.
You know he’s not
the type of brother that . . .
Enough. Enough!
Enough about Phil.
I know he’s your friend, . . .
Friend?
. . . but the body agreed that he
no longer qualified to serve as an elder.
Friend?
He’s worked with us for years!
The body decided, unanimously,
that he should no longer serve.
Because you pushed them!
Excuse me?
It’s enough that we have
those outside the congregation
putting pressure on us;
we do not need more in here!
Do you seriously think . . .
The conversation
—the argument—
it was terrible.
We both said things we didn’t mean.
And after that,
we both handled the situation poorly.
We needed to make things right.
It wasn’t easy,
but we talked it out.
And we made peace with Jehovah’s help.
Can you imagine what it would have been like
in that cellblock if we hadn’t?
We finally told Phil the whole story
once we were all roommates.
Wow!
We’re ready!
Let’s go sing.
Like an island of calm
In dark stormy seas,
God’s people are living in peace.
With our eyes of faith,
We see beyond the clouds
And know that the storm soon will cease.
To the ends of the earth,
There’ll be peace at last
For all eternity.
From the valleys below . . .
Elders, here’s the question
before all of us now:
How can we imitate Paul and Barnabas?
First, as elders,
we must apply Scriptural counsel
in our dealings with one another.
In the video, we just saw how imperfection
got the better of Tim and Carl
—their body language,
choice of words, tone of voice.
As Tim put it,
‘The argument was terrible.’
But after the dispute,
what did those two elders
eventually do right?
They applied Scriptural counsel
and made peace.
For example, the divine counsel at James 3:17
reminds all of us
to be “peaceable [and] reasonable.”
The Watchtower  once suggested
how this could be applied to elders.
I quote: “Peacemakers
modestly express their thoughts
“and then respectfully listen
to those of others.
“Instead of insisting on his own way,
“a peacemaker will prayerfully consider
his brother’s viewpoint.
“If no Bible principle is violated,
“there is usually room
for varied points of view.
“Experienced overseers
know that preserving the peace
is more important
than getting one’s own way.”
What a beautiful thought!
So, what’s our first lesson?
If we as elders apply Scriptural counsel
in our dealings with one another,
we’ll never allow a difference of opinion
to become a cause for animosity.
Romans 12:10 outlines a second lesson.
Please open your Bible with me there.
Under inspiration, at Romans 12:10,
Paul wrote this:
“In brotherly love
“have tender affection for one another.
In showing honor to one another,
take the lead.”
Brothers (elders), now,
before life gets even more difficult,
this is what we need to do.
We need to strengthen
love and affection for one another.
We can do that by continuing to speak well
of our fellow elders
in public and in private,
by resisting the urge to talk negatively
to other elders
about any disagreements that arise,
and by regularly reflecting
on our brothers’ good qualities
and on our past service together.
In the video, weren’t we happy
to see how Tim and Carl
imitated Paul and Barnabas
and eventually reaped peace?
Though not easy,
they applied Scriptural counsel
and resolved their problem.
That warm smile on Carl’s face
when he showed up at Tim’s home,
the dessert (perhaps Tim’s favorite pie),
the heart-to-heart talk,
and their lasting friendship, even in prison,
showed that they maintained
their love and affection for each other.
Dear brothers, elders, may we do likewise.
Let’s settle disagreements
quickly and peacefully.
When we do so, we’ll reap not only peace,
but we’ll prove to be examples to the flock,
just like Paul and Barnabas.
Brother Stephen Lett,
a member of the Governing Body,
will now consider the final talk
of this symposium,
“How They Sowed and Reaped Peace
—Modern-Day Examples.”
How do many people react
when they see corruption and injustice?
They become incensed,
and they want to fix the problem.
How do they try to fix the problem?
By becoming involved
in political efforts or social movements
that claim to fight corruption and injustice.
In contrast,
why do Jehovah’s Witnesses not get involved
in political efforts or social movements?
The simple answer is
because they’ve learned from God’s Word
that the problems of this world
cannot be corrected.
Ecclesiastes 1:15 says:
“What is crooked cannot be made straight.”
Satan’s world around us
is like the trunk of a tree
that has grown so crooked, twisted, gnarled
that it cannot be made straight.
Jehovah’s Witnesses have learned
that it would be futile
to spend our time and energy
trying to correct what Jehovah tells us
cannot be corrected.
Additionally, Jehovah’s Witnesses
have learned how and where
real peace can be found even now.
In this regard,
let’s consider two modern-day examples
of ones who came
to acquire Jehovah’s thinking
on this matter.
Let’s talk about Egidio Nahakbria
and Frede Bruun.
Now, first Egidio
—born in a remote part of East Timor,
he experienced horrible
guerrilla warfare during his childhood.
Many of his neighbors
disappeared or were killed,
and he feared he would be next.
But some years later,
he moved to the capital city
and entered a university
where he met many other youths
with backgrounds similar to his.
He became part of a student group
that was trying to achieve social change
through political action.
Many political demonstrations were organized,
but most ended up in riots,
with many of his friends injured.
Some were even killed.
But then through a relative
who was studying with Jehovah’s Witnesses,
Egidio started to study.
Now, here’s what he said
as he started this study:
“As I studied the Bible,
“I began to feel that I had
never really known love.
“Despite my rough
appearance and disposition,
“the Witnesses treated me
with ‘fellow feeling’
and ‘brotherly affection.’”
Well, soon he was baptized,
became a regular pioneer,
and he was so happy because now he knew
he was truly helping people.
He ended his life story with these words:
“In the past,
I felt angry, unloved, and unlovable.
“But thanks to Jehovah,
at last I have found true love and peace!”
But now let’s talk about Frede.
From an early age,
he was very upset
by all the hatred, bloodshed,
and war he saw around him.
But especially was he disturbed
by religion’s role in all of this.
He observed that much
of this hatred, bloodshed, and war
was encouraged, supported,
or at least condoned by religion.
But in 1955, he attended
a convention of Jehovah’s Witnesses.
And after the convention,
he accepted a Bible study.
Now, during his studies,
he learned many wonderful things,
but something he learned
really motivated him.
He learned the identity
of the “great prostitute,”
Babylon the Great,
mentioned in Revelation chapters 17 and 18.
He learned that this prostitute
is the world empire of false religion.
Then he was really amazed
when he was shown Revelation 18:24,
which says:
“In her [the prostitute] was found the blood
of all those
who have been slaughtered on the earth.”
So he learned that the world’s religions
could never be a force
for international peace
because they take sides,
they’re divided,
and they go to war.
In contrast,
he saw that Jehovah’s Witnesses
are an international brotherhood
that truly practices what Jesus taught.
Frede’s progress was very fast.
He got baptized, started pioneering,
attended the 50th class of Gilead,
and has served many years in Guatemala,
helping people (as he was helped)
to find the true Source of peace.
But now we ask,
What are lessons we can learn
from Egidio and Frede?
Well, many,
but here are three big ones.
Number one:
We can never correct the corruption
and injustice of this world
by means of political efforts
or social movements.
That reminds me
of the illustration a brother used
about trying to get rid of a problem
with spiderwebs but being unable
to get rid of the spider.
You knock the webs down;
the spider builds them right back.
You knock them down;
it builds them back.
You never get rid of the problem.
Well, in this illustration,
Satan is the spider.
And since he’s the source
of corruption and injustice,
as long as he exists,
the problem will exist.
Little puny humans can’t get rid of Satan.
He’s superhuman,
so the solution must also be superhuman.
And that’s where God’s Kingdom comes in.
God’s Kingdom can and will
not only get rid of the webs
but the old spider Satan himself too.
Now here’s our second lesson:
We must remember that political activism
often leads to violence,
which is the opposite of peace.
We pursue peace
—don’t we?—
not conduct that often leads to violence.
Our third lesson:
Unlike the religions of this world,
we must promote peace with all people,
which definitely means
we refuse to get involved in any way
in the wars of Satan’s world.
That reminds me of an experience
a young brother had in the ministry.
A very emotional woman said to him:
“My son died
“for you to have the freedom you have.
Why won’t you fight for your country?”
Well, very calmly,
the young brother said:
“I’m very sorry
about the loss of your dear son.
“But one thing I can guarantee you
“is that it was not
one of Jehovah’s Witnesses
“who killed your son.
“Now, I don’t know if you can make
that guarantee about your religion,
but I can make that guarantee.”
Well, as it turned out,
she was Catholic,
so she definitely was unable
to make that guarantee.
So let’s remember
these three powerful lessons
that we have discussed.
But now we’d like to say
to you dear interested ones in attendance,
if you’re not yet one of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
we warmly invite you to please
study the Bible with us.
See for yourself how genuine love
is the best way of life
and is the best way to deal with the problems
that divide society today.
Jesus made it crystal clear
that the identifying mark
of true Christians is love.
At John 13:35, he said:
“By this all will know
that you are my disciples
—if you have love among yourselves.”
So dear interested ones,
see for yourself whether this genuine love
exists among Jehovah’s Witnesses.
But now we say to those of you
who are already Jehovah’s Witnesses,
please continue to cultivate and show
“love for the whole association of brothers.”
And doing so will require
that you remain strictly neutral
regarding the world’s political affairs
and other controversies,
just as our Leader remained neutral.
At John 17:14,
Jesus said of his disciples:
“They are no part of the world,
just as I am no part of the world.”
So during discussions in the ministry
or anywhere for that matter,
remain strictly neutral
on political topics.
Take no position regarding what laws
should be enacted,
repealed, or changed.
And don’t pressure others
to agree with your view.
But to succeed in this,
we must be careful not to allow
the media of this world
to manipulate our thinking.
News broadcasts are often presented
in a biased, opinionated way.
So we’ve got to be careful
not to adopt the bias of a commentator.
Only if we keep our thinking neutral
will we be able to keep
our speech and actions neutral also.
And remember, your good example
of showing love in Christian neutrality
may attract honest-hearted ones to the truth.
But now we ask,
What have we learned from this symposium?
Well, let’s highlight just one
valuable takeaway lesson
from each of our six parts.
The first part,
“Joseph and His Brothers”:
Our lesson is sow peace
by letting go of resentment.
The second part,
“The Gibeonites”:
Humbly submit to Jehovah’s will,
even if it differs from what you prefer.
The third part,
“Gideon”:
Prevent conflicts from escalating
by choosing words that calm,
reassure, and heal.
The fourth part,
“Abigail”:
Do what you can to promote peace,
and then leave matters with Jehovah.
The fifth part,
“Mephibosheth”:
Be willing to suffer loss
rather than disturb the peace
in the congregation.
And just another thought on this:
Let’s always remember
that defending Jehovah’s name and reputation
is far more important
than trying to defend
our own name and reputation.
Be willing to suffer loss
rather than disturb the peace
in the congregation.
The sixth part (this part),
“Modern-Day Examples”:
Serve the God of peace with his people,
and you will have peace.
Yes, during this symposium,
we’ve learned many valuable lessons
as to how we can sow peace.
Let’s all be determined to do so
with all our heart.
And what will be the final result?
For the answer,
let’s watch the final dramatization
of this symposium.
There’s one more story to tell.
I didn’t know it at the time,
but seeds of truth
were being planted in my heart.
You were all so different.
I couldn’t understand it.
You were prisoners, yes,
but you felt free
—truly free.
After you were released,
it became clear to me
that you have God’s blessing,
and I wanted to know why.
Phil helped me find the answer.
“And you will know the truth,
and the truth will set you free.”
Phil encouraged me to make the truth my own.
I had real trouble at first.
With all the turmoil going on at the time,
the idea of being peaceable
and waiting on God’s Kingdom
—it was hard to grasp.
But with Jehovah’s help
and the patience of these good people,
I was baptized
before the start of the great tribulation.
Joseph, during our time in prison,
the story of your life
—your time in prison
and how Jehovah was always with you—
became a real source of strength
for us.
I remember one day,
Carl said—
What did you say?
I said, “One day,
we’ll have a meal with Joseph,
and we’ll say ‘thank you.’”
And here we are!
Really, it’s I who should thank you.
Each and every one
of your stories
touches my heart.
You know a lot about my life,
but would it be all right
if I shared a few more stories?
Please!
We have so many questions.
Can you tell us about Egypt?
What was Pharaoh really like?
Dreams!
We have to talk about those dreams.
You do have many questions!
And I have many details to share.
And thanks to our God, Jehovah,
we have all the time we need.
What a touching video!
If we wholeheartedly sow peace,
we’ll ‘save ourselves
and those who listen to us.’
But what fundamental truth from our great God
have we discussed during this symposium?
It’s expressed at Galatians 6:7:
“For whatever a person is sowing,
this he will also reap.”
If we sow a tomato seed,
we will always get tomato plants.
Well, this unfailing fundamental truth
applies to peace.
If we sow peace,
we will always reap peace.
Although in some cases,
it may take some time
for the peace we sowed to bring good results.
But if we persevere in sowing peace,
we will reap peace of mind,
peace with others and, most important,
peace with Jehovah.
And we’ll reap the reward
of living forever in a world
where there will be an abundance of peace.
So let’s be determined to sow peace now
so that we can reap peace forever.
And if you think about it,
that’s a pretty good investment
of our time and effort, isn’t it?
Sow peace now
and reap peace forever.
Thank you, brothers,
for those practical talks.
May we all remember these useful examples
and sow peace now
so that we can reap peace eternally.
Let’s sing together song number 28,
“Gaining Jehovah’s Friendship.”
That’s song number 28.