On behalf of the Governing Body
and all of those working
at the World Headquarters
of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
it’s my pleasure to welcome you
to the 2022 “Pursue Peace”! Convention.
These convention segments,
which constitute special editions
of JW Broadcasting® this month and next,
have been translated
into more than 500 languages.
The scripture theme
for this session and the next
is Psalm 29:11:
“Jehovah will bless his people with peace.”
As you watch
the following music-video presentation,
notice the peace we find
by observing Jehovah’s creations,
reading his Word,
and sharing his message with others.
Please enjoy the presentation.
We are delighted you could join us
for the opening session
of the “Pursue Peace”! Convention
of Jehovah’s Witnesses!
Let’s sing together song number 86, entitled
“We Must Be Taught.”
That’s song number 86.
What kind of peace does God give,
and to whom does he give it?
Brother Stephen Lett, a member
of the Governing Body of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
will answer these questions
in the opening talk of our program.
Please pay close attention
as he develops the theme
“Jehovah Is ‘the God Who Gives Peace.’”
It is my great pleasure
to warmly welcome all of you
and to say, “Shalom.”
Why is saying that appropriate?
Well, shalom  is the Hebrew word for “peace,”
and it occurs over 200 times in the Bible.
When it’s used as a greeting
(just as I used it),
it means: “May you have peace.”
So, what could be a more appropriate way
to greet all of you at the start
of this “Pursue Peace”!
Convention of Jehovah’s Witnesses!
We are very pleased that you’re with us,
and we assure you
that you will not be disappointed.
To the contrary, you’ll be glad you were able
to devote three days to learning
what the Bible says
about how to gain and maintain peace
in all areas of your life.
But now let’s begin
by talking about the Person
who has drawn us all together
for this convention—Jehovah.
And how we delight in talking
about our marvelous heavenly Father!
Philippians 4:9
calls Jehovah “the God of peace.”
Now, it’s true
that he possesses many qualities
—love, justice, wisdom, power—
but he also possesses the quality of peace.
If you think about it,
he is at peace with himself,
at peace with angels,
at peace with faithful humans.
Yes, he is “the God of peace.”
But now here’s a question:
Does Jehovah keep this peace to himself?
Well, let’s get the answer
at Romans chapter 15.
Romans chapter 15
and please let’s read verse 33:
“May the God who gives peace
be with all of you. Amen.”
So he generously gives this peace,
as we’ll be discussing.
In fact, he gives
“every good gift and every perfect present,”
according to James 1:17.
And one of his finest presents
is the gift of peace.
But now here’s another question:
What kind of peace does Jehovah give?
Well, many equate peace
with freedom from conflict
and strife in one’s life.
But the peace Jehovah gives
is a lot more than that.
The peace that only Jehovah can supply
brings in feelings of safety,
security, well-being.
This Jehovah-given peace
is described very nicely
in Philippians chapter 4.
Let’s go there.
Philippians chapter 4 beginning in verse 6:
“Do not be anxious over anything,
“but in everything by prayer and supplication
“along with thanksgiving,
“let your petitions be made known to God;
“and the peace of God
that surpasses all understanding
“will guard your hearts
and your mental powers
by means of Christ Jesus.”
So notice that Jehovah is saying:
“Do not be anxious over anything.”
Would Jehovah tell us to do something
that was impossible for us to do?
No.
But, obviously, he’s talking about not being
overly anxious.
Controlled anxiety
can actually be beneficial.
It can move us to show concern for others.
It can motivate us to work enthusiastically
to accomplish an assignment.
But now, what about excessive,
uncontrolled anxiety?
Well, that can lead to physical problems.
Depression can be crippling,
debilitating, enfeebling.
But now, how can we avoid
being overly anxious over anything?
The answer is given in the next words
of Philippians 4:6, 7.
After telling us not to be anxious,
Jehovah gives the antidote.
He basically tells us to pray,
supplicate, and petition him,
and we will get that “peace of God.”
But now, what does the scripture mean
when it says that this ‘peace of God
surpasses all understanding’?
Well, we could say
that it’s so amazing and so powerful
that we limited humans
cannot fully understand it.
It defies logic from a human standpoint.
Our hearts and minds may be filled
with so much worry, fear, anxiety
that we see no way out, but we beg Jehovah
for the peace that he can supply.
And then what happens?
Our minds and hearts
are amazingly filled with calmness,
security, tranquility.
Loraine, a young girl
whose mother was dying
of cancer, said this:
“I was in the room
when my mother took her last breath.
“I . . . asked Jehovah
to give me the strength
“to endure and to get through this.
I immediately felt the peace of God.”
But now, what is meant by the expression
“the peace of God . . .
will guard your hearts
and your mental powers”?
Well, the Greek word translated “guard”
is a military term
that evokes a mental picture
of soldiers
maintaining a day-and-night watch.
In the same way,
this peace of God
can act like a 24-hour guard
over our hearts and mental powers
—keeping them calm, secure, and tranquil.
Now, here’s a question:
What is the key ingredient
to our being able to receive
this miraculous peace of God?
The answer:
Having a close friendship with Jehovah.
The apostle Paul
experienced firsthand many times
that having inner peace depends,
not on circumstances,
but, rather, on a close,
personal relationship with Jehovah.
For example, on one occasion
because Paul and Silas boldly preached,
they had their garments ripped off of them.
They were beaten—many blows with rods.
They were thrown into the inner prison.
Their feet were fastened in stocks.
But in the middle of the night,
what did Paul and Silas begin to do?
They began to pray
and sing songs of praise to Jehovah.
In amazement,
all the other prisoners
were listening to them.
So obviously, their very,
very unfavorable circumstances
had not robbed them
of their precious peace of God.
So let’s learn
this valuable lesson from Paul and Silas.
Having the peace of God
is not dependent on our circumstances,
but it is dependent
on having a close,
personal relationship with Jehovah.
Thus far, we’ve discussed how Jehovah
is the God of peace who gives peace,
and we’ve talked
about what kind of peace he gives.
But now we ask,
To whom does Jehovah give peace?
The simple answer is,
Jehovah gives peace
to those who draw close to him
and want to follow his guidance.
So receiving peace from Jehovah starts
with living a clean life,
following Jehovah’s
righteous moral standards.
Many people in Satan’s world, as you know,
believe that God will accept them as they are
—that God in effect
will lower his standard to accommodate them.
Can you imagine such pride?
That would be like a pot
telling its maker, the potter,
how the pot must be used,
and the potter must accept this,
whether he likes it or not.
Well, we know
it doesn’t work that way, does it?
We have to come up
to Jehovah’s righteous standards.
Now, he’ll help us, but we do the changing
—certainly not Jehovah.
Interestingly, James 3:17
says that “the wisdom from above
“is first of all pure,
then peaceable.”
So if we want peace from Jehovah
that will result in peaceful lives,
we must be pure
according to Jehovah’s moral standards.
Isaiah 48:22 reads:
“‘There is no peace,’
says Jehovah, ‘for the wicked.’”
Or put another way,
those who wickedly set
their own moral standards
will receive no peace from Jehovah
and will not have peaceful lives.
But we work hard
to live by Jehovah’s standards.
Now, it’s true
that Jehovah does his part to help us,
but he does expect us to do our part.
We could say that his blessing on our effort
is somewhat like multiplication.
What do we mean?
Well, if we put forth no effort,
there’s nothing for Jehovah to multiply.
What is ten times zero?
Zero.
a hundred times zero?
a thousand times zero?
a million times zero?
We still have zero.
So if we don’t do anything,
Jehovah has nothing to multiply.
Galatians 5:22 tells us that peace
is an aspect
of “the fruitage of the [holy] spirit.”
So the holy spirit will help us
cultivate and demonstrate peace.
In fact, John 14:26
describes the holy spirit as a “helper.”
But that expression “helper”
doesn’t indicate
it will miraculously do the job for us
with no effort on our part.
To illustrate this if we can:
Imagine that you’re working very hard
to paint the outside of your house,
and a good friend comes to help you.
Now you’re painting together.
But then you decide,
‘I’ll just go back in the house,
and I’ll just take it easy.’
Well, how long
will your friend keep painting?
If he continued painting,
he’s no longer a helper;
he’s doing the job for you.
Luke 11:13 tells us that Jehovah
will “give holy spirit
to those asking him” for it.
So if we ask for holy spirit
and then do our very best
to work in harmony with that helper,
we will enjoy peace with God
and we will enjoy and promote harmony,
unity, and good relations with others.
And what a pleasure it is
to associate with those who display peace
—this important aspect
of the spirit’s fruitage!
When a sleeping baby
is suddenly awakened
in the middle of the night by a loud noise,
he becomes frightened
—doesn’t he?—
and he cries out for help.
But when a parent cuddles him
and soothes him with reassuring words,
he calms down immediately.
Well, David at Psalm 55:16-18
said that when he was troubled,
he ‘called out to God’
and that Jehovah
‘heard his voice’ and ‘gave him peace.’
Like David, when we’re in anguish,
we can supplicate our heavenly Father,
and he will soothe and restore our peace.
In fact, our loving Father
is eager to do this for us.
Open up to Jeremiah chapter 29,
and notice that he’s eager
to replace our anxiety
with the peace from him.
Jeremiah 29:11:
“‘For I well know the thoughts
that I am thinking toward you,’
“declares Jehovah,
“‘thoughts of peace, and not of calamity,
“‘to give you a future and a hope.
“‘And you will call me
and come and pray to me,
and I will listen to you.’”
Isn’t that beautiful?
Our God is ready, willing, and able
to replace our anxieties
with this amazing peace
that only he can give.
Well, we’ve now discussed
how Jehovah is the God of peace.
We’ve discussed who he gives the peace to
—to those who draw close to him
and earnestly seek peace from him.
But now let’s examine how each of us
can promote peace with others.
In the following video,
Brother Kenneth Cook of the Governing Body
will explain how this convention program
will help us to pursue peace.
On behalf of the Governing Body,
I can say that we really appreciate
your attending
this “Pursue Peace”! Convention.
Speaking of peace,
we love the serene setting
here at our world headquarters
on Blue Lake in New York State.
At times, the water is as smooth as a mirror.
We occasionally see eagles and hawks fly by.
And in the fall of the year
when the leaves change color,
the forest can look spectacular.
More important
than this tranquil setting, though,
is the abundant peace
that Jehovah has given to his organization.
We can say this because of the peace
and harmony that unite us
no matter what our nationality,
language, race, tribe,
or social background is.
This is truly spectacular,
especially when we consider
all the turmoil in the world
and how divided people are
politically, socially, and religiously.
However, we cannot take
our beautiful peace for granted;
it’s not maintained automatically.
Each of us personally must pursue peace
in order to have God’s approval.
Jehovah certainly wants his worshippers
to enjoy lasting peace.
That was true in ancient times.
God told Moses to have the priests in Israel
bless the people with very reassuring words.
Notice these words that we find
at Numbers 6:24-26,
and hear what the priests
were to say to the people:
“May Jehovah bless you and safeguard you.
“May Jehovah make his face shine upon you,
“and may he favor you.
“May Jehovah lift up his face toward you
and grant you peace.”
The next verse states:
“And they must place my name
“upon the people of Israel,
that I may bless them.”
Jehovah has placed his name on us too,
and he is richly blessing us.
Let’s consider what
this convention program is going to cover
so that we’ll know how we can continue
to enjoy God’s blessing of peace.
First, we’ll consider
how to be at peace with God.
Our greatest peace comes
from having
a personal relationship with Jehovah.
Making him our best Friend benefits us
and leads to peace
in every other aspect of our life.
How can we reach out
for a close relationship with God?
We need more
than a superficial knowledge of him.
We need to get to know Jehovah as a person
and admire his qualities and ways.
Then we can love what he loves
and hate what he hates.
During this program,
listen for details about Jehovah
that will draw you ever closer to him.
Second, we’ll consider
how to be at peace with others.
Our homes should be havens
for peace for our families.
This means more than the absence of arguing.
It involves putting the interests
of our family members ahead of our own.
As we’ll learn from this program,
that includes showing love
and respect to one another,
working as a team,
improving family communication,
and worshipping Jehovah together.
Third, we’ll consider
how to be at peace despite trials
and troublesome world conditions.
During this convention,
we’re going to tour the world to see how,
despite opposition, illness,
economic problems, and natural disasters,
our brothers really care for one another,
how they receive help
from Jehovah’s organization,
and how they continue
their spiritual activity.
No matter what may threaten
our lives or livelihood,
we can be confident
that Jehovah can help us get through it
and retain our peace of mind and heart.
Fourth, we’ll consider
how to enjoy peace eternally.
Once God’s Kingdom
has lifted mankind to perfection,
we’ll no longer have to pursue peace.
As Psalm 72:7 promises:
“The righteous will flourish,
and peace will abound
until the moon is no more.”
In other words, there will be peace forever.
This program will help us
to anticipate future blessings from Jehovah.
Can you see why “Pursue Peace!”
was well chosen
as the theme for this year’s convention?
To pursue something means
to chase it in order to capture it.
Because of the influence of Satan,
his wicked world, and our own imperfections,
peace is constantly trying to elude us.
Therefore, we have to chase after it
to capture it in our lives.
This convention program will help us do that.
May the God of peace
be with all of you now and forever!
That’s the heartfelt wish
of all of us on the Governing Body
because we love you dearly.
Please enjoy the entire convention program!
We warmly thank Brother Cook
for highlighting
some of the ways
this convention program
will help us to pursue peace.
But now let’s briefly preview
the convention program that is coming our way
that has been provided by the God of peace,
and you may want to follow along
by using your copy
of the convention program.
You’ll note that day one has the theme
“Jehovah will bless his people with peace.”
The first symposium will illustrate
how love for God, love for neighbor,
and love for God’s Word
lead to genuine peace.
This year’s dramatic Bible reading
is based on the life of Jacob.
And as you will see,
Jacob gives us an excellent example
as to how we can
“pursue the things
making for peace.”
Thereafter, we’ll have the talk
“The Result of True Righteousness
Will Be Peace,”
and we’ll see in that talk
how we can resist temptation.
Just as a lion devours prey
and assimilates it into his body,
Satan tries to get us
to succumb to temptations
so that he can devour us
and assimilate us into his world.
But during that talk,
we’ll learn how to reject his temptations.
Then in the second half of day one,
we’ll enjoy our second convention symposium,
“Take Delight in God’s Promises of Peace.”
We will be greatly heartened
by Jehovah’s promises of peace
found in the book of Isaiah.
For example, one of the talks has the theme
“The Wolf and the Lamb Will Feed Together.”
Today, we can’t even imagine
feeding a wolf and a lamb together.
If we tried such, it would likely result
in lamb chops for the wolf.
But Jehovah’s promise in Isaiah assures us
that peace will exist
between humans and animals
and between animals and other animals.
The third convention symposium
has a thought-provoking theme
“Follow the Road Map to Family Peace.”
We’ll learn how, despite challenges,
marriage mates, parents, and children
can successfully follow
that road map to family peace.
Then we’ll enjoy the talk
“Loyally Support the ‘Prince of Peace.’”
That talk will remind us
of the importance
of maintaining our neutrality
by not taking sides on political issues.
To conclude day one,
we’ll have the intriguing talk
“Do Not Be Misled by Imitation Peace!”
It will contrast the world’s so-called peace
with a genuine peace
that Jesus will give his followers.
But then on day two,
notice the theme
“Be found . . . spotless
and unblemished and in peace.”
The second day starts with a symposium
designed to invigorate us for our ministry
so that we can be ready
to share the good news of peace.
That will be followed by the talk
“Young People
—Choose a Path That Leads to Peace!”
And that talk will encourage
our dear young ones
to pursue the full-time ministry.
And we want to say to you dear young ones
that if you do this,
you will enjoy a happy life
and you will have no regrets.
Next, we will see a video
that shows how our brothers around the world
are continuing their spiritual activity
and are enjoying peace
despite difficult trials.
Then a highlight of the day
will be the baptism
of new disciples of Jesus.
In the baptism talk, the baptism candidates
will be encouraged
to “Go On Walking ‘in the Way of Peace.’”
And why?
Because this is truly the best way of life.
Two more symposiums
will use video dramatizations
to contrast traits of peace wreckers
with the qualities of peacemakers.
And what a stark contrast between the two
you’ll see in these symposiums!
It’s kind of like the contrast
between bitter and sweet.
Part 1 of this year’s Bible drama
will remind us of ancient examples
of God’s people who pursued peace,
and we’ll definitely be able
to relate to their examples
and relate it
to our current situation in life.
The day will conclude with showing us
how to “Safeguard
Our ‘Uniting Bond of Peace’!”
We’ll see how we can do so
by putting the application
of Bible principles
always ahead
of following local culture and traditions.
Now on day three, the theme is
“May the God who gives hope
fill you with all joy and peace.”
The opening symposium
will examine seven examples
of ones who sowed peace and reaped peace.
We will examine Joseph and his brothers,
the Gibeonites, Gideon, Abigail,
Mephibosheth, Paul and Barnabas,
and modern examples.
We truly hope that many accept our invitation
to hear the enlightening
public Bible discourse
entitled “Friendship With God
—How Possible?”
Now, if we think about it,
we’re not born as friends of God
because we’re born
as sinful offspring of Adam.
Actually, if you think about it,
we’re born as enemies of God.
Sometimes you’ll hear
people say of a little baby,
“Look at that little angel,”
but more accurate would be to say,
“Look at that little enemy of God.”
Now, of course, we love that little baby.
And it’s not hopeless
because our loving Creator
has made reconciliation with him
within the reach of everyone.
We can become a good friend of God.
And that close relationship with Jehovah
will become our most valuable possession.
But then after we enjoy
Part 2 of the Bible drama,
the concluding talk of this convention
will fill our hearts with a joyful prospect
that “Universal Peace Is Sure to Come!”
It’s guaranteed by the God “who cannot lie.”
Finally, we’ll join in singing
a beautiful new original song
and we’ll close with a prayer of praise
to Jehovah,
the Source of peace.
So, dear brothers and sisters,
there’s a brief synopsis
of our wonderful three-day convention
provided by the God of peace
that is coming our way.
And throughout,
the program will be enhanced
with dozens of videos,
and we’ll see our brothers
either in real-life settings
or dramatizations
that we’ll definitely be able to relate to.
In fact, the following video
is a little, or small, sampling of the videos
you will see during this convention.
Hey, everyone.
Guess who just walked in?
Olivia.
Today’s poll: Would she ever?
No, she would never; she’s an angel.
I wanted to go up to the girls
and smash their phones.
Neutral?
Ain’t no neutral.
You’re just a coward.
Take your trash.
What I was feeling back then
was just sadness,
never really peace.
Hello, everyone.
Haley from DeNure Design here.
Is there just a little bit of envy in there?
In June of 2018,
a huge group of armed men came to us.
They represented the ideals of my childhood.
Do you have any idea
what this is going to cost us?
I didn’t have a choice.
You went behind my back!
Where’s your mask?
Do you know how many people
have actually gotten sick?
Zero.
That’s what always happens.
When you’re just
about to lose all your strength,
Jehovah does that something for you.
I’m so grateful that we made peace
before the world turned upside down.
But here’s an important question
for all of us:
Will we prepare our heart
to receive God’s peace
during this convention?
Ezra 7:10 tells us
that ‘Ezra prepared his heart
to consult the Law of Jehovah
and to practice it,
and to teach it to the Israelites.’
Now, what was the result?
Verse 11 tells us
he became “an expert in the study
of the commandments of Jehovah.”
Well, in imitation of Ezra,
how can we prepare our heart
for what we’re going to take in
at this convention?
Well, for one thing (very important),
by prayer and meditation,
we can make sure that our heart is ready,
receptive to receive Jehovah’s instruction.
And we can also make sure that in our heart,
we are determined
to apply what Jehovah teaches us.
But then another thing we can do
is we can pay close attention
to the music-video presentations
that will be shown before every session
as the convention begins.
Now, these presentations
have been carefully crafted
to help prepare our heart for each session.
Much time, effort, and expense
has been expended in preparing
these beautiful presentations.
So please listen carefully
as the sounds and scenes
prepare your heart to accept
the spiritual instruction
that will follow.
Yes, may each of us be determined
to listen attentively
to what Jehovah is teaching us.
May we be determined to imitate the psalmist
who humbly stated at Psalm 85:8:
“I will listen
to what the true God Jehovah says,
for he will speak peace to his people.”
If we do, we will learn
how to pursue peace with all people
to the praise of Jehovah, the God of peace,
who blesses his people with peace.
Yes, we will be successful in pursuing peace
until we no longer have to pursue it.
Now, what do we mean?
Well, think about it.
Does Jehovah have to pursue peace?
Does he have to chase it
in an effort to try to catch it?
No.
Jehovah merely displays peace.
Well, in the new world,
what a wonderful time it will be
when we no longer have to pursue peace,
but like Jehovah,
we can merely display peace.
But right now, let’s be determined
to continue to pursue peace.
And may this wonderful convention
that is coming our way help us to do so!
Thank you, Brother Lett, for helping us
prepare our hearts
for the rest of the program.
We are ready for Jehovah to teach us
how to pursue peace.
How is peace related to love?
How can we show love?
And what blessings result when we do?
The first symposium of this convention
will answer those questions.
Brother Seth Hyatt,
a helper to the Service Committee
of the Governing Body,
will begin with the talk
“How Love Leads to Genuine Peace
—Love for God.”
What do you think?
Is there a connection, a relationship,
between love and peace?
And if so, what role does love play
in achieving genuine peace?
The Bible helps us to appreciate
that love is an essential element
in achieving genuine peace.
So we’re interested in showing love.
As students of the Bible, we know
that humans were created
in the image of God.
And as a result,
you and I have the ability to show love.
But we also know that we live in a world
that has a very distorted view
and definition of love.
That, combined with our own imperfection,
means that if we’re not careful,
our view of love can become distorted.
So how do we guard against that?
By allowing Jehovah to teach us how to love.
And when you think about it,
what better teacher could we have?
The Bible says that “God is love.”
That means that Jehovah, our Creator
—who knows us better than we know ourselves,
who embodies, who personifies love—
is willing to teach us how to love.
And how does he do that?
Well, by means of his Word, the Bible,
and by means of his own beautiful example.
As we get acquainted with Jehovah,
we learn what love really is.
And as we put that love to work,
as Jesus did,
then we’re in a position
to enjoy genuine peace.
In this symposium,
we’re going to explore how love for God,
love of neighbor,
and love for God’s Word, the Bible,
can lead to genuine peace.
First, let’s talk about love for God.
How important is that
if we want to enjoy genuine peace?
Well, Jesus provides some insight
in a statement he made
that’s recorded in our Bibles
at Matthew chapter 22.
Let’s look at it.
Matthew chapter 22,
and we’re going to read verse 37.
Now, to provide some context for these words,
Jesus has been asked a question by a man
who is well-versed in the Law.
“[What] is the greatest commandment
in the Law?”
Notice how Jesus responds:
“He said to him:
“‘You must love Jehovah your God
“‘with your whole heart
“‘and with your whole soul
“and with your whole mind.’
This is the greatest and first commandment.”
“You must love Jehovah your God”
—a command.
Love for Jehovah is essential.
It has to be
the most important relationship in our life.
More important than any human,
more important than any thing
—we want to love Jehovah.
To what extent?
Well, Jesus says: “with your whole heart.”
What does that involve?
The context of Jesus’ words
helps us to understand that he was talking
about a person’s feelings,
emotions, desires.
So does love for God involve our emotions?
Absolutely!
But it has to involve more
than a simple affection for God.
Why do we say that?
Well, what did Jesus say next?
“With your whole soul,”
that is, with your entire being.
We use everything we have
to praise Jehovah
and to prove our love for him.
But even more is involved.
Jesus concludes by saying:
“with your whole mind.”
So our intellectual faculties are involved.
We’re willing to take the time
to get to know Jehovah’s thinking
and make it our thinking.
We want to think the way Jehovah thinks.
We want to understand his purpose
and his requirements for us,
and we want to understand his personality.
Now, when we think about that kind of love,
it’s clear that it encompasses
our thoughts, our words, and our actions.
Nothing is left out.
And that kind of love
provides a basis for a friendship with God.
And that results in peace with God.
So there we see the progression.
Loving Jehovah with our whole heart,
soul, and mind
leads to peace with God.
And as we enjoy peace with God,
we can also enjoy inner peace
and peace with those around us.
Now, how does that work?
Well, our love for Jehovah
motivates us to imitate him,
and we cultivate the qualities
that Jehovah displays,
for example: patience,
kindness, mildness
—qualities that make us attractive to others,
and qualities that promote peace with others.
I’m sure you would agree
that we want to be at peace with God.
But sometimes our peace can be threatened.
We may experience pressure.
We may be the subject of some wrong,
some injustice, some evil
that threatens our peace.
And then the question is this:
Will we handle things in a way
that is pleasing to Jehovah
or will we become impatient
or try to take matters into our own hands?
In the following dramatization,
notice how a family draws strength
from a Bible account
that highlights love and respect
for Jehovah’s sovereignty.
Olivia!
Hurry, you’re going to be late for school!
Thank you.
OK, Mom. I’m going to preach.
See you.
Love you.
Bye, Mom. Love you.
Have a good day.
See you later, Mom.
Today’s poll: Would she ever?
She would never; she’s an angel.
I think it’s all a front.
You know she’s wild.
Oh, yeah.
Oh, she totally just saw us.
OK. I’m totally posting that.
Do it.
OK. It’s up.
Hey, everyone . . .
Did you just get that?
Yeah.
Look at that.
Hey, everyone . . .
That’s the craziest.
Oh, my goodness.
Hey, everyone, Brooke here.
And Amanda.
Guess who just walked in?
Olivia.
And there’s Jake.
Today’s poll: Would she ever?
No, she would never; she’s an angel.
I think it’s all an act.
You know she’s wild.
Oops, she saw us.
She saw us.
I don’t believe it.
What are you going to comment?
I have no idea.
I don’t even think she likes guys.
What if she’s into girls?
That’s true. Yeah.
Comments!
Everybody is getting it.
I bet she’s still a virgin.
Hey, can I see that?
Yeah, of course.
Here you go.
Enjoy Life Forever!
Now, how are you going to do that?
Well, that’s a very good question, actually.
Well, God promises . . .
No, no, no, not God, you!
What are you doing?
Me? Well, I try to help others . . .
Try?
Man, all you do
is stand next to your little cart
while the rest of us
stand up for your rights, bro.
Well, I’m actually neutral when it . . .
Neutral?
Ain’t no neutral. You’re just a coward.
Take your trash.
How did it go?
It was a tough day at the cart, but I’m OK.
Hey, everyone, Brooke here.
And Amanda.
Guess who just walked in?
Olivia.
Olivia,
what’s wrong?
Hey, everyone, Brooke here.
And Amanda.
Guess who just walked in?
Olivia.
And there’s Jake.
Today’s poll: Would she ever?
No, she would never; she’s an angel.
I think it’s all an act.
You know she’s wild.
Oops, she saw us.
I’m so sorry that happened to you.
You know,
it reminds me of a situation Paul was in.
I think it was at Acts chapter 16
and verse 23:
“After they had inflicted many blows on them,
“they threw them into prison
“and ordered the jailer
to guard them securely.
“Because he got such an order, he threw them
“into the inner prison
“and fastened their feet in the stocks.
“But about the middle of the night,
“Paul and Silas were praying
“and praising God with song,
and the prisoners were listening to them.”
What do you think made them want to sing?
They loved Jehovah.
And when they focused on that,
how do you think they felt?
I think
they felt some peace.
That’s right.
How about we dig a little bit deeper?
OK.
Well, what did you notice?
Gabe and Olivia are under pressure
—Olivia in the classroom,
Gabe at the witnessing cart.
How will they handle the pressure
in a way that preserves
their peace with Jehovah?
Well, it’s a good question.
And really, all of us
need to reflect on that question
when we’re under pressure.
We know that Jehovah’s way is the best way.
We’re convinced that his way of ruling
is the best way.
But when we’re subjected to pressure,
perhaps the victim of some injustice
or even of some evil,
we may be inclined
to take matters into our own hands.
And when we do,
it can jeopardize our peace.
So how do we demonstrate respect
for Jehovah’s sovereignty?
The inspired advice
in Romans chapter 12 can help.
Let’s look together at Romans chapter 12,
beginning in verse 17:
“Return evil for evil to no one.”
So this provides the context
for what follows.
We may suffer some evil.
“Return evil for evil to no one.
Take into consideration what is fine
from the viewpoint of all men.”
And then notice verse 18:
“If possible, as far as it depends
“on you,
be peaceable (be a peacemaker)
with all men.”
Now, these words
really heighten our appreciation
for Jehovah’s reasonableness.
Why do we say that?
Because Jehovah doesn’t ask us
to do something that we can’t do.
He doesn’t ask us to control others.
No,
to the extent “it depends on you.”
Jehovah asks that each of us
control ourselves,
our response to a situation,
and to be peacemakers.
And then an explanation, verse 19:
“Do not avenge yourselves, beloved,
but yield place to the wrath.”
Why?
“For it is written: ‘Vengeance is mine;
I will repay,’ says Jehovah.”
So the advice is this:
Be a peacemaker,
and leave wrath to God.
Let him determine
if and when and upon whom
vengeance will be brought.
It’s easy to say,
but is it always easy to do?
No.
The example of King David
can be very helpful to us.
Through no fault of his own,
David became the target
of King Saul’s murderous hatred.
And on several occasions,
Saul tried to kill David.
For several years David lived as a fugitive.
But there were opportunities during that time
for David to harm Saul, even to kill him.
He could have justified that in his mind.
But do you think had he done so
it would have threatened his peace
—his peace, especially, with Jehovah?
We know that it would.
So how did David respond?
On one occasion, he said to his men:
“It is unthinkable from Jehovah’s standpoint
“that I should do such a thing to my lord,
the anointed of Jehovah.”
What helped David?
Well, he saw a bigger picture
than David and Saul, didn’t he?
He saw a picture with David, Saul,
and Jehovah.
He knew that if Saul needed to be corrected,
Jehovah would do it in his time and way.
As a result, David was willing to be patient
and he preserved his peace
—his peace with God, his inner peace,
and his peace with those around him.
What a beautiful example!
We can be sure that if we demonstrate
our love for Jehovah
by respecting his sovereignty
and waiting on him,
we will enjoy peace as well.
Jehovah assures us
that he will bless his people
and he will bless us with peace.
So let us be determined to love Jehovah
with our whole heart, soul, and mind
and to demonstrate our love for Jehovah
by patiently waiting on him
and respecting his sovereignty
—his way of doing things.
If we do, we will enjoy
the incomparable peace of God.
Now, Brother Ralph Walls,
a helper to the Personnel Committee,
will present the next talk of this symposium,
“How Love Leads to Genuine Peace
—Love of Neighbor.”
Foretelling dominant traits
that would exist in the last days,
2 Timothy chapter 3 says
that “men will be lovers of themselves.”
Is it wrong for us to love ourselves?
No, it’s normal, even necessary,
to have a healthy love of oneself.
After all, Jesus said:
“You must love your neighbor as yourself.”
And we’ll talk more about that in a minute.
However, the love mentioned here
is distorted and selfish.
And because it prevents love of neighbor,
it becomes a barrier to peace.
Some Bible scholars suggest that Paul
put love of self at the top of his list
at 2 Timothy 3:1-5
because all the remaining
negative characteristics in the list
result from it.
And those traits too are a barrier to peace.
For example,
“not [being] open to any agreement”
mentioned at 2 Timothy 3:3,
often leads to “anger, wrath,
screaming, and abusive speech.”
Rather than bringing peace,
such a lack of self-control
“stirs up strife.”
On the other hand, love of neighbor
has the opposite effect.
It leads to genuine peace.
Please turn to Matthew chapter 22,
verse 36.
One of the Pharisees versed in the Law
tests Jesus:
“Teacher,
which is the greatest commandment
in the Law?”
Jesus responded with the words in verse 37
just considered at length
in the preceding talk:
“You must love Jehovah your God.”
But then, Jesus goes
beyond the original question
and quotes a second commandment.
Let’s read verse 39:
“The second, like it, is this:
‘You must love your neighbor as yourself.’”
Jesus is saying that the two commandments
—love of God and love of neighbor—
are linked.
Now, how exactly would you define “neighbor”?
Please turn to Luke chapter 10.
Notice how Jesus answered this very question:
“Who really is my neighbor?”
Jesus responds clearly
with his renowned illustration
of the neighborly Samaritan.
In Jesus’ day, the Jews disdained Samaritans.
Their attitude moved Jesus
to make a powerful point.
In his illustration,
Jesus said that the Samaritan
took extraordinary measures
to help a Jewish man.
The Jew had fallen victim to robbers,
and his own countrymen ignored him
—leaving him half-dead.
What Jesus said
must have stunned the audience.
Luke 10:33, 34 reads:
“But a certain Samaritan
“traveling the road came upon him,
“and at seeing him, he was moved with pity.
“So he approached him
and bandaged his wounds,
“pouring oil and wine on them.
“Then he mounted him on his own animal
and brought him to an inn
and took care of him.”
Jesus then asked a penetrating question
in verse 36:
“Who of these three
seems to you
to have made himself neighbor?”
His words recorded in verse 37
are also directed to you and to me:
“Go and do the same yourself.”
Yes, our neighbors include
not only our family members
and our Christian brothers and sisters
but all whom we encounter from day to day.
In other words, our love
extends to those who are not of our own race,
tribe, nationality, or religion.
How do we show that love?
Please turn with me to Romans chapter 13.
Because we love our neighbor,
we avoid conduct that disrupts peace.
Instead, we strive to apply
the inspired counsel
at Romans 13:8-10:
“Do not owe anything to anyone
except to love one another;
“for whoever loves his fellow man
has fulfilled the law.
“For the law code,
‘You must not commit adultery,
“you must not murder,
you must not steal, you must not covet,’
“and whatever other commandment there is,
“is summed up in this saying:
“‘You must love your neighbor as yourself.’
“Love does not work evil to one’s neighbor;
therefore, love is the law’s fulfillment.”
That means that our responsibility
is to treat others
in ways that promote peace.
When others treat us unkindly,
we endeavor to imitate Jesus.
When he was being insulted,
he did not return the insult.
When he was suffering,
he didn’t go threatening.
Imitating the Prince of Peace
and the God of peace
gives us inner peace.
In the following dramatization,
notice how a family benefits
from the apostle Paul’s example
of displaying love of neighbor,
even when provoked.
What are you going to do?
You’re just a coward.
Man, all you do
is stand next to your little cart.
You don’t do anything.
You’re just a coward.
You just stand next to your little cart.
Ain’t no neutral.
Stand up for your rights.
You’re just a coward.
Gabe,
what happened today?
It’s just that I’ve been yelled at
in service before, but
this time I wanted to—I don’t know.
I wanted to go up to the girls
and smash their phones.
I’m so glad that you didn’t.
Yeah, but
I feel guilty
because I was like—I was like so angry.
It’s OK.
Let’s keep reading.
We had left off in verse 26.
“Suddenly a great earthquake occurred,
“so that the foundations of the jail
were shaken.
“Moreover, all the doors
were instantly opened,
“and everyone’s bonds came loose.
“When the jailer woke up
and saw that the prison doors were open,
“he drew his sword
“and was about to kill himself,
“assuming that the prisoners had escaped.
“But Paul called out with a loud voice:
“‘Do not hurt yourself, for we are all here!’
“So he asked for lights and rushed in,
“and seized with trembling,
he fell down before Paul and Silas.”
Now, think about what the jailer
had done to Paul.
He could have hated him for it.
Yeah, he could have.
But I guess he saw the jailer’s pain
instead of just his own.
Yeah, Paul loved his neighbor.
He didn’t hold back
from trying to save his life.
Come on, man.
Hey, how do you have the nerve
to keep coming out here?
Look, you were right
about what you said.
No one should stand around
while other people suffer injustice.
So do something. Fight like we do.
This is my way of making a difference
—the only way that I know
the world can really change.
Come on, man, the Bible?
Look, I get what you’re thinking,
but let me show you just one scripture.
All right, one scripture.
So this is a verse in the Bible
that convinced me
of how I can make a difference.
It’s at Matthew 24:14.
Here it says:
“And this good news of the Kingdom
will be preached
“in all the inhabited earth
“for a witness to all the nations,
and then the end will come.”
In the dramatization, Paul could have reacted
in a negative way toward the jailer.
However, in spite of the way
he had been treated,
he displayed neighborly love.
And this had a powerful effect on the jailer
and brought praise to Jehovah.
Because we are imperfect,
we must work hard
at cultivating love for our neighbor.
This is illustrated in what happened
with the apostle Peter.
Prior to becoming a follower of Jesus,
he did not have fellowship
with non-Jewish people.
But after he became a Christian,
God taught him
that division between Jews and Gentiles
was not to continue,
and Peter got the point.
At Acts 10:34, 35,
Peter is quoted as saying:
“Now I truly understand
that God is not partial,
“but in every nation the man who fears him
and does what is right
is acceptable to him.”
Peter even stayed in the newly converted
Gentiles’ home for days.
And he continued the practice of eating
with non-Jewish Christians.
However, 13 years later
while in Syrian Antioch,
Peter suddenly stopped associating
with Gentile Christians.
Why?
He feared the reaction
of some Jewish Christians
who were slow to accept change.
This illustrates that prejudice
can be deeply rooted.
It takes constant effort
to rid ourselves of it.
But we must learn to view others impartially
as Jehovah does.
We want to treat others
as Jehovah treats them.
In his Sermon on the Mount, Jesus said:
“You heard that it was said:
“‘You must love your neighbor
and hate your enemy.’
“However, I say to you:
“Continue to love your enemies
and to pray for those who persecute you.”
Then, as recorded at Matthew chapter 5,
and verse 45,
he explains why we want to show
that type of love:
“So that you may prove yourselves
sons of your Father who is in the heavens,
“since he makes his sun rise
on both the wicked and the good
“and makes it rain on both the righteous
and the unrighteous.”
This love produced by holy spirit
is markedly different from the sort of love
that is common in the world.
It’s based on a higher principle.
Jesus said even sinners
will follow a policy of like for like.
But if we want to prove ourselves
sons of our “Father who is in the heavens,”
we must be different.
We welcome others
as God and Christ have welcomed us.
At Romans 15:7, the Bible says to us:
“Welcome one another,
just as Christ also welcomed you.”
The Greek word used there conveys the idea
of receiving someone kindly or hospitably
—such as into one’s home
or circle of friends.
Prejudice withers as love grows.
Remember that at one time,
we were all strangers, or foreigners,
not close to God.
But Jehovah drew us to him
with “cords of love.”
Christ welcomed us.
He opened the door, as it were,
so that we could become part of God’s family.
Since Jesus has kindly accepted us
as imperfect as we are,
it should be unthinkable for us
to reject anyone else.
Dear brothers and sisters,
divisions, prejudice, and hostility
will doubtless increase in the world
as we approach the end of this wicked system.
As servants of Jehovah, though,
we seek “the wisdom from above,”
which is impartial
and promotes peace.
We rejoice
as we forge friendships
with people from other lands,
accept cultural differences,
and possibly even learn
the languages of others.
When we do this,
peace flows “just like a river”
and justice “like the waves of the sea.”
We “work what is good toward all,
but especially [our brothers].”
Love of neighbor moves us
to make sacrifices in behalf of others
and to share the good news
at every opportunity.
Our Master, Jesus, said:
“This is my commandment,
that you love one another
just as I have loved you.”
What are the blessings
that come from love of neighbor?
Jesus answers that
at John chapter 15,
and we’ll read verses 8 through 10,
beginning with verse 8.
Number one:
“My father is glorified in this,
“that you keep bearing much fruit
and prove yourselves my disciples.”
The second blessing, verse 9:
“Just as the Father has loved me,
so I have loved you;
“remain in my love.
“If you observe my commandments,
“you will remain in my love,
“just as I have observed
the commandments of the Father
and remain in his love.”
Brother Robert Ciranko,
a helper to the Writing Committee,
will now present the final talk
of this symposium,
“How Love Leads to Genuine Peace
—Love for God’s Word.”
Can you imagine a collection
of some 40 million books?
They would fill more than 800 miles,
or 1,300 kilometers, of bookshelves?
And yet, that is what you can find
in what has been described
as the largest library in the world
—the Library of Congress
in Washington, D.C.,
in the United States.
Which book would you say
is the most worthwhile to read
among all of those millions of volumes?
We can let the apostle Paul
answer that question.
In his second letter to Timothy
at 2 Timothy 3:15,
he referred to “the holy writings,
which are able to make [us]
wise for salvation
through faith in Christ Jesus.”
He was referring, of course,
to God’s own written Word
that we know as the Bible.
The contents of this book can give us
the wisdom that we need to gain salvation,
and that makes it
the most worthwhile book on earth.
But how can a book have
such a profound effect on a person?
Well, when describing books
and their authors per se,
the secular writer Gilbert Highet once stated
that books are not “lumps of lifeless paper,
“but minds alive on the shelves.
“From each of them goes out
its own voice . . .
“So by taking down one of these volumes
and opening it,
“one can call into range
the voice of a man the author,
“far distant in time and space,
and hear him speaking to us,
mind to mind, heart to heart.”
When we take this book, the Bible,
down off the shelf and open it,
we are calling into range
the voice of its Author, Jehovah.
And is he speaking to us
mind to mind, heart to heart?
Indeed, he is.
For example, at Jeremiah 29:11,
Jehovah tells us:
“I well know the thoughts
that I am thinking toward you, . . .
“thoughts of peace, and not of calamity,
to give you a future and a hope.”
And at Proverbs 27:11, Jehovah tells us:
“Be wise . . . and make my heart rejoice,
so that I can make a reply
to him who taunts me.”
How grateful we are
that Jehovah has given us
his precious Word, the Bible,
that reveals his intimate thoughts
and feelings,
that draws us close to him,
and that teaches us
how to gain everlasting life!
Because we love Jehovah,
we also love and cherish
what he tells us
through the pages of his written Word.
And that is exactly how the psalmist felt
who wrote the 119th Psalm.
Please open your Bible to Psalm 119,
and find verse 161.
That’s Psalm 119:161.
In the latter part, it says:
“But my heart stands in awe of your words.”
Now see what more he wrote
in verses 167 and 168:
“I keep your reminders,
and I love them dearly.
“I observe your orders and your reminders,
for you are aware of all that I do.”
This Bible writer did not view
God’s orders and reminders
as just a list of cold, legalistic statutes.
And we can be sure
that he did not consider them
to be burdensome.
Instead, he knew that they formed the basis
for the best life possible.
And that is why he not only wanted
to learn God’s orders,
but he also desired to observe,
or obey, them.
The psalmist believed that God’s Word
is the one thing worth studying,
and that because of knowing
God’s orders and reminders,
we are far wiser than people
who know everything else
except God’s Word.
Now look at what more he wrote in verse 165:
“Abundant peace
belongs to those who love your law;
nothing can make them stumble.”
Herein lies a major reason
why we love God’s Word:
Abiding by it leads to genuine peace.
Everyone longs for peace in their life,
and through the pages of the Bible,
we learn how to attain it.
That is why we choose to live by God’s Word
even in the face of the trials
that arise in our life
—some of which may try to steal away
our peace of mind and heart.
And yet, Jehovah knows what we
are going through every day of our lives
and stands ready to help us.
If we love and obey Jehovah’s Word,
we will not be stumbled spiritually
by what someone else does or says
or by any other matter or situation in life.
But how does love for God’s Word
lead to such peace
and keep us from stumbling?
We know
that “all scripture is inspired of God,”
making the Bible the most reliable guide
for every aspect of life.
After all, his wisdom
is infinitely superior to our own.
Reading the Bible enables us
to look at matters
from God’s elevated point of view.
It is just as the prophet Isaiah wrote
at Isaiah 55:8, 9.
If you’d like to open to that, please
—Isaiah 55:8, 9.
He wrote: “‘For my thoughts
are not your thoughts,
“and your ways are not my ways,’
declares Jehovah.
“‘For as the heavens
are higher than the earth,
“‘so my ways are higher than your ways
and my thoughts than your thoughts.’”
Just imagine
—Jehovah’s thoughts and language
must be vastly superior to those of humans.
When he communicates with us,
as he does through the pages of the Bible,
he simplifies how he expresses his thoughts
so that we can understand them.
Then as we take in all that Jehovah says,
we can let his thinking guide our thinking.
Reading the Bible
can be likened to peering into a mirror
because its message
has the power to allow us
to see ourselves as we really are
and it shows us where adjustments
are needed
in our attitude and conduct.
Thus far in this symposium,
we have seen how this can actually work.
We have seen two dramatizations
of a widowed mother
using the Bible to help her teenage children
avoid being stumbled
by other young people
who had been harassing them.
Remember, her son, Gabe,
had been called a coward
by a couple of tough-looking youths
while he was engaged in public witnessing.
And her daughter, Olivia,
had been chided by other girls
for not being interested in dating
one of the guys in her class.
Their mother used what Jehovah inspired
the apostle Paul to write about
with his ordeal in prison
to show how he was able
to preserve his peace
in a very difficult situation.
And that, in turn, helped Olivia and Gabe
to safeguard their own peace.
Let’s see what more the mother finds
in the Bible to help Olivia
avoid being stumbled into conduct
that could rob her of peace.
Guess who just walked in?
Olivia.
And there’s Jake.
Would she ever?
You know she’s wild.
I don’t even think she likes guys.
What if she’s into girls?
I bet she’s still a virgin.
Olivia, what are you thinking?
I don’t—I don’t know how they could do that.
I don’t even follow them.
If this doesn’t stop,
I don’t know if I can . . .
You’re strong, OK.
You just can’t let them get to you.
It feels out of your control, doesn’t it?
Hey, I think we need another Bible example.
Remember when we studied
about the Shulammite girl?
Yeah, I remember.
And who was pressuring her?
Solomon.
But she wasn’t interested in him,
just like I’m not interested
in that boy Jake, so . . .
But it wasn’t just him;
there were the daughters of Jerusalem
in Solomon’s court.
They urged her to accept his attentions.
But do you remember what she said
in Song of Solomon chapter 2?
It says: “I put you under oath,
“O daughters of Jerusalem,
“by the gazelles and the does of the field:
“Do not try to awaken or arouse love in me
until it feels inclined.”
So despite all of the pressure,
who was really in control?
She was.
No one was going to push her
into something that she didn’t want to do.
She even said: “I am a wall.”
You have the same power.
And if you believe that,
it’ll change how you handle the pressure.
Now give me a hug.
Hey, guys, update on yesterday’s topic.
I guess she still needs a man.
She needs something.
I just posted it. Go like my video.
All they want is to see me give in.
Hey, guys, update on yesterday’s topic.
I guess she still needs . . .
Why would I give them the satisfaction?
My peace comes from doing the right thing.
Nobody can make me stumble.
“I am a wall.”
Olivia’s mother thought
of another inspired Bible example,
that of the Shulammite girl
who was being urged
by the young women in Solomon’s court
to accept his amorous attentions.
But despite the pressure,
the Shulammite girl remained in control
for no one was going to push her
into something that she did not want to do.
Olivia got the point
as she thought to herself:
‘My peace comes from doing the right thing.
Nobody can make me stumble. I am a wall.’
It’s obvious that the mother
had a real love for God’s Word, knew it well,
and calmly and skillfully used it
to guide the thinking of her children
to keep them from stumbling.
So many people these days
put God’s Word out of their mind
to prevent it from influencing their life.
But as the world’s morals decline,
we must stick loyally to God’s Word
to conform our conduct
to his pure and holy thinking
and strengthen our determination
to live by his standards.
That is just what the apostle Paul
urged us to do
at Romans 12:2.
If you would turn there, please
—Romans 12:2.
Paul wrote:
“And stop being molded
by this system of things,
“but be transformed
by making your mind over,
“so that you may prove to yourselves
the good and acceptable
and perfect will of God.”
God’s Word strengthens us
to resist conforming
to the corrupting practices of Satan’s world
and to suppress temptations
toward wrongdoing.
Now, as we prove to ourselves
that the will of God is good and perfect,
then we should also accept
that loyally obeying God
is the best way of living.
There is a direct connection
between heeding Scriptural teachings
and obeying or enjoying genuine peace.
However, for Jehovah’s Word
to have such power in our lives,
we need to read the Bible every day
and meditate on why its counsel
is beneficial.
That means reading it at a pace
that allows us to ponder
on what we are reading.
And doing this helps to fix in our minds
the portions
that are especially helpful to us.
When asked why he reads the Bible
every day,
one Christian replied:
“If I repeatedly pray to Jehovah
during the day
“and expect him to hear me,
“why shouldn’t I also listen to God
by reading his Word every day?
“If we want to be a good friend,
why would we do all the talking?”
He makes a very good point, doesn’t he?
By reading the Bible,
we are listening to Jehovah,
and that is how we get
his viewpoint on matters.
So do you allow God
to speak to you every day?
We can measure
how effective our Bible reading is
by the influence it has
on our attitude and conduct.
When our peace is disturbed,
we can look into the source of divine wisdom
for God’s guidance.
Speaking prophetically of anointed Christians
at Isaiah 54:13, the prophet wrote:
“All your sons will be taught by Jehovah,
and [their] peace . . . will be abundant.”
Now, those words apply in principle
to Christ’s other sheep as well.
Thankfully, when Christ’s anointed brothers,
“the faithful and discreet slave,”
prepare spiritual food for us,
such as this convention program,
they hold firmly to Jehovah’s Word
and they never water it down.
We always receive spiritual instruction
that upholds Jehovah’s high moral standards,
and we are blessed with abundant peace
when we accept Jehovah’s instruction.
Isaiah penned another prophecy
that is being fulfilled today,
and we find that at Isaiah 2:2-4.
He saw in a vision of the last days
people from all the nations
streaming to true worship.
And for what reason?
Isaiah wrote of Jehovah:
“He will instruct us about his ways,
and we will walk in his paths.”
And in what would this result?
So that “they will beat their swords
into plowshares
“and their spears into pruning shears.
“Nation will not lift up sword
against nation,
nor will they learn war anymore.”
In his goodness, Jehovah is willing
to teach us imperfect humans
how to achieve genuine,
abundant peace earth wide.
And he does that through the pages
of his own written Word.
What a privilege it is
to be taught by our God!
No matter what problem may threaten
the peace of our personal life,
our family, or our congregation,
we are confident that the solution
can be found in the Bible.
And as we have learned from this symposium,
our continued love for Jehovah,
for our neighbor, and for God’s Word
will lead to our enjoying everlasting peace
in God’s new world.
Thank you, brothers, for teaching us
how love motivates our pursuit of peace.
Each of us now has an opportunity
to praise Jehovah with song.
We will sing song number 24, entitled
“Come to Jehovah’s Mountain.”
That’s song number 24.