This convention program will be translated
into more than 450 languages.
This work is supported
by branch offices around the globe.
Each of us has
an opportunity to show appreciation
for the spiritual blessings
we have received in our own language.
One way we can do this
is by making voluntary gifts
in accord with our circumstances.
Donations can be made online
at donate.jw.org.
Whether young or old, we face tests of faith.
Changing circumstances
can bring new challenges.
How can we meet
each test with unwavering faith?
We invite you to put yourself in the scene
as you watch the drama
Daniel: A Lifetime of Faith—Part I.
My king.
General.
We’ve starved them out,
but Jehoiachin still refuses to meet.
Negotiations don’t concern me, General,
but your incompetence does.
Finish it,
or you’ll not find me as forgiving as the gods.
Yes, my king.
This is what Jehovah of armies says,
‘Because you did not obey my words,
‘all this land will be reduced to ruins,
‘and this land and its inhabitants
‘will have to serve the king of Babylon
for 70 years.’
Daniel!
Where have you been?
It’s almost sundown!
Sorry, Jeremiah was speaking today, and I, uh
—I stopped by the temple on the way home.
Well, we’re almost ready.
You were at the temple again today.
I was.
“To gaze upon the pleasantness of Jehovah
and to look with appreciation upon his temple.”
I have something for you
so you can always have Jehovah’s words with you.
Thank you, Papa.
What’s wrong?
What’s going to happen to us?
What always happens to Jehovah’s faithful servants.
Have no fear, Jehovah is our shield.
Dinner’s ready.
Did you see our old neighbor at all?
No, I didn’t see him at all today.
Speaking of strange,
I saw our neighbor Eli the other day.
Eli is always getting into trouble.
Let’s sing.
Son, pick a psalm.
“Jehovah is my light and my salvation.”
You always choose that one.
Hushim.
“Jehovah is my light
“and my salvation.
Whom should I fear?”
Daniel!
Stay and play?
I’ve got to go with Papa.
When you come back, do you want to play Noah’s ark?
Sure.
And who will you be?
I’ll be a lion.
Hmm.
Then I’ll be an elephant.
Jehoiachin has surrendered!
Household of Eber, tribe of Judah,
open up at once!
All of you outside! Now!
It’s happened. They’re here.
Gather your things.
We have to go.
Go?
Go where?
We don’t live here anymore.
Hushim, grab our bags.
I hate this place!
Let’s go inside.
Open up!
All four—outside!
Check the back room.
By the order of the king, you are coming with us.
Daniel, of the tribe of Judah—
You will receive training
in the house of the great King Nebuchadnezzar.
But this is my family.
Princes and nobles belong in the palace.
He’s not a prince; he’s just a boy.
Daniel!
Please, I will go if it’s a servant you seek.
No! I’m taking the boy.
Daniel!
Wait!
Can we say goodbye?
Make it quick.
Be strong, my son.
Jehovah is with you.
Daniel!
Mishael.
Have you seen anyone else?
You didn’t think we’d let you come here alone, did you?
Azariah!
Hananiah!
This is Chislon and Ahitub.
Nice to meet you.
Move along.
So where are we going?
The palace, I guess.
So like Joseph in Pharaoh’s house?
No, like Joseph in the dungeon.
Doesn’t seem so bad to me.
Wait!
Chislon, look!
If you don’t say something, I will.
Hello.
Hi.
Move!
Come back again sometime.
These are the Jewish boys that Ashpenaz summoned.
You have been chosen
because you are wise,
but you are lacking.
You will learn our writing
and our language.
You will be given new names,
and at the end of three years,
you will serve the great King Nebuchadnezzar.
Today,
you are foreigners
—tomorrow, the gods willing,
Babylonians.
Meshach.
You look like a Meshach.
Our new names sound like their gods.
New names, new language—
Soon they’ll want us to worship their gods.
Calm down.
My father had idols, and he worshipped Jehovah.
Did you see the same city I did?
It’s the center of the world.
We’ll even eat from the king’s table.
What do Babylonians eat?
His servants are given only the best.
We can’t eat from this food.
Why are you making a big deal out of this?
Because it’s unclean.
Is there a problem?
Our, uh, our God
doesn’t allow us to eat such foods.
You fear your God?
I do.
Well, I am afraid of my lord the king,
who has assigned your food and drink.
He insists on these selections
to maintain your strength and vitality.
What if he should see you
looking worse in appearance
than the other youths?
You would make me guilty before the king.
I must obey the king.
So must you
—all of you!
When dinner is served, I expect you to be hungry.
You don’t speak for us!
You’re right.
You can make your own choice.
Didn’t you hear him?
We don’t have a choice.
This is a new land with new laws.
So what if some of the food is unbled?
It’s just food!
But Jehovah commanded us not to eat blood.
That’s your interpretation.
“You must not eat . . . any blood at all.”
What’s to interpret in that?
Maybe we should all take a moment and pray.
Pray.
Here.
What’s the point?
Jehovah is in Israel.
We’re in Babylon now.
Don’t you believe that Jehovah is here too?
Jehovah said that we’re his witnesses.
What will people say about Jehovah
if we give in and break his laws?
Your meal is ready.
Did you hear me?
Thank you.
But if we eat those foods, we’ll disobey our God.
Do you want to starve?
No, of course not,
but He forbids us from eating blood
and food that he calls “unclean.”
Please, test your servants for ten days,
and let us be given some vegetables to eat
and water to drink.
Vegetables?
Just give us ten days.
And then deal with your servants
according to what you see.
Ten days.
Here you go, thanks to Jehovah.
You need to try this meat. It’s amazing!
Have you seen anything like this before?
Oh! Really!
Yes! Oh, wow!
Yes!
Ashpenaz has summoned you.
My lord, these young men are of royal . . .
I know who they are.
We’ve been watching you
—all of you.
You don’t bow to our idols,
you pray only to your God,
and you are not eating our foods.
They insisted that their God would not . . .
Somehow,
you look healthier than the others.
Continue giving them the diet they’ve requested.
And Belteshazzar,
your future is bright.
Don’t waste it.
Bring in the next group.
The total rations would be fifteen kurru,
two pānu,
and five sūtu.
Correct.
How much interest
may a merchant charge on money and grain?
It would be 40 percent, my lord.
Forty percent?
Have you learned only to be a thief
the past three years?
And you, Meshach?
The rate is 20 percent.
Very good.
Which star of Enlil is brightest
in the Urgula constellation?
Do you know?
It is the Lugal star.
Impressive.
There is a tower that is high
but, nonetheless, has no shade.
What is it?
Your ziggurat?
Hopeless.
You can solve the riddle?
It is sunlight, my lord.
Correct.
My wise men teach that the gods
are responsible for everything.
If that’s so,
why do the good suffer and the evil prosper?
No one has been able to answer . . .
As you say, O king,
‘the wise do not always have the food,
‘nor do the intelligent always have the riches,
‘nor do those with knowledge always have success,
‘because time and unexpected events
overtake them all.’
Who wrote those words?
Solomon.
Famed for his wisdom.
But its source was his God,
our God, Jehovah.
Take them away.
When should we return?
You won’t!
Go back to your families.
You’ve proven worthless.
Belteshazzar, no—not the four of you.
We have more to discuss.
I do not know your God,
but you’ve proven to be ten times better
than any priest or conjurer that I’ve met.
Ashpenaz will arrange
for you to serve in the palace with my wise men.
Maybe your gifts were wasted in Jerusalem,
but here they will be put to use.
The victory in Jerusalem is complete.
Our forces are now preparing to besiege Tyre.
They should remember what happened to Zedekiah.
The gods are with us!
Jerah,
what is it?
It’s about Jerusalem.
Where are you going?
To see my family.
This year, we’ve had to make do.
Daniel.
Come, eat.
What’s wrong?
It’s Jerusalem.
They tore down the walls;
they torched its towers.
Many died.
And they burned down Jehovah’s house!
Why didn’t our people listen?
Did they think Jehovah couldn’t see
what they were doing?
As long as our temple existed,
our people had hope.
As long as Jehovah exists,
we have hope.
But he’s rejected us
because of our unrighteousness.
He hasn’t
—not everyone.
Jehovah told Ezekiel
that in his eyes you
are as righteous as Noah
and Job.
He said that?
He did.
If Jehovah cares so much,
then why are we in exile?
Why can’t we go home?
Why can’t we be together?
You are home, Son.
I don’t have all the answers.
Stay close to Jehovah.
You will be blessed.
Call the wise men!
I had a dream,
and I’m agitated.
I need to know what I dreamed.
O king, may you live on forever.
Relate the dream to your servants.
We will tell the interpretation.
No!
If you don’t make the dream known to me
along with the interpretation,
you’ll be dismembered,
and your houses will be turned into public latrines.
But if you do tell me the dream
and the interpretation,
you will receive gifts and a reward
and great honor.
We’ve got to buy some time
so we can consult the spirits.
The scrolls will tell you what the dreams say.
We need to come up with a plan.
He wants us to tell him the dream!
Yes.
No one has ever asked this before.
Can we do it?
What do we do?
If you can buy us some time,
we can consult the spirits.
You’ve agreed to tell me something false
and deceitful until the situation changes.
Deceitful?
Deceitful!
There is not a man on earth
who can do what the king demands.
What the king is asking is difficult.
No one exists who could tell this to the king except
—except the gods.
Arioch,
seize them!
Down!
Kill them!
Call the wise men!
Hurry!
Go, go, go!
By the order of the king, round them up!
Jerah.
You’re in danger.
Why? What happened?
I didn’t hear everything,
but the wise men angered the king.
Everyone is to be executed by dawn.
Bring Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah here.
I’ll try to learn more.
Yes—Chaldean, Egyptian, Jewish
—all the wise men.
Arioch?
Belteshazzar, you shouldn’t be here.
Why is there such a harsh order from the king?
He had a dream,
and no one can tell him what it is.
Flee now!
If you escape before dawn, you might survive.
Tell me why I asked for them
and you haven’t brought them?
Why aren’t the gods talking to them?
I want them and all of their families brought here.
I want to look into the whites of their eyes
and ask them why.
Hang them without their skins!
Let the gods look down on their flesh,
and then throw their bodies in the Euphrates.
Ashpenaz.
What good are wise men without wisdom?
What are you doing here?
I need to speak with the king.
You need to go!
Please, let me speak with him!
My lord, this is Belteshazzar.
O king,
interpretations belong to my God, Jehovah.
He knows your dream and what it means.
Well, where is your God? Where?
I believe that he—
I know that he will reveal it to me.
Please, give me time.
We have until morning.
To do what?
To reveal the dream to the king.
Well, how much of the dream
has Jehovah revealed to you?
Well, nothing yet.
But Jehovah revealed
that he would interpret it, right?
Not exactly.
Daniel,
how do you know this is even going to happen?
Well, I can’t be sure.
You’d better be sure!
His name is at stake.
If he reveals the dream,
it proves that he’s the true God!
If?
What can we do to help?
Pray.
Pray that Jehovah have mercy on us.
O Jehovah,
surely you didn’t bring us here just to die.
What will people say?
We told them that you
are the God of the heavens,
the only God who can reveal secrets.
Please,
vindicate yourself.
Jerah!
I have found a man from the exiles of Judah
who can make known the interpretation to the king.
I know who he is.
Can you really make known to me
the dream that I saw
and its interpretation?
There is a God in the heavens
who is a Revealer of secrets,
and he has made known to King Nebuchadnezzar
what is to happen in the final part of the days.
This is your dream:
You saw an immense image.
That image was standing in front of you.
You yourself are the head of gold.
But after you another kingdom will rise,
inferior to you.
Then another kingdom,
a third one, of copper,
that will rule over the whole earth.
As for the fourth kingdom,
it will be strong like iron.
The kingdom will be divided.
And as the toes of the feet
were partly of iron and partly of clay,
so the kingdom will be partly strong
and partly fragile.
In the days of those kings,
the God of heaven
will set up a kingdom
that will never be destroyed.
And this kingdom
will not be passed on to any other people.
It will crush and put an end
to all these kingdoms.
And it alone will stand forever.
The dream is true,
and its interpretation is trustworthy.
Quick!
Bring a fine robe
and a necklace of gold.
Burn incense before him.
Truly your God is a God of gods
and a Lord of kings
and a Revealer of secrets.
May your God be honored
by the honor I give you.
You are now ruler over all the province of Babylon.
O king, these servants
also worship the God in the heavens.
May they too be appointed to administer the province?
Make the necessary arrangements.
You have proven far superior
than these so-called wise men.
I now appoint you their chief prefect.
Did you hear Nebuchadnezzar?
When he said, “Your God is a God of gods
and a Lord of kings.”
Jehovah answered your prayer.
Jehovah answered our prayers.
What’s going to happen next?
Can we go back to Jerusalem?
I don’t know what happens next,
but as long as we stay close to Jehovah . . .
He will always be with us
as long as we have faith in him.
There’s nothing in the stars
about kingdoms crushing kingdoms.
Of course not.
It’s a trick!
But how did he know the dream?
Amar-Utu!
Amar-Utu, what message from the gods?
I have examined a sheep’s liver.
Your future is bright.
The stars of Shabatu, the giant,
speak only of your grandeur.
And I’m the head of gold.
Jehovah said so.
Your dream revealed many good things.
But this Belteshazzar, he’s a Jew—
He’s a clever Jew, to be sure,
but he couldn’t interpret dreams
before he came to Babylon.
He first had to be educated here
and given a Babylonian name,
a name that honors our great god Bel.
Bel used this young captive
to reveal great things to you—
Bel,
not Jehovah, who you defeated in Jerusalem.
So the tree is my enemies.
Who is it after the seven times pass over?
Then it is you again, O great king.
You are fools.
At last—
Belteshazzar, chief of the magic-practicing priests,
all of the other wise men are unable
to make the interpretation known to me.
But you are able to do so.
Explain to me the visions I’ve seen in my dreams.
What did you dream?
I saw a tree in the midst of the earth,
and its height, it was enormous
—it was enormous.
And the tree grew and became strong,
and its top—
And its top reached the heavens,
reached the heavens,
and the tree grew and became strong.
. . . holy one . . .
Chop down the tree!
And I saw a watcher . . .
. . . with a banding of iron
and of copper.
So who’s the tree?
O my lord,
may the dream apply to those hating you
and its interpretation to your enemies.
The tree that you saw
that grew great and became strong,
whose top reached the heavens
and was visible to all the earth,
which had beautiful foliage, abundant fruit,
and food for all,
beneath which the beasts of the field would dwell
and on whose branches
the birds of the heavens would reside,
it is you, O king.
And the king saw a watcher, a holy one,
coming down from the heavens who was saying:
“Chop down the tree and destroy it,
“but leave the stump with its roots in the ground
“with a banding of iron and of copper.
“And let the dew of the heavens make it wet,
“and let its portion be
“with the beasts of the field
until seven times pass over it.”
This is the interpretation, O king;
it is the decree of the Most High.
You will be driven away from among men,
and your dwelling will be with the beasts of the field,
and you will be given vegetation to eat
just like bulls,
and you will become wet
with the dew of the heavens,
and seven times will pass over you
until you know
that the Most High is Ruler
in the kingdom of mankind
and that he grants it to whomever he wants.
But because they said to leave
the stump of the tree with its roots,
your kingdom will be yours again
after you come to know
that the heavens are ruling.
Turn away from your sins
by doing what is right
and from your iniquity
by showing mercy to the poor.
It may be that your prosperity will be extended.
Does Belteshazzar know when this will happen?
No.
But your wise men
doubt that his interpretation can be trusted.
Look at the facts:
Egypt’s gods told the Egyptians
that they would defeat us.
Yet, you destroyed them.
So why should the God of the Jews
be given any more credit?
Look at what you’ve done.
The gods are with you.
You have made Babylon
the greatest kingdom on earth.
Belteshazzar wants you to grovel like a slave
—you.
A strong king means a strong kingdom.
Let us continue with our discussion
of the stars of Enlil.
Now, the Lugal star is the brightest star
in the Urgula constellation.
The stars are reliable,
unlike the gods of defeated nations.
Go back to Jerusalem.
Oh, you could
if there was anything left of it.
Has Jehovah revealed anything new?
It’s been ten months
and still no sign of this supposed insanity.
I trust my God.
Yes, as we do when we read the stars.
But we still shape the message.
You will be held responsible for the words,
and when a wise man speaks lies, well . . .
I spoke only what Jehovah revealed.
Have you forgotten what happened
when some couldn’t interpret the dream image?
A death sentence followed.
And that was a flattering interpretation,
that the king was a head of gold.
This time, you’ve said he’ll go mad,
and nothing has happened.
It will happen.
Maybe, maybe not.
But your words are against the king.
It’s treason.
And no one can protect you from that.
Ten months.
Nothing has happened.
But your words are against the king.
Still no sign of this supposed insanity.
It’s treason.
And no one can protect you from that.
So you can always have Jehovah’s words with you.
“Instruct me in your way, O Jehovah.”
“Do not hand me over to my adversaries,
“for false witnesses have risen up against me,
“and they threaten me with violence.
“Where would I be if I did not have faith
“that I would see Jehovah’s goodness
in the land of the living?”
Please, test your servants for ten days.
Somehow, you look healthier than the others.
Continue giving them the diet they’ve requested.
I do not know your God,
but you’ve proven
to be ten times better than any priest
or conjurer I’ve met.
He had a dream,
and no one can tell him what it is.
Jehovah answered your prayer.
“Hope in Jehovah;
“be courageous and strong of heart.
Yes, hope in Jehovah.”
Prepare a sacrifice to Bel.
To the gods.
This city is the jewel of the world.
Look at the Ishtar Gate, the gardens,
the ziggurat so high
it reaches the gods themselves.
No one would question that.
It’s odd that only twelve months ago
one of your servants
dared to suggest that you’d go insane.
Is this not Babylon the Great
that I myself have built for the royal house
with my own strength and might
and for the glory of my majesty?
“To you it is being said,
“O King Nebuchadnezzar,
“‘The kingdom has gone away from you,
“‘and from mankind you are being driven away.
“‘With the beasts of the field your dwelling will be,
“‘and you will be given vegetation
“‘to eat just like bulls,
“‘and seven times will pass over you,
“‘until you know that the Most High
“‘is Ruler in the kingdom
“‘of mankind and that he grants it
to whomever he wants.’”
No! Stop! Stop! Stop!
Father!
When you and your wise men
have failed consistently,
how can you claim Daniel to be a fraud?
This was a trick.
Daniel conspired against your father.
A trick.
Then how did he make it happen?
Everything he has said has come true,
which is quite different from our history with you.
My father trusted you,
and I trusted you, and you were all wrong.
Either you failed or Marduk did.
Either way, . . .
Tell me:
Who is this God in the heavens, Jehovah?
What a thrilling drama!
And there’s much more
to learn from the life of Daniel.
We will enjoy Part II
during the final session of this convention.
Like Daniel, we encounter
some who oppose and misrepresent us.
How can we prevent
our faith from being undermined?
Please pay close attention
to Brother David Splane of the Governing Body
as he delivers the talk
“Put Up a Hard Fight for the Faith”!
“Put up a hard fight for the faith”!
Now, those are the words of Jude,
the half brother of Jesus,
and it’s important to consider them
in their context.
So let’s do that.
Please turn to Jude 3,
and then leave your Bibles open
because we’re going
to consider another verse in Jude,
and this will help us
to get the point that Jude was making.
At Jude 3,
he says:
“Beloved ones,
“although I was making
every effort to write you
“about the salvation we hold in common,
“I found it necessary to write you
to urge you to put up
a hard fight for the faith.”
Now, Jude himself
had been “[putting] up
a hard fight for the faith.”
Consider this:
Just three years earlier,
his own fleshly brother James
was stoned to death
at the order of High Priest Ananias.
That was an open attack on God’s people,
and it must have been
very painful to Jude and to others.
But here is something interesting:
Jude is not warning his brothers
about High Priest Ananias
or about persecution.
He has something else in mind,
a different type of attack,
and this is a sneaky one.
Let’s look at verse 4,
and we’ll see why he wrote his letter.
Notice that the very first words are
“my reason is.”
‘So this is what I have in mind
when I’m writing you brothers.’
“My reason is that certain men
have slipped in among you
who were long ago appointed
to this judgment by the Scriptures.”
So Jude is talking about false brothers
who are presenting a real danger
to the congregations
—in some ways,
a greater danger than outright persecution.
And did you notice what Jude said
about those false brothers?
They had “slipped in.”
They were sneaky.
Well, that was true back then,
and it’s true today, as we’ll see.
And, brothers, this is a very serious matter
that we’re considering today.
Think of this:
Was the Christian congregation
brought down by persecution
in the second and third centuries?
It wasn’t.
It was brought down by false brothers
and apostate teachings.
And so the Devil can use an outright attack.
He can use persecution
to try to batter the structure
of the Christian congregation.
But sometimes he uses rot from within,
a subtle means to attack us.
But whatever method he uses,
we have to fight.
Our faith is involved,
and our faith is worth fighting for.
It’s a gift from Jehovah.
We have to hold on to it.
It’s a product of his holy spirit.
So we have to put up
a hard fight for our faith.
So in this talk,
we’re not going to discuss persecution.
We’re going to discuss
two of the subtle means
Satan uses to weaken our faith:
apostasy
and negative reports
about Jehovah’s Witnesses in the media.
So first, let’s talk about apostasy,
and we’ll call it spiritual poison.
Now, think about poison.
What’s the best way to avoid being poisoned?
Well, we have to recognize poison
when we see it, and then avoid it.
And the same principle applies
to teachings that could destroy our faith.
And that’s not always easy.
No, not many of our brothers and sisters
would deliberately get involved
with apostates,
but it could happen without our realizing it.
We receive letters at times
from brothers and sisters
who are troubled by something
they saw on a web page,
an accusation, a rumor about the Society,
or about the organization.
And the problem is,
they had no idea
that apostates were behind it.
It’s tricky
because the apostates don’t advertise,
“You are now on an apostate web page.”
They often pose as sincere Witnesses
who just have questions or concerns.
And some who aren’t really apostates
can cause just as much trouble
as the apostates do
by their negative talk and criticism.
Brothers, we need to be on the alert.
This is serious.
Suppose that out of curiosity
you get into a discussion forum
with individuals
who claim to be Jehovah’s Witnesses.
Now, maybe they are, maybe they aren’t.
You don’t know.
You’ve never met them.
And someone starts asking questions:
“What did you think
of last month’s broadcast?
Did you really find it encouraging?”
or “Do you think the brothers
who write Watchtower  articles
“are living in the real world?
I wonder if they realize
just how hard it is out here.”
And then a few others join in
with their own negative comments.
Now, you don’t know
whether these individuals are apostates
or just brothers and sisters
who are in serious spiritual trouble.
But does it matter?
How does it make you feel?
When you leave the forum,
do you feel upbuilt,
determined to expand your ministry,
more convinced than ever that Jehovah
has an organization that you love
and that you’re delighted to be a part of?
Do you feel honored
to be a part of that organization?
Or does the experience leave you sad,
uneasy, uncomfortable?
Now, someone might say,
“I need to get involved in that forum
so that I can help those people.”
They shouldn’t be together.
Even if they aren’t apostates,
they’re not good for one another.
Staying in that forum to “help someone”
is like holding his hand
while he drinks poison
and then having some yourself
so that he doesn’t have to drink alone.
We need to follow the advice
recorded at Romans 16:17.
Now think about this imaginary forum
that we just described
in the light of Romans 16:17.
Remember,
there are all kinds of negative talk
flying around in this forum;
you don’t know who’s behind it.
And here’s what it says at Romans 16:17:
“Now I urge you, brothers,
to keep your eye
“on those who create divisions
“and causes for stumbling
“contrary to the teaching
that you have learned,
and avoid them.”
Now think about that forum.
Does it create divisions?
Yes.
Is it a cause for stumbling?
Could be.
Is it contrary to what we have learned?
Do we even have to answer that question?
Now, whether it’s intended or not,
the effect will be to weaken our faith.
So, what do we do?
What does Paul tell us to do
here at the end of verse 17?
He says: “Avoid them.”
Now, I’d like to say a kind word
to some who may be involved
in discussion forums.
You may like to use this medium
to blow off steam, so to speak.
Maybe there are
little things in the congregation
that are happening
that you wonder about
or decisions the elders have made
that you wonder about,
and so you write.
You get involved in the forum,
and you blow off steam,
and after that, you feel better.
But what about others in the forum?
How do they feel?
Wouldn’t you feel awful
if negative comments you made
were responsible
for someone leaving the truth?
I know you wouldn’t want that to happen.
So please, please,
be careful about what you say.
Now, another person might say:
“Well, I can see where those warnings
about apostates apply to so-and-so.
“He’s weak,
but don’t worry about me.
I’m spiritually strong.
I can handle it.”
That’s like a weight lifter thinking
that he can drink a vial of poison
and it won’t hurt him
because he’s so big and strong.
We are not so strong,
so spiritual, so intelligent
that we can’t be affected
by the poison of apostate ideas.
Now, when might we feel pressured
to read something
that the apostates have written?
Consider this scenario:
The unbelieving husband of your Bible student
sends his wife a link
to an apostate web page and says,
“Here, you better look at this
and see what you’re getting into.”
Well, your student is concerned,
and she wants you to take a look
and tell her what you think.
Well, that’s not an option.
Paul says: “Avoid them.”
That doesn’t mean reading apostate literature
or searching social media
to see what they’re saying about us.
So, what do you say to your student?
You might say something like this:
“I can imagine
that this is very upsetting for you,
“and you certainly do need to know
what you’re getting into.
“I have a suggestion.
“We have nothing to hide.
“When you’re at the meetings,
listen carefully
“to what the brothers are saying.
“Watch how we interact with one another.
“Take note
of how the organization is financed.
“Get to know the elders and their wives.
“Introduce yourself to the circuit overseer
and his wife when they come.
“Visit world headquarters or the branch.
“I’ll come with you.
I’ll help you.
“And I want you to get really acquainted
with the organization.
“And if you do,
I’m sure you’ll soon realize
that what these people
are saying about us isn’t true.”
Well, maybe you can think of a better answer,
but you get the idea.
Just a few drops of poison in a drink
are enough to cause serious harm.
And apostates
often mix a few truths with lies.
Do you remember Eliphaz,
one of Job’s false comforters?
Some of what he said was true.
Let’s turn to Job 5:13.
Job chapter 5 (I’ll give you a moment)
and verse 13.
See if what I read sounds familiar:
“He catches the wise in their own cunning,
so that the plans of the shrewd
are thwarted.”
“He catches the wise in their own cunning.”
Does that sound familiar?
Why, yes.
The apostle Paul said the very same thing
at 1 Corinthians 3:19.
In fact, in the marginal reference,
we see (in the little a  in the middle there)
1 Corinthians 3:19.
Paul may even have been quoting Eliphaz.
So that was a truth.
But how did Jehovah feel
about Eliphaz’s argument overall?
Let’s turn to Job 42:7
and see how Jehovah felt about it.
Job 42:7:
“After Jehovah had spoken these words to Job,
“Jehovah said to Eliphaz the Temanite:
“‘My anger burns against you
and your two companions,
“‘for you have not spoken
the truth about me
as my servant Job has.’”
A few grains of truth
were mixed in with falsehoods,
and at least some of what Eliphaz said
was inspired by the demons.
How do we know that?
He admitted it.
Notice Job 4:15-17.
I’ll give you a moment.
This is interesting.
At Job 4:15-17,
Eliphaz says:
“A spirit passed over my face;
“the hair of my flesh bristled.
“It then stood still,
but I did not recognize its appearance.”
Let’s stop there for a second.
“I did not recognize its appearance.”
So he didn’t know whom he was talking to,
just like someone in a discussion forum
may not know whom he is talking to.
Let’s continue; he says:
“A form was in front of my eyes;
there was a calm,
“and then I heard a voice:
“‘Can a mortal man
be more righteous than God?
Can a man
be cleaner than his own Maker?’”
Does it surprise you
that a demon would get involved
in the debate
between Job and the false comforters?
It shouldn’t.
This was no small debate.
It was a big issue.
Satan had challenged Jehovah
in the presence of all the angels
that no man
would keep his integrity under test.
That demon was using Eliphaz
to demoralize Job and weaken his faith.
This was something that Job had to fight for,
and Job fought back.
Apostates are more active in some places
than they are in others.
So if there’s a lot of apostate activity
in your area,
people in the territory may be listening
and they may challenge you
when you meet them in the ministry.
So how should you handle it?
Don’t try to argue with the apostates;
don’t read their comments.
Ask the elders
or other experienced publishers
for suggestions
on how to answer the householders.
Well, how poisonous are apostate teachings?
Let’s find out
as we watch the following video.
When I was in my 40’s, I was divorced,
I had three younger kids at home,
I was working three jobs,
and I had drifted away from the congregation.
I had an acquaintance who was telling me
that I was in a cult
and that I needed to look
at some information that he had.
When I was about 30 years old,
a fellow employee saw
that I was one of Jehovah’s Witnesses
and was trying to access jw.org.
He told me about someone
he knew in another country
who could prove to me
that Jehovah’s Witnesses
didn’t have the truth.
That made me curious,
and little by little, I was persuaded to look
at apostate material.
I was born and raised in the truth,
chose to dedicate myself to Jehovah
at the age of 16,
but I began to associate with people
who had either formerly been associated
with the truth
or were very loosely associated
with Jehovah and his organization,
and that’s really where the apostasy
began to take root.
As I was reading this literature,
I saw through it to an extent,
but when you’re drifting away,
you’re looking for a reason not to believe.
I began to feed my mind
with different philosophies, different ideas.
I even studied different religions.
And, you know, I told myself
that I was doing that academically,
but it started to influence the way
that I thought and felt about things.
Eventually, the elders reached out to me.
I was very combative with those brothers.
I even made the accusation
that Noah’s ark was
a fairy tale,
that it was part of mythology.
Those apostate doubts that I was reading
kept going deeper and deeper into my heart.
I stopped reading the publications,
I stopped going to the meetings,
and as a result,
my spiritual routine was dead.
So I thought I’d try to find truth elsewhere.
And I looked for something out there that was
in accord with what I knew the Bible taught.
But I couldn’t find anything.
One Sunday morning,
I rode by the Kingdom Hall,
and I said to myself,
‘Oh, they’re all in there
waiting for Armageddon.’
Immediately when I thought that thought,
I said to myself:
‘Well, at least they
feel good about themselves.
How do you feel?’
And the answer was I felt terrible.
Eventually, by skillful use of the Scriptures
and just reasoning with me,
the elders got me to realize
that I had been ‘carried off’
or that I had been ‘taken captive’
by human philosophy,
by the deceptions
and the empty reasoning of men.
I actually said a prayer;
I supplicated Jehovah
that he would really show me
the way to the truth.
And he took away
this feeling of emptiness,
spiritually speaking.
I realized that a relationship with Jehovah
—that’s our most precious possession.
I had to get back.
I started to study the Bible with sincerity.
I wanted it to affect my mind and my heart,
and I wanted it to effect
change in my behavior.
Now as I did that,
I felt Jehovah blessing those efforts.
He began to help me
to rebuild that relationship with him.
So I began to use Jehovah’s name.
Speaking about Jehovah became a wonderful joy
and a great pleasure to me.
And the result was that my ministry
was very productive.
And it’s an amazing joy
to be able to help someone
come to love Jehovah.
I was just so happy
to be back under Jehovah’s wings
and have that peace of mind.
How loving Jehovah is!
He wants to help us.
And what better helper could we have?
He’s the best in the universe.
Now let’s consider
the second challenge we face:
negative reports
about Jehovah’s Witnesses in the media.
Now, here’s a good principle to follow
—Proverbs 14:15.
I’ll give you a moment.
At Proverbs chapter 14
and verse 15,
it says:
“The naive person believes every word,
but the shrewd one ponders each step.”
Some people believe everything
they read in the newspaper or see on TV.
Do you?
Should you?
Consider this:
Now, you’re working from door to door,
and you meet a householder who says:
“You Jehovah’s Witnesses are terrible people.
You let your children die.
You don’t accept medical treatment.”
Well, you ask the householder,
“Do you know
any Jehovah’s Witnesses personally?”
“No.”
“Then where did you get the idea
that we let our children die
and don’t accept medical treatment?”
The householder says:
“I have it on good authority.
I read it in the newspaper.”
Well, if it’s in the newspaper,
it must be true, right?
Not necessarily.
Remember this:
Reporters have a deadline to meet,
and a reporter may not have the time
or the inclination to check the facts.
Or the reporter
may have written a balanced article,
but then the editor changes it.
Maybe the editor
doesn’t like Jehovah’s Witnesses,
or he’s been misinformed about us.
Now, it’s bad enough if people in the world
believe everything they read in the newspaper
but, brothers, let’s not be among them.
Let’s not be naive;
let’s consider things carefully.
Similarly, sometimes there’s a TV program
about Jehovah’s Witnesses.
Now, a few of these programs
are balanced and fair.
Many or, I daresay, most are not.
And when they’re not, you’ll often find
that the producers started out
with a negative view of Jehovah’s Witnesses
and then they looked for information
to support their prejudice.
So whom did they turn to?
Apostates and the clergy.
From them,
they got suggestions for people to interview.
And we know what those people would say.
At the very last minute,
they may ask the brothers for a comment
just to give an appearance of fairness,
but the program wasn’t designed to be fair.
It was designed to be unfair.
It was slanted against Jehovah’s Witnesses.
Now let’s be clear.
Some news organizations
are very conscientious about their reporting,
and they want to present
both sides of an issue.
And where Jehovah’s Witnesses
are concerned,
they do so at their cost.
If a newspaper publishes
anything positive about us,
the churches will push back.
‘Our parishioners are upset.
‘They subscribe to your newspaper,
and they don’t like reading favorable things
about Jehovah’s Witnesses.’
The message:
‘If it ever happens again,
you’re going to lose subscribers.’
Now, this matter of Jehovah’s people
being the subject of malicious reports
isn’t new.
Think about the days of Queen Esther.
Wicked Haman brings a bad report
to King Ahasuerus.
‘The Jews don’t obey our laws.
They’re a danger to society.’
Does Ahasuerus check the facts?
Does he demand proof?
No.
Ahasuerus is naive;
he allows himself to be taken in by Haman.
Well, there are
a lot of modern-day Hamans today,
and they use similar tactics.
As a result,
some government officials are taken in.
They believe the slanderous accusations
of the apostates.
Now, if they just took the time
to check the facts,
they’d see that they’re being lied to,
but they don’t check the facts.
Now again, it’s bad enough, brothers,
when government officials
are taken in by false reports,
so don’t you be taken in.
Have you ever heard the expression
“trial by media”?
It works like this:
Someone is charged with a crime,
and the case
is widely publicized in the media,
and the media
presents the case in such a way
that everyone who hears about it
thinks the man is guilty.
Of course,
to avoid a lawsuit for slander or libel,
these media reports
are very carefully worded,
and we need to understand
what the wording means.
Here’s a good principle to keep in mind
—Job chapter 12
and verse 11.
It’s amazing how many principles
we can draw from the book of Job
for this talk.
At Job 12:11,
this is Job speaking and he says:
“Does not the ear test out words
as the tongue tastes food?”
“Does not the ear test out words?”
What does that mean?
Does it mean that if we learn that apostates
are going to be featured on a TV program,
we should watch it
to see if what they say is true?
No.
It basically means
to consider the source of the words.
If they are the words of apostates,
why would we believe them?
Now, think of it this way:
You have a bottle on your shelf
that’s marked “poison.”
Do you need to open it up and take a swig
to see if it really is poison?
Believe what the label says.
Now, for the purpose of this discussion,
let’s consider another way
we can test out words
—and that is to pay attention
to what the words mean.
Remember, we talked about media reports
and how these are very often carefully worded
to avoid a lawsuit.
So suppose a report indicates
that someone has been charged with a crime
or that he’s being investigated.
All right, you have two words:
charged and investigated.
It doesn’t mean he’s guilty.
Or suppose that someone
is convicted and put in jail.
Well, that would apply
to our young brothers in Korea, wouldn’t it?
They were convicted and jailed.
And what was their crime?
They refused to kill someone.
Did they do anything wrong?
Or if someone is found guilty by man,
as Jesus was,
it doesn’t mean that he’s guilty
in the sight of God.
So, brothers,
we really have to think about these things.
We may read that a person
or an organization was sued
and then settled out of court.
Does settling out of court
mean that they were guilty?
Not necessarily.
Now, in this country and others,
court cases are often handled by a jury.
Now, who are on the jury?
Ordinary citizens with no legal training.
But not only that,
these ordinary citizens
don’t always have access to all the facts
because the judge and lawyers decide
which facts will be shared with the jury,
so it’s unlikely that the whole truth
will ever come out in court.
Actually, neither side probably wants
the whole truth to come out in court.
Now, sometimes attorneys
deliberately withhold information
that would be prejudicial to their clients.
And, in addition, the juries
have prejudices like everyone else,
and some of them
just can’t set their prejudices aside.
I’ll tell you an actual experience.
Some time ago,
a lawyer told me about a case he had.
There was a case
of medical malpractice by a doctor.
There was a jury.
And at trial, the doctor was clearly shown
to be in the wrong
but the jury didn’t give the patient a penny.
The lawyer was confused.
So after the trial,
he approached two of the jurors and asked,
“If you don’t mind, tell me which part
of the testimony you didn’t believe.”
The jurors replied:
“Oh, we didn’t get that far.
“The doctor was cute,
and we didn’t want him
to have to pay anything.”
With deep thinkers like that,
no wonder many lawyers
try to settle their cases
rather than bring them to a jury.
But someone will say:
“No, I don’t believe
in settling out of court.
I believe in justice and truth.”
So that brings up the question,
Is it wrong to settle a matter
before it goes to trial?
Or is it Scriptural?
Let’s let Jesus answer that question.
Turn to Matthew 5:25, 26.
It’s interesting
that Jesus should mention this
with all the important things
that Jesus taught.
Matthew 5:25, 26:
“Be quick to settle matters
“with your legal opponent,
“while you are with him on the way there,
“so that somehow the opponent
may not turn you over to the judge,
“and the judge to the court attendant,
“and you get thrown into prison.
“I say to you for a fact,
“you will certainly not come out of there
until you have paid over
your last small coin.”
Now, this is interesting.
Think about the Mosaic Law.
Was there any provision in the Mosaic Law
to throw someone in jail
if he couldn’t pay a debt?
That wasn’t the way.
If he couldn’t pay, he’d have to work it off
or a family member would have to work it off.
So when Jesus talks about prison and a judge,
he’s obviously referring
to what a Gentile judge would do.
Now, you couldn’t necessarily expect
justice from him.
Why might he rule against our brother?
Well, maybe he got paid
under the table by the other party.
Or maybe he was prejudiced
against the race
or the religion of the other party.
Now notice, Jesus didn’t say
that the man should settle
only if he was guilty.
So, brothers, let’s not be naive;
don’t believe everything you read.
Just because an article
is called a news report
doesn’t make it true,
and an editorial is someone’s opinion
—and that someone may be wrong.
And TV producers
may have their own agenda,
prejudice, and viewpoint.
So, what do we say in conclusion?
Our faith is under attack,
and we have to fight.
And Jehovah gives us
what we need to fight with.
One of the things he gives us
is good associations.
Satan will try to lure us
away from good associations.
He’ll try to weaken our faith
by getting us involved in bad associations
without our knowing it,
but Jehovah provides
good association in the congregation.
These are people we know.
These are people we love.
These are people
who have our best interests at heart.
Keep in mind the principle we find
at Proverbs 13:20:
“The one walking with the wise
will become wise,
but the one who has dealings with the stupid
will fare badly.”
You know the members of your congregation;
you know that they are wise;
you know that they have
your best interests at heart.
But if you get involved in a forum,
you might not know whether you’re walking
with wise persons or not
—at least not at first.
So be careful.
If the conversation turns negative,
get out.
Satan is behind
the twisted teachings of apostates.
He is “the father of the lie.”
And those who lie
are doing exactly what their father does.
The apostates have nothing
to offer us, brothers.
All they have to offer is hate.
All they have to offer
is criticism and negative talk.
But, oh, how upbuilt we feel
when we’re with those who love Jehovah!
So Jehovah provides us
with good, wholesome associations.
He also provides us with his Word of truth,
and an accurate knowledge of the truth
is the best defense against apostasy.
Read the Bible every day and meditate on it.
Pay attention to the words;
pay attention to what they mean.
Be like the Beroeans
referred to at Acts chapter 17
and verses 10 and 11.
Let’s read that.
Acts 17:10, 11:
“Immediately by night the brothers
sent both Paul and Silas to Beroea.
“On arriving,
they went into the synagogue of the Jews.
“Now these were more noble-minded
than those in Thessalonica,
“for they accepted the word
with the greatest eagerness of mind,
“carefully examining the Scriptures daily
“[carefully examining the Scriptures daily]
to see whether these things were so.”
Now, Paul compares the Beroeans
with the Thessalonians.
What do we know about the Thessalonians?
They didn’t have YouTube in those days,
but at one point, the Thessalonians
apparently heard a rumor
that “the day of Jehovah” had arrived.
Who circulated the rumor?
An apostate?
Maybe.
But maybe it was just someone
who had heard the rumor
and passed it on without checking it out.
Have you ever done that
—passed on a report
without checking the facts?
I think all of us have to admit
that we’ve been guilty of that
at one time or another.
But now,
how did the Thessalonians react?
They were alarmed.
They were “quickly shaken
from [their] reason.”
We mustn’t let that happen to us.
When you hear something,
check it out;
don’t just circulate it;
don’t just believe it;
check it out.
Colossians 2:6, 7
—the last scripture we’ll read
during this talk.
Now, here Paul explains how we can avoid
being quickly shaken from our reason.
Let’s read this final scripture.
Colossians 2:6, 7:
“Therefore, just as you
have accepted Christ Jesus the Lord,
“go on walking in union with him
“[you do that, and you’ll be walking
with a wise one, certainly],
“being rooted and built up in him
“[and then notice this]
and being stabilized in the faith,
just as you were taught.”
If we’re “stabilized in the faith,”
we won’t be quickly shaken
by unfounded accusations
by apostates or the media.
False rumors are often spread during wartime.
Brothers, this is war.
We need to put up a hard fight for the faith
as if our life depended on it
—because it does!
Thank you, Brother Splane,
for that insightful talk.
This session has helped us
to safeguard our faith and to act in faith.
What can we look
forward to in the next two sessions?
The Scriptural theme is Matthew 21:21,
which says in part:
“If you have faith . . . , it will happen.”
The next session begins with a symposium
highlighting women of strong faith.
And we eagerly anticipate
the public Bible discourse
“Have Faith in the Good News.”
Now let’s sing together song number 38,
which draws attention
to our source of power, Jehovah God.
This song is entitled
“He Will Make You Strong.”
After the song,
you may have your local concluding prayer.
Again, that’s song number 38.