We extend a warm welcome
to all who accepted an invitation
to join us for this convention.
We live in an unfriendly world
where true friends are hard to find.
Is it possible to draw close to God
and have him as our Friend?
If so, what must we do
to gain God’s friendship?
Brother Kenneth Cook,
a member of the Governing Body,
will answer those questions
in the discourse entitled
“Friendship With God—How Possible?”
Is it realistic to believe
that you can be a friend of God?
If until now you’ve answered no
to that question,
please consider this:
The lives of millions of people today
prove that friendship with God is possible.
Their lives prove that we can find
a peaceful and meaningful life now,
as well as hope
for an everlasting and peaceful future.
If you desire that for yourself and others,
we urge you
to listen to this Scriptural talk.
We emphasize the need to listen
because many people ignore
that important question,
that is, Can you be a friend of God?
Why is it that many put
such an important question out of their mind?
There are a number of reasons.
For example, some believe
that God is impersonal or unknowable
or that he does not exist
and that he’s not interested in humans.
They are taught that God is a mystery
and that he’s cruel, harsh, and demanding.
Many religious leaders claim
that God will punish bad people forever
in a place of torment.
Do you feel drawn into friendship
with a God like that?
Who in their right mind would?
Still other people, after seeing
all of the injustice and suffering
in the world,
have concluded that God must be dead
or that he never existed at all.
And then there are those who believe
that they have done
too many bad things in their life
to ever be a friend of God.
Do any of those causes for doubt or concern
apply to you?
If so, please listen carefully
to the following four key points
that may help you to see
that friendship with God is truly possible.
We will then develop each one.
First, we’ll look at how sin
separates us from God.
Second, we’ll look at how God
has taken the initiative to heal the breach
and bring obedient humans
back into friendship with him.
Then, we’ll examine what we can do
to become God’s friend in an everlasting way.
And finally, we will consider
how friendship with God
brings peace now and in the future.
So for our first point:
What is it that separates us from God?
In a word, sin.
Why does sin separate us?
Because the true God is holy, he’s pure,
and his conduct is perfect.
He does not have a trace of sin;
he’s clean in the highest sense.
No human can be holy to that degree,
not even close.
To illustrate: Consider the words
“human” and “imperfect.”
They go together, don’t they?
You cannot fully describe humans
without mentioning imperfection.
It’s just a part of us,
and human history shows this
to be sadly and painfully true.
So then our sins or imperfections
create a barrier between us and God.
This separation is described
at Isaiah 59:2,
where we are told in part:
“Your own errors have separated you
from your God.
Your sins have made him
hide his face from you.”
‘Separated from God,’ it says.
We were born into this state,
but God did not create us to be sinful.
Our sins are not his fault.
The first humans, Adam and Eve,
were created perfect.
But they proved to be ungrateful and selfish,
and they rejected God’s friendship.
They destroyed their peace with God
by sinning against him,
and they became his enemies.
Adam then passed sin on
to his descendants, as well as death.
We read about this terrible inheritance
at Romans 5:12.
In this verse, the apostle Paul summarizes
why our inherited sinful condition
leads to death.
He wrote:
“That is why, just as through one man
“sin entered into the world
and death through sin,
“and so death spread to all men
because they had all sinned.”
“Death spread to all men.”
This pandemic of sin
has a 100 percent infection rate
and a 100 percent mortality rate.
No human can escape it.
As Paul said: “Death spread . . .
because they had all sinned.”
On our own,
we cannot correct our sinful state.
It’s as if we have fallen into a deep pit
with seemingly no way out.
But are we left without hope?
No.
In fact, although God views some people
as his enemies,
he treats others as his friends.
For example, regarding the man Abraham,
the Bible book of James
says in chapter 2 and verse 23
that “Abraham put faith in Jehovah,
“and it was counted to him as righteousness,
and he came to be called Jehovah’s friend.”
Abraham was as imperfect as we are,
but he came to be called God’s friend.
What has God done
to make it possible for humans
to gain his favor and blessing?
Simply put, our Creator
has taken the initiative.
He has taken steps to heal the breach
that was caused by sin
and to eliminate the separation
between us and him.
How has he done this?
First, the Holy Scriptures tell us
that God desires for us to come to know him
and to be at peace with him.
In fact, he appeals to us to do this.
In the Bible book of Acts 17:27,
we are told that God wants us
to sincerely seek him
and that if we do,
we will find that “he is not far off
from each one of us.”
Next, and very important,
God took the initiative to make this possible
by providing the sacrifice of his Son, Jesus,
in order to redeem us from sin.
That was an unparalleled act of love.
As we now read 1 John 4:10,
please think about what it says
regarding this matchless act of love
on God’s part
so that we may never forget
that God took the initiative
to heal the breach, so to speak.
First John 4:10 says:
“The love is in this respect,
“not that we have loved God,
“but that he loved us
“and sent his Son as a propitiatory sacrifice
for our sins.”
What did God do?
“God . . . loved us,” it says,
“and [he] sent his Son.”
This sacrifice that God provided
by means of his Son
is called “propitiatory”
because it can atone for our sins.
And here is how it can do so:
What Jesus gave in sacrifice for us
was equal to what Adam lost for us,
that is, a perfect human life.
Adam exchanged his perfect life for death
by his rebellion against God.
As mentioned earlier, Adam then
passed sin on to his descendants,
and he placed us on a path
outside of God’s friendship.
On the other hand,
the death of Jesus allowed for a ransom,
or a means to satisfy God’s justice
so that we could receive back
what Adam lost for us.
That undeserved gift from God
was given at great cost.
Clearly, our Creator wants us
to come to know him
and to enjoy a beautiful friendship with him.
We should be very grateful
that God took the necessary step
to close the gap
and provide a way for us
to become his friend.
The next step involves each of us.
What is required of us?
Humility.
We must be humble enough
to accept God’s gift.
If we are humble, we’ll see
our need for God’s mercy,
and we’ll then do our part
to show appreciation.
The Bible book of Acts 3:19 tells us
that this involves
‘repenting and turning around.’
In other words, to receive God’s gift,
which includes his mercy,
we must adjust our thinking by repenting
and then turn around
by adjusting our conduct and course in life
wherever necessary.
The opportunity to do this
is open to all people.
As our Creator,
God is not partial in his mercy
and in the friendship he offers.
He has kindly put everything in place for us.
All we must do is be grateful and humble
and then take the next step.
That step involves accepting Jesus
and his teachings.
God requires that we follow
the example of his Son.
How closely must we do so?
At John 14:6, Jesus explained:
“I am the way and the truth and the life.
No one comes to the Father
except through me.”
“No one.”
So, then, to come into God’s friendship,
we must follow his Son as true Christians.
So far, we have reviewed
how sin separated humans from God.
Then we considered what God has done
to heal the breach, or close the gap,
so that we can come back
into his favor as his friends.
Now let’s look even further
into what we must do,
which brings us to the third key point:
How can a person become God’s friend?
We invite you to consider what is said
at James 4:8.
If you have a copy of the Bible,
we urge you to follow along
—James 4:8.
As we read it,
please notice first the invitation,
then the response,
and finally what we must do.
It reads:
“Draw close to God,
and he will draw close to you.
“Cleanse your hands, you sinners,
and purify your hearts, you indecisive ones.”
So, first, what is the invitation?
It is to “draw close to God.”
That is followed
by what response on God’s part?
“He will draw close to you.”
But for God to do this, what must we do
to show that we accept his invitation?
We must cleanse and purify ourselves
according to his standards.
This will take effort.
For example,
we must learn about his standards,
and we must come to appreciate
that they are the best for us,
and then we must be determined
to follow them.
Above all, we do this
because we want to please God
and to be his friend.
So, then, how can you develop
a friendship with God?
Show initiative and put forth the effort.
Consider this: If you have a houseplant,
you know that it doesn’t grow on its own.
You have to water it regularly
and keep it in an environment
that helps it to grow.
True?
Something similar is true
of our friendship with God.
We nurture this friendship by reading
and studying God’s Word, the Bible.
When we do so,
we learn important things about God.
For example,
we learn that God’s name is Jehovah.
And as is true of any good friendship,
it’s important that we use his name.
If we’re sincere in our efforts
to “draw close” to him,
as we read at James 4:8,
Jehovah will “draw close” to us.
And he never abandons his true friends.
In fact, John 17:3 tells us
that coming to know God
“means everlasting life” for us.
What an undeserved kindness
and priceless gift
for Jehovah’s true friends!
So that you too can enjoy
a bright future as God’s friends,
we warmly invite you to accept
a free interactive Bible course
offered by Jehovah’s Witnesses
using the publication Enjoy life Forever!
Here’s what it looks like.
Jehovah’s Witnesses can help you
to get either a printed
or an electronic copy.
It begins with the lessons:
“How Can the Bible Help You?”
“The Bible Gives Hope,”
and “Can You Trust the Bible?”
We urge you to learn these things
and to worship God in harmony with the truth
that is revealed in his Word.
So, what important points have we considered
regarding how a person
can become God’s friend?
First, get to know God
by reading and studying his Word.
Jesus said that doing this
“means everlasting life.”
And then,
learn about God’s name and use it.
Now we’ll list four more things
that those who desire
to become God’s friends must do.
They are: imitate God’s qualities,
reject thinking and actions that offend God,
associate with those
who want to be God’s friend,
and avoid friendship with people
who ignore or mock God’s standards.
Now, a few things in that list
speak for themselves—don’t they?—
such as associate with those
who want to be God’s friend
and avoid friendship with people
who ignore or mock God’s standards.
That makes sense, doesn’t it?
Think back to our illustration
about the houseplant.
You must not only water and nurture it,
but you must keep it
in the right environment,
one that helps it to grow.
Likewise, associating with those
who also want to be God’s friend
is the right environment for us.
But what about the requirement
to imitate God’s qualities?
How can imperfect people do this?
Well, for a few minutes,
we’ll look at just two of God’s qualities
and how we can imitate him.
And we will begin with God’s love.
An important way that we can imitate
God’s love and become his friend
is by applying what his Son, Jesus,
taught us.
For example, Jesus said:
“Just as you want men to do to you,
do the same way to them”
—a simple statement
but one that takes effort to apply, true?
Can we do this?
Yes.
And a person who desires to be God’s friend
will put forth the effort needed to do this.
To succeed in imitating God’s love,
we must try to see people
as Jehovah sees them.
We must try to put ourselves
in the place of others
so that we can understand
their needs, their concerns,
and even their pain of heart.
Some may be challenged physically
because of injury, disease, or aging.
Others are coping with emotional trials
because of depression or anxiety.
Many people face difficulties
that we have not experienced.
For instance, a young person
may find it hard
to understand older people,
and he or she will really need to think
about what it must be like
to be an older person.
If that is true of you,
how can you imitate God’s love?
One important way is by listening carefully
until you understand
the other person’s feelings.
When you do so, you are in a better position
to imitate God’s love.
Those who desire to be Jehovah’s friends
will be moved to imitate his love
by acting according
to what others really need.
That brings us to a second
and related quality,
that of kindness.
Anyone who desires to be God’s friend
must be kind to others.
Here again, we can learn much
from what Jesus said and did.
God’s Son said that the Most High
“is kind toward the unthankful and wicked.”
Jesus appreciated this outstanding quality
of his heavenly Father,
and he imitated God’s kindness.
What helped Jesus to do so?
He treated people in a kind manner
by anticipating how his words and actions
might affect their feelings.
For example, the Bible tells us
that a woman known to be a sinner
approached Jesus,
weeping and wetting his feet with her tears.
Jesus discerned that she was repentant,
and he knew how heartbroken she would be
if he just dismissed her unkindly.
Like his heavenly Father,
Jesus looked for the good in her.
We know this because he commended her;
then he forgave her.
Following Jesus’ example,
how can we also imitate God’s kindness?
We can do so by being gentle to all people
whenever possible.
Kind people discern
how to deal with delicate situations.
Kind people avoid hurting
the feelings of others.
When we do this, we try to anticipate
how our words and actions might affect them.
That is how a true friend of God
will treat others.
Well, this review of just a few
of Jehovah’s many outstanding qualities
gives us an idea of how much we can benefit
from reading the Bible
and then applying its many lessons for us.
Yes, friendship with God is possible,
and we can imitate his outstanding qualities.
In the following video,
please take note of how we can use the Bible
to build a friendship with God.
Have you ever wanted to ask God:
“Who are you?
“Where are you?
Do you care about me?”
You are not alone.
For centuries,
people everywhere have felt the need
to know their Maker.
Imagine a woman
who has never known her father.
All her life she has been told lies
that her father abandoned her.
But deep inside she feels
—she knows—
it’s not true.
One day,
she receives a letter from her father.
She learns that he is alive
and that, unbeknownst to her,
he had been reaching out
to be part of her life
since the day she was born.
The daughter learns who her father is,
and eventually
she finds him.
They learn about one another
and build a strong bond
until they are inseparable friends.
The Bible is like a group
of letters from our heavenly Father.
As we read the Bible,
we learn how to talk to God,
how he responds,
and the many ways
he shows his tender care.
The Bible can help us to do something
we may never have thought possible
—be God’s friend.
That friendship starts by learning the name
of your heavenly Father and new Friend,
and God tells us his name:
“You, whose name is Jehovah,
you alone are the Most High.”
Jehovah guarantees that if you
‘draw close to him,
he will draw close to you.’
Our loving Father openly extends friendship
to all who search for him.
Will you accept his invitation?
To learn more about what the Bible says
on this and many other topics,
go to jw.org.
As that thought-provoking video asked,
do you see the need
to come to know your Creator?
Are you willing to put forth
the effort needed
to accept his invitation
and become his friend?
If so, the Bible contains
the guidance that you need,
and the reward for applying what it says
is not reserved for the future only.
Friendship with God brings peace now.
You can have a more peaceful
and meaningful life right now
by becoming Jehovah’s friend.
When you become a friend of God,
he will listen to your prayers
and extend his mercy to you.
And when you sense his forgiveness,
you will experience deep-seated joy.
Psalm 32:1, 2 says in part:
“Happy is the one
whose transgression is pardoned,
“whose sin is covered.
Happy is the man
whom Jehovah does not charge with guilt.”
What a blessing it is
to sense Jehovah’s forgiveness!
God’s forgiveness can free you
from the burden of guilt
that you may feel because of past wrongs.
This includes wrongs
that you may have committed
before you came to know God
and became his friend.
Is such a thing possible for you?
Yes, it is.
As our video pointed out,
the Bible teaches us how to pray to God
and how God responds to our prayers.
And you can be assured
that he will listen to your prayers,
including your prayers
for his forgiveness and his help.
At Proverbs 15:29 we read
that Jehovah
“hears the prayer of the righteous.”
Who are the righteous?
The righteous are those who strive
to live by his requirements.
What a comfort for us to know
that we can be God’s friend,
because he sees what we are trying to do
and he listens to us!
But there is more.
Our friendship with God can also result
in peace with other people.
In fact, Jesus urged us
to seek such peace with others.
He said that we should ‘love even our enemies
and do good to others
without hoping for anything back.’
And then we read at Luke 6:36 that he added:
“Continue being merciful,
just as your Father is merciful.”
Such a good example
can touch the hearts of others
and move them
to become Jehovah’s friends as well.
Consider the experience of José,
who learned how to love
from true friends of God.
At the age of 13, José was involved
in guerrilla warfare.
He was taught to hate the people
who were allegedly responsible
for the injustices
that he saw all around him.
His aim was to eliminate those people.
He saw many of his companions fall in death,
and José became filled
with feelings of bitterness
and revenge.
While making grenades or bombs,
he would ask himself:
‘Why is there so much suffering?
If there is a God, does he even notice?’
Many times, José wept.
He was depressed and confused.
Eventually, José came in contact
with a local congregation
of Jehovah’s Witnesses.
At his first congregation meeting,
he noticed the loving atmosphere there.
Everyone greeted him
in a warm and friendly manner.
Later, a discussion on the subject
“Why Does God Permit Wickedness?”
provided answers to the very questions
that he had been asking.
As he learned more from the Bible,
José made changes
in his way of life and in his thinking.
He learned to imitate God’s love
and thereby become his friend.
Breaking his ties with his companions,
though, proved to be challenging.
Every time he went
to the Kingdom Hall of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
he was followed.
Some former associates
even attended a few meetings
so as to understand what brought about
such a great change in José.
But once they were satisfied
that he was not a danger to them,
they left him alone.
At age 17, José was baptized
as one of Jehovah’s Witnesses.
As God’s friend,
José soon started sharing
what he was learning full-time.
Instead of scheming to kill people,
he could now share a message
of love and of hope with them.
What a great reward for choosing
to become Jehovah’s friend!
Yes, even those who were once enemies
can learn to be at peace with one another
and be God’s friends.
So, what have we learned?
We have reviewed why friendship with God
is realistic and possible for us.
The Bible tells us that since ancient times,
God has called some humans his friends.
We also looked at what God has done
to heal the breach, or close the gap,
between us and him.
How has he done so?
By means of his Son.
Through Jesus, Jehovah God provided
the ransom sacrifice
that was needed to redeem us from sin.
Then, we looked at what you must do
to take advantage
of God’s mercy and become his friend.
This includes studying his Word, the Bible,
and then imitating his outstanding qualities.
Finally, we considered
how you can find a meaningful life now,
as well as true peace with others.
Jehovah promises that his friends
will receive eternal life in peace.
If that is what you yearn for,
then please accept our invitation
to study the Bible with Jehovah’s Witnesses.
By doing so, you will learn
about an unending future
when anguish of heart is gone forever,
an unending future
in which God will permanently
wipe away tears
from the faces of his friends.
That future is not only possible,
it is the future that God promises!
Thank you, Brother Cook,
for helping us to see
how friendship with God
leads to genuine peace.
Around the earth, millions are pursuing peace
and building faith in Jehovah God
and his Word, the Bible.
If you would like to have Bible discussions,
free of charge,
at a time and place convenient for you,
please inform one of Jehovah’s Witnesses
or visit jw.org
and fill out an online request
for a Bible study.
We will be happy to arrange
for one of Jehovah’s Witnesses to assist you.
Additionally, you can find
interactive, self-guided Bible study lessons
on our website, jw.org.
We have reached the conclusion
of this session.
We look forward to the next session
in which we will see
part two of our feature Bible drama,
“Jehovah Guides Us in the Way of Peace,”
and we will hear the final talk
of this convention.
Now let’s sing a song
that expresses our confidence
in God’s promises.
We invite you to sing
song number 147, entitled
“Life Everlasting Is Promised.”
That’s song number 147,
after which you may have
your local concluding prayer.