Each year, we look forward
to the high-quality video presentations
that have become
a highlight of our conventions.
Work is underway
on videos and dramas for future conventions.
The set construction
and other work needed for the series
The Good News According to Jesus
is well along.
Additionally, planning and construction
of our new media production facility
in the United States
is moving ahead steadily.
All of these efforts
are supported by voluntary donations.
If you would like to have a share
in supporting the worldwide work
of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
one way you can do so
is through your financial contributions.
For more information,
please visit donate.jw.org.
We have seen
that Jehovah promises us a future
filled with happiness and peace.
How will universal peace come about,
and what will it mean for mankind?
Please pay close attention
to Brother Geoffrey Jackson,
a member of the Governing Body,
as he answers those questions
in the final talk of this convention,
entitled “Universal Peace Is Sure to Come!”
What is true peace?
For those who live in lands
where they have wars,
no doubt the focus they have on true peace
is to stop fighting, to stop the conflicts,
to not have any wars.
And it’s true that peace
does include an absence of war.
But in many cases, the efforts of mankind
to try and gain peace by stopping wars
is similar to what we say
is a Band-Aid solution.
What do we mean by that?
Well, a person may have a horrible sore,
perhaps even cancerous.
And if he just puts a Band-Aid over the top,
maybe it hides the sore,
but it really doesn’t solve the problem
—does it?—
because peace is not just an end of war.
You know yourself, if you were to live
in a country where there isn’t any war
but you’re still worried about your health,
your well-being, and your safety
or if you feel sick and hungry,
would you say that you’re having
a peaceful life?
Of course not.
According to the Bible, the word “peace”
means far more than just an absence of war.
It means good health, well-being, and safety.
And from our convention, we’ve seen
that there’s a lot involved with true peace.
It includes having
a peaceful relationship with Jehovah God.
It also means having
a peaceful relationship with others.
And also it includes
the peace of heart and mind
that gives us tranquility.
But now in this final talk,
we’re going to consider a bigger issue,
and that is universal peace.
Now, what do we mean by universal peace?
What we mean by universal peace
is a type of peace
that is everywhere in heaven and on earth
—in all aspects of life.
It’s the type of peace that only the God
of peace, Jehovah, can bring
along with the “Prince of Peace,”
Jesus Christ.
Soon they will take dramatic steps
toward the restoration of universal peace.
Let’s take our Bibles,
and if we turn together
to Romans 16:20,
we’ll see what’s included
in this restoration of universal peace
—that’s Romans 16:20.
There we’re told: “For his part,
“the God who gives peace will crush Satan
“under your feet shortly.
May the undeserved kindness
of our Lord Jesus be with you.”
Yes, the restoration of universal peace
also includes
the crushing of Satan the Devil.
So in our final discussion,
the final talk of this convention,
we’re going to consider four basic questions.
The first one is,
When was universal peace disturbed?
Second, Who will restore universal peace?
The third question, How will it be restored?
And then finally, we’re going to think
about what further blessings
mankind will enjoy at that time.
But before we go on
to answer those questions,
let’s review together
the program that we’ve had.
I’m sure you’ll agree that this has been
a beautiful convention.
And it’s encouraged us to pursue peace.
But what are some of the good points
that you remember from the program?
Well, as we mentioned already, there are
three aspects to peace that we’ll discuss.
First of all, our peace with Jehovah God.
The Friday program finished
with the final talk,
and that’s where it mentions
about not being misled
by imitation peace.
And then Sunday,
what a beautiful public discourse we had!
It said “Friendship With God—How Possible?”
And then the second aspect of our peace
is peace with one another.
The first day, remember,
we had that beautiful symposium
on family peace.
What were some of the things
that we need to do
to have peace in our family?
Well, love and respect are important.
We need to improve
our communication with one another.
We need to work as a team
and worship together.
And then Saturday, we had
another interesting symposium
on what it said about peace wreckers,
things that can wreck peace.
Do you remember some of those?
Inappropriate boasting,
envy, dishonesty, harmful gossip,
and uncontrolled anger.
And then the third aspect of peace
deals with our personal peace,
our inner calm despite trials.
On Saturday, we had a very interesting talk
that mentioned the need
to safeguard our bond of peace.
And then on Sunday, we went through
another symposium where it gave examples
of those who had sowed peace
and then reaped peace.
As we look through the program,
I’m sure there are so many points
that you can remember that you enjoyed.
Of course, one of the highlights
at any convention
is when we have the baptism.
If you were baptized at this convention,
we’d like to welcome you!
Yes, we welcome you
to the Christian brotherhood
because we know that you’re working hard
to have peace with Jehovah God.
But now at this point, let’s watch a video
that gives us some lessons
with regard to what we saw
in the various videos in this convention.
Enjoy!
Hey, everyone, Brooke here.
Guess who just walked in?
Olivia.
And there’s Jake.
Would she ever?
No, she would never; she’s an angel.
It feels out of your control, doesn’t it?
Remember when we studied
about the Shulammite girl?
Who was really in control?
She was.
You have the same power.
If you believe that,
it’ll change how you handle the pressure.
My peace comes from doing the right thing.
“I am a wall.”
You’re just a coward.
Take your trash.
Think about what the jailer had done to Paul.
He could have hated him for it.
Yeah, he could have.
But I guess he saw the jailer’s pain
instead of just his own.
Let me show you just one scripture.
All right, one scripture.
Jehovah has taught us to love,
and he’s given our family
peace.
Hello, everyone.
Haley from DeNure Design here.
You don’t think she’s showing off?
Is this just about Haley?
Can you believe her?
I haven’t seen all her posts.
If Celia agrees that Haley
is doing something she shouldn’t,
you should talk to her.
I’ve noticed
your posts lately on QuicPost.
What about them?
Some people might think you’re bragging.
Who would think like that?
You?
I didn’t want to upset you.
Jake said that I needed to take . . .
Jake! So everyone thinks
my posts are inappropriate?
That’s not what I am saying at all.
You are such . . .
Think back to a time
when you wanted forgiveness.
“Love is patient and kind.”
It’s not jealous.
I’m sorry, Haley.
Genuine affection fights peace wreckers.
And affection grows when we really know
our brothers and sisters well.
I was always impressed
with how close you two were.
Well, it wasn’t always that way.
No.
What started as a small disagreement
just exploded.
You!
You’re the problem.
I needed a lot of help from Jehovah
to make things right with Nick.
There was a misunderstanding
that got blown all out of proportion.
And I didn’t handle it the best.
That’s when our peace
was really put to the test.
The body decided, unanimously,
that he should no longer serve.
Because you pushed them!
Phil didn’t know just how tense things were
between Tim and I.
I found comfort
in accounts of Jehovah’s servants.
They helped me realize that
being at peace with my brothers
was more important
than any appointed position.
It wasn’t easy,
but we talked it out.
And we were able to make peace
with Jehovah’s help.
Without peace,
I don’t know how we could’ve managed
what was to come.
At that moment when you hear the verdict
that you’ll stay in prison,
it’s like you’ve been knocked unconscious.
But then
the doors of the elevator opened up,
and in front of us . . .
That’s Jehovah.
When you’re just about to lose
all your strength,
Jehovah does that something for you.
The Russian brothers and sisters,
I pray for them constantly
because they are going
through a very tough time.
What I’ve learned from all of this
is peace isn’t from what’s outside,
from what’s going on,
or from what you’re experiencing.
I’ve learned that peace is on the inside,
and that comes from Jehovah.
What priceless lessons those were!
But now, at this point, friends,
we’re going to turn our attention
to that bigger issue
—universal peace.
Remember the first question
we’re going to answer?
When was universal peace disturbed?
Before mankind was created,
universal peace existed for countless ages.
It was just like a beautiful pond of water
that was undisturbed
—no ripples, mirrorlike in appearance.
In other words, there was
utmost harmony with Jehovah
and with all the spirit creatures.
But then it’s just as if a rock was thrown
into that beautiful pond
and peace started to be disturbed.
When do you think that happened?
Well, we’ll find the answer to that question
by turning to the Bible,
and this time, if we look at 1 John 3:8
—that’s 1 John 3:8—
notice the answer to the question,
When did the problem start?
There we’re told: “The one who practices sin
“originates with the Devil,
“because the Devil has been sinning
from the beginning.
“For this purpose the Son of God
was made manifest,
to break up the works of the Devil.”
So notice the answer to the question.
“Because the Devil has been sinning
from the beginning,”
or, as the footnote says,
‘from the time that he began.’
Does that mean right from the very time
when he was created?
No, he wasn’t the Devil then, was he?
He was a perfect angel.
So when was it
that this universal peace
started to be disturbed?
When was it that the ripples
started to go through the universe?
Well, you might remember
that it wasn’t at the time
that he deceived Eve.
It’s a little bit like when the Bible says
a woman gives birth to a child,
that’s not when the child’s life starts,
is it?
It starts well before then.
So likewise, this disruption
of the universal peace
began in heaven first,
at the time that the angel who became Satan
started to covet the position of Jehovah
to want worship from others.
And by doing this,
he alienated himself from God
and no longer was he in harmony
with Jehovah’s will.
Then that sinful attitude
was manifested in the garden of Eden.
That’s when he took the next step
and started to disturb the peace
of Adam and Eve
and, of course,
they lost their peace with God.
But let’s take a moment and think
about what was really involved
with those events
there in the garden of Eden.
Some very important issues were raised.
Remember how Satan, first of all,
spoke to Eve?
He asked what seemed
like a ridiculous question: ‘Is it true
‘that God hasn’t allowed you to eat
from any tree in the garden?
All the trees are banned?’
Well, of course, that’s ridiculous.
But what was he doing?
He was calling into question
Jehovah’s qualities.
Yes, he was inferring
that Jehovah may not be so generous.
Maybe he’s stingy.
Perhaps he’s holding things back
from Adam and Eve
that they really should have.
And then Satan went one step further.
He said: “You . . . will not die.”
Really what he was saying is,
‘Jehovah is a liar.’
What a horrible accusation!
Sadly, Eve didn’t defend Jehovah.
We would have expected
that she would have said to Satan:
‘Who are you? I don’t know you.
‘Why would I believe you?
I know my loving heavenly Father, Jehovah.’
But no, she sided with the Devil.
So, what would Jehovah do?
Well, think for a moment about this:
What if someone accused you wrongly
in front of everybody,
calling you a liar,
saying all sorts of bad things about you?
What would you do?
Would you go and punch them in the face?
Well, if you did, that wouldn’t be
the right thing to do
and it certainly wouldn’t answer
the questions raised.
You see, was that person really true
in what they said or not?
How would you probably solve this?
Well, you might take the person to court.
And in that court case, that person
could offer whatever evidence they feel
they have to prove that you’re a liar.
On the other hand,
you can produce witnesses to prove
that really you aren’t a liar,
but you’re very truthful.
And then finally, there would be
a decision made
as to who was right and who was wrong.
Well, in a similar way,
these issues (these questions)
raised in the garden of Eden
started a symbolic court case.
So how did Jehovah respond?
Wisely, he allowed time
to settle these issues.
He allowed Satan the opportunity
to try and rule mankind to do things his way.
At the same time, mercifully,
he provided the hope
for the unborn children of Adam and Eve.
You remember at Genesis 3:15,
it speaks of an “offspring,” or a Son,
who’d come later
and eventually undo the bad
that Satan had done there in the beginning
and eventually free mankind
from sin and death.
But what has Satan been doing
since this opportunity has been given to him?
He’s still craving worship from other people.
He wants them to bow down to him
and acknowledge him as their god.
He also uses lies and deceit
to ‘blind the minds’ of persons.
And he also has great anger,
particularly at this time in history,
where he knows his end is near.
And so he’s influencing the world to hate
anyone who stands up on Jehovah’s side.
But now, let’s think
about a very interesting question:
Even though we’re living
in a world that is ruled by Satan,
is it possible at all
for us to have a measure of peace with God?
We’re experiencing
so many trials and challenges.
We face opposition.
We have illness, economic problems,
disasters.
Is it possible to have some measure of peace?
The answer is found again in the Scriptures,
and this time, if you turn with me, please,
to the book of 2 Corinthians chapter 1
—Second Corinthians 1:3, 4—
notice this beautiful promise:
“Praised be the God and Father
of our Lord Jesus Christ,
“the Father of tender mercies
“and the God of all comfort,
“who comforts us in all our trials
“so that we may be able to comfort others
in any sort of trial
with the comfort that we receive from God.”
Isn’t that a beautiful scripture?
What does it highlight?
Notice, Jehovah obviously is aware
of our suffering.
He feels for us.
He wants to help us.
It mentions he’s
“the Father of tender mercies.”
But at the same time, we realize
that Jehovah won’t step in
and fix all our problems at this point.
Why?
Because this is the time that Satan
has the opportunity
to try and rule the world,
and the problems of this world
really come from Satan.
At the same time,
we wouldn’t expect Jehovah to step in
and start to solve the problems
as if he were helping Satan the Devil.
But there is a time
when Satan will be taken away
and the problems will be solved.
We could think of Jehovah’s position
as similar to that of a father
whose son is running in a marathon race.
As he sees his son running in the race,
he may see his son is starting to tire out.
Well, perhaps you may see that others
in the race are not obeying the rules.
Does that mean that the father then jumps in
and takes the place of his son
and helps him as he runs along?
No, the rules don’t allow it.
But what the father can do
is continue to encourage his son:
“Keep on going.
Yes, you can do it!”
So in a similar way,
what does this verse tell us?
It said that Jehovah gives us comfort.
How does he do that?
He gives us peace
by means of his Word, the Bible;
by means of holy spirit;
and by the loving brotherhood that we have.
So at this point, what we’d like to do
is have a look at a video that will highlight
how Jehovah lovingly helps us
even in times of need.
We are living
in “critical times
hard to deal with.”
Many people have lost all hope,
and servants of Jehovah
are not free from trials.
We may face loss of property,
loss of health,
loss of loved ones.
We may experience deep emotional trauma
or even imprisonment for our faith.
Our trials are similar to those of Job,
a faithful servant of Jehovah
who was so saddened that he once asked,
‘Why didn’t I die at birth?’
Perhaps we’ve had moments like that.
But why should we not lose hope?
Because with every trial
comes Jehovah’s support
—support received in many forms:
material support,
emotional support,
and spiritual support.
And while Jehovah
will not remove all our trials now,
we trust that with his support,
we can endure them
until they disappear
in “the real life” to come.
Psalm 34:17, 18 says:
“They cried out, and Jehovah heard . . .
He saves those who are crushed in spirit.”
So we can see that even though
our peace has been disturbed,
we can enjoy peace with God.
So let’s think about our second question.
Remember, that question was,
Who will restore universal peace?
Well, we already saw the answer
when we referred to Genesis 3:15,
the first prophecy in the Bible.
It mentioned the promised offspring, or Son,
and that one is Jesus Christ
—the Prince of Peace.
He has the key role
in restoring universal peace.
Very soon,
he’s going to take the decisive action
to remove this old world
and then take progressive steps
toward the restoration of universal peace.
But why can we be so sure
that Jesus will come soon?
It’s a very simple answer
—by seeing the current events
that are happening in the world today.
Yes, as we look around us,
we see so many things that are happening
that proves to us
that Jesus will soon step in to help us.
Now, how can we say that?
Well, let’s have a look together
at the famous prophecy
that’s recorded in Matthew chapter 24
—Matthew 24:3.
Remember, the apostles
at this particular time
were asking Jesus a very important question.
It’s at the second part of verse 3.
It says they asked: “Tell us,
“when will these things be,
“and what will be the sign of your presence
and of the conclusion
of the system of things?”
Now, you remember, no doubt
from your previous studies of the Bible,
how Jesus then went on to list
many events that would occur
during the last days.
He mentioned wars;
he mentioned earthquakes;
he mentioned famines
and all sorts of pestilences.
Truly we have seen those things happen
in recent times.
In addition to all of that, Matthew 24:14
mentioned the need to preach
the “good news of the Kingdom.”
But there could be some who
perhaps may doubt a little
and say: ‘Well, there’s been wars
all through time.
‘There’s been earthquakes at other times,
not just in the last days,
‘and food shortages.
‘So why can we be so sure
‘that this is the time
‘when we know that Jesus
will soon bring about
an end to wickedness?’
Well, let’s use an illustration.
Most of us are familiar
with using a computer.
Now, when you sit at your computer,
what’s the first thing that you need to do
after you’ve turned it on?
Usually, you have to type in a password,
don’t you?
And you have to get it right.
You have to put in all those numbers
and letters that are required.
Otherwise, you won’t be able
to start working on the computer.
Now, these days people are very concerned
about having strong passwords.
What do you think if you had a password
that had 24 different letters and numbers?
That’s a very strong password,
and it would be very difficult for someone
to just randomly try and find out
what those numbers are
and unlock your computer.
Well, how does that relate
to the sign that Jesus gave?
Notice that if you look back at Matthew 24:3,
the question was not
the “signs” of your presence
but the “sign.”
Just like a password—one sign.
But then that sign
has many different features
—in fact, at least 24 different features.
So even though there have been wars
in the past,
this is the time when we see
all those features
coming together at one time.
And in that way, we could say
it opens the fulfillment
of Bible prophecy.
Yes, as we look around us,
as we listen to the news each day,
we can see
that there is a definite fulfillment
of what Jesus said.
Truly, the end is close.
It’s just like a jigsaw puzzle,
to use another illustration.
When you have all the pieces
of a jigsaw puzzle
and you start to put them all together,
eventually when all the pieces are in place,
the picture is clear, isn’t it?
And that’s exactly how we should feel
about the prophecy that Jesus gave.
Soon, very soon,
he is going to step in and take action.
But, of course, sometimes we may feel,
‘Yes, we’ve known about this
for quite some time.’
And it means that we’ve had to wait
a long time.
But that doesn’t negate the fact
that the evidence of the last days is here.
Perhaps we could illustrate it this way:
Most of us have gone to an airport
to meet someone
who’s coming maybe from overseas
or another part of the country.
Now, since 9/11,
it’s very hard to go to an airport
and actually stand on the side of the runway
and see the plane land.
Usually, what happens?
Once you get to the airport, you’re allowed
to go into a large room with other people,
and all you see are monitors on the wall.
Now, what may the monitors say?
Well, you see, it says there
that the flight has left.
Then later, maybe the monitor says
the flight is on time.
Then it says the flight has landed.
Then it says the flight is taxiing.
Then it says it’s at the gate.
Well, now you start to get really excited,
don’t you?
And yet you haven’t seen the plane,
and you haven’t seen your friend yet.
But you can see from the indications
of what you see on the monitor
that it must be close.
And then all of a sudden, the doors open
and people start to come out.
Well, now you’re really excited
because you know,
yes, you’re going to meet your friend.
Well, that is similar
to how we can view the last days.
There has been a lot of things happening
that we don’t actually see.
But we see the indications
of what’s happened.
And we know that very soon
Jesus, the angels, and the 144,000
will take steps to remove this old world
and then take further steps
toward the restoration of peace.
Isn’t that a beautiful promise?
So naturally, that takes us
to the third question:
How will universal peace be restored?
What will Jesus need to do?
Basically, we could say
there are two actions required.
One is to remove Satan
and the peace disturbers.
And then the second action
is to undo all the evil that Satan has done.
You see, we don’t want a Band-Aid solution
—do we?—
where you’re just hiding something
that’s very serious
by putting a Band-Aid over it.
So not only does Jesus need to take away
those that are disrupting the peace,
but he also has to take steps
to heal mankind and to heal the earth
so that all the evil, the bad things
that Satan has done,
will be overturned.
So let’s think about those two actions
for a moment.
Remember, the first one
is to remove the peace disturbers.
What steps are involved with that?
Remember, this is a progressive action.
If we take our Bibles
and turn to the book of Revelation,
we’ll see there are several things
mentioned here that help us to see
how progressively Jesus
has and will bring about
this removal of peace disturbers.
If you turn with me, please,
to Revelation chapter 12,
let’s read together verse 9
—Revelation 12.
Now, immediately, no doubt you remember
that Revelation 12
is talking about the time
when Jesus’ government, his Kingdom,
was established in the heavens.
That was in 1914.
In verse 9, it mentions
what happened shortly after that time.
Let’s read it:
“So down the great dragon was hurled,
“the original serpent,
the one called Devil and Satan,
“who is misleading
the entire inhabited earth;
“he was hurled down to the earth,
and his angels were hurled down with him.”
Did you notice that word
that came up several times
—“hurled” down?
You see, Jesus didn’t go and say to Satan:
‘Well, look, if you don’t mind,
‘we’d like you to relocate to the earth.
Whenever you’re ready.’
No, Satan was hurled down.
And what confidence that gives us!
That means that Jesus has the power
to be able to remove Satan from the heavens.
That gives us some idea
of what’s going to happen in the future
with regard to the earth.
Of course, now we’re living in a time
when Satan and his demons
are here in the vicinity of the earth,
and they are causing so much trouble.
So, what’s another step that Jesus will take
in removing those who disrupt the peace?
Well, let’s look at another chapter
in the same book,
Revelation chapter 19
—Revelation chapter 19.
And we’re going to read starting at verse 19
right through to 21.
We might mention before we start reading it
that here it describes
political organizations, kings,
and those who oppose
Jesus and Jehovah God.
And in a symbolic way,
it refers to these as beasts,
as organizations,
that have disrupted the peace.
Let’s see what happens to them:
“And I saw the wild beast
and the kings of the earth and their armies
“gathered together to wage war
against the one seated on the horse
“and against his army
[now, that one is Jesus Christ].
“And the wild beast was caught,
“and along with it the false prophet
“that performed in front of it the signs
“with which he misled those who received
the mark of the wild beast
“and those who worship its image.
“While still alive,
“they both were hurled into the fiery lake
that burns with sulfur.”
So, what happens
to these political organizations
in opposition to Jehovah and Jesus?
Again, we see the word
“hurled” down into destruction.
And what about the rest of mankind
that opposes Jesus’ rule?
Well, let’s look at verse 21.
What does it say?
“But the rest were killed off
“with the long sword
that proceeded out of the mouth
“of the one seated on the horse.
And all the birds
were filled with their flesh.”
Now, that’s a very interesting comment,
isn’t it?
It helps us to see here
that all those who oppose Jesus
will be destroyed
in the battle of Armageddon.
So that’s another step
in getting ready for universal peace.
First of all, Satan is cast out of heaven.
And then secondly, at Armageddon,
all those humans who rebelled against Jesus
and reject his rule
will be taken away, destroyed.
But there’s something else too.
Let’s look at chapter 20 of Revelation
—chapter 20 and verses 1-3:
“And I saw an angel coming down
out of heaven with the key of the abyss
“and a great chain in his hand.
“He seized the dragon, the original serpent,
“who is the Devil and Satan,
“and bound him for 1,000 years.
“And he [notice the word again]
hurled him into the abyss
“and shut it and sealed it over him,
“so that he would not mislead
the nations anymore
“until the 1,000 years were ended.
After this he must be released
for a little while.”
What do we notice from this description?
You see, gradually, in a progressive manner,
Jesus will eradicate and remove
those who disrupt peace.
So Satan and his demons
are cast down to the earth.
At the battle of Armageddon,
those who rebelled will be destroyed.
And then Satan will be put
in a symbolic prison, in this abyss,
for 1,000 years along with his demons.
So that’s the first action
that Jesus needs to do
—to get rid of these troublemakers.
That opens up the way
for what the Bible refers to
as the Thousand Year Reign of Jesus Christ
with his Kingdom and corulers.
What is going to happen
during that Thousand Year Reign?
Remember we said that it’s not
a Band-Aid-type solution, is it?
He will need to help
mankind and the earth to heal.
Notice, please, how this is described for us
in a scripture that we’ve already read.
Let’s turn to it again—1 John 3:8.
Remember in the beginning of that verse,
that’s where it told us how universal peace
was disrupted in the beginning,
at the time when that angel
became the Devil and started sinning.
But notice what it says
in the second part of this verse:
“For this purpose
“the Son of God was made manifest,
[to do what?]
to break up [or to destroy]
the works of the Devil.”
Isn’t that an amazing concept?
Jesus not only removes
those who disrupt peace,
but he will “break up
the works of the Devil,”
the things that he’s done
over these thousands of years
that he’s been ruling this earth.
That means all the evil,
all the suffering, death,
all of that will be taken away.
Mankind will be gradually healed.
Now, Jesus started to break up
the works of the Devil
when he willingly gave his life as a ransom.
So even now we have the opportunity
to gain a measure of peace
with Jehovah and with others.
We can ask Jehovah for forgiveness
based on the ransom sacrifice.
But during the Thousand Year Reign,
there will be further things
that Jesus will accomplish.
Notice these three aspects:
He will undo all harm.
Now, that includes sickness, war,
disease, famine, all these problems;
all the harm will be undone.
He will also undo death
by resurrecting those who have died.
And he will also undo sin
by helping mankind to grow to perfection.
Isn’t that a beautiful promise,
undoing all these works of the Devil?
And then by the end of the thousand years,
what will we see with regard to the earth?
It will be a paradise.
It will be exactly
as Jehovah purposed it to be
in the beginning.
Yes, Jesus, by means of the Kingdom,
will have completely broken up
the works of the Devil.
Now, is that the time then
when universal peace is restored?
No, not quite yet.
Why not?
Something else has to happen.
And we’re going to reread another scripture,
and that’s Romans 16.
Remember we referred to that
in the beginning.
Here we see a very interesting connection
between two different things.
So that’s Romans 16:20:
“For his part, the God who gives peace
“[will do what?]
will crush Satan under your feet shortly.”
Do we see the connection here?
Universal peace is connected
with the crushing of Satan the Devil.
So universal peace can only be restored
after Satan has been destroyed.
Now, what events will occur
leading up to Satan’s destruction?
Well, remember,
as we read already in Revelation,
Satan is going to be allowed
to be released from that prison
(the symbolic prison),
and he’ll have an opportunity
to try to mislead
people who are living on the earth
at that time.
Those who join Satan
will be destroyed forever.
Then Satan will be permanently destroyed.
But what will happen to those perfect persons
who prove faithful to Jehovah?
Let’s see what the Bible says
if we turn to the book of Romans,
Romans 8:21
—Romans 8:21:
“That the creation itself
“will also be set free
from enslavement to corruption
“and have the glorious freedom
of the children of God.”
What does that really mean?
It means that at that point,
everyone will become part
of Jehovah’s universal family.
All intelligent creatures
in heaven and on earth
will be united as one family
in the pure worship
of the one true God, Jehovah.
What a beautiful time that will be!
But what further blessings
are involved with this process
of gradually bringing universal peace?
Well, during the Thousand Year Reign
of Jesus,
there’s going to be wonderful blessings.
Those who are obedient
to Jehovah and Jesus
will experience the things
that were described
in the Bible book of Psalms, in Psalm 72.
Let’s turn there together
—Psalm 72.
And here we see portrayed
some very interesting prophetic statements
about the Thousand Year Reign.
You’ll notice at the beginning,
it says regarding Solomon—
So although initially
this was referring to an extent
with regard to Solomon,
Jesus mentioned
that he’s greater than Solomon.
So this has a prophetic application
to the Thousand Year Reign.
Let’s see what it says about peace.
Starting in verse 1,
we’ll go through to verse 4:
“O God, give your judgments to the king,
“and endow the son of the king
with your righteousness.
“May he plead the cause of your people
with righteousness,
“and of your lowly ones with justice.
“May the mountains bring peace to the people,
“and may the hills bring righteousness.
“Let him defend the lowly among the people,
“let him save the sons of the poor,
and let him crush the defrauder.”
What a beautiful description
of what will happen
in the Thousand Year Reign!
Yes, all those under Satan’s rule
who were lowly, beaten up, disadvantaged
—all these will experience relief
because of the righteous rule
of Jesus Christ.
Let’s go down a little further
to verses 12 through 14.
It tells us a little more
about what Jesus will accomplish.
Starting in verse 12, we’re told:
“For he will rescue the poor
who cry for help,
“also the lowly one
and whoever has no helper.
“He will have pity on the lowly and the poor,
“and the lives of the poor he will save.
“From oppression and from violence
he will rescue them,
“[and notice
this very interesting expression]
and their blood will be
precious in his eyes.”
What does that mean?
“Their blood will be precious in his eyes.”
In the Bible, usually the word “blood”
is associated with life, isn’t it?
So it’s saying that each person’s life
will be precious to Jesus Christ.
What a beautiful description
of what will happen
during the Thousand Year Reign!
Then if we go back a little to verse 5,
we’ll notice that this part of the psalm
helps us to see
how widespread peace will be at that point.
It uses very picturesque language.
Notice there in verse 5, it says:
“They will fear you
as long as there is a sun
“[well, we know the sun continues on,
so they’ll continue to fear him]
“and as long as the moon remains,
“for generation after generation.
“He will be like the rain
that falls on the mown grass,
“like showers of rain that water the earth.
“In his days the righteous will flourish,
“and peace will abound
until the moon is no more.
“He will have subjects from sea to sea
and from the River to the ends of the earth.”
Yes, what a beautiful description
of the peaceful arrangements
that will prevail
during the Thousand Year Reign
of Jesus’ Kingdom!
But then the thousand years finishes.
What can we expect when that reign ends?
I’m sure you’re going to enjoy
our consideration
of a very special part of the Scriptures
—1 Corinthians chapter 15.
Please turn there with me,
and we’re going to go through
and look at what these verses tell us
about after the end
of the Thousand Year Reign.
The section of Scripture
we’re going to consider
is 1 Corinthians chapter 15,
verses 24-28.
Starting in verse 24, we’re told:
“Next, the end,
“when he hands over the Kingdom
to his God and Father,
“when he has brought to nothing
“all government and all authority and power.
“For he must rule as king
“until God has put
all enemies under his feet.
“And the last enemy, death,
“is to be brought to nothing.
“For God ‘subjected all things
under his feet.’
“But when he says
that ‘all things have been subjected,’
“it is evident that this does not include
“the One who subjected all things to him.
“But when all things
will have been subjected to him,
“then the Son himself
will also subject himself
“to the One who subjected all things to him,
that God may be all things to everyone.”
What do these verses tell us
about the end of the Thousand Year Reign?
Well, let’s go back to verse 24.
There it says: “Next, the end . . .”
Now, this “end” mentioned here
is not Armageddon.
This is the end of the Thousand Year Reign.
At the end of the Thousand Year Reign,
there are some other things too
that will have finished.
That means for a start,
the end of the Kingdom arrangement.
There will also be an end to sin,
which means that mankind will no longer need
the ransom or a mediator or priesthood.
And then in verse 26, notice it says:
“The last enemy, death,
is to be brought to nothing.”
In other words, the graves will be empty.
Those who have experienced the Adamic death
will have been brought back.
Mankind will all attain to perfection
with the end of sin
—Adamic sin.
So at that point in time,
something very, very special happens.
What is it?
Well, let’s go back
to the beginning of our discussion
when we talked about the problems
that occurred in the garden of Eden.
Remember, Satan the Devil raised some issues
that resulted in a symbolic court case
that involves the sanctification
of Jehovah’s name.
Yes, Satan had claimed
that Jehovah is a liar,
that he doesn’t rule mankind out of love,
and he even raised the question later
about who would actually serve Jehovah.
So this issue has continued on
—the issue of the sanctification
of Jehovah’s name—right down through history.
And over and over again,
Jehovah’s name has been sanctified.
His reputation has been vindicated.
We can see that he’s a loving God,
unlike Satan
—such a horrible person.
But Jehovah has stood out
as being a loving heavenly Father.
So now at this point in time,
we can say the universal court case
comes to a conclusion.
The issue is settled—the verdict is given.
In what way?
Well, Jesus has just finished ruling mankind
for a thousand years,
along with the 144,000
that have made the earth a paradise.
Mankind is now no longer sinners;
they’re perfect.
All the problems have been healed.
So at this point in time, what does Jesus do?
Does he follow the example of Satan
and say: ‘Well, you know,
‘I think we did a very, very good job
for this thousand years.
‘So let’s just keep everything in place,
and we’ll keep on ruling in the Kingdom.’
No, we saw what he does.
At that point in time,
there’s a marvelous answer in this court case
because Jesus hands over
the Kingdom back to his Father.
He submits to Jehovah’s rule.
And it’s just as if Jehovah
is told by his loving Son, Jesus:
“You were right all along.
“This whole thing
“has been a terrible travesty of justice.
Satan is a despicable liar.”
And all mankind, including Jesus
and the 144,000,
submit themselves to Jehovah’s rulership.
Yes, the end of the universal issue.
Jehovah will then rule directly
over perfect mankind.
But is that the point in time
when universal peace is restored?
No, remember, there are some other things
that need to occur.
We’ve already mentioned
that Satan will be released
from his symbolic prison.
He’ll have an opportunity
to try and mislead some.
And for those who side with him,
Jehovah morally and ethically
doesn’t have to wait any longer
and say: ‘Well, let’s have
another court case.’
No, they are executed immediately.
But what about the rest of mankind?
They become Jehovah’s sons and daughters.
They can talk to him directly
without the need of a mediator.
And then names will be written permanently
in “the book of life.”
They’ll be approved
to live forever in Paradise.
So at this point, when we’re thinking
about all these beautiful things
that will occur,
let’s enjoy the final video
of our convention.
It highlights the blessings
of the Thousand Year Reign and beyond.
And also, we’re going to listen
to the original song that we will sing
at the conclusion of our program.
Like an island of calm
In dark stormy seas,
God’s people
are living in peace.
With our eyes of faith,
We see beyond the clouds
And know that the storm
soon will cease.
To the ends of the earth,
There’ll be peace at last
For all eternity.
From the valleys below
To the mountaintops,
All creation will see
Peace at last.
When the new world is here,
All will be one
On earth
and in heaven above.
And the peace we’ll know
We’ve never known before—
A world ruled
by justice and love.
To the ends of the earth,
There’ll be peace at last
For all eternity.
From the valleys below
To the mountaintops,
All creation will see
Peace at last.
To the ends of the earth,
There’ll be peace at last
For all eternity.
From the valleys below
To the mountaintops,
All creation will see.
To the ends of the earth,
There’ll be peace at last
For all eternity.
From the valleys below
To the mountaintops,
All creation will see
Peace at last,
Peace at last!
What a beautiful song!
And what beautiful images to encourage us!
So brothers and sisters, we’ve enjoyed
our convention program, haven’t we?
Let us be determined to keep pursuing peace,
not an imitation peace, but the real peace.
We can enjoy rich blessings now
by having a peaceful relationship
with Jehovah God,
yes, trying to continue
to maintain peace with one another
and also attaining to this inner peace
—calmness and tranquility—
because we have friendship
with the God who gives us hope.
And that hope helps us to look to the future,
even though we have difficulties now,
and we look forward to the time
when universal peace is finally restored.
But in the meantime, may the God of peace
be with each one of you now and forever!
Thank you, Brother Jackson.
Your talk and this entire convention
have strengthened our confidence
in Jehovah’s prophetic Word
and helped us to understand
how close we are to its fulfillment.
On behalf of the Governing Body
and all the hardworking members
of our Bethel families
and translation offices around the world,
we thank you for watching
the 2022 convention program.
We have deep appreciation and affection
for each one of you,
and it is our prayer
that Jehovah continue
to bless you with peace.
Let’s conclude by singing a song
that reflects the complete peace
that Jehovah will soon bring about.
Please join in singing
the original song
“Peace at Last!”
which we heard during the concluding talk.
After the song,
you may have your concluding prayer
at your individual locations.
Now we invite all to sing out along
with the Watchtower chorus
“Peace at Last!”