This convention program will be translated
into more than 400 languages.
This work is supported
by branch offices around the globe.
Each of us has an opportunity
to show appreciation
for the spiritual blessings
we have received in our own language.
One way we can do this
is by making voluntary gifts
in accord with our circumstances.
Donations can be made online
at donate.jw.org.
Please be seated.
Have you faced serious obstacles
as you try to do what Jehovah commands?
How can servants of God
maintain their joy despite such challenges?
We invite you to watch and learn
from the drama
Nehemiah: “The Joy of Jehovah
Is Your Stronghold”—Part I.
As we learned in our audio drama,
the Jews returned to Jerusalem
to rebuild the temple in 537 B.C.E.
And by 515 B.C.E., it was finally completed.
However, the city’s walls were still left in ruins.
Jehovah’s time had now come to rebuild the walls,
and he used the faithful man Nehemiah
to take the lead in this work.
This would be a massive undertaking for the Jews.
And once again, there were opposers.
Nehemiah told the nation of Israel
that “the joy of Jehovah is your stronghold.”
How could he encourage them to be joyful
despite all the opposition?
What lessons can we learn from their example?
There are many,
but here are three to think about as you watch:
What role did prayer play in helping Nehemiah
to be a courageous person for Jehovah?
In addition to direct attacks,
what schemes did the enemies employ
to oppose the work?
Despite setbacks,
what was Nehemiah’s main source of joy?
Got it?
All right, then, with that in mind, please sit back
and enjoy the following video presentation
“The Joy of Jehovah Is Your Stronghold.”
It was a privilege to have a share
in the restoration of Jehovah’s worship.
People know we rebuilt the wall,
but there is so much more to the story.
Let’s start at the beginning.
In the 20th year of King Artaxerxes Longimanus,
I was in Shushan the palace.
I was cupbearer to the king.
He trusted me with his life.
Although I was far from Jerusalem,
I found great joy just thinking
about our people there serving Jehovah
—until one day when I received a visit
from my brother Hanani.
That visit changed everything.
What’s going on, Hanani?
How are our people?
Not good.
The conditions are disgraceful.
The walls of Jerusalem are broken down,
and its gates have been burned with fire.
What about the temple?
It stands,
but the services are nothing but empty rituals.
Most of the people and the priests ignore God’s Law.
You have to return with us.
For days, my conscience plagued me.
Would the king even allow me to go?
Our people had sinned
by not keeping Jehovah’s commandments,
but now I felt as if I were sinning
by not helping them in their time of need.
I begged Jehovah to grant me success.
Nehemiah,
why are you so gloomy when you’re not sick?
This can be nothing but gloominess of heart.
Why should I not look gloomy
when the city,
the place where my forefathers are buried,
lies in ruins,
and its gates have been consumed by fire?
Nehemiah, what is this?
Speak frankly.
What are you seeking?
At once, I prayed to the God of the heavens.
If it pleases the king
and if your servant has found favor with you,
send me to Judah,
to the city where my forefathers are buried,
and let me rebuild it.
You may go.
Jehovah was with us.
The king gave me supplies,
an army,
and an appointment as governor.
We were on our way to help rebuild Jerusalem’s walls.
I had seen a portion of the city,
but it wasn’t until I rose
by night to inspect the walls
that I saw just how badly God’s city had been treated.
Wait here.
I couldn’t believe the destruction.
The time had come
to reveal Jehovah’s purpose for Jerusalem.
I gathered the leaders.
Who is this man?
I’m told he’s Nehemiah, cupbearer to the king.
What does he want from us?
Men!
The holy city is completely vulnerable.
Let us rebuild the walls of Jerusalem,
so that this disgrace will not continue.
But what will our neighbors think?
Yes, we have many powerful enemies.
Artaxerxes commissioned me
to rebuild the walls and the entire city.
Didn’t you see the horsemen he sent
and all the timber?
He gave it all!
Brothers, the good hand of our God was upon me.
He is the one to fear, not men.
He will give us success.
Not everyone was happy
that we had come to do something good
for the people of Israel.
So that’s what this Nehemiah is up to.
Geshem, do you see what I’m seeing?
Without a wall,
we can keep the Jews under control.
If they rebuild it,
the Jews won’t need our land or resources.
That means he’s planning to rebel.
We can’t let him.
We must act, and act together.
Are you with me?
You have my support.
And mine, as always.
Good!
We must go to Jerusalem to keep an eye on Nehemiah.
The opposers wanted to maintain control
and to profit from Jehovah’s people.
They wasted little time trying to intimidate us.
Who are these?
That’s Sanballat, governor of Samaria.
Next to him is Tobiah, an Ammonite official
and landowner to many of our people.
They all look up to him.
That’s Geshem;
he’s a very wealthy Arabian and close ally to Sanballat.
Nehemiah, are you rebelling against the king?
The king himself gave us the authority.
To rebuild the city and the wall?
To rebuild the city and the wall
is what the king expects us to do.
Why did you not consult with me?
I am the governor of Samaria.
Well, yes, but the king appointed
Nehemiah as governor of Judah.
So why have you not asked for our help?
We worship Jehovah too.
We’ve sacrificed to him for generations.
Along with sacrifices to all of your other gods.
The God of the heavens
is the One that will grant us success,
and we, his servants,
will get up and build.
No one should let his religious beliefs
come before national unity.
You have neither share
nor claim nor memorial in Jerusalem.
Sanballat,
could it be you
who is rebelling against the highest King of all?
Despite opposition,
the people worked strenuously.
Nehemiah, these things have to go somewhere.
Their struggles went far beyond building a wall.
Jehovah remembers brothers like Peleth.
Seeing how he dealt with personal challenges
strengthened my faith.
Peleth.
Raham.
We’ll never finish this work.
It’s nothing but rubble.
At least we’re trying to make a change.
Always an optimist.
By the way, you’re late on your rent
—again.
Raham, I’m sorry;
I need more time.
With the work on the wall, . . .
I have enough troubles.
Look, if I don’t get payment
by the end of the month,
you and your family are out.
Is there anything we can do?
Maybe I can work it off till we get caught up.
Seriously?
You don’t have time to work it off,
but maybe your daughter can help.
She can come stay with us.
As a slave?
No, I’ll hire her to help Azubah
—to pay off your debt.
Look, I’m trying to help,
but you don’t have many options here, my friend.
Think about it.
So Raham spoke to me today.
About what?
He wants to hire Simcha to help Azubah in the house.
He says he’ll care for her like his own daughter.
Imma, I’ve known Raham and Azubah
ever since I came here with Ezra.
Raham helped us.
Our house belongs to him.
I don’t trust him.
He wants our Simcha to live with him?
Imma, . . .
What about Jehovah’s command
that parents raise their own children?
Don’t you want her to have a better life?
I-I cannot agree
to having her live apart from us,
even if we have to survive on gleanings.
How do you know we’ll survive at all?
Because Jehovah always takes care
of those who love and obey him.
Men like Peleth threw their burden on Jehovah
and kept working.
Sanballat set up camp near Jerusalem
to keep an eye on our progress.
So, what is it?
My lord.
Yes?
The wall
—it’s up to half its height all around the city.
This has gone too far!
Geshem, how long will it take
to assemble an attack force?
Attack force?
My lord, Sanballat, an attack on the Jews
would be an attack on the king.
What are you talking about?
He’s right.
Nehemiah has authorization from Artaxerxes himself.
You saw how many horsemen the king sent with him.
Yes!
Would you be talking like this if those horsemen
were still here?
And they can come back.
Nonsense!
Never mind the horsemen.
This is my province!
Out here, I decide what to do.
Now, we need to threaten them.
Geshem, you bring Samaritan troops
and come in from this way.
They’re preparing to attack us!
How do you know that?
I heard them talking.
Brothers, please.
Have they attacked anyone yet?
They must have.
He saw something.
Are you going to wait until they start killing us?
Of course not!
Hanani,
post men by families at the lowest parts of the wall
—at all the exposed places.
Yes, Nehemiah.
That’s not going to work.
Brothers,
if we let mere threats frighten us into stopping,
they will have achieved their goal.
It’s no use. Don’t you see?
These people hate what we’re doing.
They hate us.
You don’t have to live and work around them like we do.
Brothers,
where is your faith?
It is Jehovah’s will that we build this wall.
If it is really Jehovah’s will,
then why are we getting all this opposition?
Maybe this isn’t the right time.
Besides, this work is too much for us.
We’re worn out.
Why do we need a wall anyway?
To protect Jehovah’s people.
Brothers,
do not be afraid of them.
Remember Jehovah,
who is great and awe-inspiring;
and fight for your brothers,
your sons and daughters,
your wives and homes.
So when you hear the sound of the horn,
gather together to where we are.
Our God will fight for us.
Listen for this signal.
The threats aren’t working.
The next sound they hear will be our battle cry.
Wait!
We already spoke about this.
A direct attack would be seditious.
Besides, they’ve armed themselves.
Wait!
My-my lord,
Geshem is right.
We’d never get away with this.
Don’t you recall who commissioned Nehemiah?
It was the king.
It was the king of Persia, let me remind you.
Nehemiah is setting himself up as a king.
I recommend we turn the accusation of sedition
against Nehemiah.
That’s brilliant!
Yes,
he will beg for our help.
Let’s go back to Samaria.
Hanani,
you look like you’ve been working.
I must smell like it too.
Yes!
Yes, you do.
Brothers!
Brothers, we are well on our way to completing the wall.
Jehovah is helping us,
but we must not let our hands drop.
From now on,
we will all spend the night inside Jerusalem.
We will take turns keeping watch.
Hanani will give out assignments.
Good work today.
Everyone was working hard on the wall.
But there were more issues to contend with.
My brothers, how can I help you?
Nehemiah, we, with our sons and daughters, are many.
We need food to stay alive.
We gave our fields and vineyards
and houses as security to get grain during
the food shortage.
We borrowed money
on our fields and our vineyards to pay the king’s tribute.
And we’ve had to sell some of our children into slavery.
We’re powerless to stop this
because our fields and vineyards belong to others.
Thank you for bringing this to my attention.
I must ponder all this.
Thank you, Nehemiah.
Thank you.
Hanani, please tell all the nobles
and deputy rulers to come to me
first thing tomorrow morning.
With God’s help, we can make this right.
Men of Judah,
each of you is demanding interest from your brother.
You should be ashamed of yourselves.
Should you not walk in the fear of our God
so that the nations, our enemies,
cannot reproach us?
Let us, please, stop this lending on interest.
Please restore to them their fields,
vineyards, olive groves, houses,
and the interest.
Nehemiah, I will restore the fields this day at sunset.
We all will restore these things to our brothers.
Before Jehovah,
do you swear to these promises?
We do!
May the true God shake out from his house
every man who does not carry out this promise.
Amen!
Meshullam,
we must inform Tobiah about this.
This will be successful.
Jehovah will bless it.
Raham!
I bring good news.
Is that so?
Yes.
We have your rent.
Oh?
Come by anytime and collect it.
But I thought we—
What about Simcha?
She’ll be staying with us.
Well, how were you able to put it together so quickly?
Jehovah always takes care of those
who love and obey him.
Ever since Nehemiah got here,
things have been getting better and better.
Nehemiah thinks we’re still as young
as when we came here with Ezra.
I’ve worked hard.
But now Nehemiah treats us like it all fell out of heaven,
and we just have to pick it up.
I worked hard for what I have, didn’t I?
Yes, you worked hard.
If I give back my fields,
what am I to eat?
What am I to drink?
What’s wrong with lending on interest?
You borrow, you pay with interest.
Raham, Jehovah just wants us
to treat our brothers fairly, doesn’t he?
Haven’t you heard a word I said?
I treat everyone fairly!
Then why are you so angry?
I’m not angry!
Why are you talking to me like this?
I just feel betrayed.
By whom?
By the people I’ve lent money to!
What can I do about it?
Only what a wife is supposed to do!
Give me a son!
If not a son, then a daughter.
I cannot give you what Jehovah does not give us.
One day,
it will be too late.
I say we write a letter to the king.
Well, let’s see what the boy reports when he returns.
My lord, Sanballat.
Now what?
The wall has no more gaps.
What?
How can they advance so quickly?
Also, there’s a letter for Tobiah.
Nehemiah is forcing
landlords to return their fields to the original owners.
We’re running out of time.
Enough!
Tell this to Nehemiah:
“Come, and let us set a time
to meet together in the Valley Plain of Ono.”
They’re trying to lure me away from Jerusalem
to do me harm.
Please, tell your master:
“I am engaged in a great work,
“and I am not able to go down.
“Why should the work stop
while I leave it to come to you?”
They sent me the same message several times.
Each time I gave them the same response.
My lord, he has rejected your offer a fourth time.
Geshem,
it’s time to implement your plan.
Tobiah,
write this down:
“Among the nations it has been heard,
“and Geshem is also saying it,
“that you and the Jews
“are scheming to rebel.
That is why you are building the wall.”
Yes?
Give this to Nehemiah.
Tell your master:
“None of the things you are saying have taken place.
You are making them up out of your own imagination.”
They’re bluffing.
They’re trying to frighten us into stopping the work.
Yes, they know that the king won’t change his decree.
But believe me, they won’t stop.
Jehovah, I pray,
strengthen my hands.
What can we do to stop him?
We don’t have much time.
The wall is almost complete.
Sanballat,
I think I know a way.
Shemaiah, you called for me.
Yes!
Quickly!
You are in great danger.
And so am I because I know about it.
Talk sense, man!
What danger?
They’re coming to kill you—by night!
We must go into the temple and close the doors.
Shemaiah,
should a man like me run away?
You don’t understand.
What would that do to the spirit of the entire nation?
It’s the only safe place.
Besides, I’m not a priest.
If I entered the temple,
that would be valid reason to kill me.
I will not go in.
That decision would be foolish, Nehemiah.
Oh, I see!
Tobiah and Sanballat put you up to this,
didn’t they, you hypocrite?
May Jehovah remember them
and all of you false prophets
who keep trying to frighten me.
Come, Hanani,
we have work to do.
Argh!
We just kept working day and night.
But before we knew it,
we were finishing the very last section of the wall.
Jehovah helped us to achieve the impossible.
We were tired,
but we discovered something we had lost
—joy.
Nehemiah, the wall is complete!
Yeah! Yes!
That’s it.
In just 52 days.
My lord, it’s from Shemaiah.
What does it say?
The wall is complete.
Only the doors are left to be put in.
Sanballat, we must act quickly.
Sanballat . . .
Stop it, Tobiah.
No, there’s still time.
Write that letter to the king.
Tobiah,
don’t you see?
God must be helping the Jews.
It’s over.
We’ll lose all control over them.
This isn’t over.
Rebuilding the walls was only the beginning.
We would definitely need God’s help
for what was coming next.
Are you now eager to see
the conclusion of the drama?
We will enjoy Part II
during the final session of this convention.
The account of Nehemiah teaches us
to trust in Jehovah
as we carry out our assigned work.
Throughout this session
and the preceding one,
we have been focusing
on the vital work
of making disciples.
Do you recall the key lessons?
Also, what disciple-making work
do we look forward to in the future?
Please pay close attention
to Brother Stephen Lett of the Governing Body
as he delivers the talk
“Making Disciples Now Prepares Us
for New World Disciple-Making.”
There are many things in life
that prepare a person for greater things.
For example, elementary school
prepares a student for high school.
Running shorter races
prepares a person to run a marathon.
Working as an apprentice
prepares a worker to serve as a professional.
Well, in this talk, we’re going to discuss
how disciple-making now prepares us
for the greater disciple-making work
in the new world.
But first, let’s briefly discuss
how making disciples right now
brings a lot of joy.
Please turn to Psalm 105.
Now, this is the theme scripture
for today’s program,
Psalm 105:3:
“Boast about his holy name.
Let the hearts
of those seeking Jehovah rejoice.”
Notice, we’re encouraged
to “boast about [Jehovah’s] holy name.”
How do we do this?
Well, by preaching, teaching,
helping others come to know
Jehovah and his purposes.
And what is the result of this?
Well, honesthearted ones respond favorably,
and they begin to seek Jehovah.
And how are they affected?
Well, as the second part of that verse read,
that their hearts overflow with ‘rejoicing.’
Now, taking it a little further,
how are we affected
when we’re able to help someone
start seeking Jehovah
and get on that road to everlasting life?
Well, it makes our hearts rejoice,
isn’t that true?
And in fact, there are
very few things in life
that can bring more joy
than helping someone start seeking Jehovah
and get on that narrow road to life.
I mean, think about it.
To explain Bible truth to them,
to see their face light up
as little light bulbs
start going off in their mind
as they’re learning these truths,
to see them start making changes
in their life to please Jehovah,
to see them become an unbaptized publisher
and come up from that baptismal pool
and maybe later get into the pioneer work
—there’s nothing this world can offer
(no accomplishment, no paycheck)
that can equal the joy
of helping someone start seeking Jehovah.
Appropriately,
throughout this second day
of our program,
We have been taught many ways
we can improve in our disciple-making skills,
because it is vital that we do so
and because eternal lives
hang in the balance.
And what is the value of one eternal life?
Well, one brother said,
“If all of Jehovah’s Witnesses pioneered
“until the end came and one person
learned the truth, it would be worth it.”
That’s the value of one life.
In fact, with all the money, the gold,
the silver, and the diamonds combined,
you could not buy one eternal life.
It’s priceless.
Not one but almost 304,000 thousand
were helped to the point of baptism
during the last service year
as a result of Jehovah blessing
the disciple-making skills of his people.
But as we mentioned before,
learning disciple-making skills now
prepares us for the even greater
disciple-making work of the new world.
In fact, let’s talk
about how vast this work will be
—this educational work in the new world.
Think about it, millions
have been made disciples
during these last years of the last days.
But in the new world, apparently,
billions of disciples will need to be made.
How much greater is a billion than a million?
One thousand times greater!
So we’re talking about thousands of times
more disciples
needed to be made then than now.
And likely, we will carry on
this work of disciple-making
in the new world for centuries,
not just decades,
as is the case in the last days.
And that is really something
to think about, isn’t it?
In fact, it makes us think of what Jesus said
to his disciples at John 14:12.
He told them,
‘You will do works greater than I am doing.’
So, really, we could say that
that disciple-making work
of the new world will be greater.
More people will be witnessed to
and will be made disciples
—a larger area, a longer period of time.
And undoubtedly,
disciple-making in the new world
will be even more joyful
than disciple-making now.
Now, we said before, it’s
an indescribable joy to make a disciple now.
But why will it be even more enjoyable?
Well, think about the environment.
Satan the Devil will be gone.
That’ll be like a 100-pound block
off of all our shoulders.
The spirit of the world will no longer exist
—that spirit of the world exhaled by Satan—
because Satan will be locked in the abyss;
and, you could say, it’ll be airtight.
He’ll not be able to exhale
the spirit of the world from there.
One government will rule the entire earth.
All human governments will be gone.
And think of this, never again
—never, ever—
will the unrighteous outnumber the righteous.
They will always be the minority.
So this wonderful environment
will undoubtedly make disciple-making
even more exhilarating in the new world.
But now let’s think for a moment
about how voluminous the work itself will be.
John 5:28, 29 says that “all those
“in the memorial tombs
will hear [Jesus’] voice and come out”
—all in the tombs.
Who will be included among these ones
that will come out of “the memorial tombs”?
Well, open up to Acts chapter 24,
and let’s notice who will be included
—Acts 24:15:
“And I have hope toward God,
“which hope these men also look forward to,
“that there is going to be a resurrection
of both the righteous and the unrighteous.”
So, you notice, it’s guaranteed.
It is going to happen
—not maybe or a good possibility.
It’s going to happen!
And it’s going to include
“the righteous and the unrighteous.”
But now here’s a question:
Why will the righteous
who are resurrected
need further education?
Well, even though
they’re already servants of God,
they will need to learn details
concerning fulfilled prophecies,
the outworking of God’s purposes,
things that have happened since they died.
They’ll need to be
brought up to speed, so to speak.
And how much they’ll need to be taught
will depend largely upon
how long ago they died.
They will also need help
to continue in their righteous course
and to obey the things
written in the scrolls.
Revelation 20:12 talks
about these new scrolls.
It says: “I saw the dead,
the great and the small,
“standing before the throne,
and scrolls were opened. . . .
“The dead were judged
out of those things written
in the scrolls according to their deeds.”
And The Watchtower said this
about those new scrolls.
It said: “These scrolls
will most likely set forth
“Jehovah’s requirements
for mankind at that time.
“By studying these, all people,
including resurrected ones,
“will be able to know God’s will for them.
“These scrolls will surely give us
further insight into Jehovah’s mind.”
That’s exciting, indeed, to ponder, isn’t it?
Included among the righteous
to be resurrected
will be faithful ones
who will be brought back
to serve as “princes.”
Psalm 45:16 says that Jesus
will appoint “princes in all the earth.”
And The Watchtower pointed out
that one example would be Daniel.
Do you remember what Jehovah
promised him shortly before he died?
He said, “You will rest,
but you will stand up
for your lot at the end of the days.”
Well, he’s rested
in the grave for some 2,500 years,
but he will “stand up” in the resurrection.
And he’ll take his position
as one of these princes,
as pointed out in The Watchtower.
Now, of course, Daniel and others like him
will need to be brought up to speed
—updated, trained for their assignments.
Also, many of the princes will be selected
from the faithful elders
who are taking the lead today,
as pointed out by The Watchtower.
But, of course, Jesus, the Messianic King,
will make the appointments.
So, what do we know?
They will be good appointments.
They will be princes
who will truly love the people
and faithfully carry out all the directions
of the heavenly government.
Also included among “the righteous”
to be resurrected
will be many of our loved ones
who may have thought they would live
to see the end of this system,
but they died in the last days.
But now, what a joy it will be
for you brothers and sisters
to welcome these ones back and teach them
about all the things
that have happened since they died!
They’ll need to be brought up-to-date
so they can help
in this great disciple-making work.
An example: I think of my mother.
She was baptized in 1938.
She died in 2012,
a little over eight years ago.
She really wanted to see
the end of this system.
And she was
of that “Judge Rutherford generation.”
She really wanted to see
that “prostitute” destroyed,
but cancer prevented that from happening.
And I remember
shortly before she died, I said:
“Mom, I know you wanted
to go into the new world
“on the overland passageway
(never die at all).
“But you’re going to have
to take the underground tunnel.
“But the main thing is to get there.
“And you’re going to
very shortly close your eyes,
“and the next thing you’re going to see,
you’re going to open your eyes
in that new world.”
But when she comes back,
just think of the things that have happened
in the eight years that she’s been gone.
She’ll have to be
brought up to speed, won’t she?
“This is JW Broadcasting®
from the World Headquarters
of Jehovah’s Witnesses.”
She doesn’t even know about the broadcast!
She’ll have to be brought up to speed,
but she’ll be so happy
to learn about this and other developments.
But now here’s a question:
Where will the billions
of new disciples come from?
Even though the resurrected righteous ones
will need to be educated,
they’re already disciples, aren’t they?
So where will the new disciples come from?
Well, ones born after Armageddon
will need to be made disciples.
Also, there will be a vast multitude
of unrighteous ones
who will return from the Grave.
Now, they’ll come
from all different backgrounds.
And they’ll come back,
and they’ll need to be taught.
They’ll need help to accept Christ’s ransom,
to obey the things
that are written in the new scrolls,
because most of them will know nothing.
Now, maybe some studied a while,
but death prevented them from continuing.
But most will know nothing
—completely unaware about the good news.
And as we said, they’ll come
from all time periods, locations, cultures.
Some may have been rulers, maybe slaves,
maybe criminals,
maybe self-righteous persons,
maybe ones who died in combat,
died in childbirth,
died of disease
(perhaps the coronavirus),
died by starvation, natural disaster.
And it seems that the last thought
on their mind when they died
will be the first thought
when they come back.
I was thinking about the men who threw
the three Hebrews into the fiery furnace,
and they died because of the heat.
They’ll come back
with a vivid memory of that situation,
and yet they’ll have to be taught
what happened after they died
—how those three Hebrews
came out unharmed.
Just imagine all these backgrounds
of ones coming back.
Imagine situations that could develop.
Here is just an example.
Imagine a former ruler
who had hundreds,
maybe thousands, of slaves
who catered to his every desire.
Now, he comes back in the resurrection,
and his overseer is one of his former slaves.
And he tells him, gives him direction
(loving direction, but direction)
to plant a tree in a certain location.
Now, will he humble himself?
Interesting, interesting possibilities.
Think of the atheists
who will be resurrected.
Here they ate Jehovah’s food,
they drank his water,
they breathed his air,
they walked on his ground,
they never gave him any credit,
they never acknowledged him at all.
It makes us think of the illustration
of the pig under the apple tree.
He gobbles up the apples off the ground,
but he never looks up to see
where they came from.
Now, we may not use that illustration
with these atheists that come back,
but they will have to be helped to see
what a selfish life they lived.
And now they’re
going to have to praise Jehovah,
acknowledge him, give him honor,
glory, and worship.
Will they do so?
Well, it will be up to them.
But you brothers and sisters
will help such ones.
In fact, let’s just ponder
some of these ones that will come back
by means of some artwork.
Now, look at the following artwork, please.
And it’s going to show you people
from different time periods,
different backgrounds,
being taught after they’re resurrected.
And as the artwork displays,
try to imagine yourself teaching ones
of these various backgrounds.
And brothers and sisters, that artwork
is just a little, tiny sampling
of ones from various
time periods and backgrounds
who will return to the land of the living.
But, as we mentioned,
Jehovah will empower Jesus
to resurrect all of these ones
(bringing them back from the memorial tombs)
that will ‘hear his voice,
and they will come out.’
And we know it’ll be
in a controlled, orderly way.
See, Jehovah “is a God
not of disorder but of peace.”
—1 Corinthians 14:33.
He also wants things
to “take place decently and by arrangement.”
—1 Corinthians 14:40.
So if they all came back at once,
that would be
a chaotic population explosion, wouldn’t it?
They couldn’t even be taught properly.
They couldn’t be cared for.
We know it will be progressive
during the thousand years.
And The Watchtower said this:
“Faithful Christians who died
shortly before the end of Satan’s system
“will likely be among the first ones raised.
“We can also expect an early resurrection
for the faithful men of old
who will serve as ‘princes.’”
We touched on that previously.
Yes, resurrected ones
will have much to learn,
and you dear brothers and sisters
will have the privilege to help them.
They’ll need to learn
about Jehovah, his qualities,
all the wonderful things he’s done.
Many will need
to reject false religious ideas
that they believed in Satan’s world.
Here’s just an example:
Imagine one who really believed
that all good people go to heaven.
But now he’s resurrected,
and he’s brought back here to the earth.
Obviously, he’ll know
that teaching was wrong.
But what about other false teachings
that he believed?
Will he change his mind and heart?
Will he accept these truths?
It’ll be up to him.
But you brothers and sisters
will help such ones.
There’ll be many others
who will come back
who will have to abandon
their former way of life.
I was thinking, as an example, a homosexual.
Now, this former homosexual
comes back in the resurrection,
and he really thought
—and he was taught, and he came to believe—
that God accepted him with that lifestyle.
But now he’s going to learn
about Jehovah’s moral standards.
He’s going to learn
that Jehovah will not lower his standard
to accommodate us.
We have to come up to Jehovah’s standard.
Will he change?
Will he adjust?
It’ll be up to him.
But you brothers and sisters
will help such ones
to enjoy life eternal.
All must learn to walk
in Jehovah’s righteous ways
and willingly choose to do so.
But now, what if someone
refuses to make the necessary changes?
Well, The Watchtower commented on that.
It said: “After being given ample time,
“maybe even ‘a hundred years,’ to seek God,
“some will show that they refuse
to practice righteousness.
“Justly they will lose life
in that new world,
as we can see from Isaiah 65:20,” which says:
“And the sinner will be cursed,
even though he is a hundred years of age.”
But we expect this will be the minority,
that the majority will be delighted
to make the adjustments
so that they can live
in that wonderful new world.
But I think about what one brother told me
concerning his Bible student.
His Bible student kept saying:
“Well, how do I know
“I’m going to like life in the new world?
How do I know I’m not going to be bored?”
Well, finally, the brother told him, he said,
“Well, one thing about it:
If you don’t like being there,
you don’t have to stay.”
That was kind of humorous,
but it’s a lot of truth.
A person has to willingly want to be there
and make the necessary changes.
But we believe the vast majority
will be delighted to do so.
And what a privilege it will be
to teach ones
in that new world at a time
when Isaiah 11:9
will be true, which says:
“The earth will certainly be filled
with the knowledge of Jehovah
as the waters [are] cover[ing] the sea.”
I mean, think about it.
This earth—71 percent
of its surface is covered with water.
And if you smooth all the land out,
sea water would cover planet Earth
one and two thirds miles deep.
This is a watery planet, isn’t it?
Well, that illustration there in Isaiah
just shows how prolific
—how widespread, how filled—
the earth will be
“with the knowledge of Jehovah” at that time.
And that wonderful knowledge
will enable faithful humans
to grow to perfection
and to sufficiently be equipped
to face and pass the final test
at the end of the thousand years.
And the good things
that you dear brothers and sisters
have learned today
in the second day of our program
—what you’ve learned today
about helping your Bible students now—
will help you in the new world.
As you learned, you learned how to teach
your Bible students
to feed themselves spiritually,
to attend the meetings,
to avoid bad associations,
to overcome unclean habits,
to develop a personal relationship
with Jehovah.
Those very same things
you will need to teach these new ones
that come back in the resurrection.
So, at this time, let’s review
some of the good things
that we have learned today
about disciple-making.
And let’s meditate on how these skills
will help in the new world.
In fact, look at this video, please
—a brief video that gives us some highlights
from our first symposium,
which was entitled “Improve Your Skills.”
Since there’s no death or pain in heaven,
where would this promise apply?
The earth.
Would you like to learn
how to be part of that future?
If these are God’s promises,
wouldn’t it make sense to go to his Word
to find out how to enjoy them?
Maybe we can think of it this way.
When parents with a severe genetic defect
have children, what happens?
I get it!
No study is perfect.
She’s making some effort; focus on that.
If anyone’s enthusiasm
is contagious, it’s yours.
I can help, if you want.
The real question is, Do you trust him?
I want to; I really do.
As we saw in that video,
we want to improve our skills.
And in the symposium, we saw six areas
in which we can improve our skills.
And each one of the six videos
in that symposium
discussed one of those skills.
In review, Neeta, in the first video
(the Bible study conductor),
used questions to help the interested person
see the practical value of the Bible.
In the second video, the next time they met,
Neeta unleashed the power of God’s Word
by showing her student scriptures
that highlight our spiritual need.
In the third video,
Neeta illustrated Adamic sin
by likening it to inherited illness.
In the fourth video,
when her Bible student
seemed to be losing interest,
Neeta learned the importance
of enthusiasm to motivate.
In the fifth video,
Neeta showed empathy
for her student’s stressful circumstances
and provided practical help.
And then, in the last (the sixth) video,
Neeta’s conviction and Scriptural reasoning
helped to reach her student’s heart
so that she reconsidered her situation
and her views on morals.
Can you just imagine how you’ll use
those six skills in the new world?
Think about it.
You’ll use questions, won’t you?
You’ll use questions to help resurrected ones
see the practical value
of the Bible and the new scrolls.
And, by the way,
the Bible will be used in the new world.
You will unleash the power of God’s Word
and the power of the scrolls
by showing these new ones scriptures.
You will use good illustrations
to help them reason.
You will use enthusiasm to motivate.
You will show empathy,
especially for ones who have scars
as a result of a horrible life
in Satan’s old world.
You will also use conviction
and Scriptural reasoning
to reach their heart.
But now let’s move to our second symposium,
and it was entitled “Accept Jehovah’s Help.”
And we discussed three aids
that Jehovah gives us.
Let’s look at this brief video
that will remind us of that second symposium.
Her real issue was getting to know
someone that she can’t see.
Maybe that’s the best place to begin.
I did some research,
and I think you’ll really like what I found.
Come, come, sit down.
I’ve tried everything
to get Jade to a meeting.
Have you tried bringing
other people on the study?
You were in a band?
“So sweet.”
Ah, I love that song!
I actually have that vinyl.
Look, I know you’re busy.
You have no clue, do you?
I’ve got to go.
So I asked him to help Jade
and then left it with him.
Well, as reminded in that video,
Jehovah provides research tools,
he provides the brotherhood,
and he provides help by means of prayer.
And you’ll use those things
in the new world, obviously.
Just like Neeta, she used research tools
to prepare to discuss evolution
with her student.
When she realized
she had a limited understanding
of the student’s background,
she sought help from the brotherhood.
She brought along a publisher
who had a similar background to her student.
And in that third video,
when her student resisted
Neeta’s encouragement
to prepare for her Bible study,
Neeta prayed to Jehovah
to help her and to motivate the student.
And we know Jehovah hears prayers.
But imagine:
You’ll use research tools,
you’ll use the brotherhood,
you’ll use prayer
to make disciples in the new world.
But now let’s go to that third symposium:
“Help Your Bible Students to . . .”
And we talked about five things
we want to help them to do.
Let’s look at this video,
which will remind us of that third symposium.
Which do you remember more from our studies,
the answers or the things
that touch your heart?
Mm.
It’s asking how Jehovah feels about something
and then asking what that means for me.
My meeting part tonight covers that point.
Why don’t you come?
I’m having some people over this weekend.
It wasn’t the club, but it was still fun.
Beating it felt impossible.
“Be made new
in your dominant mental attitude.”
I remembered one of the Psalms:
“I will walk in your truth.
Unify my heart to fear your name.”
Well, as reminded, there are five things
we want to help our students to accomplish.
In that first video in the symposium,
Neeta helped her student learn
to feed herself spiritually by demonstrating
how she herself prepared for their study.
In the second video,
Neeta returned to the subject
of meeting attendance
by pointing out that the next meeting
would consider a question
she had raised previously.
In the third video,
Neeta helped her student
to seek good association
by arranging for her
to attend a Christian gathering.
Then in the fourth video,
when it became clear that the student
was not ready to be a publisher
because of an unclean practice,
Neeta gently helped her
to appreciate what it means
to become and remain clean in Jehovah’s eyes.
And then in the last video, that fifth one
—most important—
Neeta helped her student
to develop strong love for Jehovah
that would be so strong
that she would be able
to resist pressure from the world.
Well, you can imagine
that you’ll use the very same skills.
You’ll try to help your students there
to accomplish the same
five things we discussed.
You’ll help them to learn
to feed themselves spiritually.
You’ll help them to attend meetings.
You’ll help them to see the need
to seek out good association,
to avoid unclean practices
and, most important,
to develop deep love for Jehovah.
Yes, it’s obvious
that our skills, our experience,
our qualities learned now
in the disciple-making work
will be very valuable in the new world.
You’ll be able to put these skills
to good use then.
So let’s all strive to improve as teachers.
And that’s what Titus 1:9 says,
that we should
“[hold] firmly to the faithful word
as respects [our] art of teaching.”
And we want to be artists
—the “art of teaching.”
You may have heard
the difference between a laborer,
a craftsman, and an artist.
A laborer uses his back;
a craftsman has to add his mind;
but an artist adds his heart.
We don’t want to be
just laborers or craftsmen, but artists
—really putting our heart
into the disciple-making work.
And it does take effort.
Let’s look at one last scripture
here in 1 Timothy chapter 4
—the effort involved—
and it’s worth the effort.
First Timothy 4:15:
“Ponder over these things;
be absorbed in them,
“so that your advancement
“may be plainly seen by all people.
“Pay constant attention
to yourself and to your teaching.
“Persevere in these things, for by doing this
“you will save both yourself
and those who listen to you.”
That’s true now;
it will be true in the new world.
And Jehovah is providing what we need
—he’s giving us excellent training;
he provides excellent tools.
We want to make good use
of both of these provisions.
But we do want to give this caution:
Don’t be overwhelmed, please.
We’ve discussed a lot of skills,
a lot of suggestions,
but don’t be overwhelmed.
Jehovah is going to help you.
He will bless your efforts to do your best.
And we encourage you to just pick out
one or two skills at first and work on those.
And then you can move on to other things.
In conclusion, think about this:
There are many secular skills practiced today
that will not even exist in the new world.
Doctors (no doctors), nurses, optometrists,
undertakers, locksmiths, lawyers
—such professions will not even exist.
But your skills as a disciple-maker
will be in high demand.
You will be able
to use these skills to the full,
and you will definitely rejoice greatly
as you share in this voluminous,
this enormous,
new world educational campaign
soon to come.
Thank you, Brother Lett,
for that exciting preview
of the work that lies ahead of us!
This program has highlighted
the joy we can find in making disciples.
What can we look forward to
in the next two sessions?
The scripture theme for those sessions
is taken from Psalm 37:4, which says:
“Find exquisite delight in Jehovah,
and he will grant you
the desires of your heart.”
The next session begins with a symposium
that will show how we can imitate
the apostle Paul and others
by rejoicing in all circumstances.
In the final session,
we will enjoy the conclusion
of the Nehemiah drama,
followed by an uplifting closing talk.
Now let all in attendance stand,
if you are able to do so,
and sing together song number 140.
This song invites us
to imagine our future joy.
It is entitled “Life Without End—At Last!”
After the song, you may have
your local concluding prayer.
Again, that’s song number 140.