Welcome, one and all!
The concluding session of our
“Pursue Peace”! Convention is about to begin.
As you watch the music-video presentation,
reflect on how learning about our Creator
and speaking about him to others
can help us endure any test of faith
with joy and peace.
Please enjoy the video.
Welcome to the final portion
of this convention,
which corresponds to the Sunday
afternoon session on your program.
The theme scripture
is taken from Romans 15:13,
which says in part:
“May the God who gives hope
fill you with all joy and peace.”
To begin, let’s sing a song that describes
the blessings that God’s Kingdom will bring.
The song is number 23,
entitled “Jehovah Begins His Rule”
—song number 23.
In Part 1 of our feature Bible drama,
we saw how Jehovah gave peace
to his servants in the past.
As we near the conclusion
of this system of things,
how can we strengthen our confidence
that Jehovah will fulfill his promises
for the future?
We now invite you to watch Part 2
of the feature Bible drama
Jehovah Guides Us in the Way of Peace.
Bible prophecy is a fascinating subject.
Prophecy is far more than
just predictions about the future.
Jehovah knows all the facts.
He can even control and change factors
to ensure the outcome he desires.
At Isaiah 55:11, he says:
“My word that goes out of my mouth . . .
“will not return to me without results, . . .
and it will have sure success.”
Jehovah’s prophecies
have a perfect record of success.
He has led his people in the past.
So when he prophesies
that he’ll lead his people
to real, lasting peace in the future,
this isn’t a prediction; it’s a guarantee!
The prophecies given to Daniel
clearly show that God’s Kingdom
will without a doubt
bring lasting peace for all mankind.
I have found a man from the exiles of Judah
who can make known the interpretation to the king.
I know who he is.
Can you really make known to me
the dream that I saw
and its interpretation?
This is your dream.
Jehovah is the Great Timekeeper.
The prophetic portions of the book of Daniel
build faith by showing that Jehovah knows
the course of history centuries
—even millenniums—in advance.
While portions of these prophecies
were fulfilled in Daniel’s time,
many of the details are being fulfilled
right down to our day.
So as we discover
the significance of these prophecies,
we’re excited about what lies ahead.
And our confidence grows as we discern
how Jehovah has been leading
his people all along.
In the days of those kings,
the God of heaven will set up a kingdom
that will never be destroyed.
The divine dream
that Daniel interprets
for King Nebuchadnezzar
constitutes a prophecy
crucial for the lasting peace of mankind
—a promise from Jehovah
to set up a Kingdom
that would be vastly superior
to earthly kingdoms.
History has shown us
how every type
of human government imaginable has failed.
So how would Jehovah’s government come?
When would it arrive?
These were questions
Daniel himself likely had.
Jehovah is “a Revealer of secrets.”
He would eventually answer
these questions in due time.
As a diligent student of the Scriptures,
the prophet Daniel
had full faith and confidence
in Jehovah’s ability
to schedule events and bring them about.
And now likely in his 90’s,
Daniel was particularly interested
in prophecies regarding the restoration
of his beloved city, Jerusalem.
“When 70 years at Babylon are fulfilled,
“I will turn my attention to you,
“and I will make good my promise
by bringing you back to this place.”
Jeremiah’s prophecy
had given Daniel hope
because it indicated that the Jews
would soon return to their homeland of Judah
and rebuild Jerusalem along with its temple.
That makes sense
that Daniel would be interested
in the restoration of the temple
because from the time of King Solomon,
the temple in Jerusalem
was the world center for worship of Jehovah.
So it was very important to the Jews.
In the Scriptures,
the temple was often called
“the house of Jehovah.”
Now, after Jehovah allowed young Daniel
and the rest of the Israelites
to be taken captive to Babylon,
the city of Jerusalem
and the temple were destroyed.
So naturally, a God-fearing man like Daniel
would be interested
in seeing the temple rebuilt.
Again, as a man of faith,
Daniel supplicates Jehovah.
O Jehovah,
do hear,
do forgive.
O Jehovah, do pay attention and act.
Do not delay,
for your own sake,
O my God.
O Daniel,
now I have come to give you
insight and understanding.
The visit of this angel
gave Daniel some answers and a hope.
Jehovah’s messenger provided
so many details of promises to come.
Jehovah assured Daniel
that the Jews would be restored
to their homeland.
Their exile in Babylonia was almost over.
But that wasn’t the end
of the angel’s message.
He gave Daniel insight
into something of far greater significance.
Daniel was told when God’s people
could expect the arrival
of the foretold Messiah.
The Messiah would be the ruler
who would make it possible
for obedient humans
to regain the blessing of perfect life
—free from sickness, free from death.
The Messiah would pave the way
for lasting peace for mankind.
What a strengthening message
for Daniel to receive!
And he likely had some questions.
The angel told Daniel
that Jerusalem and its temple
would be rebuilt before the Messiah arrived.
Yet, at the time,
Jerusalem and the temple were in shambles.
How would they rebuild it?
And who would be responsible for this?
Babylon had been overtaken by Medo-Persia,
pictured by the silver chest and arms
of Nebuchadnezzar’s dream image.
Not long after
this change in world rulership,
Persian King Cyrus
issued a royal decree.
It was a commission from Cyrus himself
for the Jews to return to Jerusalem
and rebuild the temple.
King Cyrus’ release of the Jews
was in notable contrast
with the Babylonians’ desire
to keep them captive.
Cyrus even authorized funds
from the king’s house
to cover construction expenses.
Why would this pagan ruler
have any interest in, first of all,
letting the captive Jews free and, second,
financing the rebuilding
of their temple in Jerusalem?
Ezra’s words at 2 Chronicles 36:22 tell us:
“Jehovah stirred the spirit
of King Cyrus of Persia.”
Jehovah can maneuver events
to make sure his word is fulfilled.
He can use anyone to accomplish his purpose,
and this would include
even a foreign king, like Cyrus.
So with this decree,
the Jews returned to Judah.
Launching a construction project
and resettling an entire city
was a major undertaking.
High Priest Jeshua and Governor Zerubbabel
were appointed to take the lead
in setting up the altar
and rebuilding the temple.
But this wasn’t without its challenges.
Enemies of Judah sought
to sabotage the building of the temple,
attempting to disrupt the peace.
Initial attempts
to halt the building progress failed;
however, eventually these enemies succeeded
in having an official ban
placed on the temple-building work.
What was the problem here?
It appears the Jews let fear of man
stop the building work
after about 14 years of constant opposition.
Now, there is a bigger picture at play here.
Remember, Daniel’s prophecy foretold
that Jerusalem and its temple
would be rebuilt before the Messiah arrived.
Yet, with the work halted,
the temple remained unfinished.
What would that mean
for the coming of the Messiah?
Jeshua and Zerubbabel needed guidance.
This is where Jehovah
steps in to provide encouragement
—first through the prophet Haggai.
Haggai’s clear and powerful message
gets right to the heart of the matter.
He conveys Jehovah’s direction to get up
and keep building the temple despite opposition.
The Jews had a decision to make here.
Would they allow opposition
to hinder the work?
Or would they listen to Jehovah’s words
through Haggai
and keep rebuilding the temple?
To guide them further,
Jehovah spoke to the prophet Zechariah
and gave him visions
to provide the Jews with a message.
Zechariah made it clear to the Jews
that Jehovah would not allow
their opposers to harm them
or thwart the temple-rebuilding work.
It was only with Jehovah’s guidance
that the Jews would succeed.
Energized by Jehovah’s motivating words
through these two prophets,
they courageously resumed construction
of the temple, and it was inaugurated
in 515 B.C.E.
Now, it seems that at some point
over the following decades,
the Jews lost their initial zeal.
The temple was rebuilt and inaugurated,
but Jerusalem’s walls and gates remained unfinished,
with huge gaps left in them.
That was significant because the city
was surrounded by enemy nations.
Without the protection of these walls,
Jerusalem seemed vulnerable.
When Nehemiah learned of this,
he was visibly distressed.
What’s going on, Hanani?
How are our people?
Not good.
The conditions are disgraceful.
The walls of Jerusalem are broken down,
and its gates have been burned with fire.
What about the temple?
It stands,
but the services
are nothing but empty rituals.
Most of the people and the priests
ignore God’s Law.
Nehemiah must have been shocked
to hear about the condition of Jerusalem.
At this time, he was serving as cupbearer
to the Persian King in Shushan.
The journey from Shushan to Jerusalem
was about 1,000 miles (1,600 km).
Still,
Nehemiah felt compelled to act.
Nehemiah rejoiced at the prospect
of rebuilding the walls.
The Jews at this time
were still fearful of their opposers,
but Nehemiah was intent on changing that.
He knew that Jehovah was behind the work.
And if Jehovah is behind something,
there’s no amount of opposition
that can thwart his will,
so the wall repairs began.
This isn’t to say
that there were not challenges along the way.
Opposers did not give up.
I recommend we turn the accusation
of sedition against Nehemiah.
That’s brilliant!
Yes,
he will beg for our help.
These opposers threatened the Jews,
schemed against them,
and even accused Nehemiah of treason.
Nehemiah’s peace and the peace
of the Jews supporting the work was threatened.
But despite the attempts of opposers,
Nehemiah and the Jews looked to Jehovah
for guidance and kept working.
When Jehovah declares his purpose,
there is nothing that can prevent him
from carrying it out.
So if Jehovah wanted a rebuilt Jerusalem,
complete with rebuilt walls,
Nehemiah would have
complete faith in Jehovah’s ability
to support the rebuilding efforts.
And with this support,
the city walls were completed
in just 52 days.
Nehemiah, the wall is complete!
That’s it.
With rebuilt walls and a rebuilt temple,
physically the city was in good condition.
However, about 12 years later,
Nehemiah returned to Shushan.
During his prolonged absence,
the spiritual state of the Jews deteriorated.
It was so sad,
as many in Israel
fell back into bad practices.
Some in the priesthood,
including High Priest Eliashib,
no longer took their responsibilities seriously.
Therefore, Jehovah raised up the prophet Malachi
to counsel the negligent priests.
Why have you Levites despised Jehovah’s name?
Despised it?
You present a blind,
lame, or sick animal as a sacrifice
and say that it is nothing bad.
Should Jehovah accept it from your hand?
And there’s another thing you do
so that he no longer
looks favorably on anything you offer.
Because you betray the wife of your youth,
although she’s your partner, your legal wife.
The lips of a priest
should safeguard knowledge,
and people should seek the law from his mouth.
But you,
you have made many stumble.
Evidently, Malachi’s words
had little effect on the priesthood.
Despite his warnings,
the people refused to change.
When Nehemiah returned,
what he found shocked him.
For a long time,
the priests and the Levites
have not taken their duties seriously.
When the people saw that,
they stopped bringing in tithes.
Without the tithes,
most Levites and singers
returned to their fields.
Did Eliashib
not tell the people to bring your provisions?
In your absence,
the prophet Malachi warned him
and all the priests.
But Eliashib—
He took our storeroom
and emptied it of our provisions.
He gave it to Tobiah to use as a dining hall.
In addition
to no longer providing
financial support,
the people started
conducting business on the Sabbath.
What are you selling today?
Only the best quality fish from Tyre.
They were marrying foreign women.
I’m marrying Gizla today.
Gizla?
That Moabite girl?
I heard you bind yourself with an oath
and a curse not to take a wife from the nations!
This action could have disrupted
the line to the Messiah,
and it definitely threatened
to contaminate pure worship.
These men were bringing the restored nation
into disfavor with Jehovah.
This is the same reason
why Jehovah allowed Babylon
to destroy Jerusalem in the first place.
So Nehemiah took action
against these faithless ones.
Please cleanse this room
and replace the utensils.
No!
Yes, my lord.
And gather all the Levites,
the singers, and the deputy rulers to me.
I’m assigning them all back to their posts.
He enforced the strict observance
of the Sabbath.
What’s the meaning of this?
I had to sleep on the ground last night.
You know God’s Law:
No work,
no business on the Sabbath!
Go!
You and all the Levites, guard the gates
and keep the Sabbath holy.
Don’t let anyone in!
He disciplined those
who had taken foreign wives.
Did you not swear never to marry someone
who doesn’t serve Jehovah?
Nehemiah, nobody cares.
Did you not?
Yes! Yes!
Then why have you ignored the command of Jehovah
and your own oath?
There’s no doubt
that Jehovah
was guiding Nehemiah’s efforts all along.
After a spiritual cleansing was done,
a measure of peace was again enjoyed.
And with this vigorous
rooting out of apostasy,
the record of the Hebrew Scriptures
comes to a close.
Now, we don’t have
an inspired record of events
in the centuries leading up to Jesus’ birth,
but history shows that Jerusalem
underwent several changes during these years.
The Medo-Persian Empire
was overtaken by Greece,
represented by the copper belly and thighs
of Nebuchadnezzar’s dream image.
While the city seemed to survive
the change in control
without any physical damage,
its spiritual state was threatened.
The Greek Empire set the stage for the spread
of Greek language, culture, and religious thought,
and Israel was affected by this influence.
Years later, King Antiochus IV
was determined to eradicate
Jewish worship and customs.
He went so far as to sacrifice a pig
to the Greek god Zeus
at the temple of Jehovah.
This was a vicious attempt
to defile and to stamp out pure worship.
However, the desecration
had the opposite effect.
It sparked an uprising
of zealous Jews, and three years later,
they cleansed the temple
and rededicated it to Jehovah.
About a century later,
Jerusalem experienced
another change in rulership
as Rome became the dominant world power.
Rome corresponded to the legs of iron
in Nebuchadnezzar’s dream image.
Under the rule
of Herod the Great,
Jerusalem enjoyed considerable prosperity.
Herod’s greatest work, however,
was the reconstruction of the temple
and its building complex.
The temple and its daily sacrifices
remained in operation down to Jesus’ day.
The Bible record picks up
before Jesus was born.
May Jehovah have mercy on us!
What’s happening?
Is the sun up already?
Are they . . .
are they . . . angels?
Do not be afraid,
for look!
I am declaring to you good news
of a great joy that all the people will have.
For today there was born
to you in David’s city a savior,
who is Christ the Lord.
Jesus’ birth and ministry
fulfilled many prophecies.
In 29 C.E., Jehovah
anointed Jesus with holy spirit.
This corresponds exactly
to the words of Daniel’s prophecy
that Jehovah gave him
more than 500 years earlier.
The promised Messiah had arrived!
Early in his ministry, Jesus read these words
from the prophecy of Isaiah.
The scroll of Isaiah the prophet reads:
“Jehovah’s spirit is upon me,
“because he anointed me
“to declare good news to the poor.
“He sent me
“to proclaim liberty to the captives
“and a recovery of sight to the blind,
“to send the crushed ones away free,
to preach Jehovah’s acceptable year.”
Today this scripture
that you just heard is fulfilled.
Holy spirit empowered Jesus to perform
many miracles
in just a few short years on earth.
This had a profound effect
on the people living in his day.
I am a very sick woman.
I’ve suffered from a flow of blood
for some 12 years.
He can heal me!
Even if I could touch
just the fringes
of his outer garment, I will get well!
Who touched my outer garment?
Who touched me?
Please, . . .
please forgive me, my Lord.
It was I who touched you!
I have faith in you!
I knew that if I could just touch
the fringes of your outer garment,
I could get well.
Take courage, daughter!
Your faith has made you well.
The miracles Jesus performed were unlike
anything the people had seen before.
Finally, the people had hope
—a hope for the future, a hope for peace.
He even demonstrated that he had power
far beyond any human ruler.
Lord, Mary is here!
Lord!
If you had been here,
my brother would not have died!
Lazarus!
Come out!
Free him, and let him go!
There is so much we can learn
from Jesus’ miracles, works, and teachings.
They reveal Jehovah’s purpose and power.
They show how enjoyable,
how peaceful life will be
under God’s Messianic Ruler.
Humans alive at this time
could see visible proof of this.
Jesus’ ministry accomplished so much
in just three and a half years.
And prophecy regarding the Messiah
continued to be fulfilled
as his opposers succeeded
in putting him to death.
With the sacrifice
of Jesus’ perfect human life,
the entire arrangement
for worshipping Jehovah had changed.
There was no longer a need
for animal sacrifices.
Pure worship was no longer centered
around the temple in Jerusalem.
The only way to worship Jehovah acceptably
was through the Messiah.
Now people everywhere
could find the way to peace
through faith in Jesus’ ransom sacrifice.
The Jewish system of worship
under the Mosaic Law was over.
Jerusalem and the temple
no longer had Jehovah’s favor.
Jesus’ perfect human sacrifice
was the only solution for lasting peace.
So, what did this mean
for the city of Jerusalem and the temple?
Well, before his death,
Jesus provided his followers with a warning
regarding Jerusalem’s destruction.
At Luke 21:20, 21, he says:
“When you see Jerusalem
“surrounded by encamped armies,
“then know that the desolating of her
“has drawn near. . . .
“Let those in the midst of her leave,
and let those in the countryside
not enter into her.”
A good ruler guides his people.
Although it wasn’t yet time for him
to take the throne as Ruler of God’s Kingdom,
Jesus (by the way he acted) gave us insight
into the kind of ruler he would be.
By providing first-century Christians
with a warning to leave Jerusalem
and all Judea,
he was guiding them and protecting them.
Jesus prophesied the destruction of the city,
and just a few decades later,
that prophecy came true.
The Roman Empire still had control of Judea,
and tensions ran high
between the Romans and the Jews.
Eventually, the Jews
revolted against Roman rule.
With the city surrounded
and Roman forces closing in,
it seemed there was no way out.
But Jehovah’s word cannot go unfulfilled.
For no apparent reason,
the Roman forces withdrew!
For faithful Christians,
this was their opportunity.
It’s simple:
Those who followed Jesus’ direction
to leave Judea were guided to safety.
For those who delayed,
escape became difficult or impossible.
There was no doubt
that Jerusalem no longer enjoyed
Jehovah’s special favor and protection.
The city and its temple
were completely destroyed.
There are parallels we can draw
from the warning Jesus gave
to those first-century Christians
to the warning we
have been given for our day.
Jesus gave us one composite sign
that indicates the destruction
of this current system of things
is very close.
Prophecies in the Bible give us no doubt
that we are living in “the last days.”
Jehovah has not revealed all the details
of how everything will work out.
But we know that everything
he has revealed will come true.
This includes details outlining
how world events
would unfold in the time
of the end
before mankind
would experience permanent peace.
Remember, Daniel’s prophecy indicated
that there would be
only one dominant world power in place
at the time of the end.
By World War I,
the power represented by the feet
of iron and clay had emerged.
During that war, Britain and America
forged a partnership
that continued through the Second World War.
This means a special relationship
between the British Commonwealth and Empire
and the United States of America.
Neither the sure prevention of war
nor the continuous rise
of world organization will begin
without what I have called
the fraternal association
of the English-speaking people.
These two countries
continue to be a dual
English-speaking world power.
The characteristics of iron and clay
used to represent
this world power are significant.
And as the toes of the feet
were partly of iron and partly of clay,
so the kingdom
will be partly strong and partly fragile.
At times, the United States and Britain
have displayed ironlike strength
through their involvement in armed conflicts.
However, iron mixed with clay
is considerably weakened.
This can be observed as common people
undermined the Anglo-American
World Power’s ability
to act with ironlike strength.
As the political and social developments
foretold in the Bible come to a climax,
we have a measure of peace.
We know Jehovah will guide his people,
even as the world’s spiritual
and moral condition sinks to new depths.
As many in first-century Jerusalem
continued their lives
as if nothing had changed,
so, too, today many
continue on with their lives.
Meanwhile, we remain alert
as we see fulfillment of Bible prophecy
right before our eyes.
In the days of those kings,
the God of heaven will set up a kingdom
that will never be destroyed.
The book of Revelation
tells us what will soon happen.
The political rulers of the world
will give the United Nations
unprecedented power and authority.
The apostle Paul foretold
that the nations will declare
“Peace and security!”
But it won’t prove to be true peace.
The nations supporting the UN
will attack the institutions
of false religion.
Then a coalition of earth’s governments
that the prophet Ezekiel
calls “Gog of the land of Magog”
will attack God’s people.
Yet, we don’t need to be fearful.
That’s when we can put into action
all of the lessons we’ve learned.
Those who trust and obey Jehovah’s guidance
can look to the near future with confidence.
As we’ve seen, Jehovah has always been
in control of the situation.
He has never guided his people
in a certain direction
but then failed to provide for them.
That’s why we can say
that the lessons we learn
from the faithful men we’ve studied
are more than just lessons.
This has been Jehovah
paving the way for peace from the start.
Looking back, we see exactly
how Jehovah has led his people.
It took many years,
but he’s been in control the whole time.
Would it make sense
to think he isn’t in control anymore?
No power in heaven or on earth
can prevent Jehovah
from accomplishing his express purpose.
He has never relinquished control,
and he is still guiding his people.
Now think about this:
If Jehovah has guided
his people to this point,
we can have full confidence
that trust and obedience to his direction
will prove to be our salvation,
even if a way out seems impossible.
Jehovah is all-powerful!
He’s going to help us
through whatever we may face.
We won’t have to fight,
and we won’t need to fear annihilation.
Jehovah has things
under control.
“And this kingdom
“will not be passed on to any other people.
“It will crush and put an end
“to all these kingdoms.
And it alone will stand forever.”
God’s Kingdom will fill
and renew the entire earth.
Jehovah’s promises
will be completely fulfilled.
Lasting peace will finally become
a reality for all mankind.
Just imagine what faithful servants
have to look forward to
under Jesus’ heavenly rule!
He will be able to provide
what no man ever could.
Can you imagine what that will be like?
“For look!
“I am creating new heavens and a new earth;
“and the former things
will not be called to mind,
nor will they come up into the heart.”
“The righteous will possess the earth,
and they will live forever on it.”
“He will swallow up death forever,
and the Sovereign Lord Jehovah
will wipe away the tears from all faces.”
“He will wipe out every tear from their eyes,
“and death will be no more,
“neither will mourning
“nor outcry nor pain be anymore.
The former things have passed away.”
“At that time the eyes
“of the blind will be opened,
“and the ears of the deaf will be unstopped.
“At that time the lame
“will leap like the deer,
“and the tongue of the speechless
“will shout for joy.
“For waters will burst forth
in the wilderness,
and streams in the desert plain.”
“They will build houses and live in them,
and they will plant vineyards
and eat their fruitage.”
“For the days of my people
will be like the days of a tree,
“and the work of their hands
my chosen ones will enjoy to the full.”
“But the meek will possess the earth,
“and they will find exquisite delight
in the abundance of peace.”
What a faith-strengthening drama!
We are at peace knowing that Jehovah
is in complete control.
All in attendance will be pleased to know
that Parts 1 and 2
of the drama-documentary
Jehovah Guides Us in the Way of Peace
are available now for download on jw.org
Have you enjoyed the original songs
that have been featured
at recent conventions?
We now have the privilege
of watching a video medley
and reflecting on the lessons we have learned
at our conventions over the past few years.
Enjoy!
Doubt and fear surround me—
The way ahead not clear.
Through uncertainty you guide me;
I know you’re always near.
Life may not be easy,
But this I know is true:
You’re the God who’s ever loyal;
My life is safe with you.
Jehovah, give me eyes of faith
And help me always see
There are more with us than against us.
Courageous let me be.
Courage, give me courage;
With courage, I’ll endure.
Jehovah, give me courage;
Your victory is sure.
Feeling fear is human.
In my own strength, I’m frail.
You have been my rock and refuge;
Your power never fails.
Help me be courageous,
And let my heart be brave.
Lasting harm can never hold me—
No prison, gate, or grave.
Jehovah, give me eyes of faith
And help me always see
There are more with us than against us.
Courageous let me be.
Courage, give me courage;
With courage, I’ll endure.
Jehovah, give me courage;
Your victory is sure.
Look around us now;
See the love on each face—
Out there in the world, hard to find.
All these faithful friends
With the love they all show,
Glad to leave that old world behind.
Love never fails; that’s promised.
It always will endure.
Love—unfailing love—
That’s what Jehovah gives.
That’s what he is.
Love—unfailing love—
That’s what we need to live.
And the love here today,
In our heart may it stay—
Love—unfailing love—
That’s what Jehovah gives.
That’s what he is.
Love—unfailing love—
That’s what we need to live.
And the love here today,
In our heart may it stay—
Unfailing love,
Unfailing love.
Why should I fear the lion?
Why should I fear any foe?
With Jehovah by my side,
I will not run and hide.
My God is with me; this I know.
With eyes of faith,
I see beyond the darkness.
there’s nothing more to fear.
With Jehovah, I am strong,
Determined to go on,
Knowing that my God is always near—
With eyes of faith.
I see the wondrous future
God has in store for me.
I need to be strong.
I know it won’t be long
Till Jehovah claims his victory.
With eyes of faith,
I see beyond the darkness.
there’s nothing more to fear.
With Jehovah, I am strong,
Determined to go on,
Knowing that my God is always near—
With eyes of faith,
With eyes of faith.
The stars that fill the summer night
Look down from above.
The beauty of the day and night
You fashioned with love.
Your hands prepared the land and sea,
And ev’rything that came to be
Brought joy to your heart.
There is joy in your creation,
In the message of salvation,
And the Paradise to come.
But to have your love forever
Is a real and lasting treasure.
You alone will prove to be
Our joy eternally.
This joy could not be ours
Without the gift of your Son.
His sacrifice has paid the price
So joy could be ours for all time.
There is joy in your creation,
In the message of salvation,
And the Paradise to come.
But to have your love forever
Is a real and lasting treasure.
You alone will prove to be
Our joy eternally.
Our next song encourages us
to look ahead with confidence.
The song is entitled
“See Yourself When All Is New.”
Let’s sing together song number 139.
That’s song number 139.