We extend a warm welcome to one and all.
In this session, which corresponds
to the Saturday afternoon portion
of the program,
we will learn what we individually can do
to pursue peace with others.
We will begin
with a music-video presentation.
The video will encourage us
to welcome others
into our peaceful worldwide brotherhood.
Please enjoy.
Please join in singing
song number 29, entitled
“Living Up to Our Name”—song number 29.
At times, our imperfections
can disrupt our peace
and that of others.
During the next symposium,
we will consider things we must avoid
in order to cultivate peaceful relationships.
Please give your attention
to Brother Harold Corkern,
a helper to the Publishing Committee,
as he develops the theme
“‘Put Away’ Peace Wreckers
—Inappropriate Boasting.”
What comes to your mind
when you hear the expression “put away”?
You may think of related expressions
such as “cast aside,” “dispose of,”
“discard,” “get rid of.”
What did we have to put away
to become a Christian?
The Bible in the book
of Ephesians 4:22
provides the answer.
That’s Ephesians 4:22:
“You were taught
to put away the old personality
“that conforms
to your former course of conduct
and that is being corrupted
according to its deceptive desires.”
So we had “to put away the old personality.”
But it’s one thing to put it away;
it’s something else to keep it away.
And that’s why
in the very next verse, verse 23,
Paul encourages us to do this:
“And you should continue to be made new
in your dominant mental attitude.”
It’s so important to keep it away,
because the old personality has traits
that can become peace wreckers.
This symposium
will consider five peace wreckers
that we should put away and keep away.
Each talk will include
the following main points:
(1) It will define the peace wrecker,
(2) it will explain how it wrecks peace,
and (3) we will consider how to put it away.
What is the very first one
that we’re going to talk about?
It is inappropriate boasting.
What is inappropriate boasting?
Basically, it’s self-praise,
and the Bible condemns self-praise
Notice Proverbs 27:2:
“Let someone else praise you,
“and not your own mouth;
others, and not your own lips.”
Self-praise is an evidence of pride
that causes one
to elevate himself above others.
Some might develop an unhealthy pride
about their accomplishments,
even in the ministry.
It happened in the first century.
Paul had to write
to the Corinthian congregation
about the dissensions that they were having,
the lack of peace they were experiencing.
Why?
Well, some in the congregation
were “puffed up with pride” about themselves
or other men,
such as Paul, Apollos, Cephas.
They were giving
too much attention to themselves
and to other men.
Well, how could that happen today?
Well, let’s imagine
a group of brothers talking,
and one in the group says,
“With Jehovah’s help
and with diligent prayer and effort,
I finally got a Bible study.”
But right away,
another one in the group proudly declares,
“I have four Bible studies;
two are attending meetings,
and one will soon be baptized.”
Could such a statement be a peace wrecker?
How does inappropriate boasting
wreck peace?
Well, it’s not wrong
to take pleasure in our work
and to thank Jehovah
for the success that we may have.
But inappropriate boasting
about our accomplishments
can stir up competition, envy, and rivalry.
We must remember that self-promotion
does not originate
with our heavenly Father, “the God of peace.”
Where does it originate?
First John 2:16 says:
“The showy display of one’s means of life
“does not originate with the Father,
but originates with the world.”
And would you not agree
that the world is filled with self-praise?
Even on their social media, we see this.
Some of the material
that people post on social media
is designed to make one
appear very important.
And it is a showy display
of their accomplishments,
their material possessions,
or their expensive vacations that they enjoy.
In other words, it’s all about “look at me.”
Well, we want to avoid getting caught up
in the world’s spirit of self-promotion
that wrecks peace.
To illustrate just how devastating
the peace wrecker’s
inappropriate boasting can be,
let’s briefly consider
the Bible character Haman.
He was a proud and haughty man,
and he boasted a lot.
Esther chapter 5 tells us
that he was boasting
with his family and friends
about his wealth, his many sons,
how the king had promoted him
to a high station,
that he was above all the other servants,
and that he’d had a special meal, or banquet,
with the king and queen.
But Haman was hateful and arrogant.
And he was plotting to kill
Jehovah’s faithful servant Mordecai.
But his scheme
and his attitudes were exposed.
And what happened?
The very stake that Haman had built
to hang Mordecai on he was hung on.
And it reminds us
—doesn’t it?—
that at Isaiah 29:20, the Bible says:
“The boaster will come to his finish.”
So because of the devastating effects
that improper boasting
can have on ourselves and others,
we do not even want
to give the impression of boasting.
In the following dramatization,
notice how a sister’s actions
are misunderstood as boasting.
“Put away from yourselves every kind
“of malicious bitterness, anger, wrath,
“screaming, and abusive speech,
as well as everything injurious.”
Did anyone start the day thinking,
‘I believe I’ll show malicious bitterness
to my brother today’?
Of course not!
And yet the potential is there, isn’t it?
But genuine affection fights peace wreckers.
And affection grows when we really know
our brothers and sisters well.
We remember their joys
and pains,
their selfless zeal,
how they came to love Jehovah,
and what they endure.
I’ll get back as soon as I can.
Love you. Bye.
Oh, no!
Haley, love?
So sorry, I’ve got to run.
OK. I’ll ring you about this week.
Thanks. Love you both.
See you!
The afternoon would look better.
Nana!
Hello, Haley, darling.
I’m so, so sorry.
Oh, it’s not too bad.
I’ve got this.
Oh.
How are you though?
Thank you. I’m so sorry.
Oh, poor thing.
Let me clear this up.
Thank you.
Oh, Nana, it’s Sunday today, isn’t it?
This one.
It’s felt like such a long day, hasn’t it?
It has felt like a long day.
Thanks.
Sleep well.
Hello, everyone.
Haley from DeNure Design here,
helping you to be effortlessly elegant.
I want to welcome my new followers
and thank everyone
for subscribing to this channel.
So first up, I’ve got
this gorgeous earring and necklace set.
And as you can see, the first disc I’ve done
is in this warm nude tone,
and that’s great because it goes . . .
Can you believe her?
Haley’s business feed?
But what makes this set is really special.
It’s giving you
that understated elegant look.
If you haven’t done so already,
please hit the subscribe button below.
Because as you know,
when you look this good, you feel great.
Was the sister in this video
boasting inappropriately?
No, she was a humble servant of Jehovah,
kindly and patiently
helping her elderly relative.
But do you recall her business website
and the presentation she made
about her jewelry products?
She said,
“When you look this good,
you feel great.”
Her Christian sister was upset
and took those comments and her actions
to be boastful.
Well, this video reminds us
to think about how our words and our actions
may appear to others.
So now we’re going to get to the question:
How do we put away inappropriate boasting?
A key point that we must always remember
to help us to do just that
is recorded in the book
of 1 Corinthians 4:7,
1 Corinthians 4:7:
“For who makes you different from another?
“Indeed, what do you have
that you did not receive?
“If, in fact, you did receive it,
why do you boast
as though you did not receive it?”
What’s the point of this scripture?
We do not want to boast about ourselves
but give all credit to Jehovah
for the good that we can do.
Now, some people are proud
about their good looks,
their popularity,
their wealth, their position,
their physical strength,
their musical ability.
But remember, King David of ancient Israel
had all of those assets.
But throughout his entire life,
he never became a boastful person.
He remained humble.
Why?
At Psalm 113:5-8,
David gave all credit to Jehovah.
He said that in his case
Jehovah stooped down
and took this “lowly” one
and raised him up
to “sit with nobles.”
And on every occasion that he had,
David would always say, ‘Praise Jehovah,
boast about his holy name.’
Well, we, like David,
should “boast in Jehovah.”
The apostle Paul encouraged us to do that
at 1 Corinthians 1:31:
“The one who boasts,
let him boast in Jehovah.”
What does that mean?
It means that we boast in the privilege
of knowing the true God
and of being able
to be used by him to accomplish his will.
Now, another way
that we can put away improper boasting
is to not talk about ourselves,
but to acknowledge the good
and the fine qualities
that our fellow workers have.
Humble and modest people
don’t brag about what they do,
but they turn their attention
to their fellow workers
and see how Jehovah is using them
and blessing them in his service.
And when we do that,
that creates a very peaceful,
happy environment.
Well, may we continue
to put away and keep away
inappropriate boasting—self-praise.
How?
By giving praise and thanks and honor
to Jehovah for our accomplishments
and by commending our fellow workers
for all the good qualities they have
and for how Jehovah
is using them in his service.
By doing so, we will preserve
our precious possession of peace
with Jehovah and with our brothers.
Brother Seth Hyatt,
a helper to the Service Committee,
will now present
the next talk of this symposium,
“‘Put Away’ Peace Wreckers—Envy.”
What is envy?
Do you know?
It’s important that we be able to identify
the symptoms of envy.
Why?
Because envy is an expression
of hatred.
It’s an enemy of peace.
And if left unchecked,
it can result in spiritual death.
As described in the Bible,
envy has two symptoms.
The first is probably more familiar.
An envious person wants
what someone else has.
It’s the second symptom
that makes envy especially dangerous.
An envious person not only wants
what someone else has,
but he also doesn’t want
the other person to have it.
Here’s an example:
In the first century,
Jewish religious leaders envied Jesus
because Jesus was much appreciated
by the common people.
Jesus dealt with people,
including lowly ones,
in a way that dignified them.
As a result, he was appreciated.
The religious leaders envied him.
But rather than adjusting their own way
of dealing with people,
they attacked Jesus verbally
in an effort to destroy
his good reputation.
They spread malicious slander.
Not only did they want
what Jesus had,
but also they didn’t want
Jesus to have it.
No wonder envy is listed
as one of “the works of the flesh”
at Galatians 5:21.
It’s a dangerous quality
that we need to avoid.
How does envy disrupt peace?
Envy undermines, damages,
or even destroys relationships
in the family and in the congregation.
Consider the example of Jacob
and his 12 sons.
Jacob had special affection
for one of his sons, Joseph.
As a result,
Joseph’s brothers became envious.
How did the envy manifest itself?
What was the fruitage?
Well, they dealt treacherously
with Joseph, selling him into slavery.
And as if that weren’t bad enough,
they compounded their wrong
by lying to Jacob,
telling him that Joseph was dead.
According to the Bible account,
Jacob “refused to be comforted.”
He mourned Joseph for years.
What a terrible consequence of envy!
It’s clear that envy
allows no room for love,
compassion, or kindness.
Those qualities go out the window.
And they’re replaced by qualities
such as hatred, strife, fits of anger.
Can envy disrupt the peace
of a congregation?
Consider the examples
of Korah, Dathan, and Abiram.
They envied Moses and Aaron
in the congregation of Israel.
How did that envy manifest itself?
Well, they began
to speak negatively—critically—
of Jehovah’s representatives,
even accusing Moses
of playing the prince
and lifting himself up above the others.
They forgot that Jehovah
had put Moses and Aaron
in their positions of responsibility.
How did Jehovah react
to that manifestation of envy?
He destroyed those three men
and all who supported them.
For a time, the congregation
was robbed of its peace,
and the accounts
certainly provide some insight
into Jehovah’s view of envy.
Now, by this point,
you’re no doubt thinking,
‘I would never want something
so badly that I would
damage someone else to get it.’
But we’re all imperfect.
We have a treacherous heart,
and envy is insidious.
In the following dramatization,
notice how envy
threatens to disrupt peace.
Really?
Bad news?
She’s a sweetie.
It reminds me that I want to speak to her
about a necklace.
You too?
You don’t think she’s showing off?
No.
Everyone thinks she’s “Miss Wonderful”;
she’s starting to agree.
Is this just about Haley?
It seems it’s all about Haley.
Your tea is getting cold.
And you’re changing the subject.
No,
but you’ve brought this up before.
What is it?
You’re friends; you pioneer together.
Yeah, and that’s why I’m concerned.
Concern is good,
but
is there just a little bit of envy in there?
What did you notice?
Well, Emily is suffering
from an onset of envy.
Did you notice
how she questioned Haley’s motives
and potentially called
Haley’s reputation into question?
It could happen to any one of us.
So how do we battle and conquer envy?
By cultivating two beautiful qualities,
humility and contentment.
Let’s see what the Bible
has to say about humility.
Turn with me, please,
to Philippians chapter 2,
and we’re going to begin reading
in verse 3
—Philippians 2:3:
“Do nothing out of contentiousness
or out of egotism.”
What is egotism?
Well, it’s having
an exaggerated opinion of oneself.
Do you think that the religious leaders
in Jesus’ day,
Joseph’s brothers,
Korah, Dathan, and Abiram
had this affliction?
Did they have an exaggerated view
of themselves?
Without question!
But it’s an affliction
that could affect any one of us.
What is the solution?
Well, Paul continues:
“But with humility [or, lowliness of mind]
consider others superior to you”
—or consider others
as more important than yourself.
Now, that kind of mindset
allows a person to do what’s stated
in verse 4:
“As you look out not only
“for your own interests,
but also for the interests of others.”
A humble person
looks out for others.
He doesn’t feel that he deserves
more than others.
Contentment—a content person
is satisfied with what he has.
He doesn’t compare
his privilege or his possession
with another person’s privilege
or possession.
He’s content.
Humility, contentment
—with Jehovah’s help we can cultivate
these beautiful qualities—
qualities that leave no room for envy.
And in doing so, we promote peace
—inner peace, peace in our family,
and peace in the congregation.
And you can be sure
that Jehovah appreciates that.
Brother Gajus Glockentin,
a helper to the Publishing Committee,
will now present the next talk
of this symposium,
“‘Put Away’ Peace Wreckers—Dishonesty.”
What comes to your mind
when you hear the word “dishonesty”?
Maybe you think of Satan,
“the father of the lie.”
Or Ananias and his wife come to your mind.
They lost their lives because of lying.
We do not want to imitate such ones.
We avoid lying.
Is that, though, as far as our honesty goes?
Our holy God, Jehovah,
wants us to be holy as well,
and that is why he urged
the ancient Israelites
not to deceive others
as mentioned at Leviticus 19:11.
Does this not add some color to honesty?
Dishonesty includes
(and please take note of this definition)
intentionally leading someone
to a wrong conclusion.
For example, by twisting the truth
or by providing only certain details,
we endanger our peace with others.
Why can we say so?
How does dishonesty wreck peace?
Peace and a peaceful relationship
are built on trust.
Trusting someone makes you feel
safe and secure
and puts you at ease.
There is no peace without trust.
How do we develop trust?
Trust is the result
of spending time together,
speaking the truth with one another.
We trust people who act unselfishly
and do not use “crooked speech,”
as the Bible puts it.
If someone deceives us only once
or is dishonest in another way,
we might start to question
everything they say.
One single act of dishonesty may be enough.
It can ruin their reputation.
As bad as this is,
dishonesty has the potential
to create even greater damage.
Dishonesty can be compared
with a highly contagious virus.
Dishonesty breeds dishonesty.
People who have contact
with deceitful, dishonest persons
are in danger of being infected.
Dishonesty might not only wreck
one relationship
but multiple relationships,
putting the unity and peace
of the whole group at risk.
This reminds us of the relationship
between Laban and Jacob
in the Bible book of Genesis.
Based on the agreement with Laban,
Jacob worked hard for seven years
in order to marry Laban’s daughter Rachel.
And despite this high price
that Jacob had to pay,
those years seemed for him
just like “a few days.”
Sadly, instead of Rachel,
he received the older daughter, Leah,
as a wife.
So now Leah was also part of the deception.
What was the result after Jacob had found out
that Laban tricked him?
The trust was gone.
The relationship had suffered
to a great degree.
Dishonesty wrecked the peace
in those relationships,
and so the following seven years
of work for Rachel were bitter.
And Laban’s dishonesty emboldened him
to continue in his course.
He unfairly changed Jacob’s wages ten times.
He deceived Jacob.
Because of Laban’s dishonesty,
the peace in the whole family
was disrupted.
Let us now continue to watch
the next segment of the dramatization.
We left Emily and Celia sitting
in a coffee shop.
Please watch carefully, and notice
how Emily is tempted to alter the truth.
You pioneer together.
I know, and that’s why I’m concerned.
Concern is good,
but
is there just a little bit of envy in there?
I thought you would understand.
I think I understand your feelings.
But not about Haley?
I haven’t seen all her posts.
There’s nothing immoral, is there?
No.
Good. That’s not like her.
Now, if
it’s a case of her being more careful
how she comes across,
that’s another matter.
Why don’t you talk to her?
Maybe.
Emily, you are a beautiful, spiritual sister.
You know,
for years,
I had a bad habit
of comparing myself to others.
My own insecurity hurt me
and my closest friends.
So you don’t think
I should’ve spoken to Celia?
No, I’m glad you asked Celia about it
—someone you trust.
What did she say?
Well, she definitely understands how I feel.
Good.
And about Haley’s posts?
Well, she hasn’t seen
everything she has out there.
Hmm.
She did say that Haley
needs to be more careful
how she comes across.
What did she suggest?
That I should tell her
that she needs to stop,
but I’m too worked up.
Look,
if Celia agrees
that Haley is doing something she shouldn’t,
you should talk to her.
You’ll find the right time.
Thanks for understanding.
I’m hungry.
Can you say the prayer?
Sure.
Jehovah, we’d like to praise you
for your generosity and kindness . . .
Did you notice how Emily just heard
what she wanted to hear?
In talking to her husband, Jake,
she painted an incomplete picture.
She did not relay that Celia had no opinion
about the social media posts of Haley.
And contrary to what she told her husband,
Celia did not encourage her
to tell Haley to stop.
Our brothers and sisters deserve the truth.
But Emily didn’t relay that, did she?
She was dishonest, something that can have
a damaging effect, as we will see later.
Jehovah wants us to put away
this peace wrecker, dishonesty.
He wants us to always be truthful,
even in small matters.
Therefore, how do we put away dishonesty?
Let us please turn to Ephesians chapter 4.
Here the apostle Paul reminds us
of a reason to be honest.
This is Ephesians chapter 4,
and we want to read verse 25:
“Therefore, now that you
have put away deceit,
“each one of you speak truth
with his neighbor,
because we are members
belonging to one another.”
Did you notice why we put away deceit
and speak truth with one another?
Paul says: “Because we are
members belonging to one another.”
In other words, Paul reminds us of the fact
that dishonesty affects others
—our brothers and our relationship with them.
So, then, knowing this,
how can we put away dishonesty?
The answer is:
By considering the consequences
of dishonesty and honesty.
This will help us to do the right thing.
Now, what are the consequences of dishonesty?
As we’ve seen in the case of Laban and Jacob,
it will disrupt the peace with others.
And since Jehovah hates dishonesty,
it will also disrupt our peace with Jehovah.
On the other hand,
what are the consequences of honesty?
While dishonesty might seem in the moment
to be the easier way out,
in the long run,
honesty will enable us to have good friends.
They want to enjoy peace as well,
and therefore they are also searching
for someone they can trust.
And in this way, we are
like ‘body members belonging to one another.’
And even more important,
we will enjoy a good conscience
and “peace with God.”
Let us, therefore, put away
this peace wrecker (dishonesty)
by sticking to the truth
even in small things.
Dear brothers and sisters, Jehovah knows
that for us imperfect humans
this is not always easy.
Yet, he promises to help us
and to bless every step we take
to build trust and peace
and not to wreck it.
Brother Patrick LaFranca,
a helper to the Personnel Committee,
will now present
the next talk of this symposium,
“‘Put Away’ Peace Wreckers—Harmful Gossip.”
Do you gossip?
No.
Well, whenever we share
any news about others,
that is a form of gossip.
Because we are interested in others,
we might say,
“I am really concerned
about Brother Smith’s health,”
or “Did you hear about Sister Brown’s
experience in the ministry?”
Is this type of gossip harmful?
Generally not.
Still, we need to be careful.
At 1 Timothy 5:13,
Paul spoke out against certain sisters
who were “gossipers
and meddlers in other people’s affairs.”
We do not need to know
and share everything we know
about what’s happening
in other people’s lives.
What if, for example,
Brother Smith did not want others
to know details about his health problem?
We need to respect the privacy of others.
Or what if talking
about Sister Brown’s experience turns into,
“Oh, you know, she always brags
about her success in the ministry.”
When our talk about others turns negative,
it can develop into slander.
Slander is making
deliberate, false statements
that damage another’s reputation.
Let’s now consider
how harmful gossip wrecks peace.
If you have spread harmful gossip
about someone and he hears about it,
when you see him the next time,
what will be the look on his face?
Please read with me Proverbs 25:23:
“The north wind brings a downpour,
and a gossiping tongue brings an angry face.”
The north wind in Palestine
brought dark clouds and rain.
Likewise, when the one you gossiped about
catches wind of this and he sees you,
he will have a gloomy, angry face.
There will be a storm
and a chilled relationship.
Now, when that happens,
you may feel very badly and apologize,
but you may have damaged his reputation
in a way that may be difficult to undo.
Listen to this old Jewish story:
‘A man went about town
slandering the town’s wise man.
‘Later, the malicious gossiper
realized his wrong
‘and went to the wise man
and asked for his forgiveness.
‘He offered to do
whatever was needed to make amends.
‘The wise man made one request.
‘He told the gossiper
to take a feather pillow,
‘cut it open,
and scatter the feathers to the wind.
‘Well, the gossiper
was puzzled by this request,
‘but he did as instructed.
‘Then he returned to the wise man.
‘“Am I now forgiven?” he asked.
‘“First, go and gather all the feathers,”
the wise man responded.
‘“But, how can I?
‘The wind has already scattered them.”
‘The wise man replied,
‘“It is as difficult to repair
the damage done by your words
as it is to recover the feathers.”’
Yes, once spoken,
hurtful words cannot be retrieved.
Let’s not scatter feathers in the wind.
If we spread rumors,
it can seriously disturb
the peace of many in the congregation.
We find an example of this
at Acts 21:20, 21.
The older men of the Jerusalem congregation
explained to Paul
that some Jews
had spread a rumor among Jewish Christians
that he had been teaching an apostasy,
speaking against the Law of Moses.
Of course, this was a twisting of the facts.
Paul never spoke disrespectfully of the Law.
He even went to synagogues
where he reasoned
on the basis of the Hebrew Scriptures.
Such stories could have led
some newly converted Jewish Christians
to think that Paul
did not respect God’s arrangements,
and this could have seriously disrupted
the peace of the congregation.
In the following dramatization,
notice the effect
that harmful gossip can have
on the peace in a congregation.
Can you believe that?
Especially as a pioneer,
what kind of example is she setting?
Has Emily stopped following her?
No, not yet, but she probably will.
Alistair, what do you think?
About what?
Haley’s posts on QuicPost.
Is there a problem?
Emily has told me
they’re all just, “Look at me
—my clothes, my hair, my makeup.”
And even Celia agrees with her.
Well, it’s very easy to take things
out of context on social media.
I know that I’ve done that and realized later
that I was wrong.
Yeah, that’s a good point.
Listen, I don’t want to pull you away,
but if you have a minute, would you mind
giving me a hand with these boxes?
Sure.
Thanks for your help.
No problem.
Jake, back in the hall,
I know you were just expressing concern,
but here’s something to consider.
This principle is one of my favorites.
It’s found at Proverbs
chapter 18 and verse 17.
“The first to state his case seems right,
until the other party comes
and cross-examines him.”
I’m not sure I understand.
It just means that sometimes
we only hear one side of a story.
And until we personally hear both,
it’s best not to draw any conclusions.
And even then, if it’s something negative,
we wouldn’t want to spread it
any more than we’d want something spread
about ourselves.
I guess I hadn’t considered that.
Thanks.
I’m going to apologize to Harry and Marie
and have Emily talk directly to Haley.
Good idea.
Did you notice what Jake said
after the elder graciously helped him reason
on Proverbs 18:17?
He said, “I had not considered that.”
Yes, Jake just did not stop and think
before he said
those negative things about Haley.
So how can we “put away” harmful gossip
before it begins?
Let’s read Proverbs 15:28:
“The heart of the righteous one
meditates before answering,
“but the mouth of the wicked
blurts out bad things.”
So before we say bad things about others,
we need to meditate.
No, this does not mean
a long-drawn-out process.
It just requires a little thought.
What thoughts could have stopped Jake
from repeating his wife’s negative view
of Haley’s post?
He could have asked himself:
‘Is what I am about to say true?
‘Is it kind, loving?
‘How will Harry and Marie view Haley
if they hear
those negative things about her?’
Another principle
that will help us to put away harmful gossip
is the so-called Golden Rule,
as recorded at Luke 6:31.
Jesus said: “Just as you
want men to do to you,
do the same way to them.”
This means showing empathy,
putting ourselves
in the place of the other person,
and asking ourselves,
‘How would I feel
if someone said this about me?’
One situation that may tempt us
to engage in harmful gossip
is when we believe we
have been wronged by someone.
Instead of applying the counsel
at Matthew 5:23, 24
and 18:15
to talk to the person privately,
we could start talking about it
to others who are not involved.
Imagine if after finally talking
with the person
you find out he actually
did not wrong you at all.
You will have made the situation much worse.
But whether we are right or wrong,
engaging in hurtful speech
will never improve a situation.
Gossip requires a speaker and a listener.
Is it wrong to listen to harmful gossip?
Yes!
Note what Proverbs 17:4 says:
“A wicked man pays attention
to hurtful speech,
and a deceptive man
listens to a malicious tongue.”
Think about that.
In God’s eyes if we listen to hurtful,
malicious speech, we too
bear a heavy responsibility.
By listening to the gossiper,
we are encouraging him to go on.
So, what should you do?
Without taking on an air
of self-righteousness,
you could simply say,
“Let’s change the subject,”
or “I don’t really feel comfortable
talking about this;
after all, she is not here
to defend herself.”
And if we find that a brother or sister
likes to gossip,
we may find it easier to avoid harmful gossip
by stopping close association
with that person.
Proverbs 20:19 frankly counsels:
“Do not associate
with one who loves to gossip.”
So, dear friends,
let’s put away harmful gossip.
Doing so, we will maintain
our precious peace and unity.
Brother Kenneth Cook,
a member of the Governing Body,
will now present
the final talk of this symposium,
“‘Put Away’ Peace Wreckers
—Uncontrolled Anger.”
Satan is the main peace wrecker.
The Scriptures tell us
that he is driven by “great anger.”
His anger is malicious and uncontrolled.
Would any sound-minded,
God-fearing person
allow himself
to reflect Satan’s vicious anger?
Of course not!
That is why all true servants of God
are determined
to “put away” uncontrolled anger.
But apart from uncontrolled anger,
is all anger bad?
The Bible does not condemn all anger.
It teaches us that anger is wrong
when it is uncontrolled or unjustified.
At Ephesians 4:26, God’s Word tells us:
“Be wrathful, but [it adds] do not sin.”
At times, anger
may simply be a strong feeling
that comes into us
because of being upset or annoyed
by something that we see as being wrong.
That in itself is not bad.
But what makes anger bad
is when it fills a person’s heart
and he or she just loses control of it.
When that happens,
it may cause a person
to act without a sound mind.
Those who continue to lash out in anger
will not gain salvation.
Galatians 5:20 lists “fits of anger”
among “the works of the flesh”
that will prevent a person
from inheriting God’s Kingdom.
There will be no place
for such ones in God’s new world.
A brief review of how uncontrolled anger
wrecks peace for ourselves and others
will highlight why this is so.
Uncontrolled anger
harms both the angry person
as well as those around him.
We read at Proverbs 29:22
that an angry person “stirs up strife,”
adding that he “commits many transgressions.”
One of these many sins is abusive speech.
We must work to show restraint
when speaking with workmates,
with strangers in the ministry,
with our brothers and sisters
in the congregation,
and with our family members.
Bad feelings must be controlled.
Abusive speech, ridicule, contempt,
and hateful anger are wrong.
Giving vent to such feelings
can destroy precious friendships
with other people and with Jehovah.
Don’t be like a volcano
that will not quiet down.
Just like an erupting volcano
will harm those living around it,
so too a person who expresses intense anger
will harm those living around him.
He also damages himself.
In what way?
Acting on anger often leads
to even more aggression,
so uncontrolled anger
can also affect our own peace.
It can cause us to do something
that we will later regret.
It can have a negative effect on our health.
Medical studies show that uncontrolled anger
can cause high blood pressure
and respiratory problems.
It can also affect the liver and pancreas,
and such anger can cause digestive problems.
When a person becomes angry,
he or she will not always think clearly.
After a fit of rage,
a person may become depressed.
No wonder we read at Proverbs 14:30
that “a calm heart gives life to the body.”
The disastrous consequences
of uncontrolled anger
are illustrated in God’s Word
by the actions of Simeon and Levi,
sons of the patriarch Jacob.
When they learned that their sister, Dinah,
was violated by a man named Shechem,
we read at Genesis 34:7
that “they were offended and very angry.”
Now, they had a valid reason to be angry,
but they took their anger too far.
It was uncontrolled.
Simeon and Levi
took vengeance on Shechem.
Using deception, they attacked and killed
every male in Shechem’s city.
Then, along with the other sons of Jacob,
they plundered it and took
the women and little children captive.
Dinah’s tragic experience
must have grieved Jacob greatly.
Yet, he condemned
his sons’ uncontrolled anger.
Simeon and Levi
tried to justify their actions,
but that was not the end of the matter,
because Jehovah was also displeased.
For this reason, Jacob later foretold
that the descendants of Simeon and Levi
were to be scattered
among the tribes of Israel.
Their uncontrolled anger brought disfavor
from God and from their father, Jacob.
We’re wise to pay attention
to such Scriptural accounts
and put away uncontrolled anger
and all of the harm that it brings.
In the following dramatization,
notice how a person
might be tempted to give in to anger.
Yes, Nana?
Don’t forget eggs, dear.
No, no, I didn’t forget.
Are you sure, love?
No, I won’t forget. OK.
Thank you so much.
OK. Love you.
Bye.
No!
Haley, finally, I’ve caught you.
Do you have a minute?
Hi, Emily.
Can we talk later?
I’m really struggling this morning.
You know, it’s just that you’ve been so busy,
and I’ve been waiting for the right moment;
I’d really just like to address it.
OK. What’s up?
It’s just that I’ve noticed
your posts lately on QuicPost.
What about them?
Well, do you really think they’re something
that a pioneer should be posting?
What? What are you talking about?
Some people might think you’re bragging.
Some people? What people?
It’s a business account.
I’ve got to show off my products.
I know. I get that.
It’s just—
I don’t know.
It could feel like you’re drawing
a little too much attention to yourself.
Who would think like that? You?
No, not just me; Celia felt the same.
You spoke to Celia about this?
I didn’t want to upset you.
Jake said that I needed to take . . .
Jake! So everyone thinks
my posts are inappropriate?
Not everyone, Haley.
That’s not what I am saying at all.
You are such . . .
Wow! I can’t believe you.
Who else have you spoken to?
You are just such a gossip!
I’m not gossiping. I was trying to . . .
You are!
I’m just trying to help you,
if you would just listen to me.
You’re so jealous!
If you’d just listen to me.
Oh yeah, listen to this.
And I expected more from you.
Haley, what are you talking about?
Gossiping about my posts!
Are you that lonely
that you’ve got nothing better to do?
Haley,
wait, please!
Were you left feeling a bit tense?
If so, you know
what uncontrolled anger can lead to.
Now that we’ve defined uncontrolled anger
and considered what it can lead to,
the next question is,
How can we put away uncontrolled anger?
First, we need to recognize
the danger of uncontrolled anger.
Proverbs 25:28 states
that “as a city broken through,
without a wall,
is the man who cannot control his temper.”
Strong city walls
were vital in ancient times.
Without them a city
would quickly fall to invaders;
likewise, so will those
who cannot control their temper.
By losing control, they
make themselves vulnerable
to the invasion of wrong thoughts
—thoughts that can cause them
to hurt themselves and others.
Uncontrolled anger can do just that.
Next, after recognizing the danger,
we must pause and then deal with the anger
before it causes us
to do something that we will regret.
When anger grows within us,
we’re wise to recall
what happened with Simeon and Levi.
We might also recall what happened
in the video dramatization
that we just viewed.
You see, in each case,
pausing before reacting out of anger
may have spared
much pain and heartache, true?
That is why we have this warning
at Proverbs 17:14:
“Before the quarrel breaks out,
take your leave.”
With that in mind,
each of us should ask himself:
‘Do I tend to jump to conclusions
‘when I don’t have all the facts?
‘If so, can I take my leave
and put away anger
before it starts to build up?’
The inspired advice
found at James 1:19 will help us to do so
—but only if we make
a sincere and determined effort
to apply what it says.
Let’s read that verse—James 1:19.
And here we find some simple steps
to help us put away uncontrolled anger.
It says: “Know this, my beloved brothers:
“Everyone must be quick to listen,
slow to speak, slow to anger.”
If we ask Jehovah to help us with this,
namely to “be quick to listen,
slow to speak, slow to anger,”
he will assist us to do so.
He will help us
to see the facts of the matter,
show understanding,
and then put away uncontrolled anger.
A word of caution, though:
To succeed in doing our part,
we must choose our associates wisely.
We could undermine all of our good work
and Jehovah’s help in controlling our anger
if we choose associates who are arrogant,
opinionated, or quick to become angry.
Regarding someone who is disposed to rage,
Proverbs 22:25 warns:
“Never learn his ways.”
Well, we’ve enjoyed
another outstanding series of talks
that should help us to keep awake,
maintain fine conduct,
and escape the judgment
that will soon come on this world.
As this symposium has emphasized,
we must do our utmost
to continue to put away peace wreckers
such as inappropriate boasting, envy,
dishonesty, harmful gossip,
and uncontrolled anger.
If we have a problem
with any of the peacemaking qualities
that we have discussed in this symposium,
seek Jehovah’s help
to change and then work at it.
Our sincere efforts to pursue peace
with our brothers and our sisters
will influence how earnestly
we are awaiting “Jehovah’s day”
and his promised new world.
Yes, our genuine efforts
will affect our hearts
and will be noticed by our heavenly Father.
Then, in his great mercy,
Jehovah will consider us
to be, as his Word says,
“spotless and unblemished and in peace”
—both with him
and with our fellow worshippers.
Thank you, brothers, for helping us
to strengthen our bond of unity.
Since the rebellion in Eden,
peace among mankind as a whole
has been lost.
Despite this, Jehovah has given peace
to those who trust in him.
How has he done so in the past,
and how does this strengthen
our faith in him today?
We invite you to enjoy Part 1
of the documentary
Jehovah Guides Us in the Way of Peace.
Our military forces are committed to peace.
We have chosen peace.
Our wish, our prayer, is for peace.
We yearn for peace.
We pray for peace.
For thousands
of years, humans have tried
to find peace
—peace as individuals,
peace as families,
peace for the entire human race.
We want to lay the foundation of peace
for generations to come.
We want to do the hard work now
so our children and our grandchildren
can grow up in a peaceful world.
The future we want:
opportunity and security for our families,
a rising standard of living,
a sustainable, peaceful planet for our kids
—all that is within our reach.
Yet, despite humans’ best efforts,
peace
has been elusive.
For millenniums,
rulers and governments
have tried to achieve peace
through treaties,
resolutions,
summits
and, ironically, war.
Our peace as humans
is more fragile than ever.
Man’s efforts to bring about lasting peace
have failed time and time again.
This isn’t surprising to us.
Jeremiah 10:23 tells us:
“It does not belong to man . . .
to direct his step.”
Humans were simply not designed
to rule themselves.
Good health, safety, overall well-being
—these are becoming harder to find
as we move further into what the Bible
refers to as “the last days.”
As long as human rule continues,
disunity will continue.
It’s true that global peace
cannot be obtained by human efforts alone.
But those who are close to God
can find peace of mind right now.
Isaiah 48:17, 18 says:
“I, Jehovah, am your God,
“the One teaching you to benefit yourself,
“the One guiding you
“in the way you should walk.
“If only you would pay attention
“to my commandments!
“Then your peace
would become just like a river.”
It’s only Jehovah
who has the ability to guide humans
to real, lasting peace.
He promises he will bring this about.
Until this happens,
Jehovah continues to provide ways
for us to experience peace now.
How does he do that?
By giving us “the peace of God
that surpasses all understanding.”
We aren’t the only ones
whose peace has been challenged.
God’s Word is filled
with accounts of faithful servants
whose peace was challenged
by the dominating forces of their day.
As we study and meditate on these accounts,
the lessons we learn from them
help us to trust in Jehovah
as he guides us to peace.
Understanding how these accounts
relate to Jehovah’s purpose to bring peace
by means of his Messianic Kingdom
gives us confidence
that his purpose never fails
and he will support
and guide us on into the future.
One of Jehovah’s prophets
who learned this lesson firsthand was Jonah.
Jonah lived in the ninth century B.C.E.
Jehovah assigned Jonah to go to Nineveh,
a city of the Assyrian Empire.
Based on what he knew about Nineveh,
Jonah considered this to be
an intimidating and threatening assignment.
The Assyrians were known as fierce warriors,
and Nineveh itself was later described
as a “city of bloodshed.”
So you can understand Jonah’s trepidation
when Jehovah asks him
to proclaim a judgment message
against this imposing city
and its pagan inhabitants.
In an attempt to find peace,
Jonah decides to go far away from Nineveh
and boards a boat headed for Tarshish.
Tarshish is generally associated
with modern-day Spain.
So from Israel,
this is the complete opposite direction
of Nineveh.
Jonah found anything but peace.
Look!
By the gods.
Furl the sail!
Now, this was no ordinary storm.
It was so severe that the ship
was in danger of being wrecked.
Captain, we’re taking on too much water!
This storm is from the gods!
Baal!
Eshmun!
The crew cried out to their gods,
but Jonah knew the true Source of the storm.
And now he accepts
personal responsibility for the situation.
Lift me up
and throw me into the sea,
and the sea will calm down for you;
for I know that it’s because of me
that this violent storm has come upon you.
Can you imagine the courage it took
for Jonah to make this request?
He had no way of knowing
if Jehovah would save him,
but he did not want others
to perish on his account.
In his mercy, Jehovah spares Jonah’s life.
How am I still alive?
What will become of me?
When faced
with a difficult assignment,
Jonah “got up to run away from Jehovah
to Tarshish.”
Jonah’s conscience had to bother him;
he had to be questioning his decision.
He tried to take matters into his own hands,
tried to find his own peace.
Where does he find himself?
In the belly of a fish!
Yet he calls to Jehovah
in a moment of despair.
O Jehovah,
out of the depths of the Grave,
I cry to you for help.
Please hear my voice.
What I have vowed, I will pay.
Jonah could have reasoned
that this was the end
of his assignment as Jehovah’s prophet.
After all, he did disobey direction.
So likely, he was surprised
to hear the word of Jehovah come to him
a second time.
Jonah!
Get up,
go to Nineveh the great city,
and proclaim to her
the message that I tell you.
Yes.
Thank you.
At first, Jonah trusted in himself
and didn’t understand
that Jehovah would protect him
from the violent Assyrians.
But after being given
a second chance, what happens?
Well, then he puts aside
his human concerns
and looks to Jehovah for protection.
In just 40 days more,
Nineveh will be overthrown.
Jehovah, the true God, has spoken.
This city will be destroyed.
Nineveh will be overthrown.
The true God will overthrow Nineveh.
The true God has spoken.
Eventually, the king himself repents
and orders everyone
in Nineveh to do the same.
Jonah learned a valuable lesson
from this experience.
By originally running away from Nineveh,
he chose to trust in himself
rather than putting his trust in Jehovah.
Are you Jonah?
I am.
Mommy says you saved us.
No, Jehovah saved you.
I was just—I was just a messenger.
Jonah learned
that without a doubt
Jehovah protects those
who trust and obey Him.
If Jehovah has asked you to do something,
if he’s asked me to do something,
if he’s leading us,
he absolutely will guide us through it.
Jonah’s account proves this.
Although the Ninevites were spared
because they repented (that’s true),
Assyria later
returned to its evil, wicked ways.
About a century
after Jonah’s judgment message,
King Sennacherib of Assyria brought
his armies against the cities of Judah,
including the city he wanted most
—Jerusalem.
King Hezekiah of Judah
was an outstanding king
who “held fast to Jehovah.”
From the beginning of his reign,
he proved to be zealous for true worship
not only in Judah but in all of Israel.
Hezekiah had done so much
to stand up for pure worship,
yet now he is faced with the prospect
of a siege against Jerusalem
by Sennacherib’s armies.
Hezekiah agrees to pay Sennacherib
a tribute in return for peace.
Yet, the armies continue their conquests,
as Sennacherib and his men besiege
the strongly fortified city of Lachish.
From here,
Sennacherib sends a part of his army
as well as military chiefs to Jerusalem
in an attempt to demand surrender.
The spokesman for the group was the Rabshakeh,
who spoke Hebrew fluently.
He loudly ridiculed Hezekiah
and taunted Jehovah,
boasting that Jehovah
was no match against King Sennacherib.
Imagine what these soldiers
must have been thinking.
Sennacherib’s armies were on a warpath,
taking city after city.
To Hezekiah, this was a defining moment.
He had to decide if he would trust in himself
or trust in Jehovah.
My brothers,
we must remember that Jehovah
is fully able to rescue us,
just as he has in times past.
God’s Word . . .
King Hezekiah,
will you not even now face the facts?
We are trapped!
The Assyrians are at our gate,
and you cling to the belief
that nothing bad will happen.
You will destroy everything
you so hope to preserve
—the temple, Jerusalem,
our very lives.
Shebna, I am not blind
to the dangers that we face.
I too am afraid.
But if Jehovah
allows Jerusalem to fall,
so be it.
How can we give up what belongs to Jehovah?
So as a man of faith,
Hezekiah focused on Jehovah’s ability
to save His people
despite Sennacherib’s
continued advances toward Jerusalem.
I’m curious about this king of yours.
Who does he think
will come to save him from me?
Jehovah, your God,
is weak!
He will cringe before my god Asshur.
Hezekiah remained
determined to trust in Jehovah.
This decision required
a tremendous amount of faith,
especially with more than
185,000 Assyrian soldiers
headed toward Jerusalem.
Instead of trusting in himself,
he continued to look
for Jehovah as the Source of true peace
even as an attack seemed imminent.
And Jehovah again
showed just how insignificant
human rulers are in comparison to him.
Hezekiah learned
that when a way out seems impossible,
trusting in Jehovah always leads to success.
Jehovah rewarded that trust
with victory over the Assyrians.
This is a lesson
we can apply now and in the near future.
There may be situations
when true worshippers seem trapped,
but never forget
that Jehovah is all-powerful.
He’s leading his people,
and we can follow
his guidance with full confidence.
Jehovah will protect those
who trust in him at Armageddon.
Jerusalem remained safe
against attack for the time being,
but peaceful conditions didn’t last long.
Hezekiah’s son Manasseh
did what was detestable
in the eyes of Jehovah.
He brought back Baal worship
and personally took its vilest practices
to extremes,
even putting a carved image of a false god
right inside Jehovah’s temple.
So here you have a king
who’s supposed to be protecting
the people from idolatrous influence
doing the exact opposite
—building altars to false gods.
He even went so far
as to pass his own sons through the fire,
sacrificing them to these gods.
The peace with God that Hezekiah
worked so hard to achieve for the nation
is now reversed by the actions of his son.
Because of this,
Jehovah punished Manasseh severely.
He allowed the king of Assyria
to take him captive to Babylon.
While in captivity,
Manasseh ultimately repented.
He humbled himself,
and he stayed faithful
right to the end of his life.
Grandfather!
We can imagine him impressing
the importance of faithfulness
to Jehovah on his young grandson Josiah.
Listen to me.
Jehovah is holy,
and you must serve him
the way he wants us to.
All other gods
are powerless.
Yet, in spite of all this,
the people still thought
that they could serve Jehovah and Baal.
So after becoming king,
Josiah started a campaign against idolatry.
I’ve seen these cheaper.
Take it or leave it.
We start here!
No!
This is what we will do to every false god in the land.
He tore down altars used for false worship,
sacred poles, images, and statues.
He was intent
on cleansing the land of idolatry.
Now, he showed remarkable courage
to stand up for true worship
at a time when few were doing so.
There’s no doubt this was a difficult task.
At times, he may have even wondered
if he was doing the right thing.
It’s possible Jehovah provided Josiah
with assurance from the prophet Jeremiah.
This is what Jehovah says: “Look!
“A son named Josiah
“will be born to the house of David!
“He will sacrifice on you
“the priests of the high places,
“those making sacrificial smoke on you,
and he will burn human bones on you.”
That prophecy
made over 300 years earlier confirmed
that Josiah was the one
prophesied to act against false worship.
This may have given Josiah
even greater incentive and courage
to continue his campaign,
which now included repairing the temple.
These actions contributed
to the peaceful conditions
that elevated pure worship.
Josiah did so much
to restore pure worship.
That is why we love him.
Yet, the peoples’ heart condition
remained polluted,
so the nation required severe discipline.
Jeremiah prophesied
a conquest of the Babylonians
against Judah.
All this land
will be reduced to ruins,
and this land and its inhabitants
will have to serve the king of Babylon
for 70 years.
Daniel himself may have heard
Jeremiah speak those words.
And he certainly
saw it come true as he and his family
were exiled to Babylon.
Talk about peace being interrupted!
Daniel was a young Judean prince taken
from his homeland
and separated from his family.
But being chosen to receive special training
in the court of King Nebuchadnezzar
presented another set of challenges.
The entire way
of Babylonian life was contrary
to what Daniel knew growing up in Judah.
But Daniel was determined
not to pollute himself
with foods Jehovah would not approve of.
And Jehovah blessed
Daniel’s determination to be faithful,
as he was selected to serve
as one of King Nebuchadnezzar’s wise men.
Nebuchadnezzar was a warrior-king
intent on building a great empire.
After he officially
took the throne
in 624 B.C.E., his domain
grew with each conquest.
Babylon became an epicenter
of trade and commerce.
Nebuchadnezzar undertook
huge building projects throughout the city,
which made the city seem impregnable.
Imagine the sense of security
the inhabitants of Babylon must have felt,
locked safely behind the city’s walls.
Nebuchadnezzar
attributed the prosperity
and security all around him
to the power of his false gods.
The chief of these false gods
was Marduk, the god of war.
Yet, these false gods and their priests
would prove to be worthless.
One night,
King Nebuchadnezzar had a strange dream.
Call the wise men!
O king, may you live on forever.
Relate the dream to your servants.
We will tell the interpretation.
No!
If you don’t make the dream known to me
along with the interpretation,
you’ll be dismembered,
and your houses will be turned into public latrines.
There is not a man on earth
who can do what the king demands.
What the king is asking is difficult.
No one exists
who could tell this to the king except
—except the gods.
Seize them!
Kill them!
Jerah.
You’re in danger.
Why? What happened?
I didn’t hear everything,
but the wise men angered the king.
Everyone is to be executed by dawn.
Bring Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah here.
I’ll try to learn more.
This edict to kill all the wise men
would also include Daniel and his companions.
So let’s look at this
from Daniel’s perspective.
Here he is, a young man in a foreign land,
serving in the court of one
of the most powerful and violent men alive.
And that man is now demanding
that someone, in effect, read his mind:
“Tell me my dream,
and tell me what it means.”
O king,
interpretations belong to my God, Jehovah.
He knows your dream and what it means.
Well, where is your God?
Where?
I believe that he—
I know that he will reveal it to me.
Please, give me time.
Daniel is not acting
on previous experience.
He hasn’t received interpretations
of dreams from Jehovah.
Instead, he is acting on faith
—faith that he had learned
by studying the sacred books of his time.
These books
likely included the inspired writings
of Moses, David, Solomon, Isaiah,
Jeremiah, and other prophets.
Oh, we can only imagine
Daniel poring over these scrolls,
opening up his heart to Jehovah,
begging Jehovah to give him wisdom and understanding.
He loved it.
There’s no doubt that
as Daniel studied these accounts,
his faith was strengthened
and his bond with Jehovah drew even closer.
So even though Daniel knew nothing
of King Nebuchadnezzar’s dream,
he was fully convinced
that Jehovah would reveal the dream
and its interpretation
and prove to be Daniel’s salvation.
Do we know exactly which accounts
Daniel was able to draw from at this time?
It’s impossible to say for a certainty,
but we do know he had access to “the books.”
He references the prophecies of Jeremiah.
Daniel could see how Jehovah blessed
faithful, obedient men in the past.
So by asking Nebuchadnezzar for time,
he wasn’t looking to buy himself
another day of life;
he was allowing Jehovah to reward his faith
by revealing the dream to him.
Daniel strikes a balance here.
Although he is confident
that Jehovah will reveal the dream to him,
he isn’t casual in the way
he handled the situation.
He did what any God-fearing man
would do here.
He approached Jehovah in prayer.
O Jehovah,
surely you didn’t bring us here just to die.
What will people say?
We told them
that you are the God of the heavens,
the only God who can reveal secrets.
Please, vindicate yourself.
I have found a man from the exiles of Judah
who can make known
the interpretation to the king.
I know who he is.
Can you really make known to me
the dream that I saw
and its interpretation?
There is a God in the heavens
who is a Revealer of secrets,
and he has made known to King Nebuchadnezzar
what is to happen
in the final part of the days.
This is your dream:
You saw an immense image.
That image
was standing in front of you.
You yourself are the head of gold.
But after you another kingdom will rise,
inferior to you.
Then another kingdom, a third one, of copper,
that will rule over the whole earth.
As for the fourth kingdom,
it will be strong like iron.
The kingdom will be divided.
And as the toes of the feet
were partly of iron and partly of clay,
so the kingdom will be partly strong
and partly fragile.
This took a tremendous amount of faith
and courage on the part of Daniel.
Now, we may find our peace threatened,
our very lives might be on the line.
In that moment, we can turn
to Jehovah God in prayer,
opening up our hearts,
confident that he will support us.
Like both Daniel and Jonah,
we’ve been given an assignment
to proclaim a message.
This requires courage to speak out boldly
concerning Jehovah’s judgments
against those who oppose his sovereignty.
Both of these prophets are excellent examples
of Jehovah backing those who trust in him.
Jehovah will always be with us
as long as we have faith in him.
When we face situations that seem impossible,
as in the case with Hezekiah,
we have the ability to tap
into the most powerful force there is!
As this system comes to a close,
we will find ourselves in situations
that test our courage and threaten our peace.
We will have to stand up
for pure worship
just like Josiah, and this will be unpopular.
But with Jehovah on our side,
we can face those situations with confidence.
He’s all-powerful,
and he’s going to help us through it.
Now, here’s the interesting thing:
Some of the prophecies that Daniel recorded
applied not only to the future
of the Babylonian Empire
but also outline world events
to our day and beyond.
And these events are being fulfilled
right before our very eyes!
What a motivating presentation!
Even when our peace is threatened,
we can focus on how our integrity
relates to Jehovah’s purpose,
and we can endure with joy.
We look forward to watching Part 2
of this important consideration
during the final session of our convention.
Now let’s sing together song number 130,
entitled “Be Forgiving.”
That’s song number 130.