Have you applied
to the School for Kingdom Evangelizers
but not been invited?
Or have you wanted to apply
but wondered if the time was right?
You are not alone.
Because of the pandemic,
classes are still suspended.
But if you are a pioneer
between the ages of 23 and 65
and would like to attend
a future class of SKE,
please contact your congregation secretary
and fill out the online application
so that it can be considered
when classes resume.
As a reminder, your application
is active for one year.
Therefore, you must apply each year
that you desire to be considered.
Additionally, we are pleased to inform you
that graduates
of the Ministerial Training School
or the Bible School for Single Brothers
who are still single and in full-time service
may now apply
for the School for Kingdom Evangelizers.
Is it possible to maintain our peace
when dealing with intense trials
and pressures?
How does Jehovah care for our needs
when we are in distress?
The following video will introduce us
to brothers and sisters
who have been blessed by Jehovah
with peace.
The title is
How Our Brothers Are Enjoying Peace
Despite . . . Opposition, Illness,
Economic Problems, Natural Disasters.
As long as we live in Satan’s world,
all of us will face situations
that can rob us of our peace.
Regaining that peace can be difficult
but not impossible.
In this video, we will hear
from three sisters and two couples
who will speak candidly about their trials
and how they struggled to cope with them.
But in spite of what they have endured,
please take note of their smiles, their joy,
and what they did to regain
and maintain their peace.
And take special note
of how Jehovah helped them.
The Governing Body knows that many of you
are suffering circumstances
not unlike the ones we will hear about,
and they trust that the examples
in this video
will help each of you to maintain your peace
as you endure various trials.
Brothers and sisters all over the world
are facing
natural disasters,
economic collapse,
illness,
and persecution.
Despite all that,
they keep joy and peace.
I can learn a lot from them.
My name is Antoinette.
I live here in Las Vegas, Nevada,
with my supermom
and my troublemaking sister.
Family and friends have always been
important to me.
As a child, I lived with my mom and dad
and I was very close
to my dad’s side of the family.
It was very loving, unified, and fun.
I was pretty happy.
But I already was starting to feel
the effects of my cancer.
We just didn’t know what it was really.
One day I was OK, and then the next day
I started feeling bad, you know.
In my childhood,
I played an unusual game.
I would catch insects,
put them in a jar, and then bring them home.
Then, I would get books,
such as the Criminal Procedural Code,
open them up,
and start judging one of the bugs.
I would play the role
of investigator and judge at the same time.
I was born into a family where everyone,
starting with my grandparents,
was either wearing an officer’s uniform
or a judge’s robe.
That’s why I had
this strong sense of justice.
But in 1989,
my mother was in a tragic car accident,
and
she got severe burns
on her face, hands, and body.
And then my father,
at seeing my mom’s condition,
decided to leave us.
Yeah.
And it was at that moment, I guess,
that my world, my ideals,
they crumbled.
As a little kid, I always wanted, like,
one big happy family.
Once we moved to New York for my treatment,
I no longer had that big family bond anymore.
What I was feeling back then in New York was
just sadness,
never really peace.
Here in California,
we’re used to fires.
But when I got the call to evacuate
that morning,
I never knew that by that evening,
the whole town of Paradise would be gone.
Just before the fire,
we had the needs of the congregation
where they instructed us
what to do in the case of a disaster.
I had the truck full of gas,
I had my go bag ready,
and I had a map of where I was going.
I was ready.
The brothers, also in their instructions,
said to obey the traffic instructors.
The instructor told us to turn right,
and I didn’t want to turn right,
but they said obey them.
So I turned right,
though I thought it would be really bad.
The smoke got darker and darker,
and finally it got black.
You couldn’t see anything.
My mom has always told me
that I’ve always been
a caregiver ever since I was a little girl;
it was just part of who I was.
I don’t like to see people suffer;
it’s very difficult for me.
I remember that when I first started working
as a nurse,
I would always cry.
I cried—
Literally I cried
every day that I had to go to work.
Not only was I overwhelmed
being a new nurse
but also
I was battling my depression.
In 2017,
I was the treasurer
for a prestigious bank in Nicaragua,
and I was the father of a one-year-old son.
We were very happy.
But then I lost my job.
So I said, ‘I have the experience,
and Jehovah will help me find another job,
something similar.’
And I kept looking for jobs,
but doors kept closing.
I felt very tense;
it made me feel very useless,
like
I couldn’t even provide for my family.
It was something very difficult for me.
These dear brothers and sisters
faced serious challenges.
They may have had moments
when they felt like Job
when he said: “I loathe my life.”
That is not an unusual human emotion.
Sometimes things in life
don’t work out as we had hoped,
and it can hurt us deeply.
Does this mean that we are helpless victims
of our circumstances?
Not at all!
Please pay close attention
and take note of why we can say
that Margaret, Feliks,
Miguel, Nikki, and Antoinette
are not helpless victims.
To the contrary,
they are conquerors.
As you watch and listen,
look for specific actions they took
to maintain their peace
and please give thoughtful attention
to ways that you can imitate their faith.
Growing up, I wondered,
‘Why does the Supreme Judge, God,
allow injustice and suffering?’
And inside of me,
I had this need to restore justice.
It was such a burning desire within me.
And with that in mind,
I moved to Russia to stay with my sister.
She started to study the Bible
and was overflowing with the truth.
We talked for hours till late into the night.
So that’s when my special relationship
with Jehovah began.
That’s when I got a taste of what it’s like
to have a caring Father.
It had been a while
since I was able to feel that.
My baptism date was very exciting.
The spiritual family I inherited
was very vast.
You can instantly feel the love.
I got baptized,
and it seemed like miracles happened
one after the other.
We had a great life.
And then
the persecution started
with Brother Christensen,
and then there was a ripple effect
of arrests, one after the other.
Then it was our turn.
In June of 2018,
a huge group of armed men came to us,
to our home.
They represented the ideals of my childhood.
But now these people,
this judicial system,
became the source of injustice to me.
I was sitting in a cage,
the same way my bugs used to be in a jar.
I guess I felt like they did.
In your head
at that moment when you hear the verdict
that you’ll stay in prison,
it’s like you’ve been knocked unconscious.
You’ve been hit in the head with something,
and there’s just a ringing sound
in your ears.
And so I was taken away in handcuffs.
Of course, I wasn’t in the best mood.
But then
the doors of the elevator opened up,
and in front of us,
a lot of brothers and sisters
were clapping their hands
as hard as they could.
And some were crying,
but not crying
because they felt sorry for me.
They cried because they loved us
and because they were proud of us.
That’s what always happens.
When you’re just about to lose
all your strength,
Jehovah does that something for you
that gives you a second wind.
And so, the applause, the love,
the tears,
the shouts,
“Hang in there; everything will be OK!”
—they gave me a second wind.
And with renewed strength,
I could run the next part of the race.
One of the guards was so surprised
that he said,
“Now that’s some support you’ve got!”
Yeah.
Without friends, I would be very lonely.
I would constantly be focusing on my illness.
The day I met Marissa was at a convention.
She’s a really great friend,
a spiritual friend.
When she’d take me
to my hospital appointments,
we would eat out.
I think food is just the common language
between everyone, you know.
When you talk about food, you know,
it’s like:
“Ah! Yes, we have something to talk about,”
you know.
I would be excited when she would take me
to my hospital appointment.
She always makes me laugh, you know.
She always helps me have a good time
no matter what.
Again, friends really help encourage me.
Proverbs 17:17 says:
“A true friend shows love at all times
and is a brother who is born
for times of distress.”
And I have seen this come true in my life.
When I lost my job at the bank,
well, I felt very depressed, troubled, tense.
And I have a good friend who I can talk to,
and when I told him how I was feeling,
he told me:
“Look, Miguel, don’t look for the same
“line of work.
“Maybe what you need to do
is make a change in your life.
“Why don’t you find some simple work
outside of an office for a time?
“That can help you to keep your eye simple
and allow you to provide for your family.”
I watched my wife make bread for our family,
and one day I told her:
“I’m going to make that bread,
but not for our family.
I’m going to make it to sell.”
So she told me, “No, are you crazy?”
It was a big change—right?—
from having a position at a bank
and handling a lot of money
to selling on the street.
So I told her,
“Look, I’m going to put this hat on,”
and I put like a chef’s hat on.
And I told her,
“I’ll be back in less than an hour,
whether I sell or not.”
And that’s what happened.
And to her surprise,
I came back without any bread.
So when I got ready
to leave the second time to sell,
she said: “OK. Go, but leave the hat here.”
I also started to iron clothes
for people in their homes,
and it looked strange
because normally where we live
that type of work is done by a woman.
But for a man to go and iron clothes
at someone’s home,
you don’t see that.
But I didn’t want to just sit back
with my arms crossed
and see what would happen.
No!
I had to put my hands to work
to earn a living for my family.
So I would preach one day,
and the next day I would iron clothes.
The next day I would preach, and the day
after that I would go out and sell bread.
So my mind was always occupied
on doing something,
either for the Kingdom or my family.
And that helped me a lot.
I was feeling so sad.
I really needed Jehovah’s help
to figure out what was going on with me.
And I remember
that the 2009 article about depression
came out.
And I realized: ‘OK, Jehovah,
you’re telling me this is what I have.
‘So now that I realize I have this,
I’ve got to figure out how I can manage it.’
So I changed my eating habits.
I started exercising a lot more.
I realized that exercising and eating healthy
really, really did help.
Also, I made a journal,
and I made different sections
of the different aspects of my depression
that I dealt with.
In each section, I would put scriptures;
I would put articles.
And the illustrations, the pictures,
they speak a lot without saying anything.
Jehovah hears us.
Jehovah cares.
After some time in prison,
they transferred me to a different cell.
In it were inmates who followed the orders
of the investigators.
They did everything they could
to other inmates
to make life unbearable.
Why did they do this?
To break a person
so that they would start to collaborate
with the investigators,
confess to everything, and then be able
to get transferred to another area.
Psalm 37:3:
“Trust in Jehovah and do what is good.”
I said: “Jehovah, please help me
to stay loyal to you.
Please help me.”
My prayers were really simple
—actually like two words: “Jehovah, help!
Jehovah, help! Jehovah, help!”
Despite how they treated me,
when I dealt with others,
I tried to treat them with kindness.
These people,
they made life
uncomfortable, unbearable,
but when they were treated kindly,
they started to soften.
They began to treat me differently.
When I was being transferred
out of that cell,
the inmate who ran the area
called me over to him and said,
“Come sit beside me.”
And I sat down.
Then he said, “If anybody in this prison
touches you,
tell him that I’ll come looking for him.”
Then he said, “Get his things”
(he told the other prisoners).
The cell doors opened
and the guards saw
a crowd of inmates
grabbing my things
and putting them out into the hallway.
I left the cell
without having to carry a thing!
The guard quietly closed the door.
And before the inmates
returned to their cells,
they even said goodbye, hugged me,
and said: “Hang in there!
You’re going to be OK.”
They went into the cell, and the guard
closed the door and asked me,
“Boy, how long have you been in there?”
I said, “Three weeks.”
He said: “Well, normally
people leave this cell beaten up,
“and they’re thrown out by the other inmates.
“They have to carry their own things,
and that’s if the other inmates
haven’t thrown their stuff out the door.”
He couldn’t believe what had just happened.
That’s Jehovah.
Exercising, changing my diet,
the publications, journaling
—that was my lifeline.
That really actually helped me
for a long time.
But it came to a point
where it stopped working as effectively.
I remember getting ready,
dressing for the meeting,
and I was fine.
I was getting dressed for the meeting
and about to walk out the door,
but I couldn’t.
There was this overwhelming fear
that came over me
and an overwhelming sadness
that came over me.
And I just lost it; I just started crying.
I couldn’t get myself together.
It was bad.
It got really bad;
my depression got really bad.
So it was very difficult for me
to approach the brothers
to ask them for help.
But at that time, I knew that if I didn’t,
that
something bad would happen.
So I decided: ‘You know what?
I’m going to ask for a shepherding call
with my brothers,’
because I’d never talked about my depression
with the elders at all.
This was my first time speaking with them.
And there was one brother, one of the elders,
who also battled depression.
And he suggested,
“Have you thought
about seeking medical help?”
Seeking professional help
was something I never wanted to do.
I thought that I didn’t need to do it,
but sometimes there comes a point where
you need additional help
and what you’re doing is not enough.
In this world, they make you feel
that it’s a bad thing,
that depression is a dirty word,
or that seeking medical help
is something that you don’t do.
But I realized also
that seeking medical help
was part of my being able
to worship Jehovah effectively.
That’s me doing my part.
Not everyone needs to take that step,
but for me, this is what I need to do.
And I’m glad I did it because of the fact
that I’ve never ever felt this good
in my life.
About a year later,
we were released.
But my wife and I understood
that they could put me back in prison again,
so
we needed to use
the time until then to the full
in the best way possible.
So, what did we do?
Psalm 119:165:
“Abundant peace belongs to those
who love your law.”
We had family worship,
read the Bible, and prayed together.
That’s how I spent my four months of freedom.
Then I was put into prison
for three years.
When they told me
about my cancer being gone,
I was really happy; I was ecstatic.
I was like: ‘Finally I’m going
to get to do normal things
‘that a kid my age should be able to do.
I don’t need to be afraid
or anxious anymore.’
Unfortunately, I did relapse again,
and basically right now
my present condition is
there’s nothing really more to do.
They’re just waiting
to let nature take its course basically,
and that’s it.
In harmony with Ephesians 4:26,
I had to let myself process the news
and let myself be sad and be angry.
Let yourself feel those feelings;
do not try to repress them.
But you can control
your thoughts and your actions.
Pretty much my whole life
has revolved around my illness,
but I’ve learned how to shift focus.
I just don’t focus on myself all the time.
I focus on others and their trials,
which are different but just as hard.
You read the stories
on jw.org in the Newsroom.
The Russian brothers and sisters,
I pray for them constantly because
they are going through a very tough time.
“There is [definitely] more happiness
in giving than receiving.”
And in our situation, this proved true.
I would say
this really helps to relieve your pain.
If you focus on yourself,
your pain gets worse.
When you focus on others
and on their problems,
your pain lessens, diminishes.
Hello!
Antoinette, I was so—
When I was told
that we would talk with each other,
this was something very special for me.
Same for me too.
When the brothers told me as well
about meeting you, I was really excited.
Thank you for your prayers
in behalf of the brothers in Russia.
They are precious.
We can learn so much from you.
Thank you.
It’s really nice of you to say that.
We’ve both been through very many hardships.
I’m sure prison was super hard.
You know, in prison,
us brothers had a saying,
“If you ask: ‘How much worse can it get?’
you won’t have to wait long to find out.”
Or in other words, when you think,
‘How much worse can it get?’
for sure something worse is bound to happen.
And when we received our sentence,
we thought:
‘Well, that’s it.
That’s the worst that could happen.’
And then, of course, it got worse.
Upon arrival at the prison,
we were beaten up
and for hours we were humiliated.
We thought, ‘How much worse can it get?’
Then the next day, we were told,
“You are going to the punishment cell.”
We thought,
‘Well, how much worse can it get?’
At first, it started with one floor,
then it went to another floor,
and then the whole entire hospital.
Every floor had COVID patients.
That was some of the hardest nursing
that I’ve ever done in my life
in all of my years of nursing.
And we lost a lot of good nurses
who were right in the trenches with me
who were in there doing their best.
We lost a lot of good people.
Even though I was on medication to help me,
it still didn’t take the depression away.
You’re like: ‘What’s the point?
‘I can’t save anyone.
I can’t, I can’t help anyone.’
It was devastating.
It truly, truly was devastating.
Have you ever felt as Feliks did
when he asked,
“How much worse can it get?”
Nevertheless, a spiritual person
can see each new challenge
as an opportunity to rely on Jehovah.
As we watch
the concluding part of this video,
please take note of how Jehovah strengthened
these brothers and sisters
and deepened their friendship with him.
Think about your own circumstances
and the ways that Jehovah
has helped you through trials,
and have full confidence
that he will continue to do so.
And then I decided
that I was going to stop asking,
“How much worse could it get?”
I asked Jehovah for endurance
and joy for that day—just for that day.
And at those times, I just
cry to Jehovah,
talk to Jehovah about how I’m feeling,
and just ask for his peace
to help me to deal.
I’ve talked to Jehovah
very intimately and personally
but never like I have
when I was so alone there.
I realized that I was going to die.
I asked Jehovah if he saw enough good in me,
that he would just resurrect me
and that I’d love to be in his new world
and see my husband again and my children.
And I thanked him so much
for the life that I had.
And I felt such a peace
like I’d never felt before.
And then
I just knew it was Jehovah getting me out.
The obedience, just doing what we were told,
it came from Jehovah, and it was so simple.
That gave him something to bless,
and it may have saved my life.
I just never wanted to be a burden on people,
but
the brothers and sisters
had come from all over the country
to do work for this house
and the other houses—all of them.
They made me feel wanted,
and they made me feel loved.
To feel like Jehovah cared enough
to give attention to me,
I
just felt so unworthy.
And here all these people
are here taking care of me.
And you just look at them,
and then you think:
‘I’m part of this organization.
I’ve got to do better.
I’ve got to be like them
and make other people happy.’
When I’m able to help people
who are battling depression,
I feel like Jehovah is using me in that way,
and it makes me happy
that I can be of use to Jehovah.
It’s good to feel—
It’s so nice to feel good again,
to feel happy again, to be able to smile,
to be able to take in enjoyment
of the small things, you know,
in Jehovah’s creation
—and, you know, just be happy that I’m alive.
So
yeah, yeah.
Now I have a stable job.
I work at a hardware store.
And I feel at peace.
The adversities have made me stronger,
and overall, I have
a much closer relationship with Jehovah.
But I’m still making bread.
And at home, yeah,
I’m the one who irons the clothes.
After a while, I found out
that I was being deported.
I remember getting off the train.
They took me through the back door,
but my wife, Zhenya,
was standing at the main entrance.
She was on the phone. She couldn’t see me.
She was looking at the main entrance.
And I threw my bag down as I ran to her.
She could see from the corner of her eyes
someone was running.
She was a little confused, even scared.
And there I was
hugging the person I loved the most.
It was one
of the most beautiful days of my life.
Hi.
Privet.
Hello.
When I heard that you were praying for us
and for the brothers and sisters in Russia,
it really encouraged me and Feliks.
It’s such an example for me personally.
We mentioned it in our prayer yesterday;
Feliks was saying
that you are a great example
of how we need
to genuinely care
for our brothers and sisters.
We love you very much.
Goodbye.
It was nice meeting you.
My cancer is uncurable,
but I know the cure is in the new system.
So that’s the cure!
I like to imagine, ‘When that time happens,
what will I be doing?’
Obviously, I’m going to be jumping for joy
because I’m going to be rid of my cancer.
I’m going to enjoy food
that we never really got to enjoy,
and I’m going to have so many animals.
I’m going to make a house.
I’m going to learn how to make a house.
Peace in this world is not the absence
of illness,
danger,
persecution,
or economic problems.
Peace in this world
is listening to Jehovah’s guidance,
praying to Jehovah constantly,
meditating on Jehovah’s Word
and his promises.
Peace in this world is also
having good friends by our side
and having a good sense of humor.
What I’ve learned from all of this
is peace isn’t from what’s outside,
from what’s going on,
or from what you’re experiencing.
I’ve learned that peace is on the inside,
and that comes from Jehovah.
These examples we’ve just seen
are of ordinary people
“with feelings like ours.”
Yet, they felt peace
even when confronting serious trials.
How did they do it?
When Miguel lost his job,
he kept his focus on serving Jehovah
and he was not too proud to do humble work
to provide for his family.
Margaret was prepared for a natural disaster,
and throughout her ordeal,
she prayed to Jehovah.
While struggling with depression,
Nikki did research using our publications
and asked for help from the elders.
Even when facing brutal persecution,
Feliks showed kindness to his persecutors.
He knew that the way he responded
would reflect Christian qualities.
And dear Antoinette,
despite her diagnosis,
focuses not on herself
but on helping others.
As she said, the cure for her
—as it is for all of us—
is God’s Kingdom.
If you are experiencing trials,
focus on what you can control,
help others,
be grateful,
and rely on Jehovah and his organization.
If you are not experiencing serious trials,
do what you can to prepare for them
by building yourself up spiritually.
Do not be anxious.
Fear of what might happen
is often worse than the trial itself.
Trust in Jehovah, and be assured
that he will never abandon his friends.
The dear brothers and sisters
whom we’ve just listened to
are doing well spiritually.
We thank them
for participating in these interviews.
We’d also like to thank
all our brothers and sisters
working in the medical field
who have gone the extra mile
during this pandemic.
James 5:11 reads:
“We consider happy those who have endured.
“You have heard of the endurance of Job
“and have seen the outcome Jehovah gave,
that Jehovah is very tender in affection
and merciful.”
The blessings we receive by enduring trials
can strengthen us for the future
and help us to become the kind of person
that Jehovah wants us to be.
The inner peace and joy we experience
is a gift from Jehovah.
As these brothers and sisters
from around the world
have reminded us,
we need never doubt
that our wonderful heavenly Father will bless
all those who continue loving him.
We thank all of the sisters and brothers
who were interviewed
for their sincere comments
and for allowing us to benefit and learn
from their experiences.
Those candid interviews show
that we can remain at peace
even when enduring severe trials.
Jehovah always supports and cares for us,
his loyal servants.
The time has now come
for the baptism discourse.
We encourage all baptism candidates
to pay particular attention.
How does walking in Jehovah’s way
bring peace?
How can we stay on the road
to everlasting life?
Please listen carefully
as Brother William Turner,
a helper to the Service Committee,
delivers the talk
“Go On Walking ‘in the Way of Peace.’”
We cannot express
to you baptism candidates around the world
how much of a privilege it is for us
to share in this occasion with you.
You are following through
on the most important decision
you’ve ever made
—to make it known publicly
that you have dedicated your life to God.
We know your situations vary.
Some of you candidates
were raised knowing about Jehovah,
but you had to develop your own
personal relationship with him.
Others of you may be taking this step
after learning about Jehovah more recently.
But whatever your circumstances,
likely it was a journey
—a figurative road
you had to travel to get to this point.
In fact, the Bible also compares true worship
to a road, a path,
or a walkway that has to be traveled.
At Acts 9:2,
as the first-century
Christian congregation was being established,
Jesus’ disciples used the term “The Way”
to designate their newly established
form of worship.
They understood that as baptized Christians,
they were walking on a new path
and every aspect of their lives was involved.
And that’s going to be
the case for you as well.
In fact, note how the Bible describes this.
Turn with me, please,
to the book of Ephesians.
And note what is stated
in Ephesians chapter 4,
and we’ll read verses 22 through 24.
There it says: “You were taught
to put away the old personality
“that conforms
to your formal course of conduct
“and that is being corrupted
according to its deceptive desires.
“And you should continue to be made new
“in your dominant mental attitude,
“and should put on the new personality
“that was created according to God’s will
in true righteousness and loyalty.”
So like the first-century Christians,
you have come to know
the truth about Jehovah.
And the things you’ve learned
have led you to become baptism candidates.
Like all of God’s people,
you’ve done what verse 22 states,
“put away the old personality.”
But there in verse 23,
we must also “continue to be made new
in [our] dominant mental attitude.”
This involves our thoughts
—what we allow our mind to dwell on.
Now, you know, the footnote for that verse
indicates this term could also be rendered
as “the force actuating [our] mind”
or literally translated
“to the spirit of your mind.”
In the English language,
perhaps you’ve heard someone say
that they are in good spirits
or you’ve heard someone
described as being mean-spirited.
Well, that’s a description
of one’s dominant mental attitude
—one’s thoughts and motivations.
It’s what moves us to act the way that we do.
Our goal as baptized servants of Jehovah
is to gain a dominant mental attitude
that aligns and is in harmony
with God’s thoughts.
Now, that won’t always be easy.
It takes time and a lot of effort.
Those who walk
in the way of peace
often encounter trials.
And to stay on that road,
we must be willing to make sacrifices.
Like some of those first-century Christians,
we may have to endure direct persecution.
But if we continue to walk in Jehovah’s way,
we’re going to be happy
and Jehovah is going to bless us.
At Luke 1:79, he assures us
that he will “guide our feet
in the way of peace.”
That’s a comforting thought, isn’t it?
So we’re excited.
We’re excited that you baptism candidates
have undertaken this journey.
And know that you have
some eight and a half million
other Witnesses on this road with you.
And today,
it is our honor and privilege to welcome you
—to welcome you to Jehovah’s way of peace
and “the road leading off into life.”
As we go through our discussion today,
we’re going to answer three questions.
First, why is it important
that we do not give up
on walking in Jehovah’s way of peace?
Second,
how does walking
in Jehovah’s way bring us peace?
And third, what can we do
to continue walking
in Jehovah’s way of peace?
Well, let’s address our first question:
Why is it important that we do not give up
on walking in Jehovah’s way of peace?
Now, to answer that, let’s turn, please,
to 2 Corinthians chapter 4.
And we’ll note
2 Corinthians 4:16-18.
There it reads:
“Therefore, we do not give up,
“but even if the man
we are outside is wasting away,
“certainly the man we are inside
is being renewed from day to day.
“For though the tribulation
is momentary and light,
“it works out for us a glory
“that is of more and more
surpassing greatness and is everlasting;
“while we keep our eyes,
“not on the things seen,
but on the things unseen.
“For the things seen are temporary,
but the things unseen are everlasting.”
Do you see why we can’t give up?
It’s because being one of Jehovah’s Witnesses
requires that we remain active
and persevere in the way of peace.
You dear candidates have not given up
in your efforts to please Jehovah
and to qualify to become part of his people.
And why is that?
It’s because of your love for him.
And you know that any trials
and obstacles you face now
are “momentary and light”
when compared to an eternity
in God’s new world.
Today, you will enter
into a special relationship
with Jehovah God.
So don’t let anyone or anything
jeopardize that relationship.
Let it be something that you cherish
because that relationship is everlasting.
So keep walking in Jehovah’s way of peace.
Focus on what it means
to have him as a Friend,
to have him guiding your steps.
If you don’t give up,
then despite any trials you face,
you will continue
to enjoy Jehovah’s blessings.
And we’re confident that you can do so.
But to highlight how this can be done,
at this time,
we’re pleased to introduce
Sister Indira Alfonso.
Sister Alfonso was baptized in 2006
and now serves with her husband
as Bethel family members in Warwick.
Sister Alfonso,
can you tell us a little about your journey,
how you became associated
with Jehovah’s Witnesses?
Yes, I was born in Cuba,
but my mom and I moved
to the United States when I was nine.
Even though I was young,
I felt it was important to look for God.
So whenever we moved,
I would visit the local churches in the area,
even getting baptized in a number of them.
When I was 11, my mom
let me move in with my aunt,
who was one of Jehovah’s Witnesses.
And from there, she asked my mom
if I could study with a pioneer sister
from her congregation, and my mom agreed.
Well, it’s nice to see
that even at a young age
you had a spiritual need.
So during this time
leading up to your baptism
as one of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
did you encounter any trials
that threatened to make you give up?
Yes, I did.
I made changes very quickly.
I stopped celebrating holidays
and stopped praying to idols.
But these changes
were very strange to my mom
—just difficult for her to understand.
She was really afraid
that I was being brainwashed.
So after studying for several months,
she had me move back in with her,
which meant the end of my studies
and no more attending meetings.
It wasn’t long before my association
was affecting my speech and my behavior.
I found myself easily influenced
to even celebrate my birthday again.
I could feel I was moving further away
from Jehovah instead of closer to him.
I’m sorry to hear that, Sister Alfonso.
So, what helped you not to give up
and to go on walking in the way of peace?
What helped me was the scripture
at Matthew 10:37,
where Jesus said:
“Whoever has greater affection for father
or mother than for me is not worthy of me.”
I realized that a peaceful
relationship with Jehovah
might mean no peace with my family.
But I knew that if I were
to ever gain my mom,
I had to walk with Jehovah
the right way and not give up.
So one night, I prayed to him,
crying for forgiveness
and asking for his help.
And to my surprise,
a few days later without any explanation,
my mom had me move back in with my aunt.
So I resumed my Bible studies,
and a year later
at the age of 15, I got baptized.
Jehovah clearly heard
and answered your prayer.
Since then, have you seen
continued evidence of Jehovah’s guidance?
A good friend helped me to adjust the way
I was communicating with my mom.
So one day, I called her and expressed to her
how much I truly appreciate and love her.
I didn’t want us to be distant anymore.
I explained to her
that my love for her had never changed,
but my love for Jehovah had come first.
So that conversation
was a turning point for us.
Now we have had many positive discussions,
and she’s much more understanding
of my decision.
Seeing Jehovah’s guidance in my life
makes me determined
to continue walking in his way of peace.
Thank you so much, Sister Alfonso.
We appreciate
your faithful example and comments.
Well, let’s address our second point.
How does walking in Jehovah’s way
bring us peace?
And to answer this,
we’re going to compare the path,
or journey, you’ve taken on the road to life
with a literal road, or walkway.
And in making this comparison,
we find a number of similarities.
First, both roads have boundaries,
a purpose, and a destination.
Well, let’s start
with that first one: boundaries.
On a literal road, we may see “Yield”
or “Do Not Enter” signs,
guardrails on the side of the road,
or lines on the road
to help us stay in our lane.
Well, those are boundaries.
And those boundaries
are there for our protection
because if we step outside of them,
we risk getting hurt or lost.
It would be great if we could tell you
that as you continue
on the road to life after your baptism,
we would love to say that the rest
of your journey is smooth sailing.
You’ll have nothing but safe travels.
But the reality is
that you will face challenges
and tests of your faith.
The Devil will make sure of it.
He will make sure
that you are confronted
with temptations.
He wants to do whatever he can
to damage
your special relationship with Jehovah.
But we’re confident that you can succeed.
You can be successful and avoid danger
if you remain within the boundaries
of Jehovah’s way of peace.
Now, how do you stay
within those boundaries?
By continuing to learn
about Jehovah’s laws
and principles and obeying them.
That obedience will not only protect you,
but it will give you inner peace
—peace that comes
from having a clean conscience.
The next similarity between a literal road
and being on the road to life
that we’ll discuss
is having a purpose.
Now, when we travel on a literal road,
our plan usually is not to get on the road
and just stand still (to become stationary)
or watch other people or vehicles go by.
No, we’re there for a reason.
The purpose of the road
is to enable movement
—to help us get from one place to another.
Well, in a similar sense,
being on Jehovah’s way of peace
allows you to move forward,
to make continual spiritual progress.
And, of course, there are many ways
that we can make spiritual advancement.
One important way
that all Christians can do so
is by cultivating spiritual qualities.
This is so pleasing to Jehovah.
Consider with me, for example,
Galatians 6:10.
Notice what’s mentioned here
at Galatians chapter 6,
verse 10.
It says: “So, then, as long as we
have the opportunity,
“let us work what is good toward all,
but especially toward those
related to us in the faith.”
So one way to advance spiritually
is to look for ways
to do good things for others,
both inside and outside the congregation.
This pandemic has afforded us
many opportunities to do this.
We’ve been able to call and check on others
and distribute food or supplies when needed.
And think of what our brothers
have done time and again to assist others
during natural disasters.
So take a minute and think
about your local area.
How can you work what is good toward all?
Are there ones
that need assistance getting food
or running errands?
Is there someone who could use
a good word of encouragement
to cheer them up?
Do we know individuals
who have lost loved ones in death
with whom we could share words of comfort
or maybe simply provide a listening ear?
You see, by displaying spiritual qualities
—qualities such as kindness,
compassion, hospitality, generosity—
you’re going to feel deeply rewarded
for doing these things.
And you’re pleasing Jehovah
because you will show that your purpose
for being on the road to life
is not just to save yourself
but to help others.
Now, there was a third similarity
between being on a literal road
and being on the road to life.
In both cases,
we have a destination
that we want to reach.
Traveling on a literal path
will eventually take you to your destination.
And as a Witness of Jehovah,
our journey, our walk,
on this figurative road
will lead us to our destination
—the goal of enjoying
a peaceful friendship with God forever.
Although we long for that time
in God’s new world,
even now we can experience
the blessings and inner peace
that come from a life of service to Jehovah.
We now have the privilege
to speak with Sister Gloria Herd.
Sister Herd has been baptized
for over 70 years
and has enjoyed a rich spiritual life
in special full-time service
with her husband,
Brother Samuel Herd of the Governing Body.
Sister Herd, you’ve had
many rich spiritual blessings,
and we know that you’ve encountered
challenges along the way.
But as you’ve carried out
these assignments through the years,
walking in Jehovah’s way of peace,
how have you managed
to enjoy greater inner peace?
I’ve learned, Brother Turner,
that if Jehovah gives you an assignment,
he will give you what you need to fulfill it.
We learned and really benefited
from the traveling overseers and their wives.
It was such a privilege to serve along
with these faithful brothers and sisters,
and several of them had served me
and my family when I was very young.
So to see their faithfulness,
to see their happiness,
and to see that they really had inner peace
really benefited me.
I learned from that,
and I wanted to follow their example.
That help from others can be so valuable.
How else have you managed?
I’ve enjoyed inner peace too
from praying to Jehovah a lot.
Many times we had
very little money or no money,
but we never missed a meal,
and we never missed any theocratic event.
We learned that having no money
is not an obstacle to Jehovah.
He heard our prayers, he answered them,
and it was as if the blessing
sometimes just fell out of heaven.
Prayer can be so powerful.
Thank you for sharing that.
But now, how has walking
in Jehovah’s way of peace
helped you to have peace with others?
I worked and lived with many sisters,
and they all had different personalities.
So I learned that I had
to apply Romans 12:18,
where it says:
“As far as it depends [upon me],
be peaceable with all men [and women].”
So I learned that I have to adjust
my personality sometimes to keep peace.
This happened very often.
But one time, we moved in
with a sister on Tuesday morning,
and something I said upset her very much.
She got very angry.
Well, I decided not to pursue the issue
because I had to live with her for a week.
And I just decided
to let her see by my conduct
that I could never have meant
what she thought.
So as the week went by,
the days went by, the tension lessened.
And by Monday when we left,
we were the best of friends.
And she gave me a big hug,
and nothing more was said about the subject.
Well, it sounds like you
handled that beautifully, Sister Herd.
Your spiritual qualities were evident.
Well, finally, how has walking
in Jehovah’s way of peace
helped you have peace with God?
Well, when you see Jehovah act
on your behalf over and over and over again,
it makes you feel that you have his approval.
Now that Sam and I are in our senior years,
we feel He has given us
‘the desire of our heart’
by allowing us to serve at Bethel,
which had been our goal for many years.
And I know that as long as
I stay faithful to Jehovah,
he will continue to grant me inner peace.
And we have that confidence as well.
Thank you so much, Sister Herd.
We deeply appreciate your comments
and your encouraging expressions.
Well, let’s now address our final point.
What can we do to continue walking
in Jehovah’s way of peace?
Well, let’s go back
to our illustration of the road.
On a literal road,
travelers may need to make adjustments
in response to changing road conditions
or bad weather.
Similarly, as you go on walking
in the way of peace,
you will need to readjust your actions
and thinking from time to time.
Recently, a circuit overseer
shared an interesting point
regarding our thoughts
and attitudes on matters.
He said that they could either serve
as a prison or a passport:
a prison, in that our thoughts and actions
can confine or restrict us
or a passport,
in that they can take us where we need to be.
Well, right now, we need to be
and stay on this road to life.
So we want to make sure
that any needed adjustments are made
in our thoughts and our actions
so that we’re not confined or restricted
in making spiritual progress.
Well, what might be some areas
that we’ll need to make adjustments?
Notice, please, Paul’s words
in 2 Corinthians chapter 13.
And we’ll read 2 Corinthians 13:11.
Paul says: “Finally, brothers,
“continue to rejoice, to be readjusted,
“to be comforted, to think in agreement,
“to live peaceably;
and the God of love
and of peace will be with you.”
Did you notice three areas in this verse
where Paul states we can make adjustments?
First, he says: “Continue to rejoice.”
We can lose our peace and joy
if we become overwhelmed
by the anxieties of life.
So in order to rejoice,
can you make it a goal to focus on things
that bring joy rather than sadness?
So if you’re not feeling well
or coping with chronic pain,
you can focus on God’s promise
of when no one will say:
“I am sick.”
If you’re facing opposition for your beliefs,
focus on the fact
that we’re part of a brotherhood
—a brotherhood that supports
and prays for us—
and arrangements are in place
to keep us spiritually strong.
If you’re discouraged by world events,
you can rejoice in the fact
that you have a hope for the future,
and we know how this all ends.
We know that better times are ahead.
The point is, Don’t let negative thoughts
restrict or limit your progress.
Instead, make the needed adjustments
so that you can move forward
and continue to rejoice.
Note another area for readjustment
that Paul mentions in verse 11.
There he says: “Continue . . .
to think in agreement.”
There were members of the congregation
back in the first century
that were promoting apostate ideas.
Others were introducing controversial ideas
that were not directly unscriptural,
but they were divisive.
This resulted in bickering
and arguments over words,
really creating
a spiritually unhealthy atmosphere.
Well, what’s going to help us
to continue to think in agreement?
Remember Paul’s words at 2 Timothy 2:23
to “reject foolish and ignorant debates,
knowing that they produce fights.”
Of course, we react strongly
when facing issues
that clearly violate Jehovah’s moral laws.
But if no Scriptural principle
is being violated,
we’re wise to abstain
from promoting our personal opinions.
We want to do all we can to avoid starting
or being drawn into disagreements
that can disrupt the peace
of the congregation.
Now, back in verse 11,
a third area where we can make adjustments
is to continue “to live peaceably.”
Did you notice
from the interview with our sisters
what they both did when challenged,
when faced with a challenge
that threatened their peace?
They took the matter to Jehovah in prayer.
They reflected on scriptures
found in God’s Word.
And then they looked to see
how they could apply those verses
in their particular situation.
It helped them to not only have inner peace
but peace with others as well.
So let your spiritual qualities
shine through.
Continue to work on keeping peace,
showing those qualities
of being loving and generous toward all,
but especially with our close family members,
whether they are Witnesses or not.
Well, we want to conclude
by reminding you baptism candidates
that today marks a significant milestone
in your journey
in your relationship with Jehovah.
So take the time to appreciate
what this day means for you.
We’re so proud of all of you.
You will never regret
the decision you have made
to dedicate your life to Jehovah.
But keep in mind that after today and beyond,
the journey is not yet over.
Really, it’s just the beginning.
So we encourage you
to do all you can
to stay on the road to life.
Keep in mind the points we considered today.
First, do not give up
on walking in Jehovah’s way of peace.
Your life depends on it.
Allow Jehovah to guide your steps.
Second, stay within the boundaries
on the road to life.
Remember, you’re walking with a purpose,
and that will lead you to your destination
—peaceful friendship with Jehovah forever.
And finally, keep making
any needed adjustments
in your thoughts, attitude, and actions
so that you can maintain peace
with Jehovah and peace with others.
If you continue to do these things,
not only will you have peace
but as the last part
of 2 Corinthians 13:11 says:
“The God of love and of peace
will be with you.”
May you always remember that promise,
which Jehovah makes to those
who go on walking in the way of peace.
Thank you, Brother Turner.
Similar to last year,
the arrangements for baptism
will vary in each location.
Each local congregation’s elders
have made suitable provisions
in accord with local circumstances
for candidates to be baptized
after the conclusion of this session.
We thank Jehovah
for the timely spiritual food we enjoyed
during this session of the convention.
Our next session will show us how to avoid
common pitfalls to pursuing peace.
It will highlight specific activities
that peacemakers excel at.
We will also enjoy part one
of the feature Bible drama.
But now, let’s sing together
the closing song for this session,
song number 54, “‘This Is the Way.’”
After the song, you may have
your own concluding prayer.
That’s song number 54.