There is an ongoing need
for volunteers at Bethel
and on theocratic construction projects.
Although the COVID-19 pandemic has limited
the number of those who may be invited
at this time,
there is still a need for volunteers.
As you watch the following video,
please note the spirit displayed
by those who make themselves available
for Bethel service.
Making yourself available for Bethel service
is like knocking on a door that leads
to many other privileges of service.
Of course, to serve at Bethel
requires a self-sacrificing spirit
and a willingness to serve
wherever there is a need,
in harmony with the attitude
displayed by the prophet Isaiah
at Isaiah 6:8:
ŇThen I heard the voice of Jehovah saying:
ŇÔWhom shall I send, and who will go for us?Ő
And I said: ÔHere I am! Send me!ŐÓ
When Isaiah learned about an opportunity
to do more in JehovahŐs service,
he responded eagerly,
even though he did not know exactly
what he was going to be assigned to do.
It was enough for him to know
that Jehovah was extending an invitation
to serve in a special way,
and Isaiah wanted to volunteer.
The same spirit is shown
by Bethel family members worldwide.
If the Branch Committee determines
that there is a need for your services,
they will decide where you can best be used,
whether at Bethel or perhaps
on a theocratic construction assignment.
Submitting your application
may open a door of opportunity
to serve Jehovah and his organization
in a variety of ways.
That was an excerpt from the video
Making Yourself Available for Bethel Service.
If you are interested in serving at Bethel
or on theocratic construction projects
on a part-time or full-time basis,
please watch the entire video on jw.org.
Baptized Christians who are
19 years of age or older
and are interested in volunteering
should apply.
Speak to your congregation secretary
for more information.
If possible, please submit
your application electronically
on jw.org.
Have you ever found yourself in a situation
where your peace was threatened?
How did you handle it?
We can learn much
from the faithful man Jacob
about how to make peace.
Please open your Bibles
to Genesis chapter 26,
and follow along as Brother Mark Sanderson,
a member of the Governing Body,
applies the lessons
in the dramatic Bible reading
with the theme
ŇJacobŃA Man Who Loved Peace.Ó
Have you ever been
the victim of oppression or injustice?
Have you been angered by something
someone has said or done?
Who of us hasnŐt?
In situations like that,
people who donŐt know Jehovah
often react in a way
thatŐs far from peaceful.
They retaliate; they fight;
they hit back.
But we know that Jehovah
sees what happened,
and he can set matters straight.
WeŐre wise to remember the words of Jesus:
ŇHappy are the mild-tempered.Ó
ŇHappy are the peacemakers.Ó
The Bible describes a man
who remained mild and peaceable
in some extremely difficult
and stressful situations.
Repeatedly, he chose not to fight,
preferring a course that led to peace.
That man was Jacob.
Jacob learned from the peaceful example
of his father, Isaac.
There was a famine in the land,
and Isaac moved his family to Gerar,
which was ruled by Abimelech,
king of the Philistines.
LetŐs read about the problems that arose
and see how Isaac dealt with them.
Please turn to Genesis 26:12.
ŇAnd Isaac began to sow seed in that land,
Ňand in that year he reaped
100 times what he sowed,
Ňfor Jehovah was blessing him.
ŇThe man became wealthy,
Ňand he continued to prosper
until he became very wealthy.
ŇHe acquired flocks of sheep
and herds of cattle
Ňand a large body of servants,
Ňand the Philistines began to envy him.
ŇSo the Philistines took soil
Ňand stopped up all the wells
that his fatherŐs servants had dug
Ňin the days of Abraham.
ŇAbimelech then said to Isaac:
ŇÔMove from our neighborhood,
for you have grown far stronger than we are.Ő
ŇSo Isaac moved from there
and encamped in the valley of Gerar
Ňand began dwelling there.
ŇAnd Isaac again dug the wells
Ňthat had been dug
in the days of his father Abraham
Ňbut that the Philistines had stopped up
after AbrahamŐs death,
Ňand he called them by the names
that his father had given them.
ŇWhen the servants of Isaac
were digging in the valley,
Ňthey found a well of fresh water.
ŇAnd the shepherds of Gerar
Ňbegan quarreling
with the shepherds of Isaac, saying:
ŇÔThe water is ours!Ő
ŇSo he named the well Esek,
Ňbecause they had quarreled with him.
ŇAnd they started digging another well,
Ňand they began quarreling over it also.
ŇSo he named it Sitnah.
ŇLater he moved away from there
and dug another well,
Ňbut they did not quarrel over it.
ŇSo he named it Rehoboth and said:
ŇÔIt is because now Jehovah
has given us ample room
Ňand has made us fruitful in the land.Ő
ŇThen he went up from there to Beersheba.
ŇThat night Jehovah appeared to him and said:
ŇÔI am the God of your father Abraham.
ŇÔDo not be afraid, for I am with you,
ŇÔand I will bless you
and multiply your offspring
on account of Abraham my servant.ŐÓ
The Philistines, motivated by envy,
stop up all the wells that Abraham had dug,
and the king asks Isaac
to move from the neighborhood.
Isaac now has a decision to make.
Perhaps some encourage him to stay put.
Think about how they might have reasoned:
ÔYouŐve done nothing wrong, Isaac.
ÔJehovah told you that you and your offspring
Ôwould possess the land.
ÔYou have nothing to fear.
ÔYou have many servants,
Ôand theyŐre stronger than the Philistines.
ÔWhy not hit back
against those who have done this
to your wells?Ő
In this situation, what would you have done?
Isaac chooses a peaceful course.
He decides to move on.
This is not easy.
Isaac has many servants
and flocks of sheep and herds of cattle.
He has tilled the ground and planted seed,
and itŐs produced plentifully,
but he leaves that behind and moves on.
But IsaacŐs troubles are not over.
In his new location, his servants dig wells
and find fresh water.
But the shepherds in that area say:
ŇThe water is ours!Ó
Isaac then digs another well,
but the local shepherds
quarrel about that one too.
Again, instead of fighting over the matter,
Isaac moves and finally finds a place
where he can reside in peace.
Jacob saw that his fatherŐs peaceful actions
had a good effect,
and he knew that Isaac
had received JehovahŐs blessing.
WhatŐs the lesson?
Parents, never underestimate
the powerful effect
your good example can have on your children.
Jacob has a twin brother, Esau.
Of the two, Esau is born first,
but Jehovah foretells
thatŃcontrary to customŃ
the older Esau will serve
his younger brother.
Jehovah foresees
what kind of personalities theyŐll develop,
and he knows that Esau
will have little appreciation
for spiritual matters.
This becomes evident
when Esau exchanges his right as firstborn
for a mere bowl of stew,
sealing the matter with an oath.
But something more is involved.
In selling the birthright,
he also gives up the right
to receive a prophetic blessing
from his father.
Years pass, Isaac has grown old,
and he decides itŐs time to impart
the blessing to his firstborn.
He may not know
that Esau had sold his right as firstborn.
In any case, he tells Esau
that he will bless him
but asks him first
to provide him with a tasty dish
of fresh game from the field.
Rebekah, the twinsŐ mother,
overhears this conversation
and persuades Jacob
to impersonate his twin brother
while Esau is out hunting.
The plan is successful.
Isaac unwittingly blesses Jacob!
Esau, at learning of this, is furious.
LetŐs take up the account
from Genesis 27:41.
ŇHowever, Esau harbored
animosity against Jacob
Ňbecause of the blessing
his father had given him,
Ňand Esau kept saying in his heart:
ŇÔThe days of mourning for my father
are getting closer.
ŇAfter that I am going to kill
Jacob my brother.Ő
ŇWhen the words of her older son Esau
were told to Rebekah,
Ňshe at once sent for her younger son Jacob
Ňand said to him: ÔLook!
ŇÔYour brother Esau is planning
to take revenge by killing you.
ŇÔNow, my son, do as I say.
ŇÔGet up and run away
to my brother Laban at Haran.
ŇÔDwell with him for a while
ŇÔuntil your brotherŐs rage calms down,
ŇÔuntil your brotherŐs anger
toward you subsides
ŇÔand he forgets what you have done to him.
ŇÔThen I will send for you from there.
ŇWhy should I lose both of you in one day?Ő
ŇAfter that Rebekah kept saying to Isaac:
ŇÔI am disgusted with my life
because of the daughters of Heth.
ŇÔIf Jacob ever takes a wife
from the daughters of Heth,
ŇÔlike these daughters of the land,
Ňwhat good is my life?Ő
ŇSo Isaac called Jacob
Ňand blessed him and commanded him, saying:
ŇÔYou must not take a wife
from the daughters of Canaan.
ŇÔGo away to Paddanaram
ŇÔto the house of Bethuel,
your motherŐs father,
ŇÔand from there take for yourself a wife
ŇÔfrom the daughters of Laban,
your motherŐs brother.
ŇÔGod Almighty will bless you
and make you fruitful and multiply you,
ŇÔand you will certainly become
a congregation of peoples.
ŇÔAnd he will give to you
the blessing of Abraham,
ŇÔto you and to your offspring with you,
ŇÔso that you may take possession of the land
where you have been living as a foreigner,
Ňwhich God has given to Abraham.Ő
ŇSo Isaac sent Jacob away,
Ňand he departed for Paddanaram,
Ňto Laban the son of Bethuel the Aramaean,
the brother of Rebekah,
the mother of Jacob and Esau.Ó
JacobŐs parents tell him to travel
to his uncle, Laban,
to find a wife.
Of course, the core issue
is the problem with Esau.
Recall that earlier,
Isaac had a problem with the Philistines
Ńa problem that evidently
could not be settled peacefully.
So, what did Isaac do?
He moved on.
Now Jacob faces a similar situation.
His brother is seething with anger,
so Jacob leaves.
It means leaving his home and his family;
it means making a long journey
to a distant land.
Jacob could have chosen to stand his ground.
He owns the birthright.
He could argue the matter
with his father and mother:
ÔIŐm no child. IŐm 77 years old!Ő
Jacob does none of those things.
The Bible simply says:
ŇJacob obeyed his father and his mother
and departed.Ó
WhatŐs the lesson?
When we face a situation
that canŐt be settled peacefully,
we probably wonŐt need to flee for our lives
to a distant land.
Sometimes, however,
it is the course of wisdom
to walk away from a situation.
Proverbs 17:14 says:
ŇBeginning a fight
is like opening a floodgate;
before the quarrel breaks out,
take your leave.Ó
While Jacob is on his way to his uncle,
Jehovah appears to Jacob in a dream
and assures him
of his support and protection.
That does not mean
that JacobŐs troubles are over.
At the journeyŐs end,
he moves in with his uncleŐs household.
In time, a situation arises again
that shows that Jacob
is a man who loves peace.
LetŐs read about it from Genesis 29:16.
ŇNow Laban had two daughters.
ŇThe name of the older was Leah,
Ňand the name of the younger, Rachel.
ŇBut the eyes of Leah had no luster,
Ňwhereas Rachel had become
Ňa very attractive and beautiful woman.
ŇJacob had fallen in love with Rachel,
so he said:
ŇÔI am willing to serve you seven years
Ňfor your younger daughter Rachel.Ő
ŇTo this Laban said:
ŇÔIt is better for me to give her to you
than to give her to another man.
ŇKeep dwelling with me.Ő
ŇAnd Jacob served seven years for Rachel,
Ňbut in his eyes
they were like just a few days
Ňbecause of his love for her.
ŇThen Jacob said to Laban:
ŇÔGive over my wife because my days are up,
Ňand let me have relations with her.Ő
ŇWith that Laban gathered
all the men of the place
Ňand made a feast.
ŇBut during the evening,
he resorted to taking his daughter Leah
Ňand bringing her to him
that he might have relations with her.
ŇLaban also gave his female servant Zilpah
Ňto his daughter Leah as a servant.
ŇIn the morning Jacob saw that it was Leah!
ŇSo he said to Laban:
ŇÔWhat have you done to me?
ŇÔWas it not for Rachel that I served you?
ŇWhy have you tricked me?Ő
ŇTo this Laban said:
ŇÔIt is not our custom here to give
the younger woman before the firstborn.
ŇÔCelebrate the week of this woman.
ŇÔAfter that you will also be given
this other woman
Ňin exchange for serving me
seven more years.Ő
ŇJacob did so
and celebrated the week of this woman,
Ňafter which he gave him
his daughter Rachel as a wife.
ŇBesides, Laban gave
his female servant Bilhah
to his daughter Rachel as her servant.Ó
Jacob has reason to be upset.
He had arranged with Laban
to work seven years for Rachel.
At the end of the seven years,
a wedding feast is arranged.
But the heavily-veiled woman
brought in to him
is not Rachel;
itŐs Leah!
Imagine how shocked Jacob must have been!
Instead of admitting to his deceit,
Laban gives an excuse.
What thoughts come to JacobŐs mind?
Does he consider that Jehovah
might be working out his promise
to make JacobŐs offspring plentiful
Ňlike the dust particles of the earthÓ?
We donŐt know.
As it turns out,
Leah bears him six sons,
including Levi and Judah
Ńfamily heads of the two
most honored tribes of Israel.
Of course,
Jacob couldnŐt have foreknown this.
Still, Jacob the peacemaker
accepts Leah
and goes along
with LabanŐs outrageous request
that he work an additional seven years
for Rachel.
WhatŐs the lesson?
ItŐs disappointing when others
donŐt hold to their agreements.
Like Jacob, can we find it in our hearts
to forgive and find a way
to preserve peace with them?
Jacob serves Laban
for 14 years for his two wives,
and he works for Laban another 6 years
for a flock of his own.
Finally, at JehovahŐs direction,
he gathers his family along with his animals
and, without informing Laban,
he leaves for home.
When Laban learns of this, he is furious!
He chases and catches up with Jacob.
This is a dangerous situation,
one that can easily turn violent.
Imagine how it might have been:
Jacob had come to a mountainous region.
Possibly itŐs morning, and the air is cool.
There are the sounds and smells of animals
Ńsheep, donkeys, camels; there are many.
The servants attend to them,
getting them ready for the dayŐs journey.
But then come cries of alarm.
Laban has come, and heŐs not alone.
He arrives with strong men.
They gallop in on camels; they dismount.
This is not a friendly visit.
LabanŐs men are ready
to obey orders from Laban.
JacobŐs servants quickly gather to the scene.
All eyes are fixed on Laban and Jacob,
who argue.
The previous night,
Jehovah had warned Laban in a dream
to be careful about what heŐd say to Jacob.
Still, Laban is angry and aggressive.
Laban makes two charges.
First, he says:
ŇWhy have you resorted to outwitting me
Ňand carrying my daughters off like captives
Ňtaken by the sword?
ŇWhy did you run away secretly
and outwit me and not tell me?Ó
The answer to that charge is obvious.
Jacob replies:
ŇIt was because I was afraid,
Ňfor I said to myself,
ÔYou might take your daughters
away from me by force.ŐÓ
Laban also charges that Jacob has stolen
his household gods.
Rachel has indeed stolen the gods,
but Jacob knows nothing about this.
A search is made,
but the idols are not found.
Jacob then makes his defense.
LetŐs take up our reading
at Genesis 31:36.
ŇAt that Jacob became angry
Ňand began to criticize Laban.
ŇJacob then said to Laban:
ŇÔWhat is my offense, and for what sin
are you hotly pursuing me?
ŇÔNow that you have searched
through all my goods,
ŇÔwhat have you found
that belongs to your house?
ŇÔPut it here in front of my brothers
and your brothers,
ŇÔand let them decide between the two of us.
ŇÔDuring these 20 years
that I have been with you,
ŇÔyour sheep and your goats never miscarried,
ŇÔand I never ate the rams of your flock.
ŇÔI did not bring you any animal
torn by wild beasts.
ŇÔI would stand the loss of it myself.
ŇÔWhether the animal was stolen by day
or was stolen by night,
ŇÔyou would demand compensation from me.
ŇÔBy day the heat consumed me,
and the cold by night,
ŇÔand sleep would flee from my eyes.
ŇÔThis makes 20 years for me in your house.
ŇÔI have served you 14 years
for your two daughters
ŇÔand 6 years for your flock,
ŇÔand you kept changing my wages ten times.
ŇÔIf the God of my father, the God of Abraham
ŇÔand the One whom Isaac fears,
ŇÔhad not been on my side,
ŇÔyou would now have sent me away
empty-handed.
ŇÔGod has seen my affliction
and the toil of my hands,
Ňand that is why he reproved you last night.Ő
ŇThen Laban answered Jacob:
ŇÔThe daughters are my daughters
and the children my children
ŇÔand the flock my flock,
ŇÔand everything you are looking at
ŇÔis mine and my daughtersŐ.
ŇÔWhat can I do today against these
or against their children
ŇÔwhom they have borne?
ŇÔNow come, let us make a covenant,
you and I,
Ňand it will serve as a witness between us.Ő
ŇSo Jacob took a stone
and set it up as a pillar.
ŇThen Jacob said to his brothers:
ÔPick up stones!Ő
ŇAnd they took stones and made a pile.
ŇAfter that they ate there
on the pile of stones.
ŇAnd Laban began calling it Jegarsahadutha,
Ňbut Jacob called it Galeed.
ŇLaban then said:
ŇÔThis pile of stones is a witness
Ňbetween me and you today.Ő
ŇThat is why he named it Galeed,
and the Watchtower,
Ňfor he said:
ŇÔLet Jehovah keep watch between you and me
ŇÔwhen we are out of each otherŐs sight.
ŇÔIf you mistreat my daughters
ŇÔand if you start taking wives
in addition to my daughters,
ŇÔthough there is no man with us,
Ňremember that God will be a witness
between you and me.Ő
ŇLaban went on to say to Jacob:
ŇÔHere is this pile of stones,
ŇÔand here is the pillar
that I have erected between you and me.
ŇÔThis pile of stones is a witness,
ŇÔand the pillar
is something that bears witness,
ŇÔthat I will not pass beyond this pile
of stones to bring harm to you
ŇÔand you will not pass
beyond this pile of stones
ŇÔand this pillar to bring harm to me.
ŇÔLet the God of Abraham
and the God of Nahor,
Ňthe God of their father, judge between us.Ő
ŇAnd Jacob swore by the One
Ňwhom his father Isaac fears.
ŇAfter that Jacob offered
a sacrifice in the mountain
Ňand invited his brothers to eat bread.
ŇSo they ate
and spent the night in the mountain.
ŇHowever, Laban got up early in the morning
Ňand kissed his grandchildren
and his daughters and blessed them.
Then Laban departed and returned home.Ó
Jacob had served Laban faithfully
for 20 years,
even though Laban had defrauded
and exploited him.
Laban doesnŐt acknowledge that
but, rather, dishonestly claims
that he is the rightful owner
of all that Jacob has with him.
Laban then suggests
that they make a covenant of peace
ensuring that neither family
will bring harm to the other.
LabanŐs motive is not that he loves peace.
It might have been to ensure
that Jacob will not return
with the household gods after LabanŐs death
to deprive his sons of their inheritance.
In any case, Jacob agrees;
everyone relaxes;
thereŐs to be no violence.
And a monument is set up
to memorialize the agreement.
Despite the many years of oppression,
Jacob agrees to a covenant of peace.
He does not harbor resentment
or seek revenge.
That crisis is over for Jacob.
But now another one looms.
Jacob sends messengers to his brother.
They say that Jacob is returning
and that he seeks EsauŐs favor.
The messengers return with the news
that Esau is on his way to meet him
and with him are 400 men.
Oh, my!
Is Esau still angry?
Understandably, Jacob is worried.
He does not want to fight with his brother.
Let us see how he handles the situation.
Please turn to Genesis 32:13.
ŇAnd he spent the night there.
ŇThen he took some of his possessions
Ňas a gift for Esau his brother:
Ň200 female goats, 20 male goats,
Ň200 female sheep, 20 rams,
Ň30 camels nursing their young,
Ň40 cows, 10 bulls,
Ň20 female donkeys
Ňand 10 full-grown male donkeys.
ŇHe handed them over to his servants,
Ňone drove after another,
Ňand he said to his servants:
ŇÔCross over ahead of me,
Ňand you are to set a space
between one drove and the next.Ő
ŇHe also commanded the first one:
ŇÔIn case Esau my brother
should meet you and ask,
ŇÔŇTo whom do you belong,
and where are you going,
ŇÔand to whom do these ahead of you belong?Ó
ŇÔthen you should say,
ŇTo your servant Jacob.
ŇÔŇIt is a gift sent to my lord, to Esau,
Ňand look! he himself is also behind us.ÓŐ
ŇAnd he commanded also the second, the third,
Ňand all those following the droves:
ŇÔAccording to this word,
ŇÔyou are to speak to Esau when you meet him.
ŇÔAnd you should also say,
ŇŇHere is your servant Jacob behind us.ÓŐ
ŇFor he said to himself:
ŇÔIf I appease him
by sending a gift ahead of me,
ŇÔthen afterward when I see him,
he may give me a kindly reception.ŐÓ
Jacob wants peaceful relations
with his brother.
He sends a generous gift
Ńhundreds of animalsŃ
to help make that possible.
Was Jacob weak-minded,
too cowardly to stand up to his brother?
Not at all!
Why, as the time neared
for the meeting with Esau,
Jacob wrestles with an angel until dawn
to receive further assurance
of JehovahŐs blessing.
LetŐs now see what happens
when the two brothers meet.
Please turn to Genesis 33:1.
ŇNow Jacob raised his eyes
Ňand saw Esau coming,
Ňand 400 men were with him.
ŇSo he divided the children
among Leah, Rachel,
Ňand the two female servants.
ŇHe put the female servants
and their children in front,
ŇLeah and her children after them,
Ňand Rachel and Joseph behind them.
ŇThen he himself went ahead of them
Ňand bowed down to the earth seven times
Ňas he came near to his brother.
ŇBut Esau ran to meet him,
Ňand he embraced him and kissed him,
Ňand they burst into tears.
ŇWhen he raised his eyes
and saw the women and the children,
Ňhe said: ÔWho are these with you?Ő
ŇTo which he said:
ŇÔThe children with whom God
has favored your servant.Ő
ŇAt that the female servants
came forward with their children
Ňand bowed down,
Ňand Leah too came forward with her children,
Ňand they bowed down.
ŇThen Joseph came forward with Rachel,
ŇEsau said:
ŇÔWhat is the purpose of all this camp
of travelers that I have met?Ő
ŇHe replied: ÔIn order to find favor
Ňin the eyes of my lord.Ő
ŇThen Esau said:
ŇÔI have a great many possessions,
my brother.
ŇKeep what is yours.Ő
ŇHowever, Jacob said:
ŇÔNo, please.
ŇÔIf I have found favor in your eyes,
ŇÔyou must take my gift from my hand,
ŇÔbecause I brought it
so that I could see your face.
ŇÔAnd I have seen your face
ŇÔas though seeing GodŐs face,
ŇÔin that you received me with pleasure.
ŇÔTake, please,
ŇÔthe gift conveying my blessing
that was brought to you,
ŇÔfor God has favored me
Ňand I have everything I need.Ő
And he continued to urge him,
so that he took it.Ó
What a happy outcome!
Instead of an angry confrontation,
there is a joyful reunion.
The two men shed tears; they embrace.
Again, Jacob is the peacemaker.
How did he prove that?
He prayed, and he acted in harmony
with his prayers.
He sent gifts.
He showed honor and respect to his brother,
calling him lord
and bowing seven times.
WhatŐs the lesson?
DoesnŐt this account well illustrate
the extent to which we
should be willing to go
to preserve peace
with our Christian brothers and sisters?
We learn so much
about seeking peace from Jacob.
When threatened by his brother
while living at home,
he moved away.
When deceived by Laban
regarding Rachel and Leah,
he yielded.
When chased down and accused by Laban,
Jacob agreed to a covenant of peace.
And when confronting Esau, he offered a gift.
Keep in mind,
in none of these situations
was Jacob the one who needed to apologize.
Yet, throughout his life,
Jacob loved peace.
He relied on Jehovah,
and Jehovah blessed him.
Jehovah never forgot Jacob
and how he pursued peace
in his dealings with others.
When we do the same
Ńwhen we pursue peace
in the face of injustice,
in the face of persecution,
in small issues as well as in big issuesŃ
Jehovah will not forget us either.
Jehovah will richly bless us
if we love peace
just as Jacob loved peace.
How comforting it is
to reflect on JehovahŐs love and support
for those who make peace!
This Bible account is filled
with practical examples
that each of us can imitate.
You will be pleased to know
that the dramatic Bible reading
ŇJacobŃA Man Who Loved PeaceÓ
is now available for download
on the jw.org website
and in the JW Library¨  app.
How can we maintain our God-given peace
despite living in an ungodly world?
Please pay close attention
to Brother David Schafer,
a helper to the Teaching Committee,
as he answers this question in the talk
ŇThe Result of True Righteousness
Will Be Peace.Ó
Earlier, we considered
the expression at Philippians 4:7,
Ňthe peace of God
that surpasses all understanding,Ó
that is, the tranquility and calmness
we enjoy because we have
a close friendship with Jehovah.
What a remarkable blessing!
But although we enjoy God-given peace,
our life in this system of things
is not problem free, is it?
Psalm 34:19 acknowledges
as much when it says:
ŇMany are the hardships of the righteous one,
but Jehovah rescues him from them all.Ó
We may experience family opposition,
persecution, war, natural disasters,
or severe illnesses,
but none of these hardships
can Ňseparate us from GodŐs love.Ó
ŇNeither death nor life nor angels
nor governments
nor things now here nor things to comeÓ
Ńnone of these things
can rob us of the peace Jehovah gives.
And yet, there is something that can.
Please turn with me to Isaiah 32:17.
And as we read this text,
notice that it refers to peace as a result.
Do you think of peace that way, as a result?
If peace is a result, what causes it?
Isaiah 32:17:
ŇThe result
Ňof true righteousness will be peace,
Ňand the fruitage of true righteousness
will be lasting tranquility and security.Ó
What a beautiful expression,
Ňlasting tranquility and securityÓ!
Again, from what does it result?
True righteousness.
What if righteousness
no longer mattered to us?
What if a person concluded:
ÔIt makes no difference
Ôhow I live or what sacrifices I make.
ÔIŐm going to suffer hardships either way.
I might as well do
whatever I please while I canŐ?
WhatŐs wrong with that thinking?
Would it show appreciation for peace
and all that Jehovah
has done to make it possible?
Peace is a result.
And behind every result is a cause.
If we want peace,
we have to pursue righteousness.
An unrighteous person
cannot be at peace with God.
Serious transgressions put a strain
on a personŐs relationship with God.
Recall King DavidŐs words found
at Psalm 38:3.
Sensing JehovahŐs disapproval, he wrote:
ŇThere is no peace
within my bones because of my sin.Ó
Inevitably, the unrighteous person
will reap what he sows and lose his peace.
What is righteousness,
and how do we pursue it?
Righteousness is what we have or what we show
when we do what is right
according to JehovahŐs standards.
And those standards
are not just rules we follow
but principles that guide the way
we deal with each other.
As Universal Sovereign and Creator,
Jehovah God determines what is righteous.
IsnŐt that what was represented
by Ňthe tree of the knowledge
of good and badÓ in the garden of Eden?
As a result of JehovahŐs command
to abstain from its fruit,
that tree represented GodŐs right
to determine for his creatures
what is good and what is bad for them.
And although Jehovah
has given humans free will,
the right to choose,
he has not granted humans
(not even perfect ones)
the right to set the standard
for what is righteous and what is not.
Now, notice once again that Isaiah 32:17 says
that Ňthe result
of true righteousness will be peace.Ó
It uses that term twiceŃŇtrue righteousness.Ó
Not everything called righteousness
is true righteousness.
Many people view righteousness
as just a personal virtue
achieved by following the rules.
At Matthew 23:28,
Jesus said that the Pharisees
appeared righteous on the outside,
but inside they were lawless.
Ecclesiastes 7:16 talks about those
who think their standards
are more righteous even than GodŐs.
And at Romans 10:3,
Paul talked about people
who Ôseek to establish
their own righteousness.Ő
But false piety,
over-righteousness, and self-righteousness
are not what Isaiah 32:17 is talking about.
Today, many argue for the acceptance
of conduct that Jehovah forbids.
They may even find support
from a world already alienated from God.
But wide acceptance in a growing community
does not redefine righteousness.
None of that is true righteousness.
Our loving Creator sets
the standard for what is right
Ńnot our feelings,
not the community at large.
Now, while youŐre here in Isaiah,
please turn to chapter 48.
In order to be viewed as righteous,
we have to trust that Jehovah
should set the standard of right and wrong.
In addition, we must prove
by our speech and actions
that we agree with JehovahŐs standards
and obey him.
And that takes real courage
in a wicked world.
But when we do that, we enjoy the result.
Notice what it says at Isaiah chapter 48,
verses 17, 18:
ŇThis is what Jehovah says, your Repurchaser,
Ňthe Holy One of Israel:
ŇÔI, Jehovah, am your God,
ŇÔthe One teaching you to benefit yourself
ŇÔ[or as the footnote says, teaching you
Ňfor your own goodÓ],
ŇÔthe One guiding you
in the way you should walk.
ŇÔIf only you would pay attention
to my commandments!
ŇÔThen your peace
would become just like a river
and your righteousness
like the waves of the sea.ŐÓ
Paying attention to JehovahŐs commandments
results in two things.
First, our peace
will Ňbecome just like a riverÓ
Ńserene, abundant, ongoing.
Second, our righteousness
will be Ňlike the waves of the sea.Ó
Remember your last trip to the beach?
As you stood there on the shore,
perhaps on a high hill overlooking the ocean
watching the waves
roll in one after the other
just as they have for thousands of years,
could you feel a sense of constancy?
Jehovah says that our course
of doing what is right can be just like that.
He will guide us
in the path of righteousness.
He will bless us with unending peace.
In the process, we learn through experience
how JehovahŐs wise and loving ways
truly benefit us personally.
But if we refuse to do that,
we learn what agitation
and discord truly mean.
As verse 22 says:
ŇÔThere is no peace,Ő says Jehovah,
Ôfor the wicked.ŐÓ
ItŐs not a heavy-handed threat to manipulate
human behavior
as if Jehovah needed to do that.
ItŐs a fact, a truth, a timeless principle.
ŇGod is love.Ó
He teaches us for our own good.
And the result if we pay attention is peace
ŃIsaiah 48:17, 18.
And these verses assure us
that imperfect humans
truly can have a righteous standing with God.
LetŐs explore that further.
Do you recall the very first time
the word ŇrighteousÓ is used in the Bible?
Turn with me, please, to Genesis chapter 6.
Now, you likely recognize this
as the account about Noah.
Noah lived in an extremely wicked world.
During his lifetime, rebel angels
left their assignments in heaven,
materialized, married human women,
and fathered hybrid offspring
who became violent giants.
Now, how did all of that wickedness
and violence affect Jehovah?
According to Genesis 6:6,
Ňhis heart was saddened,Ó
which is a remarkable thing to contemplate,
isnŐt it?
JehovahŐs feelings are affected
by our decisions because he cares for us.
That ancient world became so wicked
that Jehovah decided it must be destroyed.
And yet, right in the midst
of all this depravity,
Noah showed a different spirit.
Notice what it says at Genesis 6:8, 9:
ŇBut Noah found favor in the eyes of Jehovah.
ŇThis is the history of Noah.
Noah was a righteous man.Ó
There it is.
And why was he described as righteous?
ŇHe proved himself faultless
among his contemporaries.Ó
Yes, Noah was not like the rebel angels
or their offspring
or like degraded human society.
ŇNoah walked with the true God.Ó
And thus the second time
we find the word ŇrighteousÓ
is at Genesis 7:1:
ŇAfter that, Jehovah said to Noah:
ŇÔGo into the ark,
you and all your household,
ŇÔbecause you are the one
ŇÔI have found to be righteous
before me among this generation.ŐÓ
Because of NoahŐs righteousness,
he and his family survived the Flood
to worship Jehovah on a cleansed earth.
And after the waters subsided
and the family emerged from the ark,
they witnessed a splendid sight,
one never before observed:
a serene, multicolored arch
in the sky
Ńa rainbowŃ
a reassuring indication
of peace with God,
peace resulting from righteousness.
And where does the word ŇrighteousÓ
appear next in the Bible?
In the account about Abraham
Ńnotably in his famous conversation
with Jehovah
found in Genesis chapter 18,
where Jehovah promised Abraham
that if he found
as few as ten righteous people
in the city of Sodom,
he would not destroy that city.
Now, what was it that distinguished Abraham
as righteous in that moral climate?
As you read Genesis chapters 12 through 22,
you get the sense that Abraham
was a man of great faith, unwavering faith.
He was ready to do whatever
Jehovah asked of him.
Now, citing Genesis 15:6
and other texts, James 2:23 says
that ŇÔAbraham put faith in Jehovah,
ŇÔand it was counted to him
Ňas righteousness,Ő
Ňand he came to be called JehovahŐs friend
Ň[JehovahŐs friend,
Ňpeace with God resulting
from righteousness].Ó
Now, what about GodŐs people today?
Turn with me, please, to Isaiah chapter 60
ŃIsaiah chapter 60.
Jehovah refers to Noah
and Abraham as Ňrighteous.Ó
But what would he say about you and me?
Well, notice what it says
toward the end of this chapter.
Isaiah chapter 60,
verses 21, 22:
ŇAnd all your people
Ňwill be righteous;
Ňthey will possess the land forever.
ŇThey are the sprout that I planted,
Ňthe work of my hands,
for me to be beautified.
ŇThe little one will become a thousand
and the small one a mighty nation.
ŇI myself, Jehovah,
will speed it up in its own time.Ó
Yes, prospective members of the great crowd
have been declared righteous
as friends of God as Abraham was.
In JehovahŐs eyes, they are, as it says
in Revelation 7:9, Ňdressed in white robes.Ó
Today, theyŐre serving
alongside GodŐs spirit-anointed ones
who are declared righteous for life.
ŇJehovah, [our] Repurchaser,
the Holy One of Israel,Ó has bought us back
from bondage to sin and death
through the ransom sacrifice of Jesus Christ.
And thus with faith
in the ransom sacrifice of Jesus Christ,
imperfect people are considered righteous
in the sight of God.
Now, in calling us righteous,
Jehovah God by means of Jesus
has done something for us
that we could not do
for ourselves in our imperfect condition.
But does that mean that we can do no wrong?
No, it does not mean that.
In order to maintain our peace,
we must cooperate with Jehovah.
Turn with me, please, to Romans chapter 1.
Now, like Noah and Abraham,
we live in a wicked and violent world
where we are exposed
to a spirit of disobedience.
Satan wants us to become part of this world
by adopting its unrighteous standards.
In the world, sexual immorality
is practiced without shame.
Homosexuals flaunt their conduct.
But Jehovah tells us
that homosexual acts are unrighteous.
God specifically warned the Israelites
against this and other forms of immorality.
Leviticus 18:22 says
that homosexual acts are Ňdetestable.Ó
Does Jehovah still find it so offensive?
Well, notice what he inspired
for both Jews and non-Jews
in the Christian Greek Scriptures here
at Romans 1:26, 27:
ŇThat is why God gave them over
Ňto disgraceful sexual passion,
Ňfor their females changed the natural use
Ňof themselves into one contrary to nature;
Ňlikewise also the males left
the natural use of the female
Ňand became violently inflamed
in their lust toward one another,
Ňmales with males, working what is obscene
Ňand receiving
in themselves the full penalty,
which was due for their error.Ó
So Jehovah has not changed.
According to the Creator, homosexual acts
constitute disgraceful,
obscene error.
Some would disagree.
As verse 28 points out,
such ones do not consider it
worthwhile Ňto acknowledge God.Ó
But with what result?
As it says there,
Ňa disapproved mental stateÓ
Ńjust the opposite of peace.
And merely approving
of unrighteous conduct displeases Jehovah.
Notice how this is indicated in verse 32:
ŇAlthough these know full well
the righteous decree of God
ŇŃthat those practicing such things
are deserving of deathŃ
Ňthey not only keep on doing them
but also approve of those practicing them.Ó
Still, we do not hate individuals
who practice unrighteousness,
nor do we judge them.
On the contrary,
we share the good news with them.
We remember that we were all born
with the same infirmities
and have the same sinful tendencies.
But we also have
the same inherent spiritual need.
And thus, we recognize that others
can have the same peace,
the same privileges,
and the same prospects we enjoy
if they pay attention to Jehovah.
First Timothy 2:3, 4 says
that GodŐs Ňwill is that all sorts of people
should be saved
and come to an accurate knowledge of truth.Ó
And people practicing
all manner of unrighteousness
have accepted the truth.
ŇThat is what some of you were,Ó
1 Corinthians 6:11 says.
So we communicate impartially
with all our neighbors.
But we hate unrighteous conduct,
and we refuse to compromise Bible principles.
Now, sometimes moral issues
become the center
of heated political debates.
We avoid getting drawn
into such controversies.
But now, in practical terms,
what might that look like?
In the following video, notice how adults
can respond effectively when questioned
on highly controversial issues.
There you are.
Did you both get the email survey I sent?
And youŐre both coming, right?
I must have missed it.
I was on calls all morning.
WhatŐs this about?
Well, the whole office is leaving early.
WeŐre going downtown
to support the march
for gay rights.
She wonŐt go.
Why?
ItŐs against her religion.
Some of her people came by my house,
and when I asked, they said your church
wonŐt support gay marriage.
Irene?
ItŐs true.
As JehovahŐs Witnesses,
we hold to the BibleŐs standard on marriage,
which is only between a man and woman.
And we remain politically neutral.
ThatŐs such ignorant thinking.
I understand itŐs a sensitive subject.
I have a daughter who deserves her rights!
Trust me, Amber,
as one of JehovahŐs Witnesses,
we believe everyone has a right
to choose how they live.
And I would never force my beliefs on anyone.
But you wonŐt go.
Just as I would never force
my beliefs on you,
all I ask is the same respect.
And, no, I wonŐt be going.
I have to go back to work.
Look, obviously, Irene,
I donŐt agree with your perspective.
But I do appreciate
that you not push it on anyone else.
Thank you.
In contrast with the majority of mankind
who are divided,
true Christians are united.
We loyally support JehovahŐs right to rule.
We donŐt set the standards,
and weŐre not trying
to solve the worldŐs problems on our own.
We fully support GodŐs Kingdom.
Now, as we observed in the video,
moral and political issues
might be brought up in the workplace.
But more often our young ones,
even very young ones,
are confronted with these same topics.
How will they respond?
Are your young ones ready?
As you watch the next video,
notice how Olivia defends
JehovahŐs righteous standards.
Great discussion today, everyone.
Remember, midterms are this Friday.
No excuses!
That includes you, Jordan.
You were noticeably silent
during our discussion today, Olivia.
I was?
I guess I just didnŐt have much to say.
ArenŐt you concerned about gay rights?
Um,
well, it seems like a political issue,
and I stay neutral
when it comes to political stuff.
But itŐs not a political issue.
This is a human rights issue.
Mr. Dallas,
sheŐs like crazy religious.
Hey!
ThereŐs nothing wrong with that.
No, you donŐt understand.
JehovahŐs Witnesses
hate everybody that isnŐt straight.
ThatŐs not true!
We donŐt hate anyone.
IŐve spoken with your people before.
They seem big on equality.
We are.
The Bible says that ÔGod isnŐt partial.Ő
So we believe that everyone
should be treated fairly.
Good.
So I assume you have
gay members in your church.
No, we donŐt.
But I thought you just said
everyone should be treated equally?
IŐm confused.
Hah, called it!
Jordan, donŐt you have a class to get to?
As I was saying,
how is that not a little hypocritical,
saying that you love everyone
and then excluding certain people?
Honestly, Mr. Dallas,
IŐve wondered the same thing.
OK.
And?
Well, I researched it in the Bible,
and I realized
that God accepts all people,
but he doesnŐt accept all conduct.
What does that mean?
It means that you canŐt be abusing drugs
and you canŐt be stealing
or be violent and still be a Witness.
There are just certain actions
that God just doesnŐt accept.
Including how someone expresses
their sexuality?
In some cases, yes.
We follow GodŐs standards
Ńnot having sex without being married.
Well,
if thatŐs how you feel, thatŐs your right.
Personally, it seems a tad archaic to me
but to each their own.
Hey.
Does the Bible really say all that?
Yeah, it does.
OK,
maybe you can show me sometime.
Yeah, for sure.
Awesome.
So we can expect future installments
in this saga.
But did you notice how Olivia
was able to defend
JehovahŐs righteous standards?
She kept her peaceful spirit, didnŐt she?
She acknowledged that she had
the same question as the teacher,
but she had done further
research on the subject.
And did you appreciate how she
subtly showed that JehovahŐs standards
benefit both the individual
and the community?
As examples, she highlighted
the avoidance of drug abuse and theft,
values she knew her teacher would appreciate.
Parents, are your young ones
able to explain why we do
or donŐt do certain things?
Do you know how your children
really feel about JehovahŐs standards?
Are they obedient simply
to avoid making you mad?
If so, will that truly be enough?
Encourage your young ones
to prove to themselves
why JehovahŐs standards are wise.
Help them to see how they can explain
their choice to live by JehovahŐs standards.
Teach them how to resist pressure
to follow the world.
We are so thankful
that even during these
Ňcritical times hard to deal withÓ
we can enjoy the inner peace
that Jehovah gives to the righteous.
But letŐs remind ourselves of what Jehovah
promises to bring about
once SatanŐs unrighteous system is removed.
Turn with me, please, to Psalm 37.
Here in these familiar verses,
we find a beautiful description
of what is to come.
And notice once again
how the Bible makes the correlation
between peace and righteousness
ŃPsalm 37:29.
Do you have it?
What does it say?
Who will possess the earth?
ŇThe righteous.Ó
And for how long will they live on it?
ŇForever.Ó
And then according to verse 11,
what will they find there?
ŇPeace.Ó
The result of true righteousness
will be peace.
And how much peace will they find?
a little peace?
just personal or family peace?
Remember, the righteous
already had peace with God,
even when wicked people still existed.
But what will Jehovah provide
to all those who continue loving him?
The abundance of peace.
And how will you feel about that?
Delighted or exquisitely delighted?
So stick with it, dear friends.
During this convention, be on the lookout
for the connection
between peace and righteousness.
Continue on the course of righteousness.
Help others to find Ňthe way of peace.Ó
In that way, we can enjoy peace
with Jehovah now,
throughout the remainder of these last days,
and on into the future when Jesus
rules as King over a cleansed earth
in which Ňthe righteous will flourish
and peace will abound.Ó
Thank you, Brother Schafer,
for helping us to understand
why upholding JehovahŐs righteousness
is essential for enjoying true peace.
We have been well-instructed
during this first session of our convention,
havenŐt we?
We look forward to our next session
in which we will consider in greater detail
promises of peace found in GodŐs Word.
We will also see how Bible principles
can help families
to enjoy greater peace now
and how we can avoid pursuing
imitation peace.
Now letŐs conclude this session
by singing song number 97, entitled
ŇLife Depends on GodŐs Word.Ó
After singing the song,
you may have your local concluding prayer.
Again, thatŐs song number 97.