My king.
General.
We’ve starved them out,
but Jehoiachin still refuses to meet.
Negotiations don’t concern me, General,
but your incompetence does.
Finish it,
or you’ll not find me as forgiving as the gods.
Yes, my king.
This is what Jehovah of armies says,
‘Because you did not obey my words,
‘all this land will be reduced to ruins,
‘and this land and its inhabitants
‘will have to serve the king of Babylon
for 70 years.’
Daniel!
Where have you been?
It’s almost sundown!
Sorry, Jeremiah was speaking today, and I, uh
—I stopped by the temple on the way home.
Well, we’re almost ready.
You were at the temple again today.
I was.
“To gaze upon the pleasantness of Jehovah
and to look with appreciation upon his temple.”
I have something for you
so you can always have Jehovah’s words with you.
Thank you, Papa.
What’s wrong?
What’s going to happen to us?
What always happens to Jehovah’s faithful servants.
Have no fear, Jehovah is our shield.
Dinner’s ready.
Did you see our old neighbor at all?
No, I didn’t see him at all today.
Speaking of strange,
I saw our neighbor Eli the other day.
Eli is always getting into trouble.
Let’s sing.
Son, pick a psalm.
“Jehovah is my light and my salvation.”
You always choose that one.
Hushim.
“Jehovah is my light
“and my salvation.
Whom should I fear?”
Daniel!
Stay and play?
I’ve got to go with Papa.
When you come back, do you want to play Noah’s ark?
Sure.
And who will you be?
I’ll be a lion.
Hmm.
Then I’ll be an elephant.
Jehoiachin has surrendered!
Household of Eber, tribe of Judah,
open up at once!
All of you outside! Now!
It’s happened. They’re here.
Gather your things.
We have to go.
Go?
Go where?
We don’t live here anymore.
Hushim, grab our bags.
I hate this place!
Let’s go inside.
Open up!
All four—outside!
Check the back room.
By the order of the king, you are coming with us.
Daniel, of the tribe of Judah—
You will receive training
in the house of the great King Nebuchadnezzar.
But this is my family.
Princes and nobles belong in the palace.
He’s not a prince; he’s just a boy.
Daniel!
Please, I will go if it’s a servant you seek.
No! I’m taking the boy.
Daniel!
Wait!
Can we say goodbye?
Make it quick.
Be strong, my son.
Jehovah is with you.
Daniel!
Mishael.
Have you seen anyone else?
You didn’t think we’d let you come here alone, did you?
Azariah!
Hananiah!
This is Chislon and Ahitub.
Nice to meet you.
Move along.
So where are we going?
The palace, I guess.
So like Joseph in Pharaoh’s house?
No, like Joseph in the dungeon.
Doesn’t seem so bad to me.
Wait!
Chislon, look!
If you don’t say something, I will.
Hello.
Hi.
Move!
Come back again sometime.
These are the Jewish boys that Ashpenaz summoned.
You have been chosen
because you are wise,
but you are lacking.
You will learn our writing
and our language.
You will be given new names,
and at the end of three years,
you will serve the great King Nebuchadnezzar.
Today,
you are foreigners
—tomorrow, the gods willing,
Babylonians.
Meshach.
You look like a Meshach.
Our new names sound like their gods.
New names, new language—
Soon they’ll want us to worship their gods.
Calm down.
My father had idols, and he worshipped Jehovah.
Did you see the same city I did?
It’s the center of the world.
We’ll even eat from the king’s table.
What do Babylonians eat?
His servants are given only the best.
We can’t eat from this food.
Why are you making a big deal out of this?
Because it’s unclean.
Is there a problem?
Our, uh, our God
doesn’t allow us to eat such foods.
You fear your God?
I do.
Well, I am afraid of my lord the king,
who has assigned your food and drink.
He insists on these selections
to maintain your strength and vitality.
What if he should see you
looking worse in appearance
than the other youths?
You would make me guilty before the king.
I must obey the king.
So must you
—all of you!
When dinner is served, I expect you to be hungry.
You don’t speak for us!
You’re right.
You can make your own choice.
Didn’t you hear him?
We don’t have a choice.
This is a new land with new laws.
So what if some of the food is unbled?
It’s just food!
But Jehovah commanded us not to eat blood.
That’s your interpretation.
“You must not eat . . . any blood at all.”
What’s to interpret in that?
Maybe we should all take a moment and pray.
Pray.
Here.
What’s the point?
Jehovah is in Israel.
We’re in Babylon now.
Don’t you believe that Jehovah is here too?
Jehovah said that we’re his witnesses.
What will people say about Jehovah
if we give in and break his laws?
Your meal is ready.
Did you hear me?
Thank you.
But if we eat those foods, we’ll disobey our God.
Do you want to starve?
No, of course not,
but He forbids us from eating blood
and food that he calls “unclean.”
Please, test your servants for ten days,
and let us be given some vegetables to eat
and water to drink.
Vegetables?
Just give us ten days.
And then deal with your servants
according to what you see.
Ten days.
Here you go, thanks to Jehovah.
You need to try this meat. It’s amazing!
Have you seen anything like this before?
Oh! Really!
Yes! Oh, wow!
Yes!
Ashpenaz has summoned you.
My lord, these young men are of royal . . .
I know who they are.
We’ve been watching you
—all of you.
You don’t bow to our idols,
you pray only to your God,
and you are not eating our foods.
They insisted that their God would not . . .
Somehow,
you look healthier than the others.
Continue giving them the diet they’ve requested.
And Belteshazzar,
your future is bright.
Don’t waste it.
Bring in the next group.
The total rations would be fifteen kurru,
two pānu,
and five sūtu.
Correct.
How much interest
may a merchant charge on money and grain?
It would be 40 percent, my lord.
Forty percent?
Have you learned only to be a thief
the past three years?
And you, Meshach?
The rate is 20 percent.
Very good.
Which star of Enlil is brightest
in the Urgula constellation?
Do you know?
It is the Lugal star.
Impressive.
There is a tower that is high
but, nonetheless, has no shade.
What is it?
Your ziggurat?
Hopeless.
You can solve the riddle?
It is sunlight, my lord.
Correct.
My wise men teach that the gods
are responsible for everything.
If that’s so,
why do the good suffer and the evil prosper?
No one has been able to answer . . .
As you say, O king,
‘the wise do not always have the food,
‘nor do the intelligent always have the riches,
‘nor do those with knowledge always have success,
‘because time and unexpected events
overtake them all.’
Who wrote those words?
Solomon.
Famed for his wisdom.
But its source was his God,
our God, Jehovah.
Take them away.
When should we return?
You won’t!
Go back to your families.
You’ve proven worthless.
Belteshazzar, no—not the four of you.
We have more to discuss.
I do not know your God,
but you’ve proven to be ten times better
than any priest or conjurer that I’ve met.
Ashpenaz will arrange
for you to serve in the palace with my wise men.
Maybe your gifts were wasted in Jerusalem,
but here they will be put to use.
The victory in Jerusalem is complete.
Our forces are now preparing to besiege Tyre.
They should remember what happened to Zedekiah.
The gods are with us!
Jerah,
what is it?
It’s about Jerusalem.
Where are you going?
To see my family.
This year, we’ve had to make do.
Daniel.
Come, eat.
What’s wrong?
It’s Jerusalem.
They tore down the walls;
they torched its towers.
Many died.
And they burned down Jehovah’s house!
Why didn’t our people listen?
Did they think Jehovah couldn’t see
what they were doing?
As long as our temple existed,
our people had hope.
As long as Jehovah exists,
we have hope.
But he’s rejected us
because of our unrighteousness.
He hasn’t
—not everyone.
Jehovah told Ezekiel
that in his eyes you
are as righteous as Noah
and Job.
He said that?
He did.
If Jehovah cares so much,
then why are we in exile?
Why can’t we go home?
Why can’t we be together?
You are home, Son.
I don’t have all the answers.
Stay close to Jehovah.
You will be blessed.
Call the wise men!
I had a dream,
and I’m agitated.
I need to know what I dreamed.
O king, may you live on forever.
Relate the dream to your servants.
We will tell the interpretation.
No!
If you don’t make the dream known to me
along with the interpretation,
you’ll be dismembered,
and your houses will be turned into public latrines.
But if you do, tell me the dream
and the interpretation,
you will receive gifts and a reward
and great honor.
We’ve got to buy some time
so we can consult the spirits.
The scrolls will tell you what the dreams say.
We need to come up with a plan.
He wants us to tell him the dream!
Yes.
No one has ever asked this before.
Can we do it?
What do we do?
If you can buy us some time,
we can consult the spirits.
You’ve agreed to tell me something false
and deceitful until the situation changes.
Deceitful?
Deceitful!
There is not a man on earth
who can do what the king demands.
What the king is asking is difficult.
No one exists who could tell this to the king except
—except the gods.
Arioch,
seize them!
Down!
Kill them!
Call the wise men!
Hurry!
Go, go, go!
By the order of the king, round them up!
Jerah.
You’re in danger.
Why? What happened?
I didn’t hear everything,
but the wise men angered the king.
Everyone is to be executed by dawn.
Bring Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah here.
I’ll try to learn more.
Yes—Chaldean, Egyptian, Jewish
—all the wise men.
Arioch?
Belteshazzar, you shouldn’t be here.
Why is there such a harsh order from the king?
He had a dream,
and no one can tell him what it is.
Flee now!
If you escape before dawn, you might survive.
Tell me why I asked for them
and you haven’t brought them?
Why aren’t the gods talking to them?
I want them and all of their families brought here.
I want to look into the whites of their eyes
and ask them why.
Hang them without their skins!
Let the gods look down on their flesh,
and then throw their bodies in the Euphrates.
Ashpenaz.
What good are wise men without wisdom?
What are you doing here?
I need to speak with the king.
You need to go!
Please, let me speak with him!
My lord, this is Belteshazzar.
O king,
interpretations belong to my God, Jehovah.
He knows your dream and what it means.
Well, where is your God? Where?
I believe that he—
I know that he will reveal it to me.
Please, give me time.
We have until morning.
To do what?
To reveal the dream to the king.
Well, how much of the dream
has Jehovah revealed to you?
Well, nothing yet.
But Jehovah revealed
that he would interpret it, right?
Not exactly.
Daniel,
how do you know this is even going to happen?
Well, I can’t be sure.
You’d better be sure!
His name is at stake.
If he reveals the dream,
it proves that he’s the true God!
If?
What can we do to help?
Pray.
Pray that Jehovah have mercy on us.
O Jehovah,
surely you didn’t bring us here just to die.
What will people say?
We told them that you
are the God of the heavens,
the only God who can reveal secrets.
Please,
vindicate yourself.
Jerah!
I have found a man from the exiles of Judah
who can make known the interpretation to the king.
I know who he is.
Can you really make known to me
the dream that I saw
and its interpretation?
There is a God in the heavens
who is a Revealer of secrets,
and he has made known to King Nebuchadnezzar
what is to happen in the final part of the days.
This is your dream:
You saw an immense image.
That image was standing in front of you.
You yourself are the head of gold.
But after you another kingdom will rise,
inferior to you.
Then another kingdom,
a third one, of copper,
that will rule over the whole earth.
As for the fourth kingdom,
it will be strong like iron.
The kingdom will be divided.
And as the toes of the feet
were partly of iron and partly of clay,
so the kingdom will be partly strong
and partly fragile.
In the days of those kings,
the God of heaven
will set up a kingdom
that will never be destroyed.
And this kingdom
will not be passed on to any other people.
It will crush and put an end
to all these kingdoms.
And it alone will stand forever.
The dream is true,
and its interpretation is trustworthy.
Quick!
Bring a fine robe
and a necklace of gold.
Burn incense before him.
Truly your God is a God of gods
and a Lord of kings
and a Revealer of secrets.
May your God be honored
by the honor I give you.
You are now ruler over all the province of Babylon.
O king, these servants
also worship the God in the heavens.
May they too be appointed to administer the province?
Make the necessary arrangements.
You have proven far superior
than these so-called wise men.
I now appoint you their chief prefect.
Did you hear Nebuchadnezzar?
When he said, “Your God is a God of gods
and a Lord of kings.”
Jehovah answered your prayer.
Jehovah answered our prayers.
What’s going to happen next?
Can we go back to Jerusalem?
I don’t know what happens next,
but as long as we stay close to Jehovah . . .
He will always be with us
as long as we have faith in him.
There’s nothing in the stars
about kingdoms crushing kingdoms.
Of course not.
It’s a trick!
But how did he know the dream?
Amar-Utu!
Amar-Utu, what message from the gods?
I have examined a sheep’s liver.
Your future is bright.
The stars of Shabatu, the giant,
speak only of your grandeur.
And I’m the head of gold.
Jehovah said so.
Your dream revealed many good things.
But this Belteshazzar, he’s a Jew—
He’s a clever Jew, to be sure,
but he couldn’t interpret dreams
before he came to Babylon.
He first had to be educated here
and given a Babylonian name,
a name that honors our great god Bel.
Bel used this young captive
to reveal great things to you—
Bel,
not Jehovah, who you defeated in Jerusalem.
So the tree is my enemies.
Who is it after the seven times pass over?
Then it is you again, O great king.
You are fools.
At last—
Belteshazzar, chief of the magic-practicing priests,
all of the other wise men are unable
to make the interpretation known to me.
But you are able to do so.
Explain to me the visions I’ve seen in my dreams.
What did you dream?
I saw a tree in the midst of the earth,
and its height, it was enormous
—it was enormous.
And the tree grew and became strong,
and its top—
And its top reached the heavens,
reached the heavens,
and the tree grew and became strong.
. . . holy one . . .
Chop down the tree!
And I saw a watcher . . .
. . . with a banding of iron
and of copper.
So who’s the tree?
O my lord,
may the dream apply to those hating you
and its interpretation to your enemies.
The tree that you saw
that grew great and became strong,
whose top reached the heavens
and was visible to all the earth,
which had beautiful foliage, abundant fruit,
and food for all,
beneath which the beasts of the field would dwell
and on whose branches
the birds of the heavens would reside,
it is you, O king.
And the king saw a watcher, a holy one,
coming down from the heavens who was saying:
“Chop down the tree and destroy it,
“but leave the stump with its roots in the ground
“with a banding of iron and of copper.
“And let the dew of the heavens make it wet,
“and let its portion be
“with the beasts of the field
until seven times pass over it.”
This is the interpretation, O king;
it is the decree of the Most High.
You will be driven away from among men,
and your dwelling will be with the beasts of the field,
and you will be given vegetation to eat
just like bulls,
and you will become wet
with the dew of the heavens,
and seven times will pass over you
until you know
that the Most High is Ruler
in the kingdom of mankind
and that he grants it to whomever he wants.
But because they said to leave
the stump of the tree with its roots,
your kingdom will be yours again
after you come to know
that the heavens are ruling.
Turn away from your sins
by doing what is right
and from your iniquity
by showing mercy to the poor.
It may be that your prosperity will be extended.
Does Belteshazzar know when this will happen?
No.
But your wise men
doubt that his interpretation can be trusted.
Look at the facts:
Egypt’s gods told the Egyptians
that they would defeat us.
Yet, you destroyed them.
So why should the God of the Jews
be given any more credit?
Look at what you’ve done.
The gods are with you.
You have made Babylon
the greatest kingdom on earth.
Belteshazzar wants you to grovel like a slave
—you.
A strong king means a strong kingdom.
Let us continue with our discussion
of the stars of Enlil.
Now, the Lugal star is the brightest star
in the Urgula constellation.
The stars are reliable,
unlike the gods of defeated nations.
Go back to Jerusalem.
Oh, you could
if there was anything left of it.
Has Jehovah revealed anything new?
It’s been ten months
and still no sign of this supposed insanity.
I trust my God.
Yes, as we do when we read the stars.
But we still shape the message.
You will be held responsible for the words,
and when a wise man speaks lies, well . . .
I spoke only what Jehovah revealed.
Have you forgotten what happened
when some couldn’t interpret the dream image?
A death sentence followed.
And that was a flattering interpretation,
that the king was a head of gold.
This time, you’ve said he’ll go mad,
and nothing has happened.
It will happen.
Maybe, maybe not.
But your words are against the king.
It’s treason.
And no one can protect you from that.
Ten months.
Nothing has happened.
But your words are against the king.
Still no sign of this supposed insanity.
It’s treason.
And no one can protect you from that.
So you can always have Jehovah’s words with you.
“Instruct me in your way, O Jehovah.”
“Do not hand me over to my adversaries,
“for false witnesses have risen up against me,
“and they threaten me with violence.
“Where would I be if I did not have faith
“that I would see Jehovah’s goodness
in the land of the living?”
Please, test your servants for ten days.
Somehow, you look healthier than the others.
Continue giving them the diet they’ve requested.
I do not know your God,
but you’ve proven
to be ten times better than any priest
or conjurer I’ve met.
He had a dream,
and no one can tell him what it is.
Jehovah answered your prayer.
“Hope in Jehovah;
“be courageous and strong of heart.
Yes, hope in Jehovah.”
Prepare a sacrifice to Bel.
To the gods.
This city is the jewel of the world.
Look at the Ishtar Gate, the gardens,
the ziggurat so high
it reaches the gods themselves.
No one would question that.
It’s odd that only twelve months ago
one of your servants
dared to suggest that you’d go insane.
Is this not Babylon the Great
that I myself have built for the royal house
with my own strength and might
and for the glory of my majesty?
“To you it is being said,
“O King Nebuchadnezzar,
“‘The kingdom has gone away from you,
“‘and from mankind you are being driven away.
“‘With the beasts of the field your dwelling will be,
“‘and you will be given vegetation
“‘to eat just like bulls,
“‘and seven times will pass over you,
“‘until you know that the Most High
“‘is Ruler in the kingdom
“‘of mankind and that he grants it
to whomever he wants.’”
No! Stop! Stop! Stop!
Father!
When you and your wise men
have failed consistently,
how can you claim Daniel to be a fraud?
This was a trick.
Daniel conspired against your father.
A trick.
Then how did he make it happen?
Everything he has said has come true,
which is quite different from our history with you.
My father trusted you,
and I trusted you, and you were all wrong.
Either you failed or Marduk did.
Either way, . . .
Tell me:
Who is this God in the heavens, Jehovah?