I thought I would find you here.
Joanna, my sister.
Please sit.
Listen to this:
“You are a holy people to Jehovah your God,
“and Jehovah your God
has chosen you to become his people,
“his special property,
out of all the peoples
who are on the face of the earth.”
The words of Moses,
speaking to our people
before they entered this land.
Yes.
And just before that,
he told them to destroy
all the idols of the Canaanites.
I wonder if there are more idols
in the land now than there were then.
At every turn,
our people bow and pray to them.
You’re doing all you can.
How dare you promote this filth!
But they don’t listen.
The true God . . .
Stop right there.
I listen.
Moses came down from the mountain.
Stop talking.
And I think you’re great.
You’re like Elijah.
I’m surprised Jehovah uses me at all.
Well, I’m not.
You always want to do the right thing.
It makes us proud.
Jonah!
Ye—
Yes, my Lord.
Get up,
go to Nineveh the great city,
and proclaim judgment against her,
for their wickedness
has come to my attention.
Nineveh?
Nineveh.
They deserve to die.
It’s not his responsibility.
He’s just going to get himself killed.
You need to talk to him.
Someone needs to talk to him.
We’ve prepared a meal for you.
I’m not hungry.
They haven’t spoken a word to me in hours.
Your brothers are young, Jonah.
The news you brought to us this morning
—it was heavy.
What did your brothers say?
Izliah is afraid they will kill me;
skin me alive.
He doesn’t think they should even be warned.
Just let Jehovah slaughter them all.
And Eber doesn’t believe they will listen.
What do you think?
I think that if it’s Jehovah’s will
to destroy them,
he wouldn’t have commanded me to go.
But I do think Eber is right.
Why would they listen?
Our own people don’t listen.
And yet the warning still goes out.
But when has Jehovah
ever asked a prophet to go to a foreign land
to preach judgment against it?
Jonah, I—
I don’t have all the answers.
To be sent to declare judgment
in the heart of Assyria,
it’s unlike anything Jehovah
has asked of his prophets to do before.
But if it’s Jehovah’s will
that you should go,
then you should go.
He must have good reason
for sending you there.
Trust him.
Jonah!
Jonah, look!
I got figs!
I’m going to pack you some cakes too.
I wish I could go with you.
Izliah is afraid they will kill me;
skin me alive.
You’re leaving without saying good-bye?
You need to go back inside, Joanna.
But we had things prepared for you!
You’ll need them in Nineveh.
You’re not going to Nineveh, are you?
No, Tarshish.
No, Jonah!
That’s the wrong way!
Go back!
We can talk to Father!
Joanna!
I can’t go to Nineveh.
I just can’t do it.
But what will you do in Tarshish?
When will you be back?
I don’t know, maybe never.
Never?
Then who’s going to Nineveh?
Who’s going to tell them what Jehovah said?
I’m sorry, Joanna.
I don’t know what Jehovah will do.
But I just can’t do it.
It’s too much.
He doesn’t need me anyway.
We need you.
And you’re Jehovah’s prophet.
You’re like Elijah.
Remember?
Not anymore.
Go home, Joanna.
I’m sorry.
If it’s Jehovah’s will
that you should go,
then you should go.
Trust him.
Look!
By the gods.
Furl the sail!
Fasten those lines, men!
Hatches!
Brace yourselves!
Secure the cargo!
Turn into the wave!
Captain, we’re taking on too much water!
Throw the cargo overboard!
All of it! Now!
Get it over!
It’s no use!
This storm is from the gods!
Baal!
Eshmun!
Melqart!
Help us!
Where is the passenger?
He’s down below!
He’s down below.
Please! Save us! Help us!
Why are you sleeping?
Get up, call out to your god!
Perhaps the true God
will show his concern for us,
and we will not perish.
Save us! Help us!
Please, help us, Melqart!
Please, help us! Baal!
Save us! Save us! Baal!
Deliver us! Baal!
Let’s cast lots to find out
who is to blame for this calamity!
It’s him!
Why has this calamity come upon us?
It is from the true and living God.
He has brought this storm because of me.
Where do you come from?
What is your country?
From what people are you?
I am a Hebrew,
and I fear Jehovah the God of the heavens,
the One who made the sea and the dry land.
I am—
I was his prophet.
What have you done?
He told me to go to Nineveh
and deliver a message.
Instead, I ran away.
What must we do to you
to make the sea calm down for us?
What must we do?
Lift me up and throw me into the sea,
and the sea will calm down for you;
for I know that it is because of me
that this violent storm has come upon you.
Let’s do it!
He’ll die!
If we kill Jehovah’s prophet,
what will He do to us?
If Jehovah wants him in Nineveh,
won’t He be angered
if we throw him overboard?
Take to the oars, men.
Row for your lives!
There’s the land over there.
Hurry!
Row!
It’s no use.
We have to do what Jonah said.
Jehovah, may we not perish
because of this man.
Do not hold us responsible
for innocent blood,
since you have done as you pleased,
O Jehovah.
He gave his life for us.
Our gods did nothing.
We should sacrifice
to his God for sparing us.
How am I still alive?
What will become of me?
O Jehovah,
out of the depths of the Grave,
I cry to you for help.
Please hear my voice.
I know I have been driven
away from your sight!
How will I gaze again upon your holy temple?
Oh, may my prayer come in to you.
With a voice of thanksgiving
I will sacrifice to you.
What I have vowed, I will pay.
Hey!
Hey, are you OK?
What happened?
Are there others?
We’re here to help.
What is your name?
Jonah.
My name is Jonah.
Grab his other arm;
we need to get him to the house.
Papa says you are a prophet.
I was a prophet.
Papa says that you
were swallowed by a big fish.
Yes.
Why would a fish swallow you?
Well, I was in the water.
Why where you in the water?
I was on a ship;
then I was in the water.
Why were you on a ship?
Because I tried to run away from Jehovah.
When you were in the fish, were you scared?
Yes.
Did you pray a lot?
Why did you pray to God
if you were running away from him?
Father!
It’s Jonah!
He’s back!
Jonah!
Joanna.
I thought I wouldn’t see you again.
I thought you wouldn’t be back.
I’m so sorry, Joanna.
Please forgive me.
Father waited for you to come home every day.
He never gave up hope.
What happened?
A fish?
How is that possible?
It was a miracle, Izliah.
Jehovah saved you.
So, what will you do now?
I don’t know.
I think it’s time
for everyone to get some rest.
We can talk more tomorrow.
Jonah,
I’m sorry about the things
I said before you left.
I didn’t realize . . .
It’s no matter, Izliah.
My decision to run was my own.
Thank you.
It’s good to have you back.
Oh, thank you.
Thank you.
I’m still proud of you.
Sleep well, my son.
Father?
Yes?
I can’t stop thinking
about those men on that ship,
all the cargo they lost,
the fear in their eyes.
What if they didn’t survive?
I put them in danger.
Disobedience often hurts others, Jonah,
not just ourselves.
We’ll pray for those men.
Do you think Jehovah will ever use me again?
He’s shown you mercy, Jonah.
He brought you home.
Let’s be content with that for now.
Father,
I’m sorry.
I know, my son.
I know.
Let’s try to get some rest.
Jonah!
My Lord!
I am so sorry.
Get up,
go to Nineveh the great city,
and proclaim to her the message
that I tell you.
Yes.
Thank you.
I will do as you command.
May Jehovah be with you, my son.
He saved me from the heart of the sea;
he can save me again in the days ahead.
Here, I made these cakes for you.
Thank you, Joanna.
How long will it take you to get to Nineveh?
If all goes well, maybe 40 days.
May it go well.
Thanks.
Where are you traveling to?
Nineveh.
Really?
I was just there.
Hmm.
I was selling some horses.
I’ll tell you this,
I’m glad to be going home.
You should really be careful over there.
That’s what I’ve heard.
Tell me about it.
Well, the city is huge.
It would probably take you
three days to walk around it.
The chariots
—they’re the best in the world.
And the horses . . .
Hmm.
The horses are magnificent.
What about the people?
The people—
They worship gods of war.
What do you think they’re like?
They love conquest and violence;
it’s like bread to them.
That’s comforting.
Hey, don’t worry.
Just don’t attract any attention to yourself.
Stick to your business,
and you’ll be just fine.
What is your business anyway?
I’m a prophet of Jehovah.
He’s sending me
to proclaim judgment against it.
Same thing again?
It’s your fault!
Hello there, Foreigner.
Where are you going, Foreigner?
Hey! Stop! Stop!
My food!
Somebody help me!
Thank you.
What about the people?
They worship gods of war.
What do you think they’re like?
In—
in just 40 days more,
Nineveh will be overthrown.
In just 40 days more,
Nineveh will be overthrown!
Who’s the foreigner?
In just 40 days more,
Nineveh will be overthrown!
Nineveh will be overthrown.
Who can possibly overthrow our city?
Is he crazy?
He looks like an Israelite.
The true God has spoken.
The great violence of this city
has come to the attention of the true God.
Jehovah, the true God, has spoken.
This city will be destroyed.
Nineveh will be overthrown.
Jehovah, the true God, has spoken.
Your city will be destroyed.
In 35 days,
this city will be destroyed.
Nineveh will be overthrown.
This city will be destroyed.
We can’t just leave everything.
What should we do?
Listen!
He is a prophet
of the Israelite God, Jehovah.
What should we do?
Should we flee the city?
We can’t just leave everything.
Leave our homes?
Where should we go?
Listen.
If we repent,
maybe his God will have mercy on us.
According to the prophet,
there are only 20 days left
until the destruction of the city.
Throughout the city,
people are fasting and putting on sackcloth.
They are asking the prophet
how Jehovah wants them to behave,
and they’re trying to do as he says.
Is that what Jonah is telling them to do?
No, the people simply reason
that because there’s a warning
and time before calamity strikes,
maybe this God will change his mind.
What else have we learned about Jonah?
A Ninevite reported
overhearing a conversation of Jonah’s.
It seems he originally chose not to come.
Instead, he fled to Tarshish
but was thrown overboard.
Then he claims Jehovah sent a fish
to swallow him and bring him back.
Is he insane?
Maybe not.
This man speaks for the God of Israel
—a God of miracles,
known for his greatness and his power.
He might be powerful in Israel,
but we have our own gods here.
True, but Jehovah is the one responsible
for humiliating the gods of Egypt,
even destroying their army in the Red Sea.
He’s also the One
who brought about the great Flood
mentioned in our histories.
He did this because the people of the time
were extremely violent.
Call my scribe.
Help us, please!
Save us!
I cannot accept gifts and bribes.
Jehovah has spoken.
In 10 days more,
the true God will overthrow Nineveh!
The true God has spoken.
The violence of the city
has come to the attention of the true God.
The true God has spoken.
Nineveh will be overthrown.
The city will be destroyed.
Hear the word of the king, people of Nineveh.
Hear the word of the king!
“By the decree of the king and his nobles:
“No man or beast,
“herd or flock, should eat anything at all.
“They should not take food,
“nor should they drink any water.
“Let them be covered with sackcloth,
“both man and beast;
“and let them call out earnestly to God
“and turn from their evil ways
“and from the violence they practice.
“Who knows whether the true God
“may reconsider what he intends to do
“and turn from his burning anger,
so that we may not perish?”
In three days,
Nineveh will be overthrown!
Jehovah has spoken!
Something should be happening;
there’s nothing.
Would Jehovah actually pardon the city?
No.
No, that’s not possible.
How could Jehovah change his mind?
What will these people think of me?
What good is a prophet
if his words don’t come true?
Was this not my concern
when I was in my own land?
That is why I tried to flee
to Tarshish in the first place;
for I knew that you are
a compassionate and merciful God,
slow to anger
and abundant in loyal love,
and one who feels grieved over calamity.
O Jehovah, please take away my life,
for it is better for me to die than to live.
Is it right for you to be so angry?
I must leave the city.
We know you are a prophet of the true God.
We have faith that you speak truth.
Please, stay in our home.
No.
We will make you comfortable.
I will not stay in this city.
Still nothing?
This plant grew so quickly.
Jehovah still cares for me.
O Jehovah, let me die.
Take my life.
It is better
for me to die than to live.
Is it right for you to be so angry
over the bottle-gourd plant?
I have a right to be angry,
so angry that I want to die.
You felt sorry for the bottle-gourd plant,
which you did not work for,
nor did you make it grow;
it grew in one night
and perished in one night.
Should I not also feel sorry
for Nineveh the great city,
in which there are more than 120,000 men
who do not even know right from wrong,
as well as their many animals?
Are you Jonah?
I am.
Mommy says you saved us.
No, Jehovah saved you.
I was just—
I was just a messenger.
Thank you.
What are you doing?
I’ve written about Nineveh
but also about Jehovah’s great mercy
both to the people there and to me.
Was it hard to write about all that?
Painful.
So, what will you do now?
Whatever Jehovah asks me to do.