At the age of 40,
a man of the royal
house of Egypt
becomes a shepherd.
Forty years later,
that shepherd
leaves his flock
to shepherd people,
a nation of slaves
numbering in the millions.
Moses is that 80-year-old shepherd.
He leads the people of Israel
out of the hands
of their cruel master, Egypt,
after they have resided in that land
for more than two centuries.
When Moses was 40 years of age,
he thought he was qualified
to break Egypt’s iron grip over his people.
How did he show this?
Moses witnessed an incident
of terrible injustice,
“an Egyptian beating a Hebrew,
one of his brothers.”
He was eager to act,
so “he killed the Egyptian
and hid him in the sand.”
Commenting on this,
the Christian disciple Stephen said:
“He thought
that his brothers would grasp
“that God was giving them
salvation by his hand,
but they did not grasp it.”
His own people branded him a killer.
Fearing for his life,
Moses fled Egypt
and journeyed
across the wilderness to Midian.
During those 40 years,
Moses would cultivate patience, meekness,
humility, mildness of temper, self-control,
and the ability to wait on Jehovah.
Who of us has not experienced
challenges similar to Moses?
Have we had to overcome shyness
or stand up to bullying?
How do we react when faced with injustice
or opposition from family or from government?
Do we tend to get impatient
as we wait on Jehovah to make things right?
Or do we put too much confidence in ourselves
and too little in Jehovah?
If so,
then we can learn a lesson in endurance
from the example of Moses.
Let us start by reading Exodus 3:1-10.
Moses now had a divine commission.
The time had come
for Jehovah to free his people.
The time had come for Moses
to be a faithful leader who does not give up.
Would he accept this assignment,
one that he had been only too eager
to take up 40 years earlier in Egypt?
Let’s pick up the Bible account
at Exodus 3:11-22.
What a dramatic change
40 years has brought to Moses!
Here is a different Moses,
one who is uncertain, shy.
Moses has serious doubts
about his own qualifications.
He believes that his commission
is too much for him.
In effect, he says: “Oh, no!
Please don’t ask me to do this!”
Can you put yourself in Moses’ sandals?
Have you ever been given an assignment
that you feel is beyond your ability?
Yet, you don’t give up.
Earnest prayer helps restore your confidence.
You obey.
What about Moses?
Jehovah reassures him by saying:
“I will prove to be with you.”
Yet, Moses is still hesitant.
Will he give up
and ask Jehovah to find someone else?
Note what Exodus 4:1-9 says:
Moses needs reassurance.
So Jehovah gives Moses, not just one,
but three signs to show the older men
proof of divine backing.
And what powerful credentials these are!
For the first time,
a human is empowered to perform miracles.
As the rest of Exodus chapter 4 shows,
Moses feels inadequate to speak to Pharaoh.
He pleads that he is “slow of tongue,”
even asking Jehovah
to excuse him from the task.
Jehovah gives him help.
Jehovah assigns Aaron
as Moses’ mouthpiece.
Both men proceed to meet Pharaoh.
Listen to what is said to Pharaoh
as found at Exodus 5:1-9:
Pharaoh defiantly says no to Jehovah.
He is angry at the Hebrews.
In turn, the people are angry at Moses.
They blame him for their hardship.
Moses feels sorry for the people
and asks Jehovah:
“Why have you sent me?”
Jehovah patiently gives Moses
a reassuring message,
beginning at Exodus 6:1.
Jehovah backs up his promise of deliverance
by means of his unique name.
Moses, therefore, does not give up.
He obeys Jehovah,
and he and Aaron prepare
to meet Pharaoh again.
Let’s read Exodus 7:1-7.
Moses now can be confident
of Jehovah’s backing
because Moses is doing
things Jehovah’s way
and at a time that fits
Jehovah’s prophetic timetable.
Jehovah is about to use ten plagues
to bring Pharaoh to his knees.
These disasters will show
that Jehovah’s sovereignty is real
and that he is worthy of worship.
The Ten Plagues will also expose
the Egyptian gods as nothing
—as mere unreality.
The first three plagues
strike both the Egyptians and the Hebrews.
However, the next seven plagues
do not touch the Hebrews
—proof that Jehovah can set apart
and protect his worshippers
if they do not give up their trust in him.
Now let’s summarize the Ten Plagues
listed at Exodus 7:14–11:10.
Plague 1:
Water is turned into blood.
Plague 2:
Frogs invade the land and houses.
Plague 3:
Gnats pester man and beast.
Plague 4:
Gadflies swarm and bite only the Egyptians.
Plague 5:
Livestock die.
Plague 6:
Boils fester on man and beast.
Plague 7:
Hail strikes man, beast, and vegetation.
Plague 8:
Locusts swarm and eat all vegetation
left after the hailstorm.
Plague 9:
Thick darkness
blankets Egypt for three days.
Plague 10:
The firstborn of man and livestock is killed.
Pharaoh sees his firstborn dead.
He hears great outcries of bitter grief
rise from the houses of all the Egyptians
because they too see their firstborn dead.
Pharaoh quickly summons Moses and Aaron
and tells them to go, to hurry away.
Will Pharaoh’s heart soften?
Let’s have Exodus 14:5-10 answer.
Will Jehovah hear their cry for help?
Let’s read Exodus 14:13-31.
Are the Hebrews happy that they endured
to see the salvation of Jehovah?
Yes!
They break out in a joyful victory song.
Listen to them sing!
You too can stand and sing along.
Song number 149 represents what is found
at Exodus 15:1-21.
If you can,
let us all stand and sing song 149.
Please be seated.
The account we just read
vividly illustrates Jehovah’s use of power
in a way that serves notice
on all who defy him.
Thus, what can we take away
from our Bible reading?
The fact that the Hebrews suffered in Egypt
and Jehovah delivered them is concrete proof
that our hope for deliverance
from Satan’s world
is not an empty one.
When you seem trapped
in a corner by life’s problems,
do not give up!
The God who parted the Red Sea
can provide escape for you too.
If, during the coming great tribulation,
you feel trapped by Satan’s hoards,
remember: Endure to the end!
Jehovah will provide escape for you
and for all his worshippers
who don’t give up!