Throughout history,
mankind has been in a constant struggle
for freedom.
Men have fought for freedom of religion,
freedom of speech, freedom of the press,
and freedom from bondage and slavery.
Man’s perception of freedom
is shaped by his environment,
his personal situation,
and even his age.
While growing up, I remember the boys
in my neighborhood getting together
on the final day of summer vacation
to enjoy what we called
“our last day of freedom” baseball game.
We called it that because school started
the next day.
But this matter of freedom is not a game.
Our view of freedom
is a matter of life and death.
No matter what our personal feelings
or needs are regarding freedom,
we must recognize one fundamental fact.
Basically, there are
only two kinds of freedom:
true freedom from Jehovah
and false freedom
that is offered by Satan and his world.
Every person must make a choice
between these two freedoms.
Let’s consider what each
of these freedoms represents
and how our choice affects our prospect
for eternal life.
Please open your Bibles to Matthew chapter 7.
We’re going to read verses 13 and 14.
And here we read an illustration
that Jesus gave in the Sermon on the Mount,
and in the illustration he speaks
about two gates and two roads.
And this also relates
to the two freedoms
that we’re discussing this morning.
Matthew 7:13, 14
—he said:
“Go in through the narrow gate,
“because broad is the gate and spacious
“is the road leading off into destruction,
“and many are going in through it;
“whereas narrow is the gate and cramped
“the road leading off into life,
and few are finding it.”
At first glance, this “spacious” road
may appear to be the road to true freedom.
Why?
Because it’s easy to travel.
Travelers on this road
can go where they please,
think as they please,
and live as they please.
There aren’t any restrictions
—no rules, no commitments.
And it’s not surprising
when we realize
that one definition of “freedom”
is “the ability or capacity to act
without undue hindrance
or restraint.”
But this is the freedom
that Satan and his world have to offer.
But is it real freedom?
Please open to Ephesians chapter 2.
We’re going to read verses 2 and 3.
This scripture describes
the situation of people
who choose to enter that broad gate
and then walk the spacious road.
Ephesians 2:2, 3
describes them this way:
“In which you at one time walked according
“to the system of things of this world,
“according to the ruler
of the authority of the air,
“the spirit that is
“now at work in the sons of disobedience.
“Yes, among them we all at one time
“conducted ourselves in harmony
with the desires of our flesh,
“carrying out the will of the flesh
“and of our thoughts,
and we were naturally children of wrath
just as the rest.”
Did you notice that the ones
walking on this road
are not free at all?
They have a ruler,
“the ruler of the authority of the air,”
Satan the Devil.
And they also have a master.
They carry out the will of the flesh;
they are slaves of the flesh and its desires.
Please turn to 2 Peter chapter 2,
and we’ll read verse 19.
These words confirm
that Satan’s promise of freedom
is a false promise that results in slavery.
Second Peter 2:19 says:
“While they are promising them freedom,
“they themselves are slaves of corruption;
“for if anyone is
overcome by someone, he is his slave.”
Satan’s road is not the road of true freedom.
Also, it’s not a freeway.
In fact, it’s a toll road,
and the toll to walk on this road
is very heavy.
This permissive, broad road takes its toll
in sexually transmitted diseases,
broken homes, bodies and minds
that are sick with drug and alcohol abuse,
and acts of violence.
This toll is way too expensive
just to walk on a dead-end street
that ends in destruction.
But now, what about the other road
that Jesus talked about?
He said ‘the gate is narrow’
and ‘the road is cramped.’
Why do so few people
choose to walk this road?
Primarily because very few people today
want God’s laws and principles
to govern their lives.
True, this road has boundaries,
but those boundaries help
the ones who walk the road
to avoid wrongdoing,
to fight wrong desires,
to resist peer pressure
and the fear of ridicule that may come
as a result of walking this road.
The broad road is centered on self
—self-indulgence, self-awareness,
self-fulfillment, and self-interest.
In contrast,
this narrow road calls for self-control,
self-denial, hard work,
and respect for authority.
But this is the road to true freedom.
Interestingly, some scriptures
that talk about the freedom
that Jehovah gives may appear to be
a little bit confusing.
For example, let’s open
to 1 Peter chapter 2
and verse16.
And as we read it, notice
the contrasting expressions in this scripture
—1 Peter 2:16.
It says: “Be as free people,
“using your freedom,
not as a cover for doing wrong,
but as slaves of God.”
How interesting that we can be free
and be a slave at the same time!
For most people, the idea of becoming
a slave to anyone or anything
is not appealing.
However, there are positive aspects
to being a slave.
Let’s consider an example.
In Israel, a man who fell into debt
could sell himself as a slave
to pay off his debt,
but this wasn’t a permanent arrangement.
He was to be freed after seven years
or in a Jubilee year, whichever came first.
While serving as a slave,
he was treated like a hired man;
he was protected from abuse.
And when he was released,
his master gave him a gift
to help him get back on his feet.
This was Jehovah’s arrangement,
so it gives us a glimpse of what it’s like
to be a slave for Jehovah.
The life of an Israelite slave
could be so secure
that the slave could choose to remain
with his master for life.
This arrangement is described
at Exodus 21:5, 6, where it says:
“But if the slave should insist and say,
“‘I love my master, my wife, and my sons;
“I do not want to be set free,’
“his master must bring him
before the true God.
“Then he will bring him
up against the door or the doorpost,
“and his master will pierce his ear
through with an awl,
and he will be his slave for life.”
We are like that slave.
Our love for Jehovah
and our appreciation
for the true freedom he gives
are so strong that we give our lives to him.
We identify ourselves as Jehovah’s slaves,
not by getting our ears pierced,
but by dedication and baptism.
When it comes to freedom,
we all must make a choice.
Do we take the broad road
of false freedom
offered by Satan and his world?
Remember, it’s literally a dead-end street.
Or do we take the narrow road
of true freedom?
That road is defined
by God’s righteous standards,
and this is the road
that leads to everlasting life.
Even now, we’ve been freed
from fear of the future
and the superstitious fear of death.
We’ve been freed from the pains
that result from a lifestyle
that ignores God’s standards.
The freedom that Jehovah provides
will eventually give the human family
all of the basic freedoms
that honest-hearted people long for today
—freedom from fear, freedom from crime,
freedom from hunger, from poverty,
pollution, sickness, and war.
May we continue to walk on the road
of true freedom ourselves
and help others to find the true freedom
that only Jehovah can give.