Welcome!
We’re so happy you can join us
for this month’s program.
I’m here with my good friend
and cohost, Leon Weaver.
There he is.
Leon, welcome!
David, I’m delighted to be here with you.
Now, I’d like to tell you
a little something about Leon.
When I was invited into Bethel in 1990,
I was assigned to the Service Department
and Leon was one of the overseers.
Now, in the Service Department,
at times we had to deal
with some very difficult matters
and sometimes you needed advice.
And I could always rely
on Leon to help me out.
I’d go into his office,
he’d set aside whatever it was
he was working on,
he’d listen, and then he’d give his input.
I really appreciated the experience
I acquired in the Service Department,
and Leon was certainly part of it.
So this is one reason why I have love
and respect for that brother.
Now, Leon, what can we look forward to
in this month’s program?
Many years ago,
Elizabeth gave up a prestigious career
to do more for Jehovah.
How did her decision
change the course of her life?
And we’ll debut a fascinating new series.
It will reveal aspects
of our theocratic history
you may not be familiar with.
That sounds very interesting.
Don’t go away!
This is JW Broadcasting® for November 2021.
Through his prophet Isaiah,
Jehovah made a wonderful promise,
one that’s being fulfilled today.
We can read about it at Isaiah 60:17:
“Instead of the copper I will bring in gold,
“and instead of the iron
I will bring in silver,
“instead of the wood, copper,
“and instead of the stones, iron;
“and I will appoint peace as your overseers
and righteousness as your task assigners.”
Well, now, this reference to “overseers”
and “task assigners”
—that sounds like organization, doesn’t it?
So, what is Jehovah telling us?
He’s saying that we can expect
to see organizational arrangements
getting better and better.
Well, if you’ve been associated
with the truth for a while,
I’m sure you’ll agree that Isaiah’s prophecy
is being fulfilled today.
So for this broadcast,
I thought we’d review
some of the improvements
we’ve seen just since World War II.
That’s the period
most of us are familiar with.
Now, some of you will be hearing
about these things for the first time.
Others will have lived through it all,
and for them it’ll bring back fond memories.
So let’s go back.
It’ll be fun!
I call this part
“Do You Remember When . . . ?”
Before World War II
and for a number of years after that,
many congregations
didn’t have a Kingdom Hall of their own.
They were actually encouraged
to meet in private homes
or in rented facilities.
The thinking was that if you
were in a rented facility or a private home,
you had more flexibility.
You could move the meeting place
from one place to the other very easily.
But there were problems; there were drawbacks.
Sometimes the space
would be shared with other organizations.
So you couldn’t leave your
literature, magazines,
speaker’s stand, and maybe even a sound system
in the hall at the end of the meeting.
When the meeting was over,
you’d have to pack it all up
and take it away.
But that’s not all.
Sometimes you had to arrive very early
and clean the place up
after a particularly rowdy group
of people had used it.
And if there were cigar smokers
in that group, you were in trouble.
It was very difficult to air the place out
in time for the meeting.
Now, remember, in those days,
people could smoke in a private hall,
and you could smoke in an airplane
—they could smoke almost anywhere.
So this was a real problem for us.
There were other problems.
Before we had a Kingdom Hall in my hometown,
the congregation met in a rented facility.
Now, in October,
the place was decorated for Halloween,
and in December, there was
a great big Christmas tree on the platform.
We couldn’t move it!
Now, this was in Canada,
and portraits
of the King and Queen of England
as well as the British flag
were permanent fixtures in the hall.
You couldn’t remove
any of it for the meeting.
Yet, to their credit,
many interested persons
attended our meetings.
And to them, it wasn’t
the meeting place that was important;
it was what
they were learning there that counted.
Speaking of our meeting places,
at first, congregations were on their own
when it came to building them.
Now, at times, the most a congregation
could afford was to purchase the land,
and sometimes that land would sit there
for years because it would
take years to get the money together
to build the hall.
And then once they had the money together,
were there enough brothers who could take
the lead in the construction?
Sometimes on a weekend, you’d see
just one or two brothers working away
at the site of the new hall.
You had to love them for their perseverance.
Nowadays,
our Kingdom Hall construction
is supervised by the LDCs,
with lots of qualified volunteers,
and practical Kingdom Halls
can be constructed in a short period of time.
What about the meetings?
For years, the Theocratic Ministry School,
Service Meeting,
Congregation Book Study,
and Watchtower  Study
were all about an hour in length.
So were the public talks
—when we had them.
Now, at first, a public talk
wasn’t scheduled every week.
There’d be a series of four or eight talks,
if you could schedule that many speakers.
And then, for a while,
the congregation wouldn’t have a public talk.
Why was that?
Remember,
the Theocratic Ministry School
didn’t get under way until 1943,
and it took time for the brothers to develop
the skills to deliver an hour talk.
But in time, they were delivering
excellent public talks!
And do you remember
when we had individual handbills
for each public talk
with the name of the speaker printed on them?
Until 1959,
only brothers were enrolled in the school.
For some years, during the first few minutes
of the school there was a roll call,
and the names of all the brothers
enrolled in the school were read out.
Now, when your name was read out,
you were to answer, “Present.”
A few rebels would say, “Here.”
But you were supposed to say, “Present.”
Now, initially,
according to the instructions,
if anyone was deliberately
and habitually absent over a period of time,
he was dropped from the school.
Later, that was discontinued.
Now, the roll-call arrangement
got me into a bit of trouble.
You see, in our congregation
when the roll was being called each week,
I noticed that there
were a few young brothers
who were just a little bit older than I was
who would answer, “Present.”
So one night after the school,
I asked the school servant
if I could have my name read out
at the next meeting.
He warmly commended me.
And sure enough,
I got my name read out the following week.
Everyone congratulated me after the meeting.
I couldn’t understand why.
I only said, “Present.”
The problem was that I didn’t know
that when you got your name read out,
you were agreeing to give a talk.
I thought I was just signing up
to have my name read out.
Well, a couple of months later,
on April 8, 1953,
I delivered my first
eight-minute talk on the theme
“Proclaiming the World’s Doom.”
Now, why an eight-minute talk?
Well, we didn’t have Bible readings yet.
So when you were on the school,
you were giving an eight-minute talk.
Well, today, we make sure
everyone understands what’s involved
in being a student in the midweek meeting.
In 1950,
we received the New World Translation
of the Christian Greek Scriptures  in English,
and we were encouraged
to bring it to the meetings.
So for the Hebrew Scriptures,
you would have the American Standard Version
or the King James Version
—mostly the American Standard Version
because it had Jehovah’s name.
So you’d have two Bibles
to bring to the meeting.
There’s the one for the Hebrew Scriptures
and then the New World Translation
for the Greek Scriptures—two Bibles.
It wasn’t too bad.
But later, the New World Translation
of the Hebrew Scriptures
was released in installments.
So you’d get a volume every year or two.
And as we received each new volume,
we were encouraged
to bring it to the meeting.
Now, in time, those volumes
started to pile up
so that by 1960,
you might have volumes 1 through 5
of the Hebrew Scriptures,
also the Greek Scriptures,
and your regular study aids!
And we had thick study aids in those days.
We had big briefcases
and strong backs in those days.
We were really happy to get
the complete New World Translation
in just one volume in 1961.
Now, let’s say a word about music.
That’s something that’s near
and dear to my heart.
For many years,
it was left up to the local servants
to decide which songs the congregation
would sing at the meetings.
So the chairman of a particular meeting
would select the songs,
but his choice wasn’t always final.
Many Kingdom Halls had a piano
or some other instrument
to accompany the singing.
But often the musician couldn’t play
all of the songs in the book,
so we’d have to sing the songs he could play.
We got to know those few songs really well!
But those humble musicians
did their best to accompany our singing.
Now, as a result of all this,
the words to those songs
we sang nearly 70 years ago
still come readily to mind.
Do you remember the written review?
Maybe you don’t.
Congregations periodically
had a written review of material
that had been covered
in the Theocratic Ministry School
over the previous weeks.
Now, we had a half hour to answer
about 25 questions.
But then, when the half hour was up,
we would write our name on the paper,
hand it in to the school servant,
and he would take
all the papers home to grade them.
Now, if there were 25 questions,
you’d get 4 points apiece
for each correct answer—100 points total.
And then a week later,
he’d return the papers to us at the meeting.
Now, in the early years of the arrangement
(I remember well),
he’d announce the highest
and lowest grade to the congregation.
Now, thankfully, he didn’t mention the names
of the one who got
the highest and lowest score.
Well, later, that arrangement to announce
the highest and lowest grade
was discontinued.
Do you remember when circuit assemblies
began on Friday evening
and continued through Sunday afternoon?
A full program
was presented Saturday afternoon and evening.
There was never a dull moment
on Saturday night.
There were lively demonstrations
that kept our interest
right up to the end of the program.
Sometimes the sets were very elaborate.
For example,
suppose a publisher was demonstrating
a presentation from door to door.
Now, today
we’d just imagine there was a door.
But back then at the circuit assembly,
there might be a frame
with a painted door on the stage,
and maybe even a doorbell
for the publisher to ring.
Now, if the householder
was supposed to be interested,
you knew it
because the house number was 777.
And if the householder
was going to be opposed,
you knew that as well
because the house number would be 666.
Now, on one program that I remember,
the publisher knocks on the door
and a brother dressed as a priest answers.
He puts up a real argument about the Trinity.
Talk about visual aids
—but you never forgot what you saw and heard!
And do you remember when
each congregation had a congregation servant
and up to seven other servants:
the assistant congregation servant,
the Bible study servant,
the accounts servant,
the Watchtower  study servant,
the magazine-territory servant,
the literature servant,
and the Theocratic Ministry School servant?
Now, at that time,
apart from book study conductors,
you couldn’t have more than
eight servants in the congregation.
So unless someone moved,
a young man had no chance
of becoming a servant.
So how could a young man
reach out for more responsibility?
And how would the prophecy recorded
at Micah 5:5 ever be fulfilled?
There Jehovah promised:
“We will raise up against him
seven shepherds,
yes, eight princes of mankind.”
Well, seven represents completeness.
So eight princes—that would indicate
that there would be
more than enough men in the congregations
to provide theocratic direction.
But how could that be
when there was basically
a limit of eight servants per congregation?
The answer came in 1971.
We were thrilled when we understood
that each congregation has a body of elders,
and there is no set number
of elders or ministerial servants.
As many as are qualified can be appointed.
Now, when I was baptized 66 years ago,
you didn’t have to be approved
for baptism by the congregation.
The only questions asked
of baptism candidates
were the two they answered
at the conclusion of the baptism talk.
That led to a few strange situations.
On a few occasions
—much to the surprise of the servants—
someone would rush up
to the front of the hall at the end
of the baptism talk,
answer the two questions,
and get baptized.
Something more was needed
—assurance that the individual
really knew what he was doing
and especially that he was living
in harmony with Scriptural principles.
So in 1967,
questions were provided
so that the responsible brothers
could be assured that each candidate
was truly qualified for baptism.
Those questions have been refined
over the years.
And today, we go over some 60 questions
with baptism candidates.
The copper has turned to gold.
Do you remember when there were
very few pictures in our publications?
And the few that we had
were usually in black and white
or only two colors.
Today, our spiritual food
is served in attractive publications
in full color.
Now, those of us who’ve served
in foreign-language congregations
will also remember
when a new publication in English
might not be available
in another language for several years.
Study articles trailed by several months.
Now, that’s before it became possible
for the branches
to do simultaneous printing.
So here’s how it worked.
Material in English
would be mailed to the branches
by regular mail for translation.
If the translators had a question
about the meaning of a sentence in English,
they would use regular mail
to send their question to headquarters.
In time, headquarters would answer back
by regular mail.
This back and forth
—it could take quite a while.
And in some countries, mail service was poor.
Now, today,
thanks to special computer programs
that our brothers have developed
and the ability to communicate electronically
and some other factors, we’re able to release
most language editions simultaneously
with the English.
What an improvement!
Now, speaking of our literature,
do you realize that it’s been some 31 years
since the decision was made
that in the United States
we’d no longer ask
for a contribution for our literature?
Later, the arrangement
was extended worldwide.
That’s been a real blessing for our brothers!
For example,
when we were asking
for contributions for literature,
some brothers in Africa and other places
couldn’t afford to have a Watchtower
for every member of the family.
They were just too poor.
And what about bound books?
I’ll tell you an experience.
In one African country, a missionary noticed
that a young brother quoted
a wide variety of scriptures
in his comments, and he got curious.
One day, he asked the young brother,
“How did you come to know
so many scriptures?”
The brother replied:
“It’s the Reasoning  book.
I read it every chance I get.”
The missionary asked him, “What do you mean
you read it every chance you get?”
Well, he replied:
“I don’t have a Reasoning  book myself.
“I could never afford one.
“But I know a sister who has one,
“and she lets me borrow it from time to time.
I read it every chance I get.”
Well, you can imagine,
the missionary went out
and bought him a Reasoning  book
and a New World Translation
for good measure.
It was a great investment.
The young brother
was later called into Bethel,
and where do you think he was assigned?
To the literature department.
The brothers knew
that he appreciated the literature so much
that he’d make sure the congregations
had the literature they needed.
Well, looking back,
we can see that the arrangements
back then served a purpose.
They were like fine copper.
We do not look down on them.
Rather, we take the view expressed
at Zechariah 4:10:
“Who has despised the day
of small beginnings?”
Now, as those taking the lead
saw a better way of doing things,
they didn’t hesitate to make adjustments.
That’s very faith-strengthening.
And the best is yet to come!
As I mentioned in the beginning,
this may be the first time that some of you
have heard about these things.
Why not ask someone
who has been in the truth for many years
what it was like
when he was new in the truth?
That could lead
to a very stimulating discussion!
Thank you
for those historical insights, David.
When you think about
how much has changed just in our lifetimes,
you really see how Jehovah
keeps improving his organization.
Next, we have a great example
of someone who has seen all of the changes
we’ve talked about and more: John Mills.
Let’s see how he
has faithfully served Jehovah
through multiple assignments and challenges.
I was raised with three sisters,
and my mom was in the truth.
I remember sitting on the sofa
and just talking about spiritual things
with my mom.
And she taught us to appreciate
any assignment that we had
—to see it as something very special.
Pioneering was my life.
Gilead to me was a way to give to others
—to be very busy in service.
I prayed to Jehovah.
I said, “I really want to go to Gilead
but, if it’s possible, to have a wife too.”
And I just thought, ‘Boy, are you pushy!’
You know, and so—
But Jehovah gave me that.
I went to Gilead.
And to my amazement,
there was the most lovely, spiritual sister,
a student in the same class, Lois.
I met her and was able to marry her
one week after Gilead.
Arriving as a newlywed couple
in a missionary home with seven other people
was quite daunting.
But we didn’t let that faze us;
we were on our honeymoon.
Colombia was a paradise spiritually.
We loved it so much!
This was the kind of life we wanted.
Lois was a great teacher in the ministry.
I always enjoyed working with her;
she was actually a great support for me.
Obviously, Colombia had its risks.
I remember in the mornings,
sometimes it got to the point when
I would look at Lois and she would look
at me and we’d just say,
“If I don’t see you, see you
in the Paradise,” you know?
Colombia became our home.
We traveled the length and breadth
of the country
in our different assignments.
We had been over 20 years in Colombia
when it became very evident
that Lois’s mom would need our care.
This, of course,
would mean leaving our assignment.
It almost tore my heart apart
to leave Colombia.
I felt I was abandoning so many privileges
and my treasured assignment.
In the U.S.A.,
we were working as a team,
and I could see Lois really organized,
making the best of the situation.
Helping her mom
was really the source,
in a way, of her deep joy.
Helping others was just a way of life
to Lois.
It doesn’t matter what privilege you have
and what responsibility;
true happiness
is always found in giving.
Really, Lois got very ill.
Lois never cried about her illness
or felt sorry for herself.
She always was focused on others
and would give of herself, even
within the pain of illness.
Now that Lois has passed,
many times I think of her example,
and it just motivates me to carry on.
Here at the Central America branch
I am surrounded by such a loving family.
I resolved when
I went through this situation
with losing my wife to find others
that were in similar situations
and maybe sit down for a coffee.
Just that fellow feeling
of just being able
to show interest and to encourage
another person is a great joy
that I personally find one
of the most helpful things
to endure trials.
John’s life of faithful service reminds me
of the truth found at 2 Corinthians 1:3, 4:
“[Jehovah] comforts us in all our trials
“so that we may be able to comfort others
“in any sort of trial with the comfort
that we receive from God.”
Have you ever wondered
why we sing at our meetings?
or why we attend conventions,
usually in the summer?
Many who are young in years
or new in the truth
may not be familiar
with certain aspects of our history.
Yet, this rich spiritual history
is your heritage,
and we want you to become acquainted with it.
So the Governing Body
has approved the development of a new series:
Our History in Motion.
Each segment will look at an aspect
of our worship through time,
similar to what David shared with us earlier.
The series will help us see
that our worship is rooted,
not in tradition or custom,
but in the truth found in God’s Word.
Now, for our first episode,
it looks at the history
of singing praises to Jehovah.
It was made in secret,
hidden in the lining of a jacket,
and then smuggled out of the country.
What was it?
A recording
of brothers and sisters in Siberia
singing Kingdom songs.
They sent it from one side
of the earth to the other
to be played at the 1958
international convention in New York
for an audience of more than 250,000 people.
Why is singing so important
to Jehovah’s Witnesses?
Let’s find out in this episode
of Our History in Motion.
Jehovah’s worshippers
have long praised him with song.
But how did singing become
a part of our modern-day worship?
The story begins more than 150 years ago.
The year is about 1869
in Allegheny, Pennsylvania, U.S.A.
Charles Taze Russell
is a young man
searching for Scriptural truth.
One evening he’s walking along
and hears something
—singing coming from a religious meeting
being held in a basement.
He goes in, and what he hears sparks a fire
for Bible study like never before.
Later, Russell and his associates
make music’s role in pure worship clear
as they rediscover Bible truth.
Charles Taze Russell
may have come to appreciate
how the power of music can stir emotions
from a music business
that his father owned for a period of time.
He believed that “the singing of the truth
“is a good way to get it into the heads
and hearts of God’s people.”
The first issue of Zion’s Watch Tower,
published in July of 1879,
announced a songbook
—the first of many to come.
It was called Songs of the Bride.
It contained 144 hymns,
or religious songs of praise.
The Bible Students sang
at their meetings and assemblies.
What was it like to sing
these songs back in the early 1900’s?
Imagine that you’re
at one of Charles Taze Russell’s lectures.
As you walk in,
you’re handed a small sheet of paper.
You look for a seat, but it’s packed.
As the crowd quiets down,
they announce that the meeting
will start with a song and prayer.
In a church,
you expect to find a hymn book in your pew,
but this is a rented hall.
Then you realize
that the paper you were handed
has the song lyrics,
and it also has a place
to leave your name and address
if you’d like a Bible study.
So when the audience
starts to sing, you join in.
What did songs sound like back then?
Let’s listen to a song
we sang for over eight decades.
Here’s a recording from 1916.
That’s a little different than how
our songs sound today.
Compare different versions of this song,
and you’ll notice that the lyrics
and theme changed over the years.
Here’s a version of “All Hail”
by the Watch Tower Male Quartet in 1935.
In our first songbook this song was called
“All Hail the Power of Jesus’ Name,”
which was about, well,
the power of Jesus’ name
with zero mention of Jehovah.
You see, many songs prior to this
were adapted from existing church hymns.
Now here’s the same song in 1950.
Instead of the lyrics
overemphasizing Jesus’ name,
the lyrics refer to “making known God’s will”
and mention Jehovah by name.
Why all the changes?
Because our songs reflect
our current understanding
of Scriptural truth.
As the light gets brighter,
we understand the truth more clearly,
so the songs change.
Our first songbook explained
explained the goal to publish
“songs free from objectionable theology,”
and it’s been the case ever since.
We don’t hold on to songs
for tradition or nostalgia.
We sing them because it’s the truth!
From the 1928 songbook onward,
there was a big shift.
Many songs were written
by our brothers and sisters.
They put more emphasis on Jehovah’s name,
his attributes, and his Kingdom.
You can even tell by the title
Songs of Praise to Jehovah.
Some of the songs might even sound familiar,
like this one.
Are your parents in the truth?
your grandparents?
even your great-grandparents?
If so, they sang the same song as you
at their meetings and assemblies.
That’s a real legacy!
Let’s fast-forward to the 1940’s.
Some of our brothers
were imprisoned for their faith.
The world was at war and needed good news.
So we intensified
our preaching and teaching work.
This is when
the Watchtower Bible School of Gilead
and the Theocratic Ministry School started,
and it’s also when
singing was reintroduced at our meetings.
Wait a minute!
Reintroduced?
That means we stopped singing at meetings.
When?
Find out in the next episode
of Our History in Motion.
Well, that’s a cliff-hanger!
Would you like to know
why we stopped singing for a time?
You’ll want to watch
the second part of this video.
It will be posted soon on jw.org.
And look for future episodes
of Our History in Motion.
Many years ago,
Awake!  magazine
published the story of Elizabeth Balnave.
Elizabeth explains
why she made a major career decision.
How did that decision affect her life?
Let’s find out in this episode
of Where Are They Now?
As a child, I dreamed
of becoming a ballerina.
I trained as a ballet dancer from childhood.
I was taught to give complete obedience
to the artistic director,
absolute loyalty to the dance company,
and to put ballet before everything else
in my life.
I finally realized there’s no way
to get ahead in this world
without compromise.
It just can’t be done.
Such a life is empty and unsatisfying.
The problem is, once you get into that,
you get lulled in by that glamour and glitz.
Now, down the road
when you finally see the trap
and what you got into,
it’s very hard to get out.
And I always tell young people, you know,
that it doesn’t matter how good everything
seems; it doesn’t matter how great.
There’s always a string attached—always.
And then one day,
you’re going to wake up and it’s a rope.
And you can’t cut a rope that easily
—meaning you can’t get out of the situation
once Satan has you trapped in it.
And it happens without you even realizing it.
Ballet is discipline,
and I had to figure out a way
to take that skill
and transfer it into my everyday life.
It took some time,
but I finally figured it out,
because it’s not a waste.
It’s good.
But what I had to learn
was to get out of my comfort zone.
We were in Bethel until 1987.
Jack had a job lined up when we left Bethel,
and that was good.
I couldn’t get a job
because of my physical health issues.
I probably was in bed for about five months.
Eventually, I started feeling better,
and that’s when I realized
how bad the medical bills were getting.
I just dragged myself out of bed
and went and looked for a part-time job.
Obviously, through all of this,
Jack and I just kept praying.
We knew Jehovah would take care of us.
No question about that.
Eventually, I did get a job at a law firm.
It was a good job.
I actually lasted there 30 years.
Absolutely Jehovah blessed me,
and I believe what he was blessing
were my efforts.
I didn’t quit, and I refused to compromise.
When I started seeing
that I was really learning this new skill
and I was getting good at it,
that’s when I sat down and I said:
“Well, Jehovah, I have this new skill.
I want to be able to use it for you.”
One thing led to another, and I became
a commuter Bethelite
for the Legal Department.
I’d say that about 11 years
after I had left Bethel,
I was working and all of a sudden,
I got sick again with the same thing
—complete rapid loss of weight
and all the weakness came back.
I was eventually diagnosed
as having celiac disease.
So once I changed my diet,
I just started getting better and better.
I stayed with the law firm until 2014,
and then my husband and I retired
and moved to another part of the country.
And now, currently,
I’m a remote Bethel consultant.
If you slave for the world,
you really are a slave.
If you slave for Jehovah,
in my opinion, you’re not slaving at all.
You couldn’t have a better partnership
than you and Jehovah,
and that’s how I view it.
And you’re never going to experience
Jehovah to the full
unless you put yourself out there
for him to use.
I’ve had a wonderful life
of extraordinary spiritual privileges.
There’s no career in the world
that is ever going to come close to that.
Wouldn’t you say that resilience
is one of the qualities
that has helped Elizabeth?
What can each of us do
to be more resilient?
Notice three practical suggestions
in this morning worship presented
by Brother Gajus Glockentin.
Mary kept listening to what Jesus was saying.
How commendable!
She set the right priorities
and is a good example for us.
Martha, her sister, however,
received loving correction from Jesus,
as our printed comment puts it.
Now let us, today, put ourselves
in the shoes of Martha for a moment.
She showed great interest in supporting Jesus
by providing him a base during his ministry
in the difficult area of Judea.
Now this time,
Mary and Martha
were probably working together
to prepare things for Jesus.
But after Jesus arrived,
Mary stopped helping as our text indicates.
How did Martha feel about it?
Now she had to care for everything herself.
Can we imagine the tension rising
within Martha’s heart?
The stress level is increased,
and her dear sister
sits and listens to Jesus.
So she asked Jesus to correct Mary,
to order her back to work.
But to her surprise, she, Martha,
received counsel from Jesus.
How would we feel in such a situation?
We are doing something well-intentioned
and, yet, instead of commendation,
we receive counsel.
Maybe our eyes filled with tears.
We feel the pain in our chest.
We might think we can’t breathe anymore.
Did Martha think for a moment,
replying to Jesus, saying:
“This is not fair!
“I am doing everything to support you,
and now this.
“You know, from now on,
I am listening too,
and I am curious to find out
who prepares the meals for you.”
Of course, we don’t know
what Martha thought and said.
But what we do know,
as our printed comment puts it,
she took to heart Jesus’ loving correction.
What can help us
to overcome such a painful moment
and to progress?
The term often used in this connection
is “resilience.”
People who are resilient
are able to recover easily and quickly
from unpleasant and damaging events.
It is like the ability of this piece of metal
to tolerate pressure
and go back to its original form.
Let us, therefore,
look at three factors that make us resilient
and different from those
who easily give up and surrender.
Now, the first factor is facing reality
—facing reality.
Let us, please,
open to Proverbs chapter 28.
The question we are asking ourselves
in a difficult moment is this:
‘Do I truly understand and accept
the reality of my situation?’
Here, at Proverbs 28:26,
it starts by saying:
“Whoever trusts in his own heart
is stupid.”
We might tend to put on emotional blinders
and see only what we want to see.
Many people slip into denial
as a coping mechanism.
However, the Proverb continues
in the second part, saying:
“But the one who walks in wisdom
will escape.”
This means seeing things the way they are.
Facing reality
—really facing reality is grueling work.
Indeed, it can be unpleasant
and often emotionally wrenching.
The apostle Peter had this experience
when Jesus looked at him
after Peter had denied him three times.
Peter faced reality, went outside,
broke down, and wept bitterly.
For sure, he was not looking for any excuses.
This experience, as well as other situations
where he received counsel,
helped him to make progress
and to fulfill his assignments even better.
Now, what is the second factor?
We call it “meaning-making.”
We might know people who
under pressure threw up their hands
and cried and said,
“Why is this happening to me?”
Such people see themselves as victims,
and living through hardship
does not teach them any lessons.
We, however,
based on our Bible knowledge,
understand why difficulties
and challenging situations
are sometimes unavoidable.
Seeing the bigger picture adds meaning.
This helps us, as a resilient person,
not only to endure
an unpleasant situation or a new circumstance
but also to look at seeming obstacles
and see an opportunity in it.
We all know that no one is perfect.
Everyone fails at something sometime.
So our choice
is the manner in which we respond.
We are actively trying
to make the best out of it,
looking ahead rather than behind,
setting goals
—maybe new goals.
We might remember how Brother Harold King
showed this resilient disposition
when he was in solitary confinement.
How did he give meaning
to his difficult situation
by making the best out of it?
He said:
“I arranged
for a program of ‘preaching’ activity.
“But to whom does one preach
when in solitary confinement?
“I decided that I would build up
some appropriate Bible sermons
“from the things I could remember
and then preach to imaginary characters.”
So in our context, we can say
meaning-making is like building a bridge
from present day hardships
to a better future.
By means of this bridge,
we make a difficult situation manageable.
We remove the sense
that the present is overwhelming.
Now let’s look at the third factor:
a balanced view of ourselves.
Well, we said at the beginning
that we have to face reality
which can go along with feelings
of sadness and disappointment.
As resilient people,
we don’t take a failure
or a challenging situation personally.
Let us, please, open to Romans chapter 7,
because we want to demonstrate this point
by means of the example of the apostle Paul.
At times,
he felt discouraged over his weaknesses.
Here in chapter 7,
he describes the pain of conscience
that he suffered
because of feeling captive to sin.
But then in verse 24,
he cries out, saying:
“Miserable man that I am!”
Evidently, though, Paul realized
that his imperfection did not define him.
Nine years later,
in his second letter to his friend Timothy,
shortly before his death,
he stated
his personal conclusion of the matter
here at 2 Timothy 4:7.
He said:
“I have fought the fine fight,
“I have run the race to the finish,
I have observed the faith.”
Paul’s problems and inner struggle
did not miraculously disappear.
Still, it did not prevent him
from accomplishing
remarkable things in Jehovah’s service.
So, therefore, we do not berate ourselves
with self-defeating language,
such as “I’m a failure”
or “I’m useless.”
Reflecting on positive aspects of our lives
and reflecting on our strengths
helps us to maintain
a balanced view of ourselves.
So in conclusion,
the experience of Martha reminded us today
of the importance of building
and maintaining resilience
by facing reality,
meaning-making,
and maintaining a balanced view of ourselves.
The Bible contains wonderful descriptions
of how life will be in Paradise.
As our new music video shows,
visualizing these future blessings
brings joy to our heart.
I close my eyes, and I can see
A world of peace, love, and harmony.
Come with me,
And you’ll see.
You will see.
It’s not a dream, as I’m sure you know.
These things God promised so long ago
Are guaranteed,
Sure to be.
You will see.
Look around—
There’s joy and laughter in ev’ry sound.
Look and see—
This is the way our God meant it to be.
Those who fell asleep along the way,
They live again; we see them ev’ry day.
Come with me,
And you’ll see.
You will see.
The pain and crying there used to be
Has gone forever; now it’s history.
Come with me,
And you’ll see.
You will see.
Look around—
There’s joy and laughter in ev’ry sound.
Look and see—
This is the way our God meant it to be.
Jehovah’s word is enough for me.
With eyes of faith, it’s reality.
As we see
What’s in store,
You can be sure
Until the moon is no more,
When you—
Close your eyes and come with me
To God’s world of peace and harmony.
Come with me,
And you’ll see.
You will see.
What a beautiful song and video!
In our program,
we looked back at theocratic history,
not to be nostalgic, but to remind us
that Jehovah
continually improves his organization,
just as he promised.
We debuted an exciting new series,
Our History in Motion,
and saw the essential role
that singing plays in our worship.
We learned
how Jehovah blesses those
who serve him.
Elizabeth gave up
a glamorous career
but gained spiritual treasures.
And we saw that although John
has experienced many difficulties,
Jehovah has helped him
maintain his joy by helping others.
Before we conclude,
let’s enjoy our video postcard.
This month,
we visit our brothers in Ecuador.
As its name suggests,
Ecuador is situated on earth’s equator.
It stretches from the Galapagos Islands
to the Andes Mountains
and the Amazon River basin.
This is Mount Chimborazo.
Measured from the center of the earth,
it’s the highest point on our planet
because of the bulging
of the earth at its equator.
This train line was carved
into the Andes more than a century ago.
It was used by the first missionaries
who arrived in 1946.
Today, more than 100,000
of Jehovah’s Witnesses
proclaim the good news in Ecuador.
Nearly 300,000 people
attended the Memorial in 2020.
The Chontapunta Quichua Congregation
began as an isolated group.
To support themselves,
our brothers raise flowers
and even pan for gold.
But their zeal is for the ministry.
They go to great lengths
to bear thorough witness in their territory.
Where bridges aren’t available,
they find a way.
They use two boats, named Enoc
and Enoc 2, to reach remote
Quichua-speaking communities.
Remote communities
have poor cellular service.
That doesn’t stop this Bible student.
Look what he does to get a good signal
so he can join meetings and have his study.
To reach those without cellular service,
the brothers use a high-frequency radio
to conduct return visits and Bible studies.
Our brothers have arranged for talks
and the Memorial to be given in Waorani,
an indigenous language
that’s not yet translated.
This little girl, whose family
is part of the congregation,
shares videos with Waorani-speaking children.
She is four years old!
Our dear brothers and sisters
from the Chontapunta Quichua Congregation
in Ecuador
send their love and greetings
to the worldwide brotherhood.
Leon, my friend,
I want to thank you so very much
for helping out with this program.
I really appreciated the help.
And together, we send all of you
our warm Christian love.
From the World Headquarters
of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
this is JW Broadcasting!