Have you ever asked, “How long?”
If you’re enduring
some challenging circumstance right now
—perhaps old age, a serious illness,
or some other pressure—
such a question is very understandable.
Or perhaps you’re in the position
of giving assistance
and trying to encourage a family member
or someone in the congregation
who’s going through
a very difficult time right now,
and perhaps you’ve wondered
about the same question: ‘How long?
How long do we all
have to endure all of this?’
Asking that question puts us in good company.
To cite one example, at Psalm 13:1, 2,
King David asked the question, “How long?”
four times in quick succession.
Maybe you recall: “How long, O Jehovah,
will you forget me?
“Forever?
“How long will you hide your face from me?
“How long will I have anxious concern,
“with grief in my heart each day?
How long will my enemy triumph over me?”
David was a human—a real person
with real problems and real feelings.
Habakkuk was another human just like us
who was plagued with questions,
and he asked the same: “How long?”
How Jehovah responded to Habakkuk
can strengthen our resolve to wait
just a little while longer
on Jehovah, to wait patiently.
Please open your Bible with me
to Habakkuk chapter 1,
and let’s read verses 2 and 3.
And notice the succession
of six emotion-filled questions
—Habakkuk 1:2, 3:
“How long, O Jehovah,
“must I cry for help, but you do not hear?
“How long must I ask for help from violence,
“but you do not intervene?
“Why do you make me witness wrongdoing?
“And why do you tolerate oppression?
“Why are destruction and violence before me?
And why do quarreling and conflict abound?”
Do you think those were good questions?
They were.
Like us, Habakkuk
was living in a very difficult time.
Violence, oppression, injustice were rampant.
Habakkuk was deeply distressed
by the circumstances
that he was experiencing, that he was seeing.
Naturally, he wanted to know
how long it would be
before Jehovah fulfilled
the promise he had already given
to bring judgment
against that wicked system of things.
But how Jehovah responded
to his faithful prophet’s questions
really can strengthen
our confidence in Jehovah.
Notice in chapter 2 and verse 3,
though not obligated to answer,
what did Jehovah tell him?
Habakkuk 2:3:
“For the vision
is yet for its appointed time,
“and it is rushing toward its end,
“and it will not lie.
“Even if it should delay,
keep in expectation of it!
“For it will without fail come true.
It will not be late!”
A beautiful reassurance from Jehovah,
wouldn’t you agree?
Analyze those words.
Notice first that Jehovah assured Habakkuk
that divine judgment was coming.
Jehovah had not changed his stated purpose.
And then Jehovah added that there was
an “appointed [or fixed] time”
for that judgment.
In effect, Jehovah was telling Habakkuk,
‘Habakkuk, the day of judgment
is on my calendar.’
Jehovah then added more.
He said that the judgment was “rushing
toward its end,” or its fulfillment.
“It [would] not lie.”
And as a result of thinking and meditating
on those assurances,
Habakkuk had no reason to be impatient
or to give way to despair.
In fact, instead of criticizing Habakkuk
for those very sincere,
very poignant questions,
Jehovah encouraged Habakkuk:
“Keep in expectation of it!”
Wait eagerly for it.
“It will not be late!”
Well, you know,
it’s one thing to receive encouragement,
but I’m sure you’d agree
that it’s another thing to fully accept it,
to take it to heart and be nourished at heart
by such encouragement.
Did Habakkuk
take Jehovah’s response to heart?
Did it encourage him?
Well, cast your eyes
to chapter 2 and verse 1,
and you’ll notice
that Habakkuk’s communication with Jehovah
did, in fact, calm his heart.
He resolved to keep waiting confidently
and patiently on Jehovah.
Later, in chapter 3 and verse 16,
Habakkuk repeated his resolve when he said
that he would
“quietly wait” for Jehovah’s day.
Well, what does all of this have to do
with you and with me?
Well, we live at a time when Jehovah
has also appointed a fixed day of judgment.
Nearly 2,000 years ago,
the Father already knew
when the end would come, according to Jesus.
At Matthew 24:36,
what had Jehovah already established?
A “day and hour.”
So that means that the day
that you and I eagerly anticipate
is on Jehovah’s calendar.
It’s been there for a long time.
It will come on time, at the right time,
at a time that Jehovah
knows to be the best time.
And isn’t that what we would expect
of our best Friend, Jehovah God;
the God of love; the Great Timekeeper;
“the King of eternity”?
Meditating on the fact
that the day and hour is established
helps us renew our resolve
to keep waiting patiently on Jehovah.
But what if the day seems to be delaying?
Interestingly, there at Habakkuk 2:3,
Jehovah himself
brought up the subject of a delay.
It was Jehovah who said:
“Even if it should delay,
keep in expectation of it!”
Well, how could the end come on time
and yet be delayed?
Well, consider the situation
back in Habakkuk’s day.
It was about 100 years earlier
that the prophet Isaiah had foretold
that Jehovah would use Babylon
to bring a day of judgment.
Now, if you or I were in Habakkuk’s sandals,
how might we have felt?
From our point of view
enduring that wicked system of things,
it may have well seemed
that the day of Jehovah was delaying.
And if Habakkuk felt that way,
then Jehovah’s assurances
surely comforted him.
Again, we noticed that Jehovah
didn’t criticize him
for asking, How long? How long? twice
and, Why? four times.
No.
Jehovah took into consideration
the pain of heart of his friend
and then reassured him.
And do you know what happened 20 years later?
Jehovah’s words were fulfilled.
Jerusalem was destroyed in 607 B.C.E.
So had there really been a delay?
Not at all.
That delay was only a perceived one
in the mind of Habakkuk.
Of course, you and I can look back
through the book of history
and see the bigger picture,
one that Habakkuk
simply could not see fully in his time.
And what do we see now
about that day of judgment
in 607 B.C.E.?
Well, like a piece
in a very detailed but beautiful puzzle,
the destruction of Jerusalem
came right on time
—at the perfect time—
because that was a pivotal date
in the fulfillment of other Bible prophecies,
prophecies that have to do
with our day during the last days.
So while Habakkuk
may have thought that there was a delay,
Jehovah knew better.
What’s the reminder
that nourishes our heart this morning?
Everything linked to Jehovah’s grand purpose
has always been and will always be
in the perfect control
of the Great Timekeeper, Jehovah.
In summary, we could conclude
from our Morning Worship program today
that Habakkuk’s experience
teaches us valuable lessons.
One, Jehovah is not indifferent
to the suffering and the emotional distress
of his servants.
So are you in some emotional distress
or assisting someone else who is?
Don’t be afraid
to keep pouring out your heart to Jehovah,
helping others to do so,
even repeatedly if needed.
Like Habakkuk,
wait patiently for the answers,
the reassurance that Jehovah will provide.
Remember this too about the salvation
that Jehovah has foretold:
His salvation for his people
is not a temporary solution.
It’s not a bandage on a wound.
His solution will completely resolve
any and all trials we may be experiencing.
Once they’re gone, they’re gone for good.
So how reassuring it is—isn’t it?—to know
that today we are one day closer
to the fixed day
that’s on Jehovah’s calendar!
Jehovah’s judgments
by means of his Kingdom will not be late.