Welcome, brothers and sisters.
In this month’s program,
we’ll review who the May 2020 Watchtower
identified as “the king of the north,”
and we’ll learn how knowing this
affects each one of us.
We’ll also see
how perseverance helps us
reach our spiritual goals.
And we’ll debut an exciting new series
made especially for teenagers.
This is JW Broadcasting for May 2021.
My theme is “‘The King of the North’
in the Time of the End.”
In recent years, the Russian government
has persecuted our brothers and sisters
who live in that country.
You’ve heard reports
about the police invading Kingdom Halls
and breaking up meetings.
The government has labeled
Jehovah’s Witnesses
as an “extremist group.”
It has seized our properties
and imprisoned our brothers.
Please watch a brief video
that reviews some of the trials
Jehovah’s people in Russia have faced.
On April 20, 2017,
the Supreme Court
of the Russian Federation criminalized
the activity of Jehovah’s Witnesses.
As of July 4, 2019,
authorities have progressively
seized 131 of the properties
owned by Jehovah’s Witnesses,
with an additional 60 properties
subject to confiscation.
One of the seized properties
was the former
Russia branch complex in Solnechnoye.
At the time of filming,
the Russian authorities continue
their aggressive attack
on Jehovah’s Witnesses.
As of August 17, 2020,
there were 42 Witnesses
who were in pretrial detention
or sentenced to prison,
32 who were under house arrest,
and 169 who were not allowed
to leave their hometown.
All have been charged with organizing,
participating in, or financing the activity
of a so-called “extremist” organization.
At least 380 Witnesses were,
at the time, under investigation
—ranging in age from 19 to 89 years old.
What has this meant
for the individuals affected?
As an example,
on June 3, 2018,
Brother Sergey Klimov was arrested.
Local authorities initiated
criminal charges against him,
placing him
in pretrial detention for two months.
This detention was extended seven times,
separating him from his wife and family
for a year and five months,
before he was finally tried and sentenced.
On November 5, 2019,
he was sentenced to six years in prison.
Two of our dear young people in Russia,
Brother Yegor Baranov
and Sister Darya Dulova,
are courageously facing criminal conviction
and potential long-term imprisonment.
Brother Baranov is only 19 years old.
When the authorities raided her home,
Sister Dulova was only 18 years old.
By means of the Newsroom on jw.org,
we are informed of updated news events.
This page includes links to name lists
of Witnesses
currently imprisoned for their faith,
which can help us include
them specifically in our prayers.
Our brothers and sisters in Russia
are resolved to remain loyal to Jehovah
despite any opposition,
and they put their confidence
in him in the assurance
that Jehovah is on their side!
It shouldn’t surprise us
that this powerful government
has been persecuting
our peaceful,
law-abiding brothers and sisters.
Why not?
Because that government
is fulfilling Bible prophecy!
Please find Daniel chapter 11.
In verse 40, it refers
to what the Bible calls
“the king of the north.”
Of that “king,” Daniel 11:41 says:
“He will also enter
into the land of the Decoration,
and many lands will be made to stumble.”
Today, Russia and its allies
are filling the role
of the king of the north.
Daniel foretold that this king would enter
“the land of the Decoration,”
meaning that he would interfere
in a significant way
with the activities of God’s people.
As discussed in the May 2020 Watchtower,
Russia and its allies
are not the first political power
to act as the king of the north,
but they may well be the last.
In this program, we will do three things:
First,
we’ll briefly trace
the fulfillment of the prophecy
recorded in Daniel chapter 11.
Second, we’ll look at how that prophecy
is being fulfilled today.
And third, we’ll discuss
how knowing this information
should affect the decisions that we make.
Brother Herman van Selm,
a helper to the Writing Committee,
will help us review
some of the key points of the prophecy
recorded in Daniel chapter 11.
Thank you, Herman,
for helping me with this presentation.
It’s a pleasure to be with you, Ken.
Thank you for inviting me.
First, let’s briefly trace
how the prophecy has been fulfilled so far.
The prophecy in Daniel chapter 11 mentions
“the king of the north”
and “the king of the south.”
Now, why are they described like that?
Well, initially,
these powers were located north and south
of the literal land of Israel,
thus the names king of the north
and king of the south.
These powers could be viewed as two thrones.
Over time, those thrones have been occupied
by various political powers
and these rival kings compete
for world domination.
And what about Jehovah’s people?
They are right at the center
of this conflict.
But let’s start at the beginning.
Ken,
what is the origin
of the kings of the north and of the south?
The kings of the north and of the south
both rose from the empire
established by Alexander the Great.
One line of kings ruled over Egypt,
which is south of Israel.
And that dynasty was the first
to fill the role of king of the south.
During this period, another line of kings
ruled an area north of Israel
and those kings filled the role
of king of the north.
Then the Roman Empire took over
as king of the north.
As discussed in the May 2020 Watchtower,
God’s people are the focal point
of the prophecy
recorded in Daniel chapter 11.
The angel who spoke with Daniel
said that the prophecy
would help him
“understand what will befall your people”
—that is, the nation of Israel.
And what, in fact, happened?
Well, the Jewish nation
was God’s people until 33 C.E.
But after that, a change occurred.
Jehovah poured out his holy spirit
on Christ’s followers.
And from then on,
the congregation of true Christians
became God’s people.
Galatians 6:16 refers to them
as “the Israel of God.”
That point is significant
because the kings of the north and south
can only be identified
when there is a clearly defined group
of God’s people on earth.
Why is that the case?
Because, as we just considered,
the angel had told Daniel
that the prophecy centers on God’s people.
In the second century C.E.,
true Christians were overgrown
by weedlike false Christians.
In his illustration
of the wheat and the weeds,
Jesus foretold that this would happen.
That illustration is recorded
at Matthew 13:36-43.
So from the second century onward,
we can no longer identify
an organized group of true Christians.
And, as we considered, for that same reason,
we also cannot identify
the king of the north
and the king of the south.
But in the 1870’s, a group of Bible students
began to separate itself
from false Christians.
This group,
which included Charles T. Russell,
rejected teachings
that were not based on the Bible.
And like the first-century Christians,
they promoted the truths
taught in God’s Word.
Now this group underwent a development
that is foretold at Malachi 3:1.
They were the “messenger”
who would “clear up a way” before Jehovah.
And as events that followed prove,
this group clearly had God’s backing.
So from the 1870’s onward,
when true Christians began
to organize themselves as a group,
we can again identify the political powers
that fill the roles of the king of the north
and king of the south.
At that time in history,
Britain was the dominant political force
and it filled the role
of the king of the south.
Amazingly, it was also in the 1870’s
that the German Empire emerged
and soon began to challenge Britain
for world domination.
This political power now filled the role
of the king of the north.
Daniel 11:25, 26 indicate
that the two kings would clash
and that the king of the north
would lose many soldiers in the battle.
And that is exactly what happened
during World War I.
And it was during that war
that Britain and its close ally,
the United States,
forged a special bond.
So from this point on,
during these last days,
the Anglo-American power
has been the king of the south.
That brings us to our second point:
How has Daniel chapter 11 been fulfilled
from that time onward
until recent times?
During World War I,
the king of the north
and the king of the south
persecuted those of God’s people
who refused to fight in the war.
The king of the south even threw into jail
those who were taking the lead
in the preaching work.
But let’s take a closer look
at the king of the north.
Has the political power filling that role
changed during the last days?
And how has it treated God’s people?
The identity of the king of the north
has changed three times during the last days.
Starting in the 1870’s
through to the end of the second world war,
the German Empire
filled the role of the king of the north.
In the period leading up to
and including World War II,
it persecuted God’s people without mercy,
imprisoning thousands of our brothers
and killing hundreds of them.
Who replaced the German Empire
as the king of the north?
That’s an important question, Herman.
After World War II,
the Soviet Union took on that role.
It also attacked God’s people,
imprisoning them or sending them into exile.
But, Ken, Daniel 11:34 says
that they—that is, God’s people—
would be “given a little help.”
What’s the significance of that statement?
This passage points forward to the time
when the Soviet Union collapsed.
Although God’s people suffered terribly
under that government,
they were “given a little help.”
In what way?
After the USSR collapsed,
God’s people there could worship freely
for a number of years.
In time, though, Russia and its allies
took on the role of the king of the north.
And like the other powers
that filled the role of king of the north,
this government has continued to oppress
God’s people.
Let’s watch the following video
that outlines what has happened.
Daniel received a prophecy
about the coming of two rivals:
“the king of the north”
and “the king of the south.”
How has it been fulfilled?
In the late 1800’s, the German Empire
became the king of the north.
That government brought
its “power and . . . heart
“against the king of the south
with a large army.”
In fact, its navy was
the second largest on earth.
Who became the king of the south?
The alliance between Britain
and the United States.
He fought during World War I
“with an exceedingly large
and mighty army.”
He “swept away” and “humbled”
the king of the north.
But that was not the end
of the king of the north.
He turned his attention to and then hurled
“denunciations against the holy covenant.”
He removed “the constant feature”
by limiting the freedom of God’s people
to preach,
imprisoning many,
and even killing hundreds
of God’s anointed ones
and their fellow workers.
After Germany was defeated in World War II,
the Soviet Union
became the king of the north.
It worked with the king of the south
to “put in place the disgusting thing
that causes desolation”
—the United Nations.
Beginning in the early 1900’s,
the Soviet government tried to eliminate
religion in the lands under its control,
fulfilling the words
that he would “show no regard
for the God of his fathers.”
He gave glory, not to the God of heaven,
but “to the god of fortresses.”
As prophesied,
he used this military might
against the king of the south
by engaging “with him in a pushing.”
Anglo-America competed
with the Soviet Union
for world domination,
fighting in and supporting wars
and political struggles around the globe.
After the Soviet Union collapsed in 1991,
it was unclear who would fill the role
of the king of the north.
For a time, God’s people there
had been able to preach
and worship peacefully.
But in recent years, Russia and its allies
have pushed back at the king of the south.
Both kings have accused each other
of destructive cyber and economic attacks.
But the king of the north has not limited
his attacks to the king of the south.
As foretold, he also entered
“into the land of the Decoration”
—our realm of spiritual activity.
Today, Russian authorities continue
to attack true worship.
We expect such persecution,
but we also expect it to end.
Our King, Jesus Christ,
is more powerful than any human government.
Soon he will destroy
not only the kings of the north and the south
but all of his enemies,
and he will deliver God’s loyal people.
That was a powerful and touching video!
How are our brothers and sisters coping
with the current persecution?
Let’s take a look.
And what you’re going to see
will break your heart
but also strengthen your faith.
At 6:00 a.m.,
my husband and I were woken up
by a loud bang on the door.
As soon as my husband had opened the door,
people burst in shouting,
“Everyone on the floor!”
I saw them taking my husband into the kitchen
and heard them
very aggressively
ordering him to do something.
Then I heard some noise, and I realized
that he was being beaten.
My husband, Feliks, and I
were on our way back from the shopping mall
to the car park.
A jeep with tinted windows
blocked our path, and people
with weapons
jumped out, shouting:
“On the ground!
Don’t move!”
We were thrown against the vehicle.
Feliks was sent
to a pretrial detention facility,
where he spent a year.
From the very first bang on the door,
I began praying to Jehovah
for wisdom, calmness,
and for holy spirit
so that I could make the right decisions
and act in the right way.
And for the whole day, I was praying.
Jehovah answered all my prayers,
and I felt that he was close at my side.
Before each court hearing
when I was very afraid
and felt overwhelmed by emotion
and couldn’t calm myself down,
it was prayer
that helped me to settle down.
When they took us for interrogation,
I started panicking and, at that moment,
I realized that I needed
to meditate on something positive.
So I thought,
‘I need to sing our songs.’
And just one song came into my mind:
“He Will Make You Strong.”
It really strengthened me.
Those words
about how Jehovah gave his Son for us
show he loves us and will never leave us.
Brothers and sisters
pray and tell me
that they are praying for me.
It gives me the feeling that I am part
of a large family.
After the interrogation,
he was sent home.
My husband and I
continue to stick to our spiritual routine.
We continue to conduct family worship,
and we are always in the ministry.
Our brothers and sisters
constantly support us.
They write kind words;
they commend us;
they send us
encouraging scriptures from the Bible.
In September 2019, Feliks was found guilty
and sentenced to three years
in a general regime colony.
When he and the other brothers arrived there,
they were beaten up by officers
from the colony.
Feliks told me
that he prayed
while he was being beaten,
and he noticed that at that moment,
he stopped feeling the pain.
While he is behind bars,
Feliks tries to conduct
family worship with me by letters.
He picks certain themes
and some specific questions.
Then I do research
in the publications
and send back what I find.
The scripture at Isaiah chapter 30
really strengthens me,
where it says that “your strength will be
in keeping calm and showing trust.”
Although I tend to worry,
I understand that calmness is expressed
by fully trusting in Jehovah.
I have become stronger
because thanks to Jehovah,
in a way, I have developed almost a shell
against the difficulties
that used to scare me.
That confidence and faith help me.
Jehovah was with me,
and he will remain
close by me,
and we will be made stronger thanks to him,
and we will get through these trials.
How can we develop courage
like our brothers and sisters in Russia?
Well, we must be convinced
that the prophecies in the Bible
are trustworthy.
That was a topic discussed
by Brother David Splane of the Governing Body
in the following Morning Worship program.
Now, if you’d just
take a look at today’s text,
it says: “Come and witness
the activities of Jehovah”—witness.
Now, according to a dictionary,
a witness is someone
who has personal knowledge of something.
So how can we be Witnesses of Jehovah?
What personal knowledge
do we have of his activities?
Well, first of all,
we can testify to the fact
that Jehovah can see into the future.
And when he does that,
he is right 100 percent of the time.
And second, we know that no one can prevent
what Jehovah foresees from coming true.
All of Jehovah’s prophecies come true.
Now, to illustrate the first point,
that Jehovah can see into the future,
let’s consider two remarkable prophecies
concerning the destruction
of Jerusalem and its temple.
Now, we know that
through the prophet Jeremiah,
Jehovah foretold
that Jerusalem and the temple
would be destroyed by the Babylonians.
Did it come true?
Absolutely—in 607 B.C.E.
But Jehovah went further.
He said that Jerusalem would be rebuilt.
“They will rebuild the ancient ruins;
“they will raise up
the desolated places of the past,
and they will restore the devastated cities.”
And true worship would also be restored.
So that was quite a level of knowledge.
But there’s more.
Jehovah went further.
Jehovah also indicated
that the spiritual revival wouldn’t last.
Now, that is remarkable.
And it’s implied by what we read
in the second part
of Daniel 9:26.
I’d like you to have a look at this.
We’re going to be reading
two parts of this verse,
and it’s quite interesting
—Daniel 9:26.
So now, what’s our objective here?
It’s to see that Jerusalem and its temple
would be destroyed a second time
and that true worship would not last.
It says in the second part of verse 26:
“And the people of a leader who is coming
will destroy the city and the holy place.”
Now, when these words were written,
Jerusalem and the temple
were already in ruins.
But Jehovah doesn’t say,
‘Nebuchadnezzar has destroyed
the city and its temple.’
He says:
“The people of a leader who is coming.”
The Roman general Titus in 70 C.E.
“will destroy the city and the holy place.”
In order for that prophecy to be fulfilled,
Jerusalem and the temple
would have to be rebuilt
and then destroyed a second time.
Now, that is quite a level of knowledge
—quite a level of information.
But what would make this necessary?
Why, when the Jews
came back to the Promised Land
and they were intent
on restoring true worship,
why would this fail?
And why would Jerusalem and the temple
be destroyed a second time?
Part of it is due to what we find
in the first part of verse 26:
“Messiah will be cut off.”
So Jehovah foretold, foresaw,
that when the Messiah came,
the Jews would reject him.
He would be cut off.
And because of that, partly because of that,
Jerusalem and the temple would be destroyed,
as it happens, in 70 C.E.
Now, wait a minute, wait a minute.
Let’s think about that a minute.
The Messiah comes first
and Jerusalem and the temple
are destroyed after that in 70 C.E.
What does that mean?
It means that the Messiah
comes before 70 C.E.
So we might ask our Jewish friends,
why are you still waiting for the Messiah?
70 C.E. has come and gone.
Well, the Messiah came,
and he too proved to be a true prophet.
And a remarkable prophecy of Jesus
is found in the Sermon on the Mount.
Let’s have a look at it and consider
the implications of this prophecy.
This is Matthew chapter 7,
and we’ll read verses 22 and 23,
an amazing prophecy.
Now, imagine: At this point, Jesus’ teachings
have not spread beyond Israel.
But notice verses 22 and 23:
“Many will say to me on that day:
“‘Lord, Lord,
did we not prophesy in your name,
“‘and expel demons in your name,
“and perform many powerful works
in your name?’
“And then I will declare to them:
‘I never knew you!
Get away from me,
you workers of lawlessness!’”
Now, isn’t that amazing?
If Jesus had simply predicted
that his teachings would spread
throughout the earth,
you might say, “Well, there’s
nothing remarkable about that.”
But Jesus is saying something different.
Jesus is foretelling
a great apostasy from his teachings.
Jesus is foretelling the birth of Christendom
300 years before the event.
So Jesus foresees that many
are going to turn away from the truth.
And by the end of the first century,
that apostasy was already at work, wasn’t it?
There were sects
—the sect of Nicolaus,
for example, and other sects.
And now they’re on the cusp
of the great darkness,
the great apostasy, that’s going to set in
from the second century on.
And with this in mind, what does Jehovah do?
He makes an amazing statement
—Revelation 14—
‘144,00 will be on Mount Zion with the Lamb.’
There were nowhere near 144,000
in the truth in the first century.
And here Jehovah is saying
there are going to be 144,000 in heaven
with the Lamb at the end.
But not only that, he goes further.
There’s going to be
a ‘great crowd that no man can number.’
How could that ever come true?
Ours is the God of true prophecy.
Well, that’s prophecy.
What about the second point?
And that is that no one
can prevent prophecy from being fulfilled.
The Devil would love
to prevent that from taking place.
Think about Revelation 14.
If the Devil could make the number
one short of 144,000,
he’d be happy because he would show
that Jehovah was inaccurate
in what he foretold.
And so that’s one
of the reasons why the Devil
has made war on the remnant
of the seed of the woman,
if at all possible, to prevent that number
of 144,000 from coming to pass.
But, of course, he’s going to fail.
And what about the prophecy in the Bible
that America and Britain
would become a dual world power?
Now, Britain wouldn’t become a world power
at all if France
had anything to say about it.
France and Britain were sworn enemies.
And for many, many, years,
France was much richer
and much more powerful
than Britain was.
And finally,
at the Battle of Waterloo in 1815,
France had one last chance
to prevent Britain
from becoming a world power.
And France should have won that battle.
Everything was stacked against the British.
But there was a driving rain,
a fatal miscalculation
on the part of Napoleon,
and a few other factors
that foiled their attempt.
And Britain did become a world power.
And at the end of the 19th century,
it’s quite true that the sun
never set on the British Empire.
But now, America and Britain
were supposed to become a dual world power,
and Britain wasn’t the least bit interested
in sharing its power with America.
It tried to prevent America
from separating as a colony.
There was a long war,
and there were mistakes made on both sides.
But finally, America gained
its independence from Britain.
Well, what do we find?
Some years after that,
Britain is sharing its power with America.
They are a dual world power.
Fighters against God will never prevail.
We serve “the God of true prophecy.”
And “what he foretells comes to be.”
As we’ve discussed,
each detail of the prophecy
recorded at Daniel chapter 11
has come true so far.
We must have confidence
that the remaining events
described in that prophecy
will also come true.
We are living in the last days
of the time of the end.
Soon, the nations will fulfill the prophecy
at 1 Thessalonians 5:3:
“Whenever it is that they are saying,
“‘Peace and security!’
“then sudden destruction
is to be instantly on them,
“just like birth pains on a pregnant woman,
and they will by no means escape.”
Then “sudden destruction”
comes upon all parts of Satan’s system.
As you can see on the screen,
Daniel 12:1 says:
“During that time Michael will stand up,
“the great prince who is standing
in behalf of your people.
“And there will occur a time of distress
such as has not occurred
“since there came to be a nation
until that time.
“And during that time
your people will escape,
everyone who is found written down
in the book.”
That leads us into our third point:
How should knowing the information
that we have just discussed
affect the decisions that we make?
Well, what we have reviewed
is not just interesting history;
it’s a dramatic prelude
to what will soon happen here on earth.
Jehovah has given his people this knowledge
so that we can act on it.
It should influence the choices we make.
In the following dramatization,
notice how one young brother makes decisions
based on his understanding
of Daniel’s prophecy.
That was my best friend, Lucas,
when we were kids.
And that was me, Oscar.
We knew exactly what we wanted to do
when we grew up:
Pioneer!
Go to Bethel!
Build Kingdom Halls!
We kept those goals.
And when graduation came,
we were ready.
Our little business needed
just a few more accounts.
Then we’d have enough for us
and to help our families.
Finally!
Day one of the service year
—and two new pioneers!
Where we live, . . .
Please don’t call me ever again!
. . . finding spiritual interest is tough.
We already have cleaners.
Thanks.
And finding enough work
was harder than we thought.
A few months in,
I was sure
Jehovah would help
if we just stuck it out.
Sorry, Oscar.
Can’t make it today.
Something came up.
Lucas.
What came up
was an opportunity for more money,
but at what cost?
Are you quitting, or what?
No, I’m not quitting.
Pioneering or our business?
Neither, but you know the struggle here.
Most brothers can afford
to pioneer for a year, two tops.
Look, it’s not full-time while I’m training.
It’s a backup plan.
So Lucas stopped pioneering?
Maybe he’s right.
He’s just being practical.
I mean, is it wrong to quit
if you think it’s not working?
I struggled with the same question
when I pioneered.
Whatever you decide,
if you can tell Jehovah your reason
with a clean conscience,
then it’s the right decision for you.
Why would I keep going
when it’s so difficult?
“Since all these things
are to be dissolved in this way,
“consider what sort of people
you ought to be
in holy acts of conduct
and deeds of godly devotion.”
It really is “the last days,”
and people need “the good news.”
And they’ll only hear it
if we keep up our “deeds of godly devotion”
as best we can.
I prayed to endure and only stop pioneering
if my circumstances left no other choice.
And I prayed to see the blessings.
And after a while,
I learned that a little perseverance,
with Jehovah’s spirit, can be contagious.
So, what do you want to do
when you grow up?
Pioneer.
And go to Bethel?
Yep!
And then maybe build Kingdom Halls.
You in?
Yeah.
That young brother was trying to figure out
what to do with his life.
He made a good decision
because he allowed Bible prophecy
to influence his thinking.
We know that teens everywhere
face many challenges, and we feel for you.
Of course, I was once a teenager,
but I can’t even imagine
some of the situations
that you find yourselves in.
But the Governing Body loves you,
and we want to help.
So I’m very happy to announce a new series
—“My Teen Life.”
You’ll hear from Witnesses
who share the challenges
they faced in their teens
and how they overcame them
with Jehovah’s help.
The interviews are candid;
the issues are real.
Here’s the first episode.
Well, when I was a teenager,
I didn’t see any benefit
in talking to my parents
because they
liked different things than I liked.
So I thought, ‘Well, what’s the point?’
And I also wanted to be an adult.
I wanted to feel like an adult
and be treated like an adult.
I remember when my mom
used to pick me up from school.
She wanted to show personal interest in me,
so she’d ask me:
“Oh, how are your friends doing?
“How was school today?
Do you have a lot of homework?”
But I just thought that she was being nosy.
I always had my earphones on.
And whenever my parents
were trying to talk to me,
that was my chance
to just pop them in and ignore them.
The way my parents grew up wasn’t
the same way that I grew up.
They grew up in a different country;
they spoke a different language;
they grew up in a different time.
When you’re talking to somebody
who doesn’t speak your language natively,
oftentimes you won’t be able
to explain things from your heart.
And so I had that challenge.
I wasn’t able to talk directly
to my parents heart to heart.
And so there was always this frustration
in trying to really convey how I felt.
And I felt like I
wasn’t really getting through to my parents.
When I went to my first pioneer school,
I learned a lot about Jehovah’s qualities.
And one of them was
how he was a very approachable Person.
And I thought to myself,
‘Am I an approachable person?’
And I thought about how
I acted in the ministry
and then at the meetings and then at home.
And I realized that at home
I had a lot of things I needed to fix.
I felt like it was two different worlds
I was living in.
One was when I was at school with my peers;
I felt like I was understood.
And at home,
I kind of just withdrew to myself.
I wouldn’t try to communicate with them
because it didn’t seem worth the effort.
I tried to figure out problems in my own way.
It was kind of trial and error.
I developed a lot of bad habits
that today I’m still trying to overcome.
If I’d been able
to communicate with them more,
if I’d been able to connect
with them and ask for their help
and get their support
and have them on my team,
things would have gone a lot better.
And I really wish I had.
Jesus, who was a perfect human being
and who had perfect judgment,
didn’t make decisions on his own.
He always looked to his Father for guidance.
And that got me thinking,
‘Well, if Jesus did that,
‘there has to be something good
in it for me too.’
What really helped me was Colossians 4:6.
I knew I needed to speak
more graciously in the family.
And I realized
that I was speaking very defensively
and that I needed
to be more approachable to my parents.
When I first tried to talk with them,
of course,
it was awkward and I didn’t want to talk
about anything personal
because I wasn’t used to it.
So I thought I could maybe
ask them about themselves
—ask them how their day was
or what they liked from the meetings.
So I just tried to show more interest in them
instead of focusing on myself.
And I think that’s what got
the conversations going
and got me comfortable
to really talk with them.
I was so focused on how my parents
weren’t understanding me
that I wasn’t really trying
to understand them.
When I thought about my parents,
I thought about how much work
it takes to be a parent.
From when I was a baby, for many years,
they were working day and night
to try to care for me.
They never demanded a thank you
or anything from me.
They were really self-sacrificing.
And I imagined:
‘If I had to work that much for somebody,
‘how would I feel if they
didn’t really say thank you?
‘Or how would I feel
‘if this person whom I worked so hard for
didn’t really view me as their friend?’
Later on, as I got older and started
that communication going with my parents,
I realized that taking their advice
and really listening to their opinions
and always letting them know
what I’m going to do
and where I’m going to go
was a mature thing to do.
Our heart oftentimes
takes the driver’s seat, and it directs us
to where it thinks it should go.
And oftentimes it goes
in the wrong direction,
and we sometimes get hurt.
Then we look back and say,
“I wish I hadn’t done that.”
And our parents have been there.
What they’re trying to do
for us now is to tell us,
“Don’t let your heart
take the driver’s seat.”
If I could talk to my teenage self,
I would tell myself to see
my mom and dad more like coaches,
because I used to think
they were always trying to criticize me
and point out my faults.
But, really, they’re just trying to help me,
and they want me to have a happy life.
I really wish I knew that as a teenager.
But I’m glad I learned that now.
We hope that you’ll enjoy and benefit
from future episodes of “My Teen Life.”
This new series is another way
the Governing Body prepares Jehovah’s people
to cope with today’s challenges
and to be ready for what’s coming.
Bible prophecy shows that in the near future,
the nations will turn
on all false religions and wipe them out.
Then, they will launch
a final attack on God’s people.
And what a mistake that will be!
As discussed in the Pure Worship book,
Jehovah will respond to that attack
by unleashing his rage on the nations.
After the dust of Armageddon settles,
those with the earthly hope can look forward
to a thousand years
of genuine peace and security,
working under the rule of God’s Kingdom.
Before that time comes,
we will continue to face
trials and opposition,
but we can endure.
We have many modern-day examples
that we can imitate right now.
Those examples can help all of us
to be prepared, to stand firm,
and to remain fully united in the faith.
This month’s original song
entitled “One United People”
encourages us to do just that.
We watch the storm clouds gather.
We’ve seen the signs before.
The wind of persecution
Is no stranger to our door.
We will face each test with courage,
With Jehovah standing near.
And ‘no weapon formed against us’
Will give any cause for fear.
We are
one united people,
Though we come
from ev’ry land.
We are
standing firm together,
For Jehovah
makes us stand,
makes us stand.
We wait with calm assurance
For Jehovah, the Most High—
The God of our salvation
Whose love will never die.
He will never leave his people,
And his spirit makes us strong.
No, our enemies won’t break us.
To Jehovah we belong!
We are
one united people,
Though we come
from ev’ry land.
We are
standing firm together,
For Jehovah
makes us stand.
We stand firm together;
Unafraid we face the crowd.
And these hearts that beat within us
We have given to our God.
We are
one united people,
Though we come
from ev’ry land.
We are
standing firm together,
For Jehovah
makes us stand,
makes us stand.
The stirring theme of this year’s convention
is “Powerful By Faith!”
We will learn what faith is,
why it is essential,
and how we can acquire it.
Here is a preview.
It can be hard to put faith
in something you cannot see.
But real faith is not blind.
Real faith is based on facts,
on realities,
on truth.
It gives us courage and strength,
and it helps us to endure.
When life gets hard, it provides peace.
It reminds us of our purpose,
and it brings us real joy.
Learn how to build and strengthen your faith
at the 2021 “Powerful by Faith!”
Convention of Jehovah’s Witnesses.
Now it’s time for our video postcard,
which comes to us
from our brothers and sisters in Belarus.
Belarus is an Eastern European nation
that borders Russia.
It’s known as
the “blue-eyed” country
because it is dotted
with more than 10,000 lakes.
Some of Europe’s
most ancient trees, as well as
its largest mammal
—the European bison—
can be found here.
Castles, some dating
from the 16th century, are popular sites.
This is Nesvizh Castle.
If you look up at the ceiling of its chapel,
you’ll see Jehovah’s name
in the form of the Tetragrammaton.
When Belarus was part of the Soviet Union,
Jehovah’s Witnesses
faced strong government opposition.
Some of our brothers
were exiled to far-away Siberia.
Today, more than 6,000 publishers
in 84 congregations
boldly declare the good news
in Belarus.
There is a zealous pioneer spirit here.
Twenty percent of the publishers
are in full-time service.
This is how our brothers share the good news
in the city of Brest.
They enjoy many aspects
of public witnessing.
Here are our brothers and sisters
in the city of Kobryn.
Their territory includes
both urban and rural areas.
The 78 publishers here conduct an average
of 74 Bible studies each month.
Our brothers and sisters in Belarus
send you their warm love and greetings.
Herman, it’s been a pleasure
reviewing this exciting material
about the “king of the north” with you.
Thank you, Ken.
This information is so important.
It helps all of us
to face the future with confidence.
Before we say goodbye,
we have a treat for you.
Here’s a preview of the video drama
from this year’s convention.
Please enjoy.
You will receive training
in the house of the great King Nebuchadnezzar.
Wait!
Daniel!
Be strong, my son.
This is a new land with new laws.
Soon they’ll want us to worship their gods.
Jehovah is in Israel.
We’re in Babylon now.
What’s going to happen to us?
He had a dream,
and no one can tell him what it is.
Everyone is to be executed by dawn.
We have until morning.
To do what?
It’s Jerusalem.
They burned down Jehovah’s house!
As long as Jehovah exists,
we have hope.
Interpretations belong to my God, Jehovah.
He knows your dream and what it means.
Where is your God?
Kill them!
O Jehovah,
surely you didn’t bring us here to die.
Please, vindicate yourself.
As we’ve discussed in our program,
Daniel played an important role
as Jehovah’s prophet.
And as we’ll see in our video drama,
there’s much we can learn
from his life and example.
And now, before we sign off,
we have a special musical gift video
that closely relates
to our monthly program theme.
You will be encouraged and inspired.
Please keep our brothers
in Russia in your prayers.
Learn from their example
of faith and courage.
See these events for what they are
—the fulfillment of Bible prophecy.
Let this knowledge
move you to make wise decisions.
Stay faithful, and stay busy
as the end of this system draws close.
From the World Headquarters
of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
this is JW Broadcasting.