Now, if we think about Jesus’ words
in today’s text,
“give us today our bread for this day,”
there’s really indirect counsel
against materialism.
See, Jesus didn’t say to pray
for our daily meat
or some other luxury food item.
He didn’t even say that we should pray
for a month’s supply of bread
but to ‘pray for and be content
with our bread for the day.’
But, as we know,
a sizable number of Jehovah’s people today
are being distracted by materialism.
So since this is not an imagined
but a real danger to Jehovah’s people,
let’s discuss the theme
“Beware of the Power of Materialism.”
I recall the story
of a sister and her two sons
who were exiled to Siberia.
Now, they were very poor.
In fact,
they were so poor that at times
they had to literally eat
the bark off trees to survive.
But they were happy
because they were all in the truth.
But years passed,
and the three of them had an opportunity
to immigrate to the United States.
The two sons got excellent jobs
—high paying jobs as machinists—
but in their material prosperity,
both sons fell out of the truth.
The sister tearfully remarked,
“I would rather be back in Siberia
“eating the bark off trees to survive
but with my two sons still in the truth.”
Well, numerous other experiences
could be related
that illustrate the power of materialism.
In fact, it may well be
that Satan’s most effective trap
against Jehovah’s people in these last days
is materialism.
But now, you might be thinking,
‘Well, isn’t sexual immorality
by far the number one cause
for disfellowshipping?’
That’s true, but we don’t have figures
for ones who fall away to materialism.
They’re not disfellowshipped.
And furthermore,
how many who succumb to sexual immorality
were first weakened spiritually
by materialism?
Well, at least we can say that materialism
is one of Satan’s most effective tools,
or traps,
against Jehovah’s people today.
And it’s no wonder
that humans in Satan’s world
are bombarded
with so many advertising messages
designed to make us want things,
even if we don’t need these things.
There was an Awake!  magazine a while back
that discussed how Americans
may be bombarded
with up to 1,600 advertising messages
every day.
Imagine that!
And none of us can feel we’re immune
to this pressure
—that it can’t happen to us.
It could happen to any of us.
We could slowly, gradually,
begin to desire material things
—even things we don’t really need.
In fact, that makes me think of the story
a circuit overseer told many years ago.
I was a young teenager.
That was over 50 years ago.
He and his wife lived in a little trailer
they would park by the Kingdom Hall.
And he said in one of his talks
how he bought a drill
to do work on his trailer.
But then shortly after he bought this drill,
they came out with a reversible drill.
And he thought:
‘Well, you know,
‘that would be nice
to have a reversible drill.
It would be much easier
to extract the drill bit out of the hole.’
So he bought a reversible drill.
Shortly after that,
they came out with a reversible drill
that had a little light on it.
You’d pull the trigger,
and a little light would come on.
And he thought:
‘You know, that would be really nice.
My drill doesn’t have a little light on it.’
He was about ready to buy this latest model,
and then he said:
“Wait a minute!
“What am I doing?
How often am I going to be drilling
at night?”
But he told that
to illustrate how materialism
can get a hold of any of us.
He was being manipulated by Satan’s system.
But now, here’s a question:
What Bible principles
can help us avoid this deadly trap,
materialism?
Let’s discuss two.
Now, there are many others,
but these two can really help us.
Let’s go to Micah chapter 7,
and let’s get this first Bible principle
that really can help us.
Micah 7:7:
“But as for me,
“I will keep on the lookout for Jehovah.
“[now notice] I will show a waiting attitude
“for the God of my salvation.
My God will hear me.”
Or the footnote says:
“I will wait patiently.”
See, are we willing
to wait patiently on Jehovah?
This certainly applies to material things.
Jehovah, in effect, is telling us today:
‘I’m giving you
‘a spiritual paradise right now.
‘Be content with that.
‘Don’t try to get your physical paradise now.
I’ll give you that later.’
But the question is,
Are we willing to wait on Jehovah, see?
Or do we, in effect,
run ahead of him and try to acquire
physical paradisaic conditions
for ourselves right now
at the expense of spiritual activity?
Ecclesiastes 3:1 says:
“There is an appointed time for everything.”
Well, Jehovah has appointed our time
—especially these last days
of “the last days”
shortly before the last day
of this old system—
not as the time to seek and spend time
acquiring physical comforts
but, rather,
as a time to beautify this spiritual paradise
and help others join us in this paradise.
No wonder at 1 Peter 1:1 and 2:11
God’s people are described
as “temporary residents!”
And it’s a real protection
if we think of ourselves that way:
temporary residents.
Now, the illustration has been used
of staying in a hotel room.
Now, you know when you’re in a hotel room,
you’re a temporary resident.
You might do a few things
to make your stay more comfortable.
You might rearrange the chairs;
you might reposition the lamps;
you might buy some flowers
and put them on the table;
you might spray some air freshener.
But you would never rip off the wallpaper
and install new wallpaper.
You’d never rip up the carpet
and install new carpet or tile.
You wouldn’t buy new furniture.
You’d keep it simple
because you know
you’re going to be checking out.
Now, even if you ended up
staying a few months in that hotel room,
especially if you didn’t know exactly when
you’re going to have to check out,
you would still keep it simple.
Well, that describes our situation.
We’re going to “check out”
of this old system.
We’re going to “check in”
to the new world.
We don’t know exactly when,
but we know it’s soon.
So we keep it simple.
We’re “temporary residents.”
But now, let’s get a second Bible principle
that can help us avoid materialism.
Let’s go to Luke chapter 10.
And Jesus’ words here
can help us identify
this second Bible principle.
At Luke 10:42, the B  part,
Jesus said:
“For her part,
“Mary chose the good portion,
and it will not be taken away from her.”
You notice she chose the good portion.
The footnote says the “best portion.”
Now, we know the story.
Martha chose physical activity.
She chose working in the kitchen.
Mary chose spiritual activity
—listening to Jesus.
Jesus correctly identified
who made the best choice,
who chose the best portion.
Well, similarly with us,
when we choose
‘storing up treasure in heaven’
over ‘storing up treasure on the earth,’
we are choosing the best portion.
How so?
Well, for one thing,
it brings Jehovah’s blessing,
and that results in happiness.
We all know what Proverbs 10:22 says:
“It is the blessing of Jehovah
“that makes one rich,
and He adds no pain with it.”
In contrast,
1 Timothy 6:9, 10
speaks about how those who go out
for money or material things
can end up ‘stabbing themselves
all over with many pains.’
Now, isn’t that a contrast
—blessing from Jehovah with no pain
and stabbing yourself all over
with many pains?
Well, we’re choosing the best portion
when we go for spiritual, heavenly, treasure.
Now, another reason is heavenly treasure
will result in preservation
into the new world,
if necessary by means of the resurrection.
Proverbs 11:4:
“Wealth will be of no benefit
on the day of fury,
but righteousness
is what will rescue from death.”
So remembering those two Bible principles
can really help us.
Remember that we are to wait on Jehovah.
And he says,
‘It’s a spiritual paradise now
and a physical paradise later.’
We wait on him, and when we do that
(that second principle),
we’re choosing “the best portion.”
And we’re going to be happy.
We’re going to get Jehovah’s blessings.
And if we do this, then, like Moses,
we’ll choose treasures
“greater than the treasures of Egypt.”
We’ll be able to do what Jesus said
—to pray for and to be content
with our daily bread.