Most likely when we speak
to our brothers and our sisters,
our friends, our family,
it seems like everyone
is going through something stressful,
something that’s causing them anxiety.
If it’s not us, it could be our mate.
It could be a close friend.
It could be our parents.
It could be anyone that we’re close to.
This causes worry.
It causes anxiety.
We get stressed out over the stress.
What can we do?
We can be like David.
What did David do?
Open your Bibles to Psalm 18:6.
David did not rely on himself.
He turned to his best Friend
and his Rescuer, Jehovah.
Psalm 18:6 reads:
“In my distress I called on Jehovah,
“to my God I kept crying for help.
“From his temple he heard my voice,
and my cry to him for help reached his ears.”
And verse 16 goes on to say in response:
“[Jehovah] reached down from on high;
“he took hold of me
and pulled me from deep waters.
“He rescued me from my strong enemy,
from those hating me,
who were stronger than I was.”
Well, it’s comforting to read
what David went through
and how Jehovah helped him.
And it’s comforting that Jehovah promises
to do the same for you, for me,
and for all of his loyal servants.
Now, in the past, Jehovah used angels
—he dispatched them, he sent them—
to help loyal ones like Jacob,
Gideon, Daniel, Mary, and Jesus.
Now, we still have angels helping us today.
But who does Jehovah use primarily
to help his servants on earth?
You, me, and our brotherhood.
And what a privilege it is
to be used by Jehovah,
to be dispatched by Jehovah,
to be an aid to someone else!
But we need to ask ourselves:
‘Am I someone who is ready to be used?
‘Am I willing to be used by Jehovah?
‘Am I willing to be dispatched
when someone
is going through difficult times?’
Picture, if you will,
a young man swimming in the ocean.
He’s doing fine until he comes into distress.
He begins yelling out to be rescued.
Thankfully, an alert lifeguard is there.
He dives into the ocean;
he plunges in
and brings this person to safety.
Now, lifeguards are there for a reason.
They’re there to warn people of danger.
But if they’re in danger,
they pull them to safety.
We expect that a lifeguard would do that.
What does Jehovah expect of us?
Well, he trains us to protect others
—to be a lifesaver, a lifeguard,
for other brothers and sisters
who are desperately needing help.
In a similar way,
we need to think about others.
We need to be observant like a lifeguard
and see if they might be drowning in sorrow
or in some sort of distress
and see what we can do
to come to their rescue.
And what can we do?
Follow today’s text at Proverbs 17:17.
Let’s read it in its entirety.
It says: “A true friend
“shows love at all times
and is a brother
who is born for times of distress.”
So, what does that mean?
“A true friend shows love at all times.”
A true friend is not one
who makes your problems disappear.
A true friend is the one who won’t disappear
when you’re facing problems.
That’s a true friend.
When David was going through
very difficult times, many abandoned him
—but not Jonathan, not Hushai.
They were there.
They were loyal.
They were true friends
through thick and thin.
They were there to assist David,
to rescue him
when he needed rescuing the most.
Yes, they stood by David
when he needed to lean on them.
Love was the very foundation
of their friendship.
Love was enduring.
Love was strong.
Now, think about lifeguards,
going back to our illustration.
Lifeguards are not born lifeguards.
They are trained to do so
—to be observant,
to come to the rescue of others.
Jehovah is training us now.
We need to use that training to help others.
We need to be observant.
We need to be on the lookout
to come to their rescue.
And when you think about true friends,
they know us very well.
Even if we don’t say anything to them,
they are observant.
They know if we’re going through
a difficult time just by a look
or maybe our tone of voice
or possibly our demeanor.
They come to our rescue.
Jesus said at John 15:13
that “no one has greater love than this,
[and what is this?]
“that someone should surrender his life
in behalf of his friends.”
Now, we know that our friends
are willing to sacrifice for us,
and at some point, sometimes it could mean
that we would die for our friends.
But likely what it means
is that we are surrendering,
giving up, sacrificing
our time and our energy
to come to the aid of others,
to build them up spiritually,
help them physically
and sometimes even emotionally.
Because love
is the very foundation, it’s enduring.
It never, ever fails.
Now, sometimes we want
to come to the aid of others,
but we don’t know what to say.
We may not know what to do.
We can’t fix their problem.
We can’t take it away.
But we can come to their aid
and be with them,
be there for them, be at their side.
Sometimes just being a good listener
—that’s true love.
The smallest act of kindness
is worth far more
than the grandest intention.
And we need to remember that.
Remember, Jehovah expects us
to be genuine and self-sacrificing
in our love at all times for others.
Unexpected events
happen at unexpected times.
So we need to ask ourselves,
‘Am I ready to give of myself
and put things aside
and jump into action
to help my brother or sister?’
Interestingly,
the second part of verse 17 says
“a brother who is born
for times of distress.”
How are we to understand
that part of the scripture?
Well, it could mean a brother or sister
who is our fleshly brother or sister,
but many times, it’s not.
It could be a brother or sister
spiritually who has come to our aid
—someone who is a true friend,
someone who is loyal.
That’s what Proverbs 18:24 says,
that ‘a true friend
is sticking closer than a brother.’
We have the opportunity
to be used by Jehovah
—to be an answer to someone’s prayer
if we allow ourselves to be used by Jehovah
to make ourselves available
and “dive in”
to come to the rescue of others.
And quite likely
we’re going to go through a distressful time,
and we’ll need someone
to be an answer to our prayer.
A true friend is one who walks into your life
when others are walking out.
They enter; they come into our life
when we need them most,
like the case of David.
We might be good
at coming to the rescue right away
when something happens in someone’s life.
But what would happen
if that illness or that issue
is prolonged and it goes on and on?
Will we still stick
to our brother and our sister
and be there for them
in their time of distress?
Well, we want to continue
to keep in contact with them
to assure them of Jehovah’s love
and our love by a note,
an email, a text, or by visiting them.
All of these will assure them
that they are truly loved.
When we think about Paul, the apostle Paul,
he went through many distressful times.
In fact, when he was in Rome
in the year 60 C.E., he was imprisoned.
He mentioned by name
in the book of Colossians, in chapter 4,
five brothers
—five friends—
that came to his rescue.
They were brothers born
for when he was going through distress.
Yes, they entered into his life
when he needed them most.
We recall they were called Tychicus,
Onesimus, Aristarchus, Mark, and Justus.
And what did Paul say
in Colossians 4:11 about them?
He said: “They have become
a source of great comfort to me,”
or as the footnote says,
“a strengthening aid.”
It’s interesting that “a strengthening aid”
comes from a Greek word,
which is rendered “medicine,”
something that provides comfort, relief.
Those five brothers, those friends,
could not relieve Paul from his prison cell,
but they could be comforting
and “a strengthening aid”
so that he could endure
what he was going through.
They were willing to do whatever
they needed to do to bring him comfort
—to be his messenger,
to provide material things for him,
like clothing and writing materials.
That’s a true friend.
From his experience,
he said at 1 Thessalonians 5:14:
“Speak consolingly to those
who are depressed [or discouraged],
support the weak, be patient toward all.”
That expression “support the weak”
has been rendered
“to hold fast, to cleave, to the weak.”
Many of our brothers and sisters today
—many of us—
are drowning in distress.
We’re overwhelmed with problems.
May we be observant;
may we be willing to “dive in”
to rescue our brother and our sister
—offering them a helping hand—
and hang on to them tight.
And may it be in our case
that when we help somebody, they say of us,
“A true friend you are,
someone who showed love
in times of distress.”