Welcome to JW Broadcasting.
We have some encouraging things
to look forward to in this month’s program.
We’ll hear the experiences
of Sister Agapita Reyes.
As a Christian wife and mother,
she successfully met the challenges
of raising a family
by applying Bible principles.
What helped her
to remain steadfast throughout her life?
How can you maintain focus
even after you achieve a spiritual goal?
Could subtle temptations
and distractions take you off course?
We’ll discuss an important quality
that can help you.
Parents are proud of young ones
who give their best to Jehovah.
Their feelings are
a reflection of how Jehovah feels
and are the inspiration
for this month’s music video.
This is JW Broadcasting for August 2017.
The complexity found in nature
has inspired
amazing achievements in technology.
But it has also moved people to ask,
“Was It Designed?”
That’s the title of an Awake! series
that first appeared in 2008.
It’s been a powerful tool
to turn people’s attention to Jehovah,
the Creator of all things.
We’re pleased to introduce the first
in an exciting new video series
based on those articles.
The trunk of the African elephant
is an impressive multitool.
It is both flexible
and strong.
It can pick up a blade of grass
or uproot a tree.
Some elephants can use
their trunks to feed themselves
around 270 kilograms (600 lbs)
of vegetation
every day.
With their trunks,
they can suck water like a straw,
spray like a fountain,
and swim with a snorkel.
The trunk can give a gentle touch,
give a strong push,
or sound a warning trumpet.
Engineers admire
the elephant trunk’s remarkable flexibility.
This comes from having no bone.
Instead, it contains
about 150,000 muscle units
—an incredible marriage
of strength and structure.
Inspired by the elephant’s trunk,
researchers are designing robots
for the future with greater flexibility.
Industrial design
often can be made better by copying
the perfectly beautiful solutions
in the natural world.
What do you think?
Did the elephant’s trunk evolve?
Or . . .
This new video series can help you
to see the proof that there is a Creator.
It can especially help
you young ones to recognize
and reject
the false teaching of evolution.
Use these new videos
in your personal study
and share them
with classmates and teachers.
They’ll help you
give an effective witness
and bring honor to Jehovah.
You’ll find them
in the Video on Demand section
of JW Broadcasting.
Young ones need strong faith
in this difficult system of things,
but they are not alone.
They have Jehovah’s holy spirit,
a congregation of brothers and sisters,
and very often,
loving Christian parents.
In Monterrey, Mexico,
Sister Agapita Reyes
set a beautiful example
in building up
the faith of her children.
What circumstances
made that effort a special challenge?
It’s not easy raising kids in the truth,
and I had ten.
I learned the truth when I was 19.
Some Witnesses came to preach in our town,
and my father offered them a place to stay.
He spoke with them all through the night
and then announced excitedly
that he had found the truth.
Eventually, I was baptized in the 1950’s.
My husband was favorable toward the truth
but got involved
in political affairs in the community,
and from there
he began his political career.
When I read 1 Peter 3:1, 2,
I understood that I needed
to be in subjection to my husband,
with the hope that he could be won over
“without a word” by means of my conduct.
When my children were young,
I made a weekly Bible study program
for each of them,
and as they grew up,
the older kids helped me
with their younger siblings.
I remember Mom always made
an effort to teach me how to preach.
I would write presentations
for the ministry on pieces of paper,
and the kids would practice while they
did their chores around the house.
We set aside time
one day a week for our family study.
It could be anything
—a sack of potatoes,
a sack of flour, or a house plant.
She would tell me:
“Imagine that this is a person
you meet in field service.
What would you say to them?”
When I finished, she would say to me,
“The way you did it just now,
do it like that when you
go out in the ministry.”
My mom was very creative.
She would assign us to play
the part of different Bible characters.
My mom taught us to appreciate the truth
through her example.
I served as a regular pioneer for many years,
and I encouraged my kids
to reach out for spiritual goals.
My daughter left home at the age of 18
to serve as a special pioneer.
Later, my oldest son did the same.
These two proved to be excellent examples
for their younger brothers.
Raising my son Noé was a challenge.
He was the youngest,
and at a very young age,
he was diagnosed with epilepsy.
Despite his limitations,
he was able to serve
as a ministerial servant
and regular pioneer.
He fought his illness for more than 40 years,
before passing away recently.
Losing my husband in death
dealt me another blow.
Now my health and my memory are fading.
I can’t do as much
in the ministry as before.
But even so, thanks to the help
of the brothers in the congregation,
I’m not giving up.
Even though my husband
was not a Witness,
I respected him
as the head of the family.
I will never forget the moment
when my husband asked me
to study the Bible with him.
I remember
that my eldest son gave the talk,
and his father was
among the candidates for baptism.
Forty-two years
after I received the Kingdom message,
my husband was baptized.
Another great blessing
was seeing my children
grow in the truth
and use their youth to serve Jehovah.
Some have served as special pioneers,
circuit overseers, or in Bethel.
If it wasn’t for her help
and the support of my siblings,
perhaps we wouldn’t be part
of the organization today.
But thanks to her,
we started out on the best course in life.
Words cannot express
how grateful I am to her.
I now find great joy
in seeing my grandchildren
and great-grandchildren
follow their parents’ example.
Thinking about all I have experienced
in over 60 years of service to Jehovah
—raising my ten children in the truth,
my husband becoming a servant of Jehovah,
and seeing 30 members
of my family in full-time service—
I can do nothing
but thank Jehovah
for his blessings.
It’s been worth all the effort.
Sister Reyes continues
to serve Jehovah faithfully
at 86 years of age.
Have you personally experienced
some of her more difficult struggles?
She’s felt the heartbreak
of losing her husband and a child in death.
In recent years,
she’s battled failing health.
But through all of that,
Sister Reyes remains
a motivating example for Christian women.
Her story is an excellent start
to our discussion.
The theme for our program is
“The Women Proclaiming the Good News.”
Sadly, throughout human history
women have been subjected
to injustice, violence, and abuse.
Why is that?
The Bible explains.
In the latter part of Genesis 3:16,
notice what God says:
“Your longing will be for your husband,
and he will dominate you.”
When God said
that Adam would “dominate” his wife,
God was not indicating His approval
of the subjugation of woman by man.
He was simply foretelling
the sad consequences
of sin on the first couple.
So abuse of women
is a direct outcome
of the sinful nature of humans,
not of God’s will.
Right down to our day,
rarely have women been accorded
the dignity that God
wants them to receive.
However, Jehovah makes clear
in his Word, the Bible,
that women and men
have equal standing before him.
In fact, he indicated
that women would play a vital role
in the outworking of his purpose.
Our theme is based on Psalm 68:11.
Let’s read it:
“Jehovah gives the command;
the women proclaiming
the good news are a large army.”
Those words were inspired by God.
But what did the psalmist
have in mind when he penned them?
The context of Psalm 68
shows that David was praising
Jehovah as a God of saving acts.
From the time of their Exodus from Egypt,
the men of Israel often had to fight
against enemy nations.
With Jehovah’s help,
they defeated them.
And the entire nation would then rejoice
over the victory Jehovah had given them.
The first of the victory celebrations
recorded in the Bible
was at the time
that Jehovah gave his people
the victory over Pharaoh
and the Egyptians who were pursuing them.
Exodus 15:20, 21
tells what happened
after this miraculous victory:
“Then Miriam the prophetess,
Aaron’s sister,
“took a tambourine in her hand,
“and all the women followed her
with tambourines and with dances.
“Miriam sang in response to the men:
“‘Sing to Jehovah,
“‘for he has become highly exalted.
The horse and its rider
he has hurled into the sea.’”
Picture that scene.
There were
an estimated three million people
in the nation of Israel.
Imagine
—out of that large number,
“all the women” were dancing
and singing praises to Jehovah.
That was undoubtedly a large army!
What a great shout of praise
to Jehovah that was!
Another example was
when King Saul and his general David
returned from victory over the Philistines.
Let’s read the account
at 1 Samuel 18:6.
“When David and the others would return
“from striking down the Philistines,
“the women would come out
“from all the cities of Israel
“with song and dances to meet King Saul
“with tambourines,
with rejoicing, and with lutes.”
Notice that the account says
that the women came out of “all the cities”
to greet them with music, song, and dance.
Occasions such as these
were not simply expressions of rejoicing
that originated with human emotion.
Recall that under inspiration, David said:
“Jehovah gives the command;
the women proclaiming
the good news are a large army.”
Yes, and Jehovah valued
their expressions of praise,
just as he valued the contributions
of the men who had engaged in battle.
What about today?
The report for the 2017 service year
shows that there were
over 8.3 million publishers
proclaiming the good news
throughout the earth.
Keep in mind that in most lands,
it is not unusual for our dear sisters
to make up over half
of our special pioneers
and nearly three quarters of those
who serve in the regular pioneer work.
In addition, many other sisters
are wholeheartedly spreading
the good news of the Kingdom
to the best of their ability
within their circumstances.
There are many single-parent families
where our sisters
are providing materially
and spiritually for their children.
Many of our faithful single sisters
are expending themselves
in Jehovah’s service
in theocratic construction
and maintenance work,
Bethel service,
and serving where the need is greater
—which includes
serving in foreign-language fields.
Faithful wives
loyally support their husbands
as well as fulfill their own roles
as preachers and teachers.
Yes, how Jehovah must be pleased
to see all of you
who serve in various ways!
And we’re grateful
for the warm spirit and positive influence
our dear sisters have on our congregations.
Clearly,
Jehovah values
this “large army” of sisters.
But does he take note
of the individual circumstances
and sacrifices of each sister?
We do not have to wonder.
By means of his Word,
Jehovah makes it evident that he sees
and appreciates each of his servants.
For example,
did you notice when we read
the scripture in Exodus chapter 15
that Miriam was described
as a “prophetess”?
Evidently,
she was privileged to be used
as an instrument
of divine communication.
In some instances,
this no doubt included singing songs
that were inspired by Jehovah.
Miriam was not the only one
in the Scriptures with this designation.
Other women in the Bible record,
such as Anna and Isaiah’s wife,
were also spoken of as prophetesses.
In the book of Judges,
another faithful servant,
Deborah, is identified.
Let’s read Judges 4:4, 5:
“Now Deborah, a prophetess,
“the wife of Lappidoth,
“was judging Israel at that time.
“She used to sit under Deborah’s palm tree
“between Ramah and Bethel
“in the mountainous region of Ephraim;
the Israelites
would go up to her for judgment.”
Evidently,
Deborah was assigned to settle
disputes that arose among Israelites
by giving Jehovah’s answer
to problems that came up.
Much later in Israel’s history,
during the reign of faithful King Josiah,
Huldah served as a prophetess.
At 2 Kings 22:8,
we read that while the temple
was being repaired,
the original book of the Law was found.
When it was read to Josiah,
he was distraught at seeing how far off
the nation had strayed from Jehovah’s Law.
In verse 13,
he directed the priest, the secretary,
and other influential men:
“Go, inquire of Jehovah in my behalf,
“in behalf of the people,
“and in behalf of all Judah
concerning the words of this book
that has been found.”
How did they accomplish this?
Verse 14 continues:
“So Hilkiah the priest,
“Ahikam, Achbor, Shaphan, and Asaiah
went to Huldah the prophetess.”
It’s interesting that Jehovah
used this faithful woman
to convey his direction
and that prominent men and priests
sought her divinely inspired advice.
The Christian Greek Scriptures, however,
do not permit sisters
to serve in such a capacity
as did Deborah
and other prophetesses
in the nation of Israel.
However,
Titus 2:3, 4
encourages “older women”
to display spiritual qualities,
“so that they may advise
the younger women”
in spiritual matters.
Let’s read those verses:
“Likewise, let the older women
be reverent in behavior,
“not slanderous,
not enslaved to a lot of wine,
“teachers of what is good,
“so that they may advise
the younger women
to love their husbands,
to love their children.”
How we appreciate
the spiritually mature sisters among us
who provide
such fine assistance to younger sisters
or those who are newer in the truth!
However, today Jehovah
has delegated authority to men.
They Scripturally qualify
to serve as elders and ministerial servants
in order to serve, guide,
and protect his people.
It is obvious that this is not due
to a lack of respect
for the gifts of our sisters
in the congregation.
In fact,
many responsible brothers will acknowledge
that they have benefited
from the experience
and practical wisdom
of our humble, spiritually mature sisters.
Finally,
think of the outstanding faith
of another woman
mentioned in the Bible, Mary.
What an awesome responsibility
Jehovah entrusted her with
—bearing and raising
his own Son as a human!
We can only imagine the thoughts
that were going through her mind
when she was told of this assignment.
But the account in Luke chapter 1
tells us much about her spirituality.
In verse 38,
after the angel Gabriel
finished speaking with her,
Mary’s response was simply:
“Look! Jehovah’s slave girl!
May it happen to me
according to your declaration.”
She must have wondered
how Jehovah would accomplish these things,
but she was humble and obedient.
Faithful men such as Moses
and Jeremiah hesitated
when given
a challenging assignment from God.
Not Mary!
What a beautiful example
she set for all of us
—men and women!
Clearly,
Jehovah has always highly valued women.
And we are privileged to serve today
with millions of hardworking sisters.
How pleased Jehovah must be
to see dear sisters
serving him humbly and faithfully!
We urge you sisters,
please keep up your good work
and continue to be
a positive influence in the congregation.
God has indeed granted
you faithful women
the privilege of participating
in the fulfillment of the psalmist’s words:
“Jehovah gives the command;
the women proclaiming
the good news are a large army.”
Thousands of our sisters have been active
for many years
in that “large army” of women.
Bertille Kupelian,
a special pioneer in West Virginia,
in the United States,
entered the full-time service in 1958.
In that time, she’s helped
more than 60 people to baptism.
How has her outlook toward the ministry
kept her going for almost 60 years?
My father was opposed
to the truth as I was growing up,
but my mother was very, very zealous.
I knew the things my mother
was teaching me was the truth.
I knew that this was
what I was going to do.
And it was not easy, but we did it.
I was Daddy’s girl,
but my mom made sure
that I and my siblings knew the truth.
And she studied with us
when no other children
in the congregation
had Bible studies at home.
Of course, we kind of kicked
and didn’t like it,
but I was glad she did it.
My mother was a very, very positive person,
and although she had the opposition,
I saw how she dealt with it
and how firm and determined she was.
And that was something she taught us.
It’s a mind-set.
You know,
your mind is a wonderful thing.
It can really influence you
toward good or maybe not so good.
And so then,
I was determined in my mind
that I was going to serve Jehovah then.
In our congregation, there were brothers
and sisters of the anointed.
They were always very kind to me,
and they encouraged me.
I worked in service with them.
And I thought,
‘That’s the way I want to be.’
Children like attention.
And so then, if you give them attention
—you talk with them
and ask if you could work
with them in the ministry
and help them prepare a presentation
and go over it and over it
so that they’re ready for the ministry
—then they’ll enjoy it more.
That was one of the things
that the anointed
did in the congregation where I was.
They paid attention to me, and I loved it.
How I learned to teach
was I think about the person,
and I think about their situation,
and I try to think in my mind
what they are thinking,
and I work on that
and think of what kind of scriptures
I can find to help them.
And so then,
I try to pattern our studies
to incorporate some of those things.
There are always challenges.
Some of the winters right on the lake
where I lived were very harsh.
And my trailer was parked
in such a way that every time
the wind blew
and the snow came and the ice came,
it sealed the door.
And so then, I carried a big knife in my car,
and I would have to cut around the door
to get the door to open
—break the ice seal.
It was interesting.
I had some opposition in the territories,
and one was this lady who was very irate.
And she went to kick me,
and she kicked me right in the stomach,
and so then, anyway,
I dismissed myself.
Then, a while later,
it was time to work the territory again.
Nobody wanted to go there,
and we didn’t have do-not-calls,
I don’t think, at that time,
at least there wasn’t any in the territory.
So then anyway, I called by
and I mentioned to her:
“Why, hello there.
I know I’ve had the opportunity
to talk with you before.”
Yes, she remembered.
And I said, “Well, perhaps
you were having a bad day that day.”
I hit a lull when I had few Bible studies,
and so I prayed diligently to Jehovah:
“Jehovah, help me.
I need Bible studies.”
And then you have to be
out there looking for them.
Well, I’ve lost my father, my mother,
my sister, my brother.
Well, naturally you feel at a loss,
but Jehovah strengthened me,
and the friends strengthened me,
and I kept busy in the ministry.
But again, it goes back to that mind-set.
Are you going to let the challenge beat you,
or are you going to beat the challenge?
You and Jehovah can beat the challenge.
You know, discouragement
is one of Satan’s biggest tools.
And I always tell myself,
‘I’m not going to let Satan beat me down.’
As far as health is concerned,
my everyday health is very good.
But I have a leg that drives me crazy.
I think back to Jacob.
He served Jehovah with a limp.
And then I think of Paul.
And so then, those things keep you humble.
I’ve prayed and prayed and prayed about it,
but just like with the apostle Paul,
it didn’t disappear.
And so then, I just say:
“Patch me up till Armageddon.
It’ll disappear then.”
If your mind is made up
that this is what you’re going to do,
this is your life,
this is what Jehovah wants you to do,
and so then you do it.
I’ve seen how he’s kept me going.
You know that I’ve needed work;
I’ve needed money;
I’ve needed strength.
I’ve needed companionship
because a lot of times
I’m in the ministry by myself.
I talk to Jehovah.
And so then, he’s always there for me.
I definitely want to keep pioneering
or serving Jehovah the best I can,
regardless of what comes up.
There is nothing more joyful
than to see that you have helped
somebody to live forever.
Well, how much better could it be?
Sister Kupelian had a profound effect
on those she witnessed to.
I know this because she found me
in the door-to-door ministry
when I was 14 years old.
At that age, I had the goal to be a doctor.
One night after the meeting,
Bertille said to me,
“Well, you know,
in the new world,
we won’t need doctors
because Jesus will do all the healing.”
Honestly, that hit me hard
because I wanted to help people
as well as provide for my mother.
But she added,
“What we will need are teachers.”
I thought that was a good idea.
Still focused on a career,
I had one type of teacher in mind,
but she had another.
Through her patience and reasoning,
she helped me to become
the most important kind of teacher
—a teacher of God’s Word.
Is there someone like Sister Kupelian
in your congregation?
We are grateful
for these sisters’ zealous spirit
and for the personal interest
they show toward us.
And we’re sure Jehovah
values them like we do.
One of Sister Kupelian’s strengths
is her perseverance.
Perseverance means to continue resolutely
in the face of adversity,
being tenacious, not giving up.
If not careful,
we could reach a spiritual goal,
only to let something
distract us away from it.
In this dramatization,
a young sister is pioneering
and working toward new goals.
How, though,
is she in danger of losing her focus?
When I started learning sign language,
it just seemed to come natural for me.
After I transferred to the congregation,
I remember feeling so happy.
I was pioneering and really enjoying
this new way of communicating.
It’s funny how
the thing you love can also be
the thing that tests you.
Soon, I took the test
for a sign-language interpreter.
I couldn’t believe I passed!
I loved my new job.
My hope was
that it would support my pioneering
and maybe
allow me to travel one day to a country
and preach where there was
a need for sign language.
My boss was very happy with my work,
so much so that he began to give me more.
Everyone seemed appreciative,
and the extra money didn’t hurt.
I was handling it all fine.
Ahh, OK, for a while.
My boss asked me to work full-time
for a few months
to get some extra training.
The raise could help me
with planning my trip abroad.
I knew my parents would be concerned.
I knew because I felt it too.
I was already dragging physically.
But then again,
it would only be for a few months.
I was really torn.
Dad kindly commended me
for having good goals
and trying my best to work toward them.
Then he showed me
a scripture that really helped me,
1 Timothy 4:16:
“Pay constant attention
to yourself and to your teaching.
“Persevere in these things,
“for by doing this
you will save both yourself
and those who listen to you.”
He helped me
to see that Timothy set spiritual goals
for himself while growing up.
But Paul was now telling him,
“Don’t stop!”
Even though Timothy
was a grown spiritual man,
Paul encouraged him
to continue setting new spiritual goals,
in fact, to ‘persevere in them.’
What was I persevering in?
I kindly turned down the offer
and explained to my boss
that I’d like to keep my hours
to a minimum
so I could support
my number one job.
It might take me longer to save my money,
but I’ll make that trip one day
with Jehovah’s help
and a little perseverance.
It’s interesting
that the skill she used
to expand her ministry
and support her pioneering
became her distraction.
That wasn’t easy for her to see at first.
Who helped her to see the problem clearly?
It was her parents,
especially her spiritually-minded father.
The interest you family heads
show in your daughters
is well worth the effort.
It can point them in the right direction
when they need guidance.
Everything you do for them
shows how precious they are
to you and to Jehovah,
and that’s the feeling
expressed in the music video
Precious Daughter.
Through all her tender years,
He watched her grow.
Many the joys and tears,
She would come to know.
But when she gave her best
And came through each test,
She made His heart feel so good.
Precious daughter,
He’s so proud of you.
Time won’t alter His love for you.
Hard work and sacrifice—
That’s just her way.
Thinking of His advice
Helps her through the day,
And she’s so glad to know
That He loves her so.
It means so much to hear him say:
“Precious daughter,
I’m so proud of you.
Time won’t alter my love for you.”
Yes, Jehovah sees
And Jehovah knows
All the work you’ve done
And the love you’ve shown.
No, He won’t forget
How you’ve loved His name
For all this time.
Precious daughter,
He’s so proud of you.
He’ll be there for you.
Precious daughter,
He will care for you.
He loves you.
The apostle John wrote
that he had no greater joy
than to hear that his spiritual children
continued “walking in the truth.”
You fathers feel that same joy
when you see your daughters
mature as Christian women.
Raising your children to love Jehovah
is just one of the many things
you do for your family.
At a Bethel morning worship,
Brother Lett focused
on the special relationship
between a husband and wife.
What can a husband do to show
that he shares Jehovah’s view of his wife?
My theme for this little discussion is
“Husbands, Love Your Wife as Yourself.”
What did Jesus say
was the second greatest commandment?
Well,
you’re familiar with it.
At Matthew 22:39,
he said:
“You must love
your neighbor as yourself.”
Now,
what an excellent illustration
is contained
in this second greatest commandment!
If you think about it,
we just naturally,
inherently, love ourselves,
don’t we?
And we show
love in many ways.
So Jesus is saying,
“Work hard to show
the same love for others
you show for yourself.”
But, now, thinking of husbands
as addressed in our theme,
who is a husband’s closest neighbor?
Well, his wife.
So especially must a husband work hard
to show the love that he shows
for himself just naturally and then
to show that love for his wife.
Now, what are some specific ways
that husbands
just naturally love themselves?
Well,
let’s talk about five.
And undoubtedly
you can think of many others
that could be discussed
during this discussion.
But number one:
A husband feeds himself.
Ephesians 5:29 says in part:
“For no man ever hated his own body,
but he feeds . . . it.”
Well, what does loving our wife,
now, as ourself require?
Well, for one thing,
we certainly would make sure
we provide for the food
and for other material needs
that our wife has.
And regarding this,
I think of our brothers
in concentration camps
in Nazi Germany.
Food was very scarce.
But our brothers, even then,
from their meager food ration
would share food
with other brothers,
even, in some cases,
with worldly people.
Well, similarly,
a husband would do without himself,
if necessary, in order to provide
what his wife really needs.
But even more importantly,
an extended application,
he would make sure
that she is well-fed spiritually.
He must make sure
that she has opportunity
to benefit from periods
of personal study,
congregation meetings,
assemblies, conventions,
and family worship.
But now let’s talk
about a second way
that a husband
just naturally loves himself:
We cherish ourselves.
Ephesians 5:29 says in part:
“For no man ever hated his own body,
but he . . . cherishes it.”
Now,
what does cherish mean?
Well,
according to the dictionary,
it means to treat
with affection and tenderness,
treasure, value,
attach importance to.
See, because of this feeling
we have toward ourselves,
we try to get rest
when we’re sick or tired;
we try to be
with friends and loved ones;
we play games; we exercise;
we do things we enjoy.
Periodically,
we treat ourselves, don’t we,
because we cherish ourselves?
So, what does loving
our wife as ourself require?
Well, it certainly means more
than just being able
to put up with our mate.
It means cherishing her,
cultivating affection,
or fondness, for her.
Think of this:
At Proverbs 8:31,
it says that Jesus
in his prehuman existence
was fond of humans.
Now, don’t you think
that fondness he had for us
made it easier for him
to come to the earth,
take the difficult assignment he took,
and even die for us
because he was fond of us?
Well, similarly,
if wives are cherished
by their husbands
—if husbands
are fond of their wives—
it’ll make it so much easier
to forgive them,
to even die for them,
if necessary, in the future.
But if we’re going to have
this proper feeling, like Jehovah,
we have to focus
on the good qualities of our wife, see,
not the flaws, the imperfections.
And as one
of the brothers commented on
(I love the thoughts
in The Watchtower comments):
“Love is best sensed
when it is expressed.
“How vital that marriage mates
“not allow the activities of daily life
to rob them of exchanging
expressions of affection!”
But now let’s get a third way
that husbands
just naturally love themselves:
We adorn ourselves.
First Timothy 2:9 speaks
of women “adorn[ing] themselves
in appropriate dress.”
Well, husbands
try to do the same thing.
And in adorning ourselves,
we try to cover over
and minimize our flaws
and cover our bulges,
our blemishes.
We try to make ourselves
look as good as possible, don’t we?
Well, what does loving
our wife as ourself require?
For one thing, we certainly
wouldn’t shine a spotlight on her flaws.
We wouldn’t do this
in the presence of others.
We would try hard
not to even do it in our own mind.
Rather, we seek to cover over
minor sins and transgressions,
as encouraged at Proverbs 19:11,
where it says:
“It is beauty . . . to overlook an offense.”
So we work hard
to adorn our wives
—make her look
as good as possible—
in the eyes of others,
even in our own mind.
Well, let’s get a fourth way
that husbands
just naturally love themselves:
We take steps to heal ourselves
when we’re sick or injured.
Mark 5:26
talks about a woman
who was very sick.
‘She suffered at the hands
of many physicians;
‘she spent all her resources;
she didn’t get any better;
she got worse.’
But the point is,
she was really trying hard
to heal herself.
Well, husbands
try to do the same thing.
So if we’re sick or injured,
we try to get extra rest,
we’ll buy medicine,
we’ll take vitamins,
we’ll make an appointment
with the doctor,
we’ll pursue therapy.
See, we try to get well.
What does loving our wife
as ourself require then?
Well, we would certainly
do all within our power
if she’s sick or injured
to try to help her get well.
But even more importantly,
if she happens
to be ailing somewhat spiritually,
we would do everything
we can possibly do
to help her get well spiritually.
What would be something,
perhaps, we could do?
Well, Proverbs 12:18 says:
“The tongue of the wise is a healing”
—so the using of wise expressions.
Also, Proverbs 16:24:
“Pleasant sayings are a honeycomb,
“sweet to the soul
and a healing to the bones.”
So, “pleasant sayings,”
we would use these
to try to help her
get well spiritually.
But now here’s one more,
a fifth way
that husbands
just naturally love themselves:
We make allowances,
excuses,
if we make mistakes.
Husbands who make mistakes
are often heard blaming it
on their heredity
or maybe the environment,
their blood-sugar level,
how much sleep they got
or didn’t get the night before,
the weather, and so forth.
We tend to well understand
our own limitations, don’t we?
And we allow for that.
Well, what about
loving our wife as ourself?
We’d make the same allowances for her
—being positive,
imputing good motives to her.
If she speaks a little roughly
or acts a little thoughtlessly,
we’ll try to discern the feelings
behind the words or actions.
We’ll make allowance,
especially if we can discern
that she’s under some kind
of emotional pressure.
We’ll make that allowance for her
like we would for ourselves.
Well, there we have five ways
that we as husbands
show love for ourselves.
We feed, cherish, adorn,
try to heal ourselves;
and we make allowances, excuses,
when we make mistakes.
Let’s work hard
to show the same love
in those five areas
for our dear, beloved wives.
And I’m sure, as we said,
you can think of other ways
that husbands just naturally
love themselves.
But what a rich illustration Jesus gave!
And interestingly,
he took it even a step further.
He further expanded the illustration
at John 13:34.
You’re familiar with this, 13:34.
He said:
“I am giving you a new commandment,
“that you love one another;
“just as I have loved you,
you also love one another.”
So he’s saying that we should have
even deeper love for our brothers
—which would definitely
include our Christian wives—
a deeper love
than we have for ourselves.
And that deeper love
would move us to treat
our dear wives even better
than we treat ourselves.
Husbands, we know your wife
will never grow tired
of your efforts to apply that counsel.
Really, the whole family
benefits when each member
loves their closest neighbor
as themselves.
And when a family
is happy and spiritually strong,
they can do so much for Jehovah.
At the Scandinavia branch,
families from 19 congregations
in Denmark, Norway, and Sweden
participated in children’s choruses
to record theocratic music.
The children worked hard
to prepare for each session,
but that meant hard work
for the parents too.
The results, however,
are a chorus of praise to Jehovah.
You get so happy
when you sing with others!
Jehovah created us like that.
The birds also sing.
I feel that Jehovah is proud of me.
The Scandinavia branch office
supervises nine languages
in audio and video production.
In the three largest languages
—Swedish, Norwegian, and Danish—
there are also three children choruses
that help us
with the recordings of the songs
for the Become Jehovah’s Friend series.
First, I listen very carefully
to the American adult chorus.
I try to spot where they breathe,
where they pause,
and the overall mood
in their way of singing.
Then, I listen
to the music we have received.
I have a piano at home
to practice the voices and figure out
where the high notes and low notes are,
where the challenging parts are,
and how I can pass this on to the children.
I also think about what the goal
with the recording is
—how other children who listen to the song
can feel the same joy as we feel
when we are singing and recording it.
Before the children arrive,
we make sure that all the equipment
is prepared and tested
so that everything
is ready when they come here.
When we receive
the assignment to participate
in the recordings of a new song,
I feel that our girls have been
full of initiative to practice.
And we have made it our custom
to sing the songs at our family worship.
When we are driving,
like to the RTO
for the recordings and on other occasions,
we usually sing in the car.
I like to sing the songs
because they are good
and have nice melodies.
I especially like the new songs
because they are so different.
One has African drums in it,
and the next is a bit Irish
and like you are walking
in a valley and on a mountain.
Alma plays the cello
and has asked to get the sheet music
for the new Kingdom songs,
which are her favorites right now.
It’s been a challenge for André and me
because we are not that musical.
There is also a serious part,
so we start with a prayer to Jehovah.
Then, we watch the video and talk
about the point of the video
and how other children and families
can benefit when listening to them.
Then, we need to loosen up a bit,
so we warm up with some exercises,
and then we’re ready to sing.
It is clear to us that they appreciate
their privilege more and more.
They actually see it as praise to Jehovah.
The joy they have of singing for Jehovah
rubs off on us who work with them.
When the children sing with joy
and express themselves freely,
it has an effect on us as parents
and the ones in the congregation.
Jehovah becomes happy when he sees it,
and also many brothers and sisters
and children become happy.
It is fun to make the recordings.
You get so happy,
and then it’s more fun
to sing at the meetings.
I see more clearly why we sing
and why it is a part of our worship.
We don’t go there just
to spend time with our friends;
we go there to sing.
It is a part of praising Jehovah
Singing is like a prayer to him.
I have been humming the songs,
and people around me wonder
what it is I am always humming.
So it has helped me,
and it is an easy way to give a witness.
My faith in Jehovah is stronger now.
I think that I am happier
knowing Jehovah
after I began singing.
You understand that singing
is a huge part of our worship,
and Jehovah wants us to use it.
When children sing out joyfully to Jehovah,
they draw closer to him.
The choruses in Scandinavia
are a good example of that fact.
Their excitement for singing
even gave them opportunities
to witness to their classmates.
You probably already include singing
as part of your family worship
and agree that we feel
a special warmth
when the family sings
to Jehovah together.
As you look ahead
at the August midweek meetings,
you’ll notice a part
for the week of August 28 that asks:
“When Can I Next Serve
as an Auxiliary Pioneer?”
You’ll want to prepare
by watching the video
With Jehovah, I Can Do Almost Anything.
It’s the life story
of Sister Sabina Hernández,
which appeared
in the December 2015 program.
You’ll find it
in the Video on Demand section
under “Interviews and Experiences.”
At the midweek meeting,
you’ll be ready to share
how Sabina’s example encouraged you.
Our program has shown us
how much Jehovah values
what women do in the family,
in the congregation, and in the ministry.
To all of our sisters,
please be assured that we love you,
and it’s our prayer
that Jehovah continues to bless your work.
We want to conclude with greetings
from our brothers and sisters
on the island of Saipan.
Part of Micronesia,
in the western Pacific Ocean,
Saipan is a popular destination
for thousands of tourists.
But make no mistake,
this is a preacher’s paradise.
After early opposition
to the preaching work,
the truth is now flourishing
with an average
of 200 Kingdom publishers
in three congregations
throughout the island,
including 33 regular pioneers.
The relaxing atmosphere
and tropical climate
make public witnessing carts
an effective way
to reach the hearts of receptive ones.
The large number of tourists
—many from Asian lands—
are finding our literature
in Japanese, Korean,
Tagalog, Chinese,
and other languages.
Among the first baptized publishers
in Saipan
are faithful sisters who are now
in their 80’s.
Sister Taeko Castro
was baptized in 1970,
and Tomasa Mafnas
was baptized in 1973.
They continue to be
zealous Kingdom proclaimers
and are fine examples
of “the women proclaiming the good news.”
We send our love and greetings
to these congregations in Saipan
and warmly commend them
for their positive spirit
and hard work
to make Jehovah’s name known.
Thank you for watching.
From the world headquarters
of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
this is JW Broadcasting.