‎I lived in the north,
with the glorious dark, starlit sky
‎and the beauty of fir trees.
‎I thought it was
the most wonderful place in the world.
‎My mom was always drawing
my attention to the beauty of creation.
‎And she always told me,
‎“My daughter, it’s so important
to live your life in the right way.”
‎And the questions
that stayed with me were:
‎‘So why are we alive?
‎Why is there so much
suffering, injustice, pain?’
‎When I was 18,
I took up a form of karate
‎known as Kyokushinkai.
‎Just imagine a large number
of people in kimonos, standing in rows
‎bravely and without a shadow of fear,
‎working on improving their blows
and striving to progress.
‎I thought: ‘This is it!
This is what I’ve been looking for!’
‎I set the goal of reaching
the next world championships,
‎winning a high place,
‎and immortalizing myself
so that my name would remain
‎and generations would remember me.
‎Among those sportsmen, although I saw
a lot of nice words and slogans,
‎not everything was
as pure as I’d hoped for.
‎And then on one occasion,
I was sitting down
‎and feelings of emptiness
‎just wouldn’t leave me alone.
‎And for the first time in my life,
‎I talked to God.
‎And then I prayed:
‎“I don’t understand you.
‎“Why is there
so much beauty in the world
‎“and yet so much suffering?
‎“Is that really what you want
‎—for us to live like this?”
‎I prayed, I guess,
for about four hours.
‎You know, the strongest feeling
of emptiness and loneliness
‎is that of a creation
‎without its Creator.
‎And I was so lonely at that time.
‎And a while afterwards,
there was a knock at my door.
‎It was Jehovah’s Witnesses.
‎I started studying the Bible.
‎It was so wonderful!
‎On one occasion,
the sister who studied with me
‎looked up at me,
and when she looked at those bruises
‎and those beaten-up knuckles,
‎she took a deep breath
and shook her head.
‎I said, “Is there something wrong?”
‎She said,
“You know, I’m in great pain.”
‎I said, “Why are you in pain?”
‎She said: “Well,
‎“I’m looking at
your hands, your elbows,
‎“your battered legs, all of that.
‎Doesn’t it hurt?”
‎I said, “Well, yes.”
‎And she said, “You know,
it hurts me to see you in pain.”
‎And I started to understand
that Jehovah is the true God
‎and that this really was the truth.
‎It was difficult.
‎The pressure from relatives
and friends was very strong.
‎But the most difficult thing
‎that I had to battle with
was my strong attachment to karate.
‎Just a year remained
until the world championships.
‎I had prepared for them.
‎I had been working
toward that goal for five years.
‎Glory can seem really sweet
‎when you are the victor,
when your opponents fall to the ground.
‎So I flew to the world championships.
‎When I made it to the last four winners
‎and I had to fight for third place,
‎I wanted to ask my trainer
to let me stop. Why?
‎Because I couldn’t feel
a single place on my body
‎—everything was beaten up.
‎But he said:
‎“You know, we love you so much.
Go for it!”
‎And at that moment,
it felt as though I was weighing love
‎—the world’s love
‎and the love of Jehovah’s organization.
‎It seemed to me
that the world was saying:
‎“We love you.
Now just go and die!”
‎But the love in the organization says,
‎“It hurts me to see you in pain.”
‎I realized that the world
can’t give you what it doesn’t have.
‎It doesn’t know how to love.
‎But, nevertheless, I went to the fight
‎and became the bronze medalist.
‎And when I stood
on the podium of glory,
‎I understood that glory
among people who don’t love you
‎weighs no more than emptiness.
‎If a person dedicates his life
‎to glorifying himself,
he will always meet
‎with disappointment and emptiness.
‎So I made the firm decision
to escape from karate.
‎I started preaching,
and I was baptized in 2005
‎at the summer convention in Kurgan.
‎Later, I started full-time service.
‎I learned the Tatar language
so that I could serve in that territory.
‎Now, when in the evenings
‎I look up at the starry sky,
I feel not hopelessness,
‎but tremendous joy
‎because I know who is behind it all:
‎our loving Creator, Jehovah God.