We extend a warm welcome to all
and are happy that you have joined us
for the December 2018 program
of JW Broadcasting.
During this program, you’ll enjoy
exciting and upbuilding Scriptural talks
delivered to the students and other attendees
during the Gilead graduation
held on September 8, 2018.
And this is just the opener!
Parts 2 and 3 of the Gilead graduation program
will be released in the upcoming weeks.
In addition to motivating Bible talks,
you’ll get to know
some of the students later this month
when you watch
another edition of The Inside Story.
But now,
please enjoy Part 1 of the graduation
of the 145th class of Gilead.
Well, what an exciting time this is
to be here for the graduation
of the 145th class of Gilead!
But let’s start by asking a question:
What makes a graduation program of Gilead
different from the various graduation programs
that people engage
in right throughout the earth?
Well, I’m sure all of us would agree,
usually with regard to worldly institutions,
graduation programs
are all about the accomplishments
and praise of individuals.
But as you dear students realize,
the Gilead program
and the training that you’ve received
is all about glorifying Jehovah,
and that’s why the theme
of our introductory comments are
“Always Seek Jehovah’s Glory
and Not Your Own Glory.”
And that’s in harmony
with what the Scriptures tell us.
If you’d like to turn with me, please,
to the book of Romans
—Romans chapter 12
and notice what verses 3 and 16 remind us.
Romans 12:3:
“For through the undeserved kindness
given to me,
“I tell everyone there among you
“not to think more of himself
than it is necessary to think,
“but to think so as to have a sound mind,
each one as God
has given to him a measure of faith.”
Notice the point there:
Whatever we have
has been given to us by Jehovah.
So we shouldn’t think
more of ourselves than is necessary.
And then verse 16 reminds us:
“Have the same attitude
toward others as toward yourselves;
“do not set your mind on lofty things,
“but be led along with the lowly things.
Do not become wise in your own eyes.”
Now, we trust that you
fully understand that admonition
because your Gilead training
has been helping you
to strengthen
your relationship with Jehovah,
and when we know Jehovah,
we can’t help but glorify him
because we know
that any good things we have come from him.
But now, as you graduate
and you go either back
to your former assignments
or to new assignments,
you may find various tests to this resolve
—that you have to always glorify
Jehovah and not yourself.
Now, what might be some of those tests?
Well, one is perhaps an obvious test.
You go back maybe to your former assignment,
and the brothers say,
“Oh, you’ve changed;
you’re so much better.”
Well, that’s humbling in itself, isn’t it?
You didn’t realize
how bad you were before you left.
“And your knowledge, the illustrations,
the way you’re teaching seems so much better”
—so now what’s your reaction?
Well, I’m sure you’re not going to say:
“You’re welcome.
I noticed that too.”
I know (and I’m sure all of us know)
that you’ll be determined
in a situation like that
to bring glory to Jehovah
and not to yourselves.
So perhaps that’s the easy time
because that’s obvious we have to be careful.
But when is the other occasion, or situation,
where we may be tempted
to show a measure
of pride and glorify ourselves?
Well, it could be if people criticize us
or perhaps don’t show us the respect
that we feel that we deserve.
Or maybe we don’t get the privileges
that we hope to receive.
Now, that could be a temptation for us
—to remind everyone of the special training
and the fact
that we graduated from that training.
You see, this is similar
to the trap that Job fell into.
Now, when we think of Job,
we think of a very faithful man
—a man of integrity.
The two words go together:
Job and integrity.
But we also realize that Job
needed to have very strong counsel.
Now, at what point in his life
did he do something
that warranted him getting counsel?
Well, let’s think about it.
We won’t read the verses
because you know them well,
but in chapter 1,
remember that Job lost everything
—his children and his possessions
one after the other.
But when we look at Job 1:22,
it tells us there that “Job did not sin.”
He didn’t “accuse God
of doing anything wrong.”
So all these horrific things happened to him.
He had these huge tests,
and he came out looking pretty good.
He hadn’t sinned at that point.
So then what happened in the second round?
Well, you remember
that he had this loathsome disease,
and then his wife said to him,
“Curse God and die!”
So now, is that when he deserved some counsel?
No.
In chapter 2 of Job and verse 10,
it tells us
that he “did not sin with his lips.”
So at that point,
he was winning we might say.
He proved himself an integrity keeper.
So when was it
that he started to make a few mistakes
that resulted in getting that strong counsel?
Well, The Watchtower, back in 1980, tells us.
It said that it was
when these three so-called friends
started to criticize him and said:
‘Maybe you did this.
Maybe you did that.
That’s the—
There’s a reason.’
Then The Watchtower said
that because of these false accusations,
it’s as if it pushed Job over the edge
and he vigorously determined to justify himself
even though that inferred
that maybe Jehovah
wasn’t treating him correctly.
So do we see that this is a situation
where if we are criticized
or some false accusations are made about us,
then all of a sudden,
the self-justification can come in?
And what is self-justification?
Glorifying ourselves
rather than glorifying Jehovah.
Of course, our Lord Jesus Christ
is an excellent example in that regard.
Let’s have a look at the record
recorded in John chapter 8
—John 8:48-50.
Now here,
we have a group of Jewish persons
criticizing Jesus,
falsely accusing him of something.
Notice there in verse 48:
“In answer the Jews said to him
[that is, to Jesus]:
“‘Are we not right in saying,
“You are a Samaritan
“‘“[now, you remember that’s not a compliment]
and have a demon”?’”
On another occasion,
they said, ‘You’re out of your mind.’
But now, what did Jesus do?
Did he fall into the trap
that Job fell into and try to justify himself?
No.
He just made a simple comment in verse 49:
“I do not have a demon,
but I honor my Father, and you dishonor me.”
Then he says:
“But I am not seeking glory for myself;
there is One who is seeking and judging.”
We see the excellent example
of our Lord Jesus
in that difficult situation,
where he was falsely accused
yet still focused on glorifying Jehovah.
So, what’s the lesson there for each one of us
—not only yourselves but all of us?
Well, you don’t need to remind other people
that you graduated from Gilead,
you don’t need to try to impress others
to get their respect,
and you don’t need to praise yourself.
What should be the goal of all of us?
Well, our final scripture
that we want to share with you
are the words of Jesus
as recorded in Matthew
—Matthew 5:16:
“Likewise, let your light shine before men,
“so that they may see your fine works
and give glory to your Father
who is in the heavens.”
What a beautiful goal!
Yes, the goal is that we don’t glorify ourselves,
but we give all the glory to Jehovah God.
So with that in mind,
we’re going to look forward
to our wonderful program.
We’ve got a number
of brothers who put a lot of effort
in thinking about what they
would like to convey to you
before you go to your assignments.
And the first of these brothers
is Brother John Ekrann.
The theme that he selected is
“What Will You Do in the Year of the Drought?”
You students
are really like beautiful trees
planted along the river Gilead.
Jeremiah 17:8
describes such beautiful trees.
Let’s read that together,
Jeremiah 17:8.
It says: “He will become
like a tree planted by the waters,
“that sends out its roots to the stream.
“He will not notice when heat comes,
“but his leaves will always flourish.
“And in the year of drought
he will not be anxious,
nor will he quit producing fruit.”
Well, you’ve enjoyed
the spiritual waters
taught here at Gilead.
And as you graduate today
and you go off to your assignments,
your leaves are flourishing
and you’re producing fruit,
figuratively speaking.
Now, did you notice,
though, in verse 8
what the righteous trees
had to deal with?
It says “when [the] heat comes”
and “in the year of drought.”
Now, it doesn’t say if the heat comes
but when the heat comes.
So, what is that heat
and year of drought?
While there are many forms
of heat we deal with
(and in addition to what you
considered about this verse in class),
I’d like to focus
on one particular form of heat,
and that is persecution.
Restrictions on our work and bans
are designed to create fear.
Negative articles in the media
about Jehovah’s Witnesses
are designed to create doubt.
Religious leaders and opposers
—they attack our neutrality,
our clear support for the Bible’s view
of sex and marriage,
or discipline by disfellowshipping,
and other matters.
And add to that,
some of our brothers
are being rounded up
and thrown into prison.
We can say that Satan
has truly “turned up the heat.”
What will happen to the trees?
Will fear and doubt cause them
to shrivel up and die
during the drought?
No.
If you notice there in verse 8,
Jehovah says that the righteous
‘will not notice the heat’
and ‘not be anxious in the drought.’
Well, why is Jehovah confident
that the righteous trees
won’t notice the heat
and won’t wither up
in the drought?
Look at verse 7
of Jeremiah 17.
It says: “Blessed is the man
who puts his trust in Jehovah,
whose confidence is in Jehovah.”
So, what will you do
in the year of drought?
Trust in Jehovah.
Satan wants to destroy
our trust in Jehovah.
Right from the very first with Eve:
“Is it really so?”
His whole system is built on fear,
uncertainty, and doubt.
Persecution—we could liken it
to when you’re in an airplane;
and it has some turbulence;
and it begins to shake.
One flight I was on,
there was one woman
that cried in terror.
She screamed out loud every time
the plane shook even just a little.
She was genuinely terrified.
I felt sorry for her.
But the experienced flyers
—they were eating,
reading, watching movies;
they didn’t even notice
the turbulence.
Why?
Well, from experience,
they knew
that the plane could easily handle
such a small amount of turbulence,
and they were not worried.
It was designed for that.
Well, we are like experienced flyers.
We don’t let the turbulence,
or persecution, of this system
cause us fear or doubt.
With Jehovah and Jesus
as our pilots,
we don’t need to be anxious,
do we?
Let’s consider two ways
that we can show trust in Jehovah
as Jeremiah 17:7 says.
First, we’re going to talk about trusting
“the faithful and discreet slave”
and trusting Bible principles.
Let’s talk first about trusting
the faithful and discreet slave.
The faithful and discreet slave
has been selected
and appointed by Jehovah,
and experience has shown
that we can trust them.
Trust is built
by repeated good experiences.
Think of all
the good experiences we’ve had
with the faithful and discreet slave
and following their direction.
Now, some might reason:
‘Well, you know, the direction
from the faithful and discreet slave
‘is good for the United States,
but they don’t understand here.
‘They don’t understand my assignment
where I’ve been assigned.
We need to do things differently.’
Trust in the faithful and discreet slave
is not geographical.
Jehovah’s direction
through the faithful and discreet slave
applies to all of God’s people
all over the earth.
Fear is really a loss of memory
of what Jehovah has done for us.
Satan wants us to forget
all the good experiences we’ve had
with the faithful and discreet slave
and let one moment of fear get to us
and cause us to wither in the heat.
Second Thessalonians 2:2 says
“not to be quickly shaken
from your reason nor to be alarmed,”
especially at rumors.
Now, your trust
in the faithful and discreet slave
is going to be put to the test.
Satan will make sure of that.
It could be your own thoughts
of ‘I know better,’
or maybe some twisted lies
you read or hear.
Either way, it’s a trap.
Stay away from such ideas.
Trust what you know
about the faithful and discreet slave.
As Isaiah 30:15 says:
“Your strength will be
in keeping calm and showing trust.”
Remember,
the faithful and discreet slave
has been selected
and appointed by Jehovah,
and our experience
has shown that we can trust them.
Now let’s consider
trusting Bible principles, our second point.
Bible principles
are timeless pearls
of wisdom from Jehovah.
But many people today
attack our decision
to live by Bible principles
in this modern world.
They say, “That’s outdated.”
However, we trust Bible principles
because experience tells us
they always work.
I asked one sister what helps her to be calm
in very difficult, or trying, situations.
And she said, “Give me a scripture.”
Jesus’ mother, Mary,
had that same
“give-me-a-scripture” attitude.
Luke 2:51 says
that Mary made it her habit
to keep “these sayings in her heart.”
Mary was really like a tree,
soaking in all of these waters
of Jesus’ teachings
and his amazing miracles.
Well, the heat for Mary came
when the Pharisees and Sadducees,
maybe even her own family,
and her neighbors began to attack Jesus,
call him names, slander his reputation,
and attack his motives.
What helped Mary
to deal with the heat?
Those waters
that she had treasured up in her heart.
What Bible principles
and experiences
are you keeping
in your heart
to help you
when you come under attack?
Be like Mary and keep in your heart
your good experiences
in applying Bible principles.
Stick to what you know works
—Bible principles.
They always work,
and they never get out of date.
Not you or anyone else
can come up
with better principles to live by.
Remember, we trust Bible principles
because they come from Jehovah
and our own experience tells us
they always work.
Now, trusting
the faithful and discreet slave
and trusting the Bible
are just two of many ways
that we can show
that we trust Jehovah.
So, what will you do
in the year of drought?
Trust in Jehovah.
Think of the birds.
When they’re flying high up there,
are they worried?
‘Oh, I think I’m going to fall.
I’m really worried.’
Well, no.
Birds don’t worry about that, do they?
Why? Well, they rely on the wings
and instincts Jehovah gave them.
They can fly.
Likewise, we don’t need to be anxious
when faced with lies,
bans, or attacks
on our Bible principles.
Jehovah has given us
what we need to fly, so to speak
—the faithful and discreet slave,
Bible principles,
prayer,
holy spirit, and more.
As we head further into this system
and as the heat
from this system intensifies, remember,
fear and doubt are reactions,
but our decision
is trust and courage.
Well, thank you very much, Brother Ekrann.
We really appreciated that.
I neglected to mention that Brother Ekrann
is a helper to the Coordinators’ Committee.
As chairman, you’d probably appreciate
that it’s hard for me to take notes.
There are a few other things
that I’m worried about.
But I did jot down a few things here:
“Drought won’t make us doubt.
Trust is a must.”
So hopefully, I’ve got something
I’ll remember from Brother Ekrann’s talk.
Well, now Brother William Turner,
who is a helper to the Service Committee,
is giving us a challenging question.
The theme is
“Have You Become a Different Person?”
Well, I think it’s safe to say
that with all of the training
and instruction you’ve received,
you definitely are not
the same individuals you were
when you first arrived at Patterson.
But how exactly have you changed,
and why is it important
that you continue to do so?
Well, let’s consider this
by looking at someone who,
just like you,
received a special privilege.
His privilege was being
the first divinely selected king of Israel.
So the man was Saul.
When Saul was anointed,
the prophet Samuel
gave him three prophetic signs
in order to confirm
that Jehovah was with him.
I invite you
to turn with me in your Bibles,
please,
to 1 Samuel chapter 10.
And as we read verse 6,
note what was to happen after the last sign.
Chapter 10, verse 6, says:
“The spirit of Jehovah
will empower you,
“and you will prophesy
along with them
and be changed
into a different person.”
Now, what did this change mean?
Would Saul all of a sudden
become unrecognizable?
Or would there be
a drastic change in his personality?
Well, let’s go back
one chapter to chapter 9.
In verse 21, here we get
a glimpse of Saul’s personality
before he was appointed as king.
Verse 21 says:
“At this Saul answered:
“‘Am I not a Benjaminite
of the smallest of the tribes of Israel,
“‘and my family
the most insignificant
“‘of all the families
of the tribe of Benjamin?
So why have you spoken
to me in this way?’”
So Saul shows himself
to be a very humble,
modest individual.
Well, how about
after his appointment as king?
Let’s go back to chapter 10.
If you look in verse 22,
here we see Saul’s introduction
as king to the people.
Verse 22 says:
“So they inquired of Jehovah:
“‘Has the man come here yet?’
“Jehovah answered: ‘There he is
hiding himself among the luggage.’”
—so evidently still modest,
still humble.
Interestingly,
the Insight book mentions
that about a month
after his appointment as king,
Saul gained a couple
of great military victorie
against the Ammonites
and later against the Philistines.
So now, you think about that.
How did Saul change,
and rather quickly,
from bashfully hiding
among luggage
to leading a nation to victory?
That is evidence
of the power of God’s spirit
and the impact that it can have
when one allows it
to be operative in their lives.
So, what’s the lesson?
All of you
have manifested qualities
that are very pleasing
and useful to Jehovah.
It has allowed you
to be productive in your assignment.
It’s allowed you to now have
this privilege of Gilead training.
But as you now
go to your assignments,
you’re going to continue to need
to have that spirit
operative in your life.
And just as we’ve seen
in the case of Saul,
that will not always mean
a drastic change in your personality.
Perhaps when we think
of that expression
of someone
becoming a different person,
maybe that’s where our mind goes
—to someone
who has come out of Satan’s world,
now into Jehovah’s organization,
and they put on the new personality.
And that’s correct.
But the reality is that all Christians,
even those spiritually mature,
need to be adjusted from time to time,
and those adjustments
can have a tremendous impact.
Perhaps your personality is such
that you are
naturally shy and reserved.
Maybe you would be quite comfortable,
no problem, staying with the luggage.
But now having God’s spirit
coupled with appreciation
for what you’ve learned
will now perhaps move you
to come out of your comfort zone
—to initiate ways to share things
that you’ve learned with others.
Or maybe before you came to Gilead,
you had very good leadership skills.
You had a take-charge personality
—one who got things done.
But now you may see
the need to adjust.
You recognize there is wisdom
in perhaps slowing down,
or even waiting,
perhaps even seeking input
from others.
With the help of God’s spirit,
it can help you
to become a kinder overseer,
a better shepherd,
one who is more tolerant,
empathetic of others.
It’s just tremendous benefits
all the way around.
But the extent
that you become different
depends upon you
and your response to God’s spirit.
Now, obviously, we know Saul’s story;
it does not end well.
Instead of maintaining
his reliance on Jehovah,
he begins
to trust his own judgment.
He focuses more
on his position as king
than he does
on his relationship with God.
And it’s quite interesting,
if you are still in chapter 10,
if you look in verse 27,
where Saul had God’s spirit
even when he encountered challenges
—in this particular case,
some questioning his appointment—
you’ll notice
that Saul didn’t feel the need
to prove himself
or challenge the men.
He just stayed silent
and focused on his assignment.
But you read a little later
that when he lost God’s spirit
and when that bad spirit
began to take over him,
well, now the negative comments
—the comments of others:
“Saul has struck down his thousands
and David his tens of thousands”
—oh, well, now it’s an issue.
It’s a problem.
It affected his judgment;
it affected his emotions
and caused him to make bad decisions.
So, what can help you
to avoid that
and to keep your focus?
Well, let’s look at the example
of the other Saul
that’s mentioned in the Bible
—the man who later
became the apostle Paul.
Now, we know, obviously, Paul’s personality
needed more than a refinement.
Paul needed a complete overhaul.
But he truly became a different person
by way of God’s spirit.
And he was given a privilege
to serve as “an apostle to the nations.”
But if you turn
to 1 Corinthians chapter 15,
let’s just note
the attitude that Paul showed.
At 1 Corinthians 15:9,
he says:
“For I am the least of the apostles,
“and I’m not worthy
of being called an apostle,
“because I persecuted
the congregation of God.
“But by God’s undeserved kindness
I am what I am.”
Beautiful perspective, isn’t it?
Now, why do you think Paul was able
to maintain this humble attitude
for the rest of his life,
whereas King Saul could not?
Well, both men knew
that it was only by means
of Jehovah’s undeserved kindness
that they could enjoy
their privilege of service.
But Paul never viewed
his privilege of service
greater than
his relationship with God.
That’s why he studied, he meditated,
he discerned God’s will for him,
and then he was alert
to follow the leadings of God’s spirit.
And in his assignment,
Paul had challenges.
You remember,
early on for parts of three years,
some of the brothers
didn’t even believe he was an apostle.
But yet he never
asserted his authority.
He never distanced himself
from his brothers;
he just loved them.
He let his example speak for him,
and you can do the same.
See, let the brothers feel.
Let them see the love
that you have for Jehovah
and the love that you have for them.
So in review, maintain
those wonderful traits
that qualified you for Gilead,
like your modesty and humility.
And then study, meditate,
continue to follow
the leadings of God’s spirit.
And when it becomes apparent
that changes need to be made
either for the sake of the work
or peace with your brother,
well, please
be willing to make them.
And if you do, you will show
that you have become
a different person
—one who is refined,
one who is useful,
one who is dearly loved
by Jehovah.
And may Jehovah
continue to bless you
and all of the hard work
that you do
in behalf of his name.
Thank you very much, Brother Turner.
We really appreciated that.
So my quick notes:
“Don’t change the change.
Continue to make the right change.”
Good.
Well, now we have the privilege of listening
to a member of the Governing Body,
Brother Kenneth Cook.
And Brother Cook
is going to talk to us on the theme
“Find Joy in Jehovah’s Gradual Blessing!”
As you know from your own life experience
and from your Gilead instruction,
Jehovah is a God of action.
And as such,
he does some things quickly, doesn’t he?
And that’s true when it’s needed,
or it’s warranted.
He makes sure it happens
just at the right time.
For example,
when a sudden stiff breeze
rushed into the upper room at Pentecost,
those present were filled with holy spirit.
In another example,
the Bible tells us
that when this world in some way says
that it has achieved “peace and security,”
what happens next?
First Thessalonians 5:3 says
that ‘sudden destruction
will come instantly on them.’
But not all things that Jehovah
causes to happen occur so quickly.
In fact, he often does things gradually.
Let’s look at two examples
and see what we can learn from them.
First, we will look
at the angels and creation,
and then resurrected ones and perfection.
Finally, we will look
at how this applies to you
and how you can find great joy
in a gradual blessing.
We begin with the angels
who were on hand
when Jehovah made
the earth and all the things in it.
What did the angels see?
Did they see an instant burst
of unimaginable power
that suddenly formed
the earth and all life on it?
Not at all.
Jehovah could have done that,
but instead he created things gradually.
Job 38:5, 6
speak of him as setting
the earth’s “measurements,”
sinking “its pedestals,”
and laying “its cornerstone.”
And in Genesis chapters 1 and 2,
we also read
about how he gradually brought forth
life on earth and ultimately humans.
Imagine the joy
that his angelic sons experienced
as they watched
what Jehovah was gradually doing.
For example, undoubtedly,
the angels could see
that their heavenly Father
received great satisfaction
from a job well done.
They would also learn about facets
of Jehovah’s marvelous personality
as they observed everything
from the first whale
breaching the surface of an ocean
to a hummingbird hovering
over a beautiful flower
or seeing lion cubs playing together.
So stupendous was Jehovah’s work
and so enriching this experience
for his angelic sons,
that Job 38:7 tells us
that at some point,
on seeing all of this
and seeing the earth formed,
they “began shouting in applause.”
That gradual blessing
is something that the faithful angels
will never forget.
In fact, God’s Word tells us that the angels
are still focused
on what Jehovah is doing on the earth,
especially with regard to his people.
First Peter 1:12 says
that “into these very things,
angels are desiring to peer.”
So then, do the angels find pleasure
in Jehovah’s gradual work and blessing?
Yes, they do.
And aren’t we grateful
that they love Jehovah so much
as well as each one of us?
What do we learn from their response
to Jehovah’s gradual work?
We learn to treasure every moment
in Jehovah’s service and to be grateful
for every opportunity we have
to learn more about him.
So be like the angels and, in effect,
shout in applause
at each new thing you learn
about our heavenly Father.
Take time to meditate on his works,
on his Word of truth,
and on his indescribable mercy
toward us through his Son.
In our next example,
we look to the future
but not too far into the future.
We’re talking about the resurrection
—specifically the resurrection
and perfection.
When Jehovah through his Son
resurrects countless millions
to life again in the new world,
they will not all come back
at the same time,
nor will they come back in perfection.
But Jehovah
will bring them back in such a way
that they will know themselves;
they will recognize themselves.
Although their serious infirmities will be gone,
they will instantly know
their own familiar thoughts and feelings.
They will know who they are as a person.
Imagine the joy that such ones will have
as they apply what they learn
and then see the progress
that they are making day after day
in serving Jehovah.
They will experience the words
of Proverbs 10:22 coming true for them.
Please follow along,
where it says in verse 22:
“It is the blessing of Jehovah
that makes one rich,
and he adds no pain with it.”
So, what will God’s gradual blessing do
for such ones at that time?
His blessing will make them rich
in the most important way of all
—and that is spiritually.
Things that they struggle
to be able to overcome
in this old world under man’s control
and Satan’s influence,
they will be able to overcome
because they love Jehovah
and he will help them to do so.
But even more than this,
in the new world,
millions and millions of people
will come to experience physical vitality
and strength that exceeds
anything imaginable today.
Jehovah’s gradual blessing will take hold,
and grateful ones will rejoice day after day.
Also important is the fact
that as each person grows
toward perfection,
they will keep hold
of the empathy needed
to teach and help still others
who will come back
in a gradual resurrection.
How can contemplating
such future blessings benefit us?
benefit you right now?
We benefit
when we patiently focus on Jehovah
and how he often fulfills his promises
in a gradual way.
Having this in mind
keeps us grounded, you could say.
We do our best, but we do not expect
everything right now, do we,
especially perfection?
That is yet in the future.
However, when we develop strong faith,
we will find joy
no matter what we will yet face.
Why?
Because we are absolutely certain
that Jehovah’s promises
will come true, right on time.
Now we get to the part
that especially involves you.
As one graduating from Gilead School,
you may look back
on the past five months
and worry that you
did not do everything perfectly.
I know that’s how I would feel,
but please don’t focus on that.
Instead, imagine the joy that you will find
as you patiently apply
the things that you have learned
and then you see
Jehovah’s gradual blessing on your efforts.
Remember, a head full of knowledge
is not what brings Jehovah’s blessing.
What matters
is what we do with what we know.
Consider the example of King Solomon.
First Kings 4:32 says
that ‘he composed 3,000 proverbs
and 1,005 songs.’
But there was a disconnect
between what was in his mind
and what was
really driving him from the heart.
And as a result,
Solomon drifted
away from Jehovah, didn’t he?
The Bible tells us that his foreign wives
gradually inclined his heart
away from Jehovah.
So you could say that he, in effect,
substituted one gradual thing
for another gradual thing.
In turn, he lost the opportunity
to find joy in Jehovah’s gradual blessing.
Now, in contrast to that example,
make it your heart’s desire
to be like the faithful angels.
Although they undoubtedly know
far more than 3,000 proverbs and songs,
they savor every morsel that they learn
about our magnificent heavenly Father.
And again, as you look to the future
—to the real life—
take what you have learned
in this beautiful schooling
and humbly work for the interests of others.
Jehovah will bless that effort,
and the gradual blessing
that you will enjoy will serve as a taste
of what is yet ahead in God’s new world.
Keep in mind that those who find joy now
in a gradual blessing
will have no problem
in patiently waiting for
and then enjoying
the gradual blessings that are still to come.
Thank you very much, Brother Cook.
We truly appreciated those fine comments.
I just had a brief note here:
“Expect the unexpected gradually.”
Well, I’m sure we all got that point,
and we’ll enjoy looking forward
to seeing that program, or that talk,
again and going through the main points.
Now, for you students,
you’re about to be addressed
by one of your instructors from Gilead.
You’ve heard
from Brother Cauthon a number of times,
and now he’s going
to address you this final time
on this intriguing theme
“Shoulder to Shoulder.”
By the spring of 1945,
Allied and Russian armies
were converging upon Germany.
The Nazis were losing the war.
The Germans gave the ominous order:
March all the concentration camp prisoners west,
and destroy all the evidence of the horrors
that had taken place in those camps.
On the 20th of April,
the evacuation of Sachsenhausen began.
The plan was to march
the prisoners to the Baltic Coast,
ship them out to sea, and drown them.
And if that wasn’t horrific enough,
the SS guards had explicit orders
to shoot any of the prisoners
who couldn’t keep up.
Already in a weakened state,
hundreds were shot along the way,
while many thousands more died
of exposure, starvation, and exhaustion.
Thus began what came to be known
as a death march.
Interestingly,
the Sachsenhausen evacuation
included 230 of our brothers.
And just like the other prisoners,
they were in no shape
to make this journey physically,
but they were
more than up to the journey spiritually.
How so?
Well, open your Bibles, if you would,
to a promise Jehovah made.
It’s found at Zephaniah 3:9.
And here,
he promised to give to his people
a pure language.
And the point being
so that they could do what?
The latter part of that verse says
“to serve him shoulder to shoulder”
or, as the footnote says, “in unity.”
And that was the key.
The secret weapon
was their shoulder-to-shoulder unity.
Even the weak become strong
when they are united.
Now, today,
you and I are on a march for life.
And never forget
that we’re not marching alone.
We have our brothers and sisters
from all backgrounds and all ages
along with us for the journey.
But the question is,
Are we marching shoulder to shoulder?
What can we learn from our brothers
who went through this death march?
Well, first of all,
to reach the coast,
the Sachsenhausen prisoners
were to march 155 miles
—that’s 250 kilometers.
And throughout that journey,
the Witnesses pooled all their food supplies
into one small bundle
that was used for the benefit of all.
Now, you can imagine
that sharing food is not an easy thing to do
when you’ve already been starved
and you’re very weak.
But our brothers knew Bible principles,
such as the one at Proverbs 11:25 that says:
“The generous person will prosper,
and whoever refreshes others
will himself be refreshed.”
So, what’s the lesson for us today?
The lesson is this:
Unity to be real
must withstand the severest test.
Being a true Christian
is more than a commitment to God;
it is a commitment to other Christians as well.
So don’t hold back.
Show a generous disposition
in your assignment.
And remember,
one of the most important resources
that you can share with others is your time.
So learn the balance.
Take time with others who may need it,
and don’t be ruled by time.
Rather than rush, refresh.
Second point:
When the SS guards
gave the Witnesses a cart to haul,
that easily could have seemed
like just another burden to bear,
but instead our brothers were thrilled.
Why?
Because they saw it as an opportunity.
How so?
Well, during the journey,
the sick and elderly ones
were able to sit
on top of the cart and rest for a while,
and then when one
would get his strength back,
another one would replace him.
And so in a very real way,
they carried one another.
The lesson for us?
Where there is unity, there is victory.
And in the middle of difficulty, lies opportunity.
So look for opportunities
to encourage one another.
The word “encourage” literally means
“to make strong or to hearten.”
Being spiritual people,
we may not lose our hope
but we could lose heart,
especially during times
of extreme crisis or grief.
But something
as simple as a reassuring word
or even a kind deed
can work like a miracle.
It can restore the weary soul.
It can carry others through a hard time.
So the point is this:
You’re not responsible
for everyone in the Christian congregation,
but you are responsible to them.
Jehovah expects us to do
whatever we can to help our brothers.
We simply cannot allow ourselves
to be separated in interest
or divided in purpose.
And then one more point:
On their last night,
the prisoners were stopped near a forest.
The SS guards encouraged
everyone to walk across to freedom.
Imagine you were there.
It must have seemed very tempting.
But naturally,
they were unsure of what to do,
so they prayed for guidance
and unitedly they decided to stay put
—not one of them left the group.
Later, it was learned that those
who had accepted the offer
were shot down.
The lesson for us?
Don’t allow anything
or anyone to cause division.
Satan is the master of divide and conquer.
We must stand together until forever.
When problems arise,
you can use your energy
for retaliation or resolution, but not both.
The Bible says:
“Have intense love for one another.”
So don’t allow differences
to develop into distance,
and don’t nurture past offenses.
The brotherhood is a place
where mistakes are not rubbed in
but rubbed out.
To recap:
We serve God in part, brothers,
by serving others.
Willingly share
your resources with one another,
especially your time.
It’s in times
of deep crisis and grief and doubt
that we need each other the most.
When you see
a brother’s or a sister’s shoulders
beginning to droop,
pull out your “cart” for them.
Do what is needed
even if it’s difficult or inconvenient.
Remember, our actions
reveal what’s in our heart,
whether we like it or not.
Have intense love for one another;
remain united in heart and mind;
continue committed to one another
as you are to Jehovah God and Jesus Christ.
And finally,
there is beauty and power in unity.
Jehovah is creating a new world,
brothers and sisters, a new world.
One world, one people
—a new world society of unified worshippers.
Stay focused on that fact.
In conclusion,
over 10,700 lost their lives
on that infamous death march
from Sachsenhausen,
but not one,
not one of our 230 brothers lost their life.
Why?
Well, let’s let them
tell us in their own words.
Here’s a quotation from a resolution
made by our brothers in that forest
just before their freedom.
I quote:
‘A long, hard time of trial is behind us
‘and we have been brought forth
from the fiery furnace
‘without a scent of the fire upon us.
‘On the contrary,
‘we are full of power and strength in Jehovah.
‘We have only one desire
‘after our stay in the “lions’ den.”
‘We will serve Jehovah throughout eternity.
This would be our most precious reward.’
It’s signed:
“YOUR CO-FIGHTERS
FOR JEHOVAH’S HOLY NAME.”
You see, they didn’t pretend to be brothers;
they were brothers.
They functioned as one united family
throughout the whole ordeal,
and they were victorious.
And so, as this world
grows colder and colder, brothers,
let us be more determined than ever
to serve our God shoulder to shoulder.
Well, thank you so much, Brother Cauthon.
There were so many excellent points in that talk.
What did I write down to remind me?
“Shoulder to shoulder.”
I did also write down, though:
“Imperfections—don’t rub in, rub out.”
Well, there are a lot of good points
that you dear students,
soon-to-be graduates,
are taking down, I’m sure.
Now you’re going to listen
to another brother who’s very familiar to you
—one of your instructors.
But the difference is that this time
you’re not going to be looking at him
and thinking of written exercises.
But you’re going to be thinking,
‘Well, I can sit back and enjoy these comments.’
Brother Mark Noumair,
a helper to the Teaching Committee
as well as an instructor of Gilead,
will now talk to you on the theme
“Four Words to Live By.”
Can there really be four words
that you can base your life on?
And if so, what would they be?
Well, we look
to our Exemplar, Christ Jesus, for the answer.
We focus on the night before his death.
The future of every human being
rested upon his shoulders.
His words, his actions,
his very thoughts in these critical moments
would be remembered for thousands of years.
What would he give the world to remember?
He left no room for guesswork.
In one verse, one verse,
Jesus reveals what governed
his every action and his decision
—in one verse.
Four words
—four words that he lived by—
and we encourage you
to live by these four words.
We encourage you
to take these four words to heart.
Take them seriously.
They’re found at John 14:31,
John 14:31,
the last night of Jesus life:
“But for the world to know
that I love the Father.”
“I love the Father.”
In these four words,
we find the most powerful bond in the universe
—an unbreakable bond of love
between Jesus and his Father.
And it is this unbreakable attachment
that enabled Jesus to unselfishly defend
his Father’s reputation to his dying breath,
trusting that Jehovah
would protect and resurrect him.
“I love the Father.”
But how did this love develop?
How did this unbreakable bond,
this attachment of love, develop?
Well, the only-begotten Son was created perfect.
True.
However, was he created
with love already fully developed?
No.
He was created with free will;
Satan was created with free will
and with the capacity to extend,
enlarge, and enrich this love.
The Son of God
was not created
with an unselfish, self-sacrificing love
already fully in place.
What did he have to do?
He had to cultivate
this deep attachment for his Father,
cultivate this deep love.
How did he do that?
By observing his Father’s personality.
In his prehuman existence,
imagine how the Son would do this.
He would observe closely
how his Father used his power,
how he used his authority,
how he used his strength
in behalf of people
—‘those crushed, those lowly in spirit.’
He would observe
how his Father used his power
to help those “crushed in spirit.”
He watched his Father
deal with Ruth the Moabite girl
—a Moabite girl from a pagan nation.
Might he have thought: ‘Now, a Moabite girl?
‘Weren’t these the Moabite women—?
‘Weren’t these the very women
that lured the Israelite men into immorality
right on the threshold of the Promised Land?’
True.
But his Father saw that this girl was different.
She was different.
What a lesson for the Son of God!
His Father did not put people in categories;
he did not stereotype individuals.
‘Oh, that’s the Moabite girl.
I’m not going to deal with her.’
No.
Jehovah God looked at Ruth as an individual.
And the Son’s love must have grown
as now He allows this girl—
He allows a Bible book
to be named in behalf of her
—Ruth as opposed to Naomi or Boaz—
Ruth, a Moabite girl.
That’s right.
And the Son’s love would’ve continued to grow
when he observed
how his Father then allowed this girl
to become an ancestress to the Messiah.
But watching and admiring
his Father wasn’t enough.
He went further.
As the Son continued to develop appreciation
for his Father’s qualities,
this bond of love
became more than just a feeling.
No.
His love for his Father
began to shape his decisions and actions,
and Jesus demonstrated this
when he was on earth.
He didn’t just say the words,
“I love the Father.”
He didn’t just feel the words
—feel “I love the Father’s cozy, warm, little feeling.”
No, no, no.
He lived those words,
and that is why Jesus could say
in the second half of John 14:31:
“I am doing just as the Father
has commanded me to do.”
“I am doing”
—you see, his entire life course
proved that he loved the Father.
For example,
when a Syrophoenician woman
begged Jesus
to cure her demonized daughter,
initially Jesus said:
‘No,
I was sent forth not to the Gentiles
but to the Jews.’
But the woman would not give up,
and showing her faith,
she kept asking and asking.
So in light of this exceptional circumstance,
Jesus could see that this was no time
to enforce a general rule
or to stereotype people
or to become inflexible
or to put her in a category.
‘Oh, no. You’re a Gentile.
You’re Syrophoenician. No, no.’
No, Jesus saw this was a time to bend
in response to higher principles.
Did he remember
how his Father handled that situation with Ruth?
And this moved him to say:
‘My Father did that with Ruth.
‘Now we have a similar situation.
What would my Father want me to do?’
Jesus helped the Syrophoenician woman.
He was ready to act
in imitation of his Father’s love.
Another example
would be what Jesus learned
from his Father about forgiveness.
He watched his Father forgive
—forgive people.
He watched his Father
forgive David for adultery,
forgive David for the murder of Uriah.
How many others
did the Son of God watch?
did he watch his Father forgive?
The Hebrew Scriptures
are replete with Jehovah forgiving people.
He’s a largehearted Forgiver.
He’s ready to forgive.
He’s on the lookout to forgive.
That’s what the Son of God learned.
So this no doubt helped him
to deal with the frequency
of the imperfections
of the apostles and others.
Jesus viewed forgiving others
as an opportunity to imitate his Father
—another opportunity to allow his actions
to declare loud and clear
“like Father, like Son.”
He didn’t just say, “I love the Father.”
He didn’t just feel it; he lived it.
Now we take this discussion out of the classroom
and apply it to your real-life situations.
Right after Jesus said,
“I love the Father,”
he said,
“Get up, let us go from here.”
Well, soon you’re going to get up
and you’re going to go from here,
and you don’t know what tests of faith
are going to come upon you.
You don’t know.
We can’t anticipate every test
that’s going to come upon us of faith.
However,
if you know these four words,
you know enough.
Etch these four words
“I love the Father”
on your minds and on your hearts.
Let these four words govern
every decision and action of yours.
For example,
if you’re entrusted with authority,
how will you treat people?
How will you treat those under you?
Learn from Jesus on this last night.
His words could’ve been all about himself.
‘For the world to know
‘that I am the Son of God,
‘“the firstborn of all creation.”
I’m the second greatest personage in the universe.’
Or he could’ve said,
‘I plan to surrender my life for you
as the ransom sacrifice for you.’
Or, ‘I am the one
—I’m the one who fulfills all prophecy.’
But none of his thoughts were about himself,
his authority, or his accomplishments.
So like Jesus, don’t focus on your position.
Show by your dealings with others
that your heartfelt desire and motives
are to please your heavenly Father.
That’s what you want to do.
So as you go from here,
who will be your “Ruth”?
Show that you don’t put people in categories.
Show it.
Instead of that department,
that nationality, that language group,
or those sisters,
who will be your “Syrophoenician woman”?
Seize opportunities to be
more flexible and reasonable.
Discern when it will be a time to bend
in response to higher principles
rather than always being
on the lookout to check and correct.
Work hard to acquire thinking ability
—thinking ability that will assist you
to respond to higher principles.
Developing thinking ability is not easy
because as you begin to think about a person,
often your emotional reactions
toward that person start interfering.
You begin registering likes, dislikes,
respect, disrespect,
trust, distrust
—reacting emotionally
before beginning an intellectual appraisal.
But if you make decisions
solely based on feelings
that have slipped in
under the guise of thoughts,
this often leads to poor decisions.
So listen
to what I’m going to tell you right now.
Ask yourself,
‘Will my decision-making process
‘—will it be in response to higher principles
or simply because I do or don’t like the person?’
When it’s a response to higher principles,
now you’re strengthening
and stabilizing the organization.
Who will be
your imperfect, disappointing “apostles”?
Be on the lookout
for opportunities to be more forgiving,
more patient with the shortcomings of others.
Maybe you’re an overseer
and your imperfect, disappointing “apostles”
will be those working under you.
For others, it might be a fellow translator
or a workmate in your department
that disappoints you.
If this happens,
will these four words govern your thinking?
They did for one sister.
This is what she says:
“Something that happened
in my department hurt me deeply,
“and it shook me to my very core.
“And since then, I struggle
with constant feelings of inadequacy.
“I felt completely discouraged and dried up.
“However, I’m not a quitter.
“I will cling to Jehovah and not let go.
“I love Jehovah above everything,
“and I’m sure
that I will overcome my negative feelings
and will become
stronger spiritually and mentally.”
She didn’t just say the words
“I love the Father”;
she lived those words
—four words
that gave her a proper perspective
and balance in life.
So it comes down to this:
When you cherish Jehovah’s approval
and your unbreakable bond of love for him
and this spiritual relationship overrides,
or supersedes, our human sphere of activity,
not much else matters.
How do you reach that point?
By thinking deeply
on Jehovah’s way of doing things,
then loving those ways,
and then imitating your heavenly Father.
At John 13:15, Jesus said:
“I set the pattern for you.”
And it’s a pattern
that we are confident that you will follow.
Like Jesus, show the world.
It’s your opportunity now to show the world
that you too can meet any challenge
and test of faith that comes your way.
We know you can do it;
we have confidence in you.
Why do we know you can do it?
Because you are clothed
with the most unbreakable bond in the universe
and empowered
by the unfailing four words to live by,
“I love the Father.”
Well, even though you
were able to listen to Brother Noumair
and not have a written exercise afterward,
I’m sure, like me,
you wrote down those four words:
“I love the Father.”
Thank you very much, Brother Noumair.
We really appreciated that.
And truly, there’s been
an abundance of good points
that we’ve learned
from the program so far.
And then, all of a sudden, I realized
that this program is going to be broadcast
on JW Broadcasting in 163 languages,
so I don’t have to take notes after all.
What an exciting and upbuilding program!
And don’t forget to tune in later this month
for Parts 2 and 3 of this special event.
To conclude,
we’d like to share greetings from Taiwan.
Taiwan is a Southeast Asian island
over 35,000 square kilometers,
or nearly 13,000 square miles, in size.
It’s densely populated
with over 23 million inhabitants.
The first Westerner who saw this island
named it Ilha Formosa, or “Island Beautiful.”
And it’s not hard to see why.
Taiwan has a beautiful coastline, fertile land,
and majestic mountains
covered in thick, luxuriant forests.
The majority of the population
live on the narrow coastal plains,
where you’ll find large bustling cities.
Manufacturing and exporting various goods
drives the economy in Taiwan.
The official language of Taiwan
is Mandarin Chinese.
However, there are
also 16 recognized indigenous language groups.
One of the languages
that our brothers reach out to is Amis.
In January 2018,
the Amis remote translation office
was opened in Hualien City.
They translate written publications
and produce audio publications in Amis.
In the Hualien Amis Congregation,
there are 80 publishers.
Five serve as elders and 22 are regular pioneers.
They conduct over 70 Bible studies each month.
These brothers search out
Amis-speaking people in Hualien City,
where they live
alongside Chinese- and Min Nan-speaking people.
In the mountains,
Amis-speaking people are more isolated,
so our brothers travel long distances,
using scooters,
to share the good news with them.
The brothers and sisters
in the Hualien Amis Congregation
send you their warm love.
From the world headquarters
of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
this is JW Broadcasting.