When Paul wrote the letter to the Colossians,
it was in the year 60-61 C.E.,
just similar to the time
that he wrote Ephesians,
which we talked about yesterday.
And he wrote for similar reasons
—to protect his brothers
from the immoral environment
that was around them
and to encourage them
to fight against the weaknesses
of the flesh.
So let’s open our Bibles
to Colossians chapter 3,
and we’ll read verse 5 in its entirety.
Colossians 3:5:
“Deaden, therefore, your body members
“that are on the earth
as respects sexual immorality, uncleanness,
“uncontrolled sexual passion, hurtful desire,
and greediness, which is idolatry.”
And we’ve been told
that these expressions
convey the idea
of totally wiping out these desires.
When we sense them
coming up in our heart and mind,
we slay them;
we wipe them out.
And it’s very important
because to fail to do that
puts us into all sorts
of difficulties with Jehovah
and with others
and causes problems for ourselves.
Look at verse 6:
“On account of those things
the wrath of God is coming.”
So it affects our everlasting future
as well, doesn’t it?
One thing that is highlighted here
is how serious these desires can become.
They get bound up with greediness,
covetousness, which is idolatry.
And covetousness has been described
as something that is insatiable.
It’s always after something
that it should not have
or it does not have the right to have.
It’s ruthless and self-seeking;
it has been defined as that.
And a covetous person,
or a greedy person,
makes the object of his desire so strong
that in essence it can become his god.
And that reminds us of the inspired words
at Philippians 3:18, 19,
where Paul used a similar expression
about those who used to be with him
in the truth but no longer were,
and he was very sad about that.
And what happened to them?
Well,
“their god [became] their belly,”
and their desires overwhelmed
even their love for Jehovah.
And it was back in 1978
that The Watchtower,
in the April 1 issue,
said this about this quality of greed
—covetousness—
and idolatry.
It said this:
‘If we become aware of a wrong desire
‘building up within ourselves,
‘we do well to call to mind
‘how precious
our relationship with God is
‘and how senseless
it would be to forfeit this
by making oneself an idolater.’
So that’s a very serious thought, isn’t it?
That a person
could actually start worshipping something
other than Jehovah.
And that was a very serious sin
even in ancient Israel, wasn’t it,
this matter of idolatry?
It carried the death penalty.
But, you know, another aspect
of the Ten Commandments
that carried the death penalty
was adultery.
So, what is the similarity
between idolatry and the death penalty
and adultery and the death penalty?
Well, worshipping an idol,
a person would break
his covenant with Jehovah.
And committing adultery,
he would break
his covenant with his spouse.
So why would Jehovah
feel so strongly about that?
Well, let’s open our Bibles to Psalm 33,
and we’ll look at the kind of person
Jehovah is when it comes to his word
and what he says.
Psalm 33, let’s read verse 4:
“For the word of Jehovah is upright,
and everything he does is trustworthy.”
And then look at verse 9:
“For he spoke, and it came to be;
he commanded, and it stood firm.”
So the psalmist is saying,
“When Jehovah says something, he means it.”
And so when a person says to Jehovah,
“I’m going to worship you exclusively”
and he doesn’t,
it’s treachery.
It’s unlike God, Jehovah.
It’s like the Devil,
who is a liar and untrustworthy.
So it adds weight, doesn’t it,
to our desire never to fall victim
to idolatry in any form?
Now, our comments in The Watchtower
(which we’ll read a little bit later today
in the actual printed comment)
do focus on this matter of marriage
and adultery and avoiding that,
of course.
And what we’d like to do now
is just take a few moments
and highlight some dangers
that could come up for married people
and see how that applies
to deadening, or slaying,
those desires
right from the very beginning
so that they do not flourish
and cause a problem.
One of the principles
that we can think about is Proverbs 22:3.
We see “the danger,” and we turn aside.
So, what are some things
that we could see as a danger,
identify them, and slay them
before they become a problem?
Well, obviously, what we look at,
listen to, and read
fills our mind with either good or bad,
so we avoid intake of bad things.
It only fuels bad desires.
But research has shown
and our publications have often commented
that when a person gets involved in adultery,
it isn’t always just a sexual greed,
or the sexual desire,
that motivates him
to go down that path in the first place
or her to go down
that path the first time.
Well, what is it?
Well, what is the fundamental function
of marriage?
It has often been said
that the fundamental function of marriage
is receiving and giving emotional support.
It’s a relationship
where a person feels loved,
appreciated, wanted,
and needed in a very special way.
And when a person begins
to feel that that is missing,
then they begin looking for someone
who can give them that
—not necessarily right away
sexual gratification.
And that’s why
the Awake! of January 8, ʹ86 Awake! said
that being a good listener
“has the capacity
“for making the other person feel
that he is especially valued
and what he is saying
is of concern and significance” to him.
So it’s this relationship
that needs to be guarded
—the friendship.
And the 1994 Watchtower of July 15
added weight to this comment
when it quoted a divorce attorney,
of all people.
And he said what was
the single biggest reason couples break up.
And this is what he said,
it was quoted in the magazine:
“The inability
to talk honestly with each other,
bare their souls
and treat each other as their best friend.”
That’s the main reason.
That can often lead
to other physical contact.
But it often is not
the one that gets it started.
So now, what can we do to avoid that?
Well, we want to treasure our relationships.
And it reminds us
of an experience that was given
in the August 15, 2012, Watchtower,
about an elder and pioneer named Daniel
and his wife, also pioneering.
He was very involved in the congregation
—always took on assignments.
He had three Bible students
—men—
who got baptized,
but they needed a lot of help;
they were newly baptized.
He was busy with other assignments.
His wife spent a lot of time
with these newly baptized brothers.
He was neglecting his wife.
She bonded emotionally
with one of these brothers;
adultery was committed.
But Daniel said he bore
a heavy responsibility in that respect.
In fact,
at the end of the lessons learned,
he said this:
“There is much more to life
than struggling to care for privileges
to the detriment of your own family.”
So a need for balance.
Pursuing Kingdom interests, of course
—and an understanding wife or husband
can understand and support that—
but there is a balance.
And if it oversteps itself,
then real problems can result.
So we want to do all we can
to slay desires
when we sense them in ourselves.
And it’s going to take earnest effort;
it’s going to take endurance
because as long as we’re
in this imperfect state,
no one can say,
“I am immune to any of those desires
that could crop up at different times.”
So our love for Jehovah,
our love for our mates,
our love for our brothers
prevents us
from going down
the path of greediness and idolatry,
which only results in harm.
How grateful we are to be with brothers
and sisters like you who love Jehovah,
love their marriage mates,
love the brotherhood,
and do all they can
to stay morally clean!
Keep it up with Jehovah’s help.