Young ones, it’s true
that the more you understand Jehovah,
the more you love him.
And what a blessing you have
if your family worships Jehovah with you
and teaches you how to draw close to him.
But some young ones
have had to build their faith
without their family’s support.
Listen to the experience of Ersi Royer
from the United States.
What spiritual decision did she face
at just 14 years old?
And what did she do
that illustrates the value
of deep personal study?
Growing up,
it wasn’t the typical,
“My mom is a pioneer, my dad is an elder,
and we’re doing great in the congregation.”
My family life wasn’t the best,
so why would I want to do this religion
that nobody is happy
in our family with?
And I think that can make you feel
very alone or odd
or awkward or secluded.
And at that time,
I was graduating eighth grade.
There were dances;
friends were hanging out, going to parties.
And I remember thinking:
‘Wow, these look like really nice kids.
Why aren’t I doing that?’
I hadn’t really delved into the Bible enough
to answer questions
that I really needed to know.
I went in prayer to Jehovah and said:
“I’m so sorry, but today I’m not a Witness.
I’m going to try to prove
everything that I’ve been taught is wrong.”
I asked him that if he’s real,
to help me understand.
So I went in my room
and shut the door.
I got every book off the shelf.
I started off organized,
but by the end of the evening,
I had books
all over the place with pages open.
The more I kept reading about Jehovah,
the more the next topic would take me
to then connect the scriptures.
Jesus is linked to Jehovah;
the angels are linked to Jehovah;
the resurrection is linked to Jehovah.
So you can’t believe in one thing
and not everything else
if you really want to know the truth.
And so that’s what did it for me,
especially the scripture in Psalms
when it said
that ‘you saw even the embryo of me.’
And it was an emotional scripture for me
because I thought:
‘Wow,
‘my parents aren’t doing great
in the truth right now.
‘But Jehovah found a way to find me,
‘and he knew what I could be.
‘Now I have my answer.
I don’t have an excuse.
‘Jehovah gave me enough knowledge
that now I’m responsible.
I now need to act on that
and show my love in return for him.’
Within a week, I found another sister
in the hall that was really helpful
in me getting out
in service quite often.
I don’t think to this day she ever knew
how much I appreciated that.
Although things were declining
in our family spiritually,
I was able to get baptized.
As I progressed spiritually,
I could see that I did not have
the support of my family,
but I had to trust that Jehovah
would help me through it.
And at least by the time I got home,
if there was an issue,
I had the strength of the meeting
and the brothers and sisters
and joy that they
couldn’t take away from me.
I remember I came home one day
with some friends.
It was a nice day
—encouraging, upbuilding.
We pulled into our driveway;
they dropped me off
and said good-bye.
My parents were really upset
when they came and met me at the door.
They couldn’t fully understand
why I was making my decisions
the way I was
to serve Jehovah more fully.
We just could not agree
on where my relationship
with Jehovah was going.
And at that point,
I left with the clothes on my back.
In a matter of a few minutes,
my life forever changed.
I had a spiritual aunt that took me in,
helped me gather myself together,
and literally fed me, clothed me,
helped me spiritually.
And so then, my support became Jehovah
and the congregation.
I remember that a sister told me years ago,
“Be who you needed when you were young.”
And so when I look at those little ones,
I look at myself and say,
‘How could I have benefited
from someone taking the time for me
when I was that age?’
I’ve always tried remembering the young ones
—because that’s just part of who I am—
and making sure that they know
that they’re not alone.
If there is a young one out there
who isn’t sure
if this is the truth or not,
I would like them to know
that Jehovah knows
who they are,
and he’s finding a way
for them to know him.
Jehovah is real,
he knows them by name,
he wants them to live,
and he’s fighting for them.
How amazing that young Ersi chose
to spend an entire day studying
—proving to herself
that Jehovah knew her and loved her.
But this was no onetime study marathon.
From there, she worked to develop
the study habits she needed
to endure, grow,
and become a spiritual person.
She pioneered for several years,
and now serves at Bethel
with her husband, Jeff.
In my conversation with Ersi,
she expressed her love for her family
and the hope that someday in the future
she’ll be reunited with them spiritually.