‎The scripture that we’re considering this morning
‎raises a very interesting question,
‎and that is,
‎How is it that we can ‘test Jehovah out’?
‎Didn’t Jesus say that we shouldn’t test Jehovah?
‎Well, the simple answer to that question
‎was given
‎in The Watchtower back in 1957.
‎It simply stated:
‎“There is a wrong way
‎and a right way
‎to put Jehovah to the test.”
‎Now, how do we know
‎what is the right way
‎and what is the wrong way?
‎Well, again, put simply,
‎it means knowing the difference
‎between faith and stupidity.
‎When we consider
‎what the Scriptures tell us,
‎it helps us to see the line
‎that is the demarcation
‎between faith and stupidity.
‎Consider, first of all, the good way
‎that we can test out Jehovah.
‎When we think about
‎showing faith in Jehovah,
‎having trust in him,
‎and then obeying him
‎—not waiting for Jehovah
‎to make the first move
‎but rather for us,
‎first of all, to obey him,
‎to reach out
‎and do what he wants us to do
‎—that, in a figurative way,
‎is putting him to the test,
‎because he’s already promised to bless us.
‎By us obeying him,
‎it means that we are showing faith.
‎It also means that we
‎don’t complain about the things
‎that Jehovah
‎allows to occur in our life,
‎and we don’t take unnecessary risks.
‎We don’t try to fool him
‎by acting one way
‎but then pretending to be another way.
‎So put quite simply, again,
‎the right way for us to test out Jehovah
‎means to trust him,
‎to have faith in him,
‎to obey him
‎even if it may be difficult to do so.
‎Well, what about the wrong way
‎to test out Jehovah?
‎Well, if we were to selfishly complain
‎about the things
‎that Jehovah allows to occur in our life
‎or if we were to do
‎something stupid,
‎something careless,
‎and expect that Jehovah
‎is going to perform a miracle to save us
‎or perhaps
‎we keep pushing Jehovah
‎to do something
‎that really is not in harmony with his will
‎or if we try to fool him
‎by pretending to serve him
‎but actually are doing things
‎that displease him,
‎all of those things really would be
‎a stupid act on our part.
‎Now, what do we really need to consider
‎with regard to this?
‎Well, let’s think about when Jesus
‎made that answer to Satan
‎and said,
‎‘You shouldn’t put Jehovah to the test.’
‎Let’s have a look at the scripture
‎that he based that comment on.
‎It’s found at Deuteronomy 6:16,
‎and this gives us
‎a little context to the meaning.
‎In verse 16, it says:
‎“You must not
‎put Jehovah your God to the test
‎the way you put him
‎to the test at Massah.”
‎Now, really, what was it
‎that the Israelites did
‎at this particular time
‎where the name of the location
‎where they were
‎meant “Testing” or “Trial”?
‎Well, if we turn back to Exodus 17:7,
‎it gives us some idea
‎of what this really involved.
‎Exodus 17:7:
‎“So he named the place
‎Massah and Meribah
‎“because of the quarreling of the Israelites
‎“and because they put Jehovah to the test
‎by saying:
‎‘Is Jehovah in our midst or not?’”
‎So, what did the Israelites do here?
‎Obviously, they didn’t trust Jehovah enough.
‎They didn’t have enough
‎faith in Jehovah to realize
‎that he wasn’t going
‎to let them all die in the wilderness.
‎But they pushed him.
‎They wanted something immediately.
‎They wanted to satisfy their selfish desires.
‎Well, that’s a very good lesson for us
‎—isn’t it?—
‎because this shows a lack of faith.
‎We could consider
‎when the Israelites decided
‎that they didn’t want to go
‎into the Promised Land.
‎Remember,
‎they were so upset with the report
‎of the two good chieftains
‎who had spied out the land
‎that they wanted to kill them.
‎They accepted the report
‎of the ten who had a negative report.
‎And why did they do that?
‎Again, lack of faith in Jehovah.
‎But then when Jehovah told them
‎what was going to happen,
‎the punishment
‎that was going to come on them,
‎what did they do?
‎They went straight ahead
‎and decided to go into the Promised Land.
‎And what happened?
‎You see, it was an act of stupidity.
‎They were going on their own,
‎and Jehovah
‎wasn’t going to give them support,
‎and that’s exactly what happened.
‎They were defeated.
‎So we see
‎this is a very interesting example
‎for us to understand the difference
‎between the wrong way
‎and the right way
‎of putting Jehovah to the test.
‎And, more important,
‎we need to remember
‎how Jehovah feels
‎when we put him to the test in the wrong way.
‎We can see this
‎if we turn to the book of Psalms,
‎Psalm 78:40, 41:
‎“How often they rebelled against him
‎“in the wilderness
‎and made him feel hurt in the desert!
‎“Again and again
‎they put God to the test,
‎and they grieved
‎the Holy One of Israel.”
‎Yes, by their lack of faith
‎and by doing things
‎that we could say
‎irritated or disappointed Jehovah,
‎they grieved Jehovah.
‎So this is
‎a very important matter for us:
‎to realize the difference
‎between the right and wrong way
‎of putting Jehovah to the test.
‎With regard to this,
‎what sort of things
‎do we need to avoid?
‎Well, we need to avoid dictating,
‎or demanding,
‎that Jehovah do
‎certain special things for us.
‎We need to avoid
‎complaining to him
‎about our expectations.
‎We need to avoid
‎taking unnecessary risks and chances.
‎And that’s why we have
‎a very important group of brothers
‎that help to remind us about safety.
‎We do need to remember
‎safety standards.
‎Now, some perhaps do not realize
‎the difference between faith and stupidity,
‎and they may have the viewpoint,
‎‘Well, Jehovah will look after me
‎if I’m doing whatever I’m doing.’
‎But notice what the Awake! magazine
‎said back in 1953.
‎It was in the article entitled
‎“You Must Not Put God to the Test.”
‎And this is what it says:
‎“It really amounts
‎to considering ourselves very important
‎“when we act as though
‎nothing could happen to us
‎“because we are serving Jehovah. . . .
‎“We dare not put God to the test
‎“with irrational actions and carelessness.
‎“We simply cannot expect God
‎“to furnish us angels
‎to keep us from harm and accident
‎in spite of what we may or may not do.”
‎Well, that’s a good reminder
‎for all of us, isn’t it?
‎I know, as a missionary,
‎this was a lesson
‎I had to learn over the years
‎—the difference
‎between faith and stupidity.
‎When I look back on the first few years
‎I was in my missionary assignment
‎and some of the scary things we did
‎—jumping off ships into little boats
‎in the open sea without life jackets—
‎at the time,
‎I thought it was an act of faith,
‎but now I view it a little differently.
‎So we do need to be careful
‎to measure what we’re doing
‎and see if it really is an act of faith
‎or if it’s just doing something stupid.
‎Jesus showed great wisdom
‎in this regard, didn’t he?
‎When he served Jehovah
‎here on earth,
‎no doubt many times
‎his life was endangered
‎because the Pharisees
‎and the Sadducees opposed him.
‎They were looking
‎for ways to kill him.
‎But because he was serving Jehovah
‎and doing what Jehovah wanted,
‎he had trust in Jehovah
‎that he wouldn’t be killed
‎before the due time.
‎But on the other hand,
‎when Satan tempted him
‎in a way to boldly show off
‎and jump off the temple,
‎what did Jesus say?
‎‘You mustn’t test Jehovah.’
‎You see, Jesus realized that
‎that would have been an act of stupidity.
‎So for us today, it’s likewise important
‎when we’re making decisions
‎to balance out very carefully
‎what Jehovah wants us to do.
‎Yes, when Jehovah
‎makes a promise and says,
‎‘If you put the Kingdom first
‎and you do
‎what I want you to do, I will bless you’
‎and then we reach out and we do that,
‎we can be confident
‎that Jehovah will ultimately bless us.
‎But never may we ever
‎take the viewpoint
‎that we will just put
‎Jehovah to the test
‎by taking chances
‎and doing rash things.
‎Yes, whenever we make a decision,
‎let’s stop and prayerfully consider,
‎Is this an act of faith or stupidity?