Emma and I were so worried
about her Bible study, Palesa.
She had spent another sleepless night
after again hearing
her dead grandmother’s voice,
plus the sound of slamming doors
and items crashing in the house.
Palesa had put an amulet
on her baby’s wrist for protection,
but the terror continued all night long.
Of course, it wasn’t really her grandmother,
and nothing in the house was broken;
but the attack was real.
Stories about the spirit world weren’t new to me.
Our neighbors, the people I work with,
the people in our territory
—almost everyone believes in spirits,
whether they admit it or not.
No—more than believe—they fear them!
I had only been studying the Bible
about six months longer than Palesa.
But my study had proved to me
that wicked spirits are here on earth,
that they try to interact with people,
and that they are dangerous enemies.
Emma called the elders for help.
She didn’t want us to handle
the situation on our own.
As Emma told the story,
I had to speak up and tell the elders
that she was leaving things out.
But I was surprised when the elders
said they didn’t need all the details.
They explained that while we are aware
of the danger the demons pose,
we do not spend time
talking about their activities.
Even Jesus, when he was on earth,
could have told his disciples many stories
about the doings of wicked spirits,
but instead,
he focused on Jehovah and His activities.
We should do the same
instead of telling stories about what the demons
may or may not have done.
The elders skillfully used the Bible,
shepherding everyone.
We read Ephesians 6:11:
“Put on the complete suit of armor from God
“so that you may be able to stand firm
against the crafty acts of the Devil.”
Those instructions were so important.
A soldier would be vulnerable
if he only wore part of his armor
or if he didn’t keep it in good repair.
Then we read Ephesians 4:27:
“Do not give the Devil an opportunity.”
The elders explained to Palesa
that the string around her daughter’s wrist
is not part of the armor from God.
Instead, it is giving Satan
an opportunity to continue to harass the family.
The brothers reminded us
that anyone who wants Jehovah’s protection
must completely break free
from anything associated with superstition,
spiritism, and demon worship.
Who would ever choose to side
with wicked spirits instead of with Jehovah?
Emma reminded Palesa
of how urgent the situation was.
But only Palesa could decide what she would do.
I want to be a loyal servant of Jehovah.
That’s why I’m getting baptized.
I’ve decided not to listen to or tell
any more stories about the demons.
But more than that,
I need to look at other parts of my life.
Am I doing anything
that would “give the Devil an opportunity”?
Clearly,
there are still changes I need to make.