The next part of our program is one
that we’ve come to enjoy so much
in the past few years.
It’s the prerecorded video The Inside Story.
This installment of The Inside Story will be hosted
by Brother Kenneth Stovall,
with our Theocratic Schools Department.
So let’s give attention to and enjoy this video.
Welcome to this edition of The Inside Story.
Imagine yourself as a child
growing up in a country
where our work is under ban.
What would that be like?
You’re going to find out
as we talk to a couple from Romania.
Are you familiar with the progress
of our work in India?
I think you’re in for a few surprises
as we talk to four students
who come to us from the India branch.
But let’s get started by introducing our first guests.
From Romania
—please welcome Ionuţ and Delia Cicio.
Nice to see you.
Good to see you, Brother Stovall.
Welcome to The Inside Story.
It’s a privilege to be here.
Yes, it is—but a nervous privilege.
Well, I hope you’re not too nervous.
Well, to start with, could you just help us
to understand how
the work got started in Romania?
The work started in 1911.
By 1919, there were over 1,700 publishers
and 150 groups or congregations in Romania.
My goodness, that was very fast growth!
But there was some opposition to the work.
Yes, in 1949,
the Communist government banned our work,
and sadly, it lasted until 1990.
That’s amazing!
So that’s 40 years under ban.
But now, as I understand it,
that’s when both of your families got the truth
—when the ban was going on.
Is that correct?
Yes, my mother was a baby
when my grandparents got baptized,
so she grew up in the truth.
In fact, my grandmother was
a pioneer under the ban for many years.
Later, my two sisters and I
were raised in the truth.
Very interesting.
And, Ionuţ, what about you?
My parents were contacted by the Witnesses
ten years before the ban was lifted,
so my sister and I were also raised in the truth.
So this is very interesting.
Often, we have talked about brothers
who were faithful under ban who were adults,
but you were children while
the ban was going on, and you stayed faithful.
So, Delia, do you remember what it was like
going to meetings under ban?
Yes, we met secretly in small groups.
The friends would arrive at different times,
but once everyone was inside the home,
we would lock the gate and the door
and pull down all of the shades.
The meetings were moved
to a different location each week.
Very interesting.
Now, it must have been, though,
that you probably had to miss
a lot of meetings under ban.
No, no—we didn’t want to miss
any opportunity to meet together.
But weren’t you frightened in these meetings
(where you’d pulled down all the shades)
that you might be discovered or arrested?
You might think so, but the opposite was true.
I felt the most safe when we were all together.
You could feel Jehovah’s protection.
That’s very touching.
So, Ionuţ, did you and Delia
know each other growing up?
Yes, we grew up in the same town, Negreşti-Oaş,
so our families knew each other.
So did your families, then,
occasionally attend the same meetings?
No, we didn’t.
You see, my family was
in a separate group from Delia’s family.
In a separate group?
Now, explain what you mean.
You might remember Brother Lösch’s video
from the 2018 annual meeting.
He explained how government spies
infiltrated the Witnesses in Romania,
and this made it difficult to know who to trust.
This caused the Witnesses to separate
into two large groups
—one group stayed in contact
with world headquarters in Brooklyn,
and the other did not.
But both groups continued to worship Jehovah.
Amazing!
So you grew up
—both of you as Jehovah’s Witnesses
but associating with different groups.
Now, did one group view
the other group as apostates?
Generally, no.
We didn’t see the other group as apostates.
Our beliefs were essentially the same.
Yes, I should mention that when I was small,
I remember my mother
stayed up one night studying.
After all night of study,
meditation, and prayer,
she decided to switch to the group
connected to the main organization.
So that’s why I grew up as a part of the group
associated with the main organization.
My, it sounds like your mother
was very conscientious
and set a really good example for you.
I deeply appreciate her and my grandparents
for being faithful examples and good teachers.
OK, when you say good teachers,
what do you mean?
For example, we kept beehives in our garden;
my mother helped us to see how
Jehovah made them to be industrious.
Then she drew the lesson
that we could be industrious like the bees,
and in spite of the ban,
we could stay busy serving Jehovah.
Those must be some cherished memories,
those lessons like that.
Now, I wonder.
At meetings, since the literature was banned,
what did you study?
At meetings, usually there was one copy
of The Watchtower for the whole group.
When the paragraph was read,
we would listen and answer the question from memory.
My goodness, you had
to pay really close attention at the meetings.
Were there ever times
when you could get together in larger groups?
We couldn’t have assemblies and conventions,
but we could have funerals,
weddings, picnics.
These became our assemblies and conventions.
Sometimes, a funeral could have
as many as 1,000 people,
and it could last up to four hours.
Wow!
Now, what about songs?
The songbook would have been part
of the banned literature.
Could you sing songs at your meetings?
I remember being a child
and getting together to memorize the songs.
We enjoyed that; it was entertainment for us.
So you memorized the songs?
So if someone called out a song number,
you could sing the song from memory?
Yes.
What was going to school like under ban?
Our classmates and our neighbors
all knew we were Jehovah’s Witnesses
because when under ban,
we didn’t hide our identity as Witnesses.
We just hid the things
that the government outlawed, such as meetings,
preaching, literature.
So you must have been very determined
to stay faithful in school.
So whatever happened to the two groups?
I’m happy to say they reunited
as one organization in 1988;
then the ban was lifted in 1990.
The brothers were overjoyed.
I can imagine.
They must have felt a great deal of relief
when they could go about
their spiritual routine without the ban.
True.
But I learned a lesson I never want to forget:
Ban or no ban,
we are always under attack by Satan.
I saw brothers that stayed faithful during the ban
but fell away once the ban was lifted.
As circumstances change,
Satan will always look for new ways to attack us.
So ban or no ban,
we must stay close to Jehovah.
Those are profound thoughts, Ionuţ.
Well, how is Jehovah blessing
the work in Romania today?
Today, there are more than
40,000 Witnesses in Romania.
Actually, we brought a video
that shows what’s being done in Romania today.
Would you like to see it?
Yes, that would be wonderful!
Jesus said:
“Be on the watch for the false prophets
“who come to you in sheep’s covering,
but inside they are ravenous wolves.”
During the mid-20th century,
government agents in Romania used techniques
to infiltrate the congregation
—feigning interest
and posing as spiritual brothers.
They were so convincing
that some were even appointed as elders
and given very responsible positions.
Not knowing who could be trusted,
a large group of brothers
separated from the organization
that was being used by headquarters.
Still, they were really brothers in their heart;
they loved the truth.
So in 1988,
a reunification of about 5,000 was accomplished.
And now that our Romanian brothers
and sisters were reunited,
they could fully work “shoulder to shoulder”
in sharing the good news of God’s Kingdom.
This was beautiful timing
because conditions in Romania were ripe
for accelerated spiritual growth.
In 1990, the ban that they had endured
for more than 40 years was finally lifted.
Brothers Ian Florian and Tetu Bindu
remember the period of fiery test.
At one time, Brother Florian
was part of the separated group.
Brother Bindu was always with a congregation
that remained with the main organization
associated with headquarters.
They now serve together
as elders in the congregation.
When I returned to Jehovah’s organization,
I had experienced
the most profound and noble feelings
that only someone who belongs
to Jehovah’s worldwide family can have.
Today, they serve in unity
and enjoy many spiritual blessings.
Like so many other mature ones
with a similar background,
their rich history and experience
benefit younger ones.
In just six years after the ban was lifted,
the number of publishers nearly doubled.
Regular pioneers increased
by nearly 3,000 percent.
There are now more than 40,000 publishers.
Looking forward,
the Romanian branch has begun working
with the Central European branch
to form foreign-language circuits
for Hungarian- and Romany-speaking people.
Recently, a seminar was organized
for language instructors.
The unity of our Romanian brothers and sisters
is making it possible to reach
people of all languages with the good news.
The cold, insidious tactics of Satan’s agents
failed to separate our brothers from Jehovah
and each other,
and even now,
Jehovah is blessing them
with a spiritual paradise.
What a wonderful video!
Obviously, the brothers in Romania,
both the adults and the children,
had a lot of courage and faith
to keep their integrity under the ban.
Thank you, Ionuţ and Delia,
for sharing your story with us.
Now let’s introduce our next guests.
From India, we have not two, but four students.
Please welcome Sarb and Geeta Dhillon
and Puneet and Ritu Aggarwal.
Ritu.
Hello.
Hello, Brother Stovall.
Thank you, good to see you.
Well, thank you so much for joining us.
Thank you!
Now, you all serve at the India branch,
and as I understand,
you are in English congregations.
Yes, there are several
English congregations in India.
Very interesting.
So could we start by having you just explain
a little bit about the background
of the work in India?
Sure!
The work got started around 1905.
There was a man called A. J. Joseph.
He had questions about the Bible,
and somebody gave him books
by Brother Russell.
He read those books
and came into the truth,
and for around 60 years,
he proved to be instrumental
in establishing the work in India.
It is amazing how Jehovah used Brother Russell
to spread the good news so far!
Yes.
And in fact, Brother Russell went to India
in 1912, and in one village,
the villagers actually changed
the name of the village to Russelpuram,
which means “The Place of Russell.”
Amazing!
So is it still there today?
Yes, it’s in the beautiful state of Kerala,
which is in the south of India.
Now, there are a lot of misconceptions about India.
Uh-huh.
Often, when you see pictures,
you see what appear to be
tremendously overcrowded cities,
but there must be more to India than that.
Yes, brother, actually India is a very, very diverse country,
and it’s a very beautiful country.
If you go to the north of India,
you will have
the world famous Himalayan Mountains;
if you go to the northwest,
you will find the Great Indian Desert;
and if you go to the southwest and southeast,
you will have miles of beaches;
and then in the southern tip of it,
we have another national beauty
that’s called backwaters.
These are actually lagoons or lakes.
What a beautiful country!
Yes.
And what diversity!
And, you know, the peoples and the cultures
are as diverse as the country.
In fact, we have over 700 languages.
Seven hundred languages!
That’s amazing!
What about religion?
Is it diverse also?
Yes, the majority of people are Hindus,
but there are also Buddhists and Muslims.
In fact, there are several states in the northeast,
known as the Seven Sisters,
where people profess to be Christians.
How many people are we talking about?
Millions of people.
So there are millions of people in India
that profess to be Christian.
Yes.
I did not know that.
So, what’s the situation
with Jehovah’s Witnesses in India?
Well, we have just under
50,000 Witnesses in the whole of India.
Now, that’s a ratio of 1 publisher
to every 27,000 people.
Now, what that means is that some 90 percent
of our territory is actually unworked,
so the need over there is very, very great!
Well, I can see there’s an amazing need.
You see, in those states where the people are,
or profess to be, Christian,
there are actually millions of people
that you can speak to about the truth very easily.
But there’s also been an amazing response
to the truth in other parts of India too.
Amazing response?
Now, what do you mean by amazing response?
Well, there have been reports
of congregations where there are 50 publishers,
but over 850 people have attended the Memorial,
for example, in places like Kaushambi and Allahabad.
And brothers have been sent
into untouched territories,
into villages where villagers just come out,
sit on the ground,
and listen to the brothers for hours.
Those are such interesting reports.
What about you personally?
I mean, what have you personally experienced
as far as response to the truth?
Brother, when I was a pioneer back in my congregation,
I found people were very, very nice.
They were always ready to listen.
It wasn’t difficult to start two
or three Bible studies in a day.
And eventually,
I came to the point that I couldn’t continue
the house-to-house ministry
because I had so many Bible studies.
That’s fantastic!
What makes the people so eager to listen?
Well, the Indian people
in general are spiritually-minded,
and the majority do believe
in the existence of a God, or even many gods.
And many people
feel downtrodden and overlooked,
and so they are drawn to the love and respect
that they experience among the brothers.
And especially when they learn about a Creator
who actually loves them and cares for them,
it changes their viewpoint toward themselves,
and that also helps them to come into the truth.
Well, given the need
and the response that you’re getting,
can you get help from other places,
like from brothers or publishers
from other countries?
Absolutely!
In fact, every year we organize special campaigns
to try to cover some of our unworked territory,
and we have friends come from other countries
who support these campaigns.
And how does that work out?
Well, the friends who come
really enjoy themselves.
They enjoy themselves so much
that they often come back again
for longer periods of time.
So you have need-greaters in India?
We do!
Could you use more?
Oh, yes, please!
And there is also
a growing sign-language field in India.
The deaf field is one
of the fastest growing fields in India.
For example, a few years ago,
there were no congregations for the deaf,
but today, we have 13 congregations
and over 46 pregroups and groups.
Wow!
Again, that’s amazing response.
What kind of sign language do you use in India?
Is it similar to American Sign Language?
No.
We have Indian Sign Language,
which is very natural and very easy to learn.
Actually, I can help you to learn some.
You can try!
Yes, OK.
So the sign for women is like this
because they wear nose rings,
and the sign for men is like this
because they have mustaches
—not all, of course.
And then I just act like I’m eating a fruit.
So now I’m going to do a sign,
and let’s see if you can understand.
You can guess.
You’re giving me a test.
Yes, it’s from the Bible; it’s very easy.
So if I do like this, which Bible character is it?
Eve.
Oh!
Very good!
And if I do like that?
Adam.
Wow!
Very good!
I’m on my way to learning Indian Sign Language.
Yes, yes!
Excellent!
And Brother Stovall, the deaf people
are really drawn to the attention
they receive in the congregation
because, unfortunately,
in the Indian society, they are neglected.
For example, there was a brother who was trying
to contact a deaf man to arrange for a meeting.
So the deaf man asked
if he could bring a friend along.
And when the brothers arrived at his village,
they found the interested person
—the deaf man—
and not just one of his friends was with him,
but 136 of his deaf friends
had come along with him to listen.
Incredible!
How in the world could
the brothers speak to 136 people?
Well, there was a school nearby,
and they divided the full group
into classrooms there.
Well, I can see there is a tremendous amount
of work to do in India!
We have a lovely video to show to you.
A video!
Let’s watch!
Have you considered India?
You may have a list of questions, such as:
Is there really a great need in India?
Here are the facts:
For every 1 Witness,
there are about 27,000
potential brothers and sisters.
What about the response?
Those who have moved here are finding
as many progressive Bible studies
as they can handle.
Are you a married couple?
Are you a single person?
No matter what your situation,
the thought of moving to India
must raise questions like:
‘What about the food?
‘What about the culture?
‘How will I get around?
What is it like to live here?’
With some research,
the answers may surprise you.
We all are searching
for those “rightly disposed for everlasting life.”
If you are praying for a fuller share in this work,
ask Jehovah if he will help you
“step over” into India.
What a fascinating view of India!
So how do you feel
as you see the work really taking off in India?
Well, there is no doubt that the end is so close,
and we all feel that now is the time for India.
And, therefore, we are very much excited
to see what Jehovah has in store for us there.
Thank you so much for coming
and sharing these things with us.
Thank you.
How encouraging to hear
how our young ones were faithful under the ban
and to see what our brothers
in Romania are doing today!
And when you heard those reports from India,
were you not reminded of Jesus’ words:
“The fields . . . are white for harvesting”
and his further words: ‘Beg the Master
to send more workers into the harvest’?
We live in exciting times!
May Jehovah continue
to bless you and your efforts
to serve him until we’re together again
to get “the inside story”!
Well, that was absolutely delightful.
Thank you, Brother Stovall
and everyone involved
in producing that video
that we just had the privilege of enjoying.