Welcome to JW Broadcasting.
This is my friend Saki Marais,
a helper to the Writing Committee
of the Governing Body.
He’s here to help me discuss
the gifts we present to Jehovah God.
Saki, can you tell us
what the program is all about?
It would be my pleasure.
We’ll meet Sister Lillian Barnes.
Regardless of our age,
we can learn from her example
of loyal endurance.
What Bible counsel for young ones
continues to motivate her
to serve Jehovah whole-souled?
We’ll go to the United States branch
in Wallkill, New York,
to see how they produce Braille Bibles.
How has the revised
New World Translation in Braille helped
these brothers and sisters
give their gifts to God?
And why is physical cleanliness
an important part of our clean worship?
We’ll find out in this dramatization
from the Principles for Daily Living series.
This is the April 2019 edition
of JW Broadcasting.
This month I’d like to talk
about “Presenting Your Gifts to God.”
We certainly have every reason
to consider this topic.
Well, why is that?
It’s because Jehovah gives us so much.
James 1:17 says:
“Every good gift
and every perfect present is from above,
coming down
from the Father of the celestial lights.”
For example,
Jehovah allows us to enjoy the gift of life,
even though our first parents
tried to take that from us.
He’s provided us with a variety of foods.
The environment is just right to support life.
He’s given us his precious Word, the Bible,
so that we can come to know
him and his purposes.
And the greatest “perfect present”
Jehovah has given us is the ransom.
Jehovah sacrificed
a great deal to arrange for Jesus
to buy back for us the hope of everlasting life.
This was at no obligation on Jehovah’s part.
It was totally a gift of love.
Please read with me 1 John 4:9:
“By this the love of God
was revealed in our case,
“that God sent
his only-begotten Son into the world
so that we might gain life through him.”
What a gift of love from Jehovah, our God!
What does that move us to do?
Maybe you’ve had the experience
of a close friend or family member
unexpectedly giving you a valuable gift.
Immediately, what are you thinking?
You are probably trying to think
of what you can give in return.
How much more so
would we want to ‘present our gifts to God’
so as to show
our sincere appreciation for all he’s done!
Let’s consider some possible gifts
that Jehovah
would be pleased to receive from us.
Many of you in our viewing audience
have been moved to give your life to Jehovah,
dedicating yourself to do his will.
That’s commendable!
That’s what Romans 12 urges us to do.
However, there are some of you listening
who have thought
about this way of giving back to Jehovah,
but you haven’t yet taken this vital step.
Notice the appeal the apostle Paul makes
at Romans 12:1:
“Therefore, I appeal to you
by the compassions of God, brothers,
“to present your bodies as a living sacrifice,
“holy and acceptable to God,
a sacred service with your power of reason.”
Your life is precious.
Presenting your body, your whole soul,
to God is one of the best gifts
you can give to him.
This involves our sacred service to Jehovah
—that’s for sure.
But what about the daily activities of life?
Some of you do housework on a daily basis.
Others of you have
school to attend and homework to do.
Many of you perform secular work.
There’s shopping to do.
Others enjoy using
a small percentage of their time
to engage in some type
of recreation or entertainment.
Once you’re dedicated and baptized,
this is all part of your gift to Jehovah.
Please consider with me
Colossians 3:23, 24.
After discussing
a whole list of daily activities of life,
what does Jehovah tell us?
Colossians 3:23, 24:
“Whatever you are doing,
“work at it whole-souled as for Jehovah,
“and not for men,
“for you know that it is from Jehovah
you will receive the inheritance as a reward.”
It’s true that a Christian’s day-to-day activities
are not part of his sacred service.
However, the fact that Paul urges us
to work “whole-souled as to Jehovah”
makes us think of our entire course of life.
Yes, our life course
can become a gift presented to God.
For example, do we act and dress
with proper decorum at all times?
Understandably,
we don’t wear a suit and tie or a dress
for every activity of life.
But in “whatever you are doing,”
is your behavior and dress a gift to Jehovah?
If while engaging in any activity,
we’d be embarrassed to identify
ourselves as one of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
then can we really claim to be presenting
a gift to Jehovah in our daily life?
What other gifts are in our possession
that we can present to God?
What about godly morality?
Keeping your dedicated body clean morally
is a gift to Jehovah.
Did you notice what Romans 12:1 said?
It said that the bodies we present to Jehovah
should be “holy and acceptable to God.”
If we give in to temptation unrepentantly,
that could be likened to asking Jehovah
to give our gift back;
we’re taking back our dedicated life from him.
Worse yet, it is tantamount
to taking the gift away from Jehovah
and giving that precious gift to Satan.
That does not make sense.
Keep clean morally.
It’s a precious gift presented to God.
It’s true, when we’re dedicated and baptized,
there are other gifts that we’d be expected
to present to Jehovah on a regular basis.
One of the most obvious ways
is mentioned here at Hebrews 10:23.
Did you already guess
what this gift to Jehovah would be?
Hebrews 10:23:
“Let us hold firmly the public declaration
of our hope without wavering,
for the one who promised is faithful.”
The public declaration of our hope
is a gift to those we speak to,
but it’s also considered
a gift extended to Jehovah.
In fact,
Hebrews 13:15 calls our preaching work
“a sacrifice of praise,
“that is, the fruit of our lips
that make public declaration to his name.”
Israelites used to regularly offer
the best of their animals or grain
as sacrificial gifts to Jehovah.
Sharing in the ministry formally or informally
is a gift to God.
Regularly attending our Christian meetings
and participating in them
is part of our worship and pleases Jehovah.
We are familiar with Hebrews 10:24, 25.
It speaks of our custom of meeting together.
And for what purpose do we meet?
If I was there in your home with you,
how would you answer?
You might quickly say,
“I go to the meetings to be built up
and to be encouraged spiritually.”
Well, no doubt you do.
But at Hebrews 10:24, 25,
the purpose of attending is expressed
in a totally different way.
Instead of going
with the sole intent of being encouraged,
verse 24 says
we are to “consider one another
“so as to incite [others]
to love and fine works.”
Verse 25 says
we are to be “encouraging one another.”
We should attend our meetings
with the goal of being a gift to others.
Encouraging others is the goal.
We do this by our sincere interest in others
before and after the meeting.
Do you come to the Kingdom Hall early
to encourage others?
When in the traveling work, years ago,
my wife and I drove in to the parking lot
and got out of our car.
Two brothers approached us and warmly said:
“Brother and Sister Herd,
we were waiting for you.
We are so happy to have you
with our congregation this week.”
Were they elders,
ministerial servants, or pioneers?
No, they were two little preteenage boys!
That boost gave us a fine start
for a special week of activity.
We also encourage others
by participating in the meetings.
What an encouragement
to the whole congregation!
Of course, if we all go to the meetings
with that goal and motive,
what will be the result to us individually?
We all will come away built up
and encouraged spiritually.
But we must never forget
that being at our Christian meetings
and participating,
including singing the songs
and saying “Amen” to the prayers,
is actually worshipping Jehovah.
You are presenting a gift to him
at every meeting you attend.
From ancient times until now,
Jehovah’s faithful servants
have contributed materially
to the support of true worship.
That’s presenting a gift to God as well,
and we thank all of you for your support.
The Governing Body is able to provide so much
for the benefit of the worldwide brotherhood
because of your generosity.
Thank you.
Thank you very much!
What about you Christian parents?
What gift can you present to Jehovah?
Your children!
When you do your best to ‘bring your children up
in the discipline and admonition of Jehovah,’
you are preparing a gift to your God.
Think of the number of brothers
taking the lead in the organization at this time.
Some are Governing Body members, helpers,
Branch Committee members, circuit overseers,
elders, and ministerial servants.
Where did so many of these come from?
Hundreds of thousands
were children of Christian parents.
The parents followed
the admonition of Ephesians 6:4.
There are thousands more brothers and sisters
that have been raised
in the truth by godly parents
who are spearheading
the work in the ministry,
in Bethel service,
on construction projects, and in relief work.
We thank you, parents,
for all that you’ve done
and the precious gifts
you have offered up to Jehovah
and his organization.
And what about the older ones
in our congregations?
I’m 84 years young with eternity in view.
But at some point,
we start to admit that we’re getting old.
We start to feel that we’re getting old.
We start to look like we’re getting old.
Some of us find ourselves
slipping physically or even mentally.
Are we becoming
less and less valuable to Jehovah?
Is our gift now tarnished by age?
We might begin to think so,
but that’s not at all how
Jehovah views older ones
who have dedicated themselves to him,
possibly many decades ago.
A tarnished gold coin
has as much value as a shiny new one.
Proverbs 16:31 instructs us
that “gray hair is a crown of beauty
when it is found in the way of righteousness.”
It’s not so much the color
of the hair that Jehovah admires.
Instead, it’s the life of self-sacrifice
that gray hair represents.
Jehovah views older ones
who are still found in the way of righteousness
as precious gifts to him.
Why do pieces of antique furniture often cost
much more than a brand new piece of furniture?
Or why is an older bottle of fine wine
often more expensive
than a newer vintage wine?
Age brings value to a gift.
You older ones have wisdom and experience
that others in the congregation can benefit from.
It’s not that you
need to be holding the microphone
and waxing eloquent
on every paragraph at a meeting,
but modestly sharing your experience
and wisdom with others on a personal basis
can be so helpful and encouraging.
Jehovah loves you older ones.
So even if you’re bent with age in your mind,
stand tall as a precious gift
presented to Jehovah.
May all of us, young and old,
consider how we can enhance
our gifts presented to Jehovah.
If we have not yet dedicated our life to God,
is it time to seriously consider this gift?
Can we enhance our gift
by more closely monitoring
our view of Christian morality?
What we look at or think about
could compromise our gift to God.
How about our ministry or attendance
and participation at the meetings
or contributing materially
to the worldwide work?
You parents,
do your best to package
the gift of your children
so that they will be useful to Jehovah.
And you older ones,
never forget that when it comes
to wisdom and experience,
you only get better with age.
Jesus is the best of Jehovah’s servants.
He’s been around the longest.
Let’s meet a sister who’s applied the counsel
to serve God from her youth on.
Sister Lillian Barnes is from Jamaica.
Her gifts to Jehovah
may have changed with age,
but what she gives to him today
is in no way less valuable.
“Remember, then,
“your Grand Creator
in the days of your youth.”
That was Sister Barnes’ determination.
Lillian is now 108 years old
and has been baptized for nearly 82 years.
Her beautiful example shows the contentment
that comes from serving God
whole-souled at any age.
To give Jehovah our best,
we need God’s Word
to know how to worship him.
That’s why Jehovah’s organization works hard
to make the Bible available
to as many people as possible.
At the United States branch
in Wallkill, New York,
they are producing Braille copies
of the revised New World Translation.
What does it take
to make a good quality Braille Bible,
and how are Braille readers
using this beautiful gift?
In 2013, our English-printed Bibles
were revised and, shortly thereafter,
the Braille Bibles were approved
to be revised in English and Portuguese.
We knew it was going to be a large job.
We were having problems
with the pages either tearing
or coming completely out of the Bible.
We tried changing the paper
to see if that would be a simple solution,
and we had a brother
who is blind come in and help us.
We were able to test the paper
in the machine and actually walk it
right over to the brother,
and he gave us immediate feedback
on adjustments to the machine
or if it wasn’t working at all.
During our testing,
we tried about 25 different types of paper,
but we ended up coming back to the idea
that the binding was
the best way to find a durable solution.
The result is that the durability
is 400 percent stronger than it was before.
You can pick up an entire book
by holding just one page.
In the Literature Production Office,
we have ones who receive
the requests for the Braille Bibles,
we have ones
who will review these requests
as they come into the system,
and then we have
a separate set of brothers who make sure
that all the materials are here on time.
We get our orders from the office,
and then the office
will tell us how many to make
—maybe the specific volume number.
Braille Bibles come
from the Wallkill printery
on the Braille production floor.
Right at the end of the machine,
we have a Braille paper roll.
We make sure
that there’s nothing wrong with that roll,
and then it gets fed into the machine
where it creates Braille
on both sides of the page.
And after that,
it gets cut and punched.
We gather it
and do some quality inspection.
We’ll bind it together;
we’ll rivet each section into a binder
that has been prelabeled
with a volume number,
do an inspection on it,
pop it in a box, and then send it out the door.
To produce the English Bible in Braille
takes about four and a half hours,
which then breaks out into 28 volumes,
and the Portuguese Bible
in Braille takes closer
to five and a half hours,
and that breaks out into 32 volumes.
We did not start production with Genesis,
because we wanted the brothers
and sisters to be able to receive the volume
that would be
on the congregation Bible reading schedule
at our midweek meetings.
So as we receive
the files for each volume,
it’s being printed and sent out
to our brothers and sisters.
It’s important to me
to be able to read God’s Word
rather than just listening
because I am a visual person.
So the eyesight is gone, but I’m still visual.
I learn better from reading
than I do from listening.
In my mind when I’m listening,
my mind wanders,
but when I’m reading, I can stop
and meditate on what I’m studying.
That helps me
with my relationship with Jehovah.
It has helped me a lot,
because a lot of things
I don’t have to look up
because it’s in plain English.
They have so many things
in this new Bible
that I can use, like the outline.
I can get that outline
and find something fast.
It has the appendix,
the word index,
and the glossary.
During the time of the Memorial,
I was able to read the events
of the last week of Jesus’ life.
I really enjoy reading with one hand
and pulling the other hand down
and reading the footnotes.
I can participate more
in the midweek meeting.
For instance, in the section
“Digging for Spiritual Gems,”
the brothers always get someone
from the audience to read the scriptures.
So once I got the new Bible,
I could raise my hand
and volunteer to read,
and so the whole meeting opened up.
The revised edition
helps me be more effective at the meeting,
and it helps me to find
exactly what I need.
Before the revision,
when he’d have a part on the meeting,
he would have to get his Brailler out
and have me dictate one sentence at a time
so he could type it all out
—what he was going to use in his part.
So this is nice because he has
the right wording
that all the friends have.
I like to carry it from house to house,
so I can only take
the one volume because they’re huge.
But whatever the initial call is,
I can take that scripture
and see if the householder
will let me read a scripture for them.
It means so much to be able to read
the Scriptures and to do personal study.
I am very thankful for all the work
our brothers have done up in Wallkill.
I really appreciate the effort
that they’ve all gone through,
because that’s a lot of work.
In Jehovah’s organization,
they care for everyone.
I was so thankful
that they had the Braille Bible for the blind.
That’s what draws me closer to Jehovah
—being able to study his Word
and look the scriptures up.
The new Bible is personal to me.
I feel like it was
a personal answer to a prayer.
Jehovah supplied it because that’s
the main thing I wanted to read,
and I am so thankful to Jehovah.
Like these brothers and sisters,
treasure the gift of God’s Word.
We pray that Jehovah
continue to bless the efforts
to make the revised New World Translation
available in more languages and formats.
With the Bible and Christian publications,
we’re equipped to do
all we can in the preaching work.
That desire to ‘fully accomplish our ministry’
is captured in this month’s original song
“All I Can Give.”
O heavenly Father,
I want to give all I can give.
My desire is to please you
and love you as long as I live.
I’ll help those who listen
to find in your Word what they need.
To preach and to teach
is the way I can really succeed.
As I praise you, Jehovah,
my faith’s getting stronger each day.
I’ll reflect on my dedication.
I’ll walk in your way.
O heavenly Father,
to you I give praise,
Determined to serve you
in so many ways.
My heart is wide open
as long as I live.
Jehovah, I’ll love you
and give you all I can give.
Whole-souled devotion
and love for my brothers I’ll show.
Volunteering to play my part
is the best way I know.
I’m happier when I am giving
than when I receive,
When I’m taking the time
to help others who may be in need.
As I praise you, Jehovah,
my faith’s getting stronger each day.
I’ll reflect on my dedication.
I’ll walk in your way.
O heavenly Father,
to you I give praise,
Determined to serve you
in so many ways.
My heart is wide open
as long as I live.
Jehovah, I’ll love you
and give you all I can give.
O heavenly Father,
to you I give praise,
Determined to serve you
in so many ways.
My heart is wide open
as long as I live.
Jehovah, I’ll love you
and give you all I can give.
In what ways did you see
the brothers and sisters
giving all they could in the ministry?
They witnessed at every opportunity.
They preached door to door,
in public witnessing,
at businesses, informally,
and in remote areas.
They used our Teaching Toolbox,
including videos,
to reach people
in a language they really understood.
The ministry is an important way
we imitate Jehovah’s love for people.
We also want to imitate Jehovah’s holiness.
Brother Herd explained
why we strive to stay morally clean.
But what about keeping physically clean?
That’s not always easy for busy Christians.
In this dramatization,
see how Grayson gives his son
the loving counsel on cleanliness that he needs.
I graduated
from high school that summer
and wanted to start
regular pioneering.
That’s my dad, Grayson.
Dad was having
car trouble that morning
and needed a ride to work,
so I gave him one.
OK, my car
was a little messy and smelly.
I mean, it was winter,
and my car is pretty old anyway.
So why bother?
When I get a new car,
then I’ll keep it clean.
But he was making
a big deal out of nothing.
That morning was not good.
I thought it was over.
But later that evening,
Dad brought it up again.
But this time, it went better.
He showed me a picture of his first car.
It looked pretty old too.
He said that while our home
or car may not be
fancy or luxurious,
it should be as clean and presentable
as circumstances allow.
I still didn’t see what the big deal was.
Then, he explained
that Jehovah is a clean God,
and from ancient times,
he has always required
that his people be a clean people.
Under the Mosaic Law
that Jehovah gave to Israel,
cleanness and worship
were inseparable.
It specified that priests were required
to wash their hands and feet
before offering sacrifices to Jehovah.
While in an unclean state, an Israelite
could not have any part in worship,
or it could mean death.
I said, “I’m not an Israelite,
and we’re not
under the Mosaic Law anymore.”
He said, “True, but it gives us insight
into Jehovah’s thinking.”
The Law emphasized that cleanness
was required
of all those who worshipped him.
And as Malachi 3:6 tells us,
‘Jehovah has not changed.’
Then, he said something
that really stuck with me,
“Besides, it’s not all about us.”
Then, he gave me a scripture to look up.
It was 2 Corinthians 6:3, 4:
“In no way are we giving
any cause for stumbling,
“so that no fault
may be found with our ministry;
“but in every way
we recommend ourselves as God’s ministers.”
I realized that things like our appearance,
our homes, and our cars
—these can all be
a silent witness to Jehovah in themselves.
It made sense to me now.
It’s not all about us.
I knew what I had to do.
Not only did I clean my car,
but later that year,
I was able to turn in
my application for pioneering.
And I’m glad for the lesson
I learned from my dad.
It’s not all about us.
Even in little ways,
we can reflect favorably
on the God we love.
What made Grayson’s counsel effective?
Although he reacted to sitting in the dirty car,
he waited until he was calm to give counsel.
He based what he said
on God’s standards in the Bible.
And it took humility
for his son to see that his cleanliness
could affect how others
view Jehovah’s clean people.
Humility helps us to accept correction,
but it can do even more.
It was the topic of this Bethel morning worship,
wherein Brother Mark Noumair asks why humility
was such an important lesson for Jesus’ apostles
and why it still is for us today.
It is interesting that Peter gives counsel
about cultivating humility.
Let’s turn the clock back
and learn why the quality of humility
was indelibly etched
in the mind and heart of Peter.
Let’s open our Bibles to Luke chapter 22.
In Luke chapter 22,
we’ll find Jesus getting ready
for that final Passover in 33 C.E.
And in Luke 22, starting in verse 8,
it is Thursday afternoon, Nisan 13,
and what happens?
Verse 8: “Jesus sent Peter [there he is]
“and John, saying: ‘Go and get
the Passover ready for us to eat.’”
‘Get it ready, Peter and John.’
Verse 9: “They said to him:
‘Where do you want us to get it ready?’”
They understood the instructions: Get it ready.
Jesus said to go into Jerusalem,
and you’ll find the man
with the earthenware jar.
Verse 12: “And that man
“will show you
a large, furnished upper room.
Get it ready there.”
Verse 13: “So they left
and found it just as he had told them,
and they prepared for the Passover.”
Get it ready; prepare the Passover.
What would that include?
Bread, wine, oil for the lamps,
lamb, a towel, a basin, water.
Basin and water
—they knew
how important washing feet was.
They witnessed when
Jesus reproved Simon the Pharisee
with the statement: Simon,
“you gave me no water for my feet.”
‘Simon, you gave me no water.
You missed the mark on this one.’
So as they stared
at that basin and water,
as they prepared
and got the room ready,
did they look at each other
and wonder:
‘Who’s going to wash the feet?
Who’s going to do it?’
They had a golden opportunity
to apply all the things that Jesus
had been teaching them
for three and a half years on humility.
This was the time.
After three and a half years,
conduct yourself as a lesser one.
Don’t lord it over others.
You want to serve others and not be served.
This was it; this was the time.
They could have showed Jesus
that they got the point; they got it.
They had time to think about it
and time to pray about it.
It was Thursday afternoon,
but now we progress
and let’s see what happens.
Let’s now progress
to the evening, and it’s Nisan 14.
Let’s pick up the account in John chapter 13.
They got the room ready,
they followed the instructions,
and now let’s go to John 13
and get John’s vantage point from this.
He was there;
he was with Peter getting it ready.
So now it’s 98 C.E.,
and John is writing this information.
He had time to reflect
and to think about this for years,
and now look what he says in verse 3:
“So Jesus,
“knowing that the Father
had given all things into his hands
and that he came from God
and was going to God.”
Knowing these things
—he understood that.
He sat back and said:
‘Jesus knew who he was; he knew all things.
‘He had the full understanding of his dignity.
‘He knew that he
had been entrusted with all things.
‘He knew.
‘He knew he was the second greatest
personage in the universe.
‘He knew he was
“the firstborn of all creation.”
‘He knew he had shared
with his Father in creating all things.
He had knowledge of all this
—knowing all these things.’
John sits back; he writes this.
And then knowing this,
verse 4 is the contrast:
‘He got up from the evening meal
and laid aside his outer garments.
‘Taking a towel,
he wraps it around his waist.
‘After that, he puts the water
into the basin
‘and starts to wash
the feet of the disciples
and dry them off with the towel
that was wrapped around him.’
Knowing who He was,
John said He did this.
But not only does John reflect
on who Jesus was,
no, he reflects on why Jesus did it.
Why did he do it?
That’s what John was interested in,
and we get that answer back in verse 1,
where John says why:
‘Because he loved his own
that were in the world;
he loved them to the end.’
John said He “loved them to the end.”
What does that mean?
He wanted to instill in them qualities
that would help them conquer the world,
qualities that would strengthen
the Christian congregation,
qualities such as unselfish love
and humility.
He loved them to the end.
He never gave up on them.
They had their weaknesses,
but he did not give up.
Now, for Peter, some 30 years later,
he’s thinking about humility.
John, some 60 years later,
after the lesson Jesus taught
about humility,
it’s echoing loud and clear
in his mind and heart.
However, the fact remains
that neither of them
had the humility at the time
to apply what Jesus
had been teaching them
for three and a half years.
Now, after John finished his writing, he sat back;
he was under inspiration;
he finished that writing.
Did he sit back,
reread what he just wrote,
and perhaps say to himself:
‘I wish I could have written
‘that after Jesus washed the feet
of one or two of his disciples,
‘I got up and washed the feet
‘of the rest of my brothers?
‘I took that towel, and I imitated the Christ?
Or, Peter and I got up?’
But the point is, they didn’t.
What can we learn?
Don’t allow valuable lessons
that Jesus teaches us
to echo in our minds and hearts
only after we missed
the opportunity to apply them.
So in a practical setting
for us serving here at Bethel:
‘Even though I know
I have the seniority
‘—I have full knowledge of my seniority—
‘will I get up and fight the attitude
of entitlement?
‘I know I have
authority entrusted to me as the overseer;
‘I am the overseer;
I know that. I have full knowledge of that.
‘Fine, will I get up
‘and roll my sleeves back
and do the grunt work?
‘Or do I just find pleasure
in giving orders?
‘I know I have
a wonderful privilege of service;
‘I know that; others know it too.
Fine, but will I get up to train others?’
Brother Jackson reminded us of this
at the last Gilead graduation
when he said to treasure your privileges,
but don’t hoard them.
That means we have to get up.
It takes humility
to train others to take our place.
‘As a brother or a sister,
‘I know I have more experience
than the other person in my job.
‘I know I have the experience; I know that.
‘I have more experience than my workmate.
‘Fine, but will I get up in all humility
‘and share information that I have
‘with others to make their job easier?
Or will I hold the knowledge I have hostage?’
If we get up in all humility
and do these things,
then we can say that Jesus’ humble act,
as recorded here in John 13,
has made a lasting
and indelible impression
not only on Peter and John
but on me.
What a powerful lesson!
Humility will improve the way
we carry out our theocratic assignments.
It honors our fellow workers,
and it promotes unity.
Unified servants of God get things done.
In Peru,
local brothers worked
with international servants and volunteers
to complete two new Assembly Halls.
In this report,
hear what the brothers
learned from working together
and how the new Assembly Halls
are being used to glorify Jehovah.
I suppose whatever we give to Jehovah
is little in comparison with what he gives to us.
And like Malachi 3:10 says, you know,
we just have to ‘bring in the tenth part.’
That’s really all that Jehovah is asking,
but he pours out a blessing.
And part of those blessings from Malachi 3:10,
I consider to be
the friendships that we’ve gained.
For me, my favorite thing is the people.
It’s always just getting to work
with your brothers every day.
The personalities shine through,
even with language differences.
You just make friends,
and you just get this taste
of what the new world is going to be like.
Side by side with our brothers,
we’ve made parent figures
and brother and sister figures,
and everybody just becomes
part of such a solid family.
Working along with the local brothers and sisters
made it clear to me
that we really are in the organization
that Jehovah is directing today.
What I have seen is how Jehovah’s spirit
operates in his organization.
There were many international servants here
from various countries,
with different personalities,
along with our local brothers
with their distinct customs.
But when it was time to work, we were as one.
There wasn’t a big guy, a little guy,
someone more intelligent, or less intelligent.
We all formed one united team.
The language definitely was an issue for me.
At first I thought,
‘Will I really be able to work with the brothers?’
Since I didn’t understand the language,
how could I explain
the work that had to be done?
Really, if you go in there with a good attitude
and you’re just having
a good time working with your brothers,
you’re not going to have too much of a problem.
Smiles
—they cross borders.
The Chiclayo dedication program
was held April 9, 2016,
and the Trujillo Assembly Hall
was dedicated shortly thereafter,
on July 31.
All present marveled with appreciation
at seeing the facilities,
their own new Assembly Hall.
Before, we had to work a lot,
maybe up to 15 days beforehand
to prepare a completely inappropriate site.
Not anymore.
Now the brothers only need to maintain it
and simply arrive
in order to enjoy their assembly.
I’m sure that this new Assembly Hall
will strengthen the spirituality
of our dear brothers and sisters.
If I can say something about the video monitors:
They’ve revolutionized
Jehovah’s method of teaching.
We get so much more out of the talks now
because we can see
the gestures of the brothers.
It really touches the heart.
It’s so amazing!
I remember more than 25 years ago,
I prayed to Jehovah and said,
“Jehovah, please,
permit me at some point to see
an Assembly Hall here.”
And now Jehovah let me
be part of the buying process,
of getting the documentation,
and of being part of the construction.
And I remember, and I say,
“Jehovah answered my prayer.”
Well, it affected me
seeing the construction progress
because when we first arrived
at our project in Chiclayo,
you know what the brothers had
and what they were using as an Assembly Hall.
And then to see the finished project
that we see now,
I’m so happy for the brothers and sisters.
It’s so beautiful, clean, neat, and tidy.
It’s like, in reality, for where it is,
it’s a little jewel within that whole city
to me when I see the completed project.
And I know that brothers
do just love to be able to care for that place,
to be able to worship Jehovah there,
and to be with their brothers and sisters.
There’s nothing that will ever compare
with this wonderful experience
we’ve been able to have.
It’s been great!
We’ve enjoyed a wonderful program.
Our videos showed us so many of the ways
we can present our gift to Jehovah.
I agree.
We saw our brothers, young and old,
give their best in the ministry,
in the congregation, at Bethel,
and on construction projects.
And we heard good counsel to be humble,
morally clean, and physically clean.
And to conclude our program,
we have greetings
from our brothers and sisters in Chad.
Chad is located in north-central Africa.
With the Sahara Desert in the north,
most of Chad’s more than 13 million people
live in the fertile southern regions.
Fewer than a thousand brothers live and preach
in this vast field dotted with remote villages.
The capital city is N’Djamena.
Five congregations
are busy spreading the good news
in the city and its surrounding area.
One of these, just south of the capital,
is the Walia Congregation.
They preach regularly along the Logone River,
where they often meet people
traveling from faraway areas.
Their busy activity also helped to establish
a new congregation in nearby Koundoul.
The brothers in Koundoul and Walia
send us
their heartfelt Christian love and greetings.
We pray for Jehovah to bless
their gifts of brotherly affection and self-sacrifice.
Thank you for joining us.
From the World Headquarters
of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
this is JW Broadcasting.