As Jehovah’s people,
we enjoy many undeserved
and precious privileges.
Among them, we bear Jehovah’s name
and render him sacred service.
As we carry out his will,
he dignifies us in a very special way.
At 1 Corinthians 3:9,
the apostle Paul under inspiration
stated that “we are God’s fellow workers.”
What an honor to be a fellow worker
with the Universal Sovereign,
our loving heavenly Father!
To build appreciation for the privilege
of working with Jehovah,
we’re going to review events
in the life of Jonathan, a son of King Saul.
First Samuel 14:45
describes Jonathan when it says:
“For it was with God
that he acted this day.”
What was the background
that led to this statement?
How did Jonathan act, or work,
with Jehovah on that day?
What lessons can we learn
from their working relationship?
And what blessings result
from being a fellow worker with God?
Let us begin with some background.
First Samuel 12:20
records the encouraging words
spoken by the prophet Samuel
to the nation of Israel:
“Do not be afraid.  . . .
“Only do not turn away
from following Jehovah,
and serve Jehovah
with all your heart.”
Verse 22 adds:
“For the sake of his great name,
Jehovah will not abandon his people.”
As long as they remained faithful,
Jehovah would always be there to guide,
protect, and rescue them.
These words no doubt strengthened
Jonathan to carry out Jehovah’s directive
to subdue the enemy nations
and take possession of the Promised Land.
At  1 Samuel chapter 13,
we read that Jonathan
was assigned 1,000 men
to attack a Philistine garrison at Geba.
Although poorly equipped,
Jonathan and his men succeeded.
This victory strengthened
Jonathan’s confidence in Jehovah
and provides a valuable lesson for us:
While we gain strength and courage
from Jehovah’s reassuring
words of the Scriptures,
our confidence in Jehovah’s support
becomes even stronger
when we successfully
carry out our assignments
that may seem overwhelming.
The account then relates
how the Philistines
were infuriated over their defeat
and mounted a massive counterattack.
They sent out raiding parties
from their camp
at Michmash near Jerusalem.
Many Israelite men hid out of fear,
and some even fled
to the other side of the Jordan River.
In contrast,
Jonathan remained courageous.
Determined to put a stop to the raids,
he confronted the Philistine outpost
at the ravine pass of Michmash.
The approach was by way of a deep gorge
with nearly vertical cliffs.
This would have seemed next to impossible
to someone unfamiliar with the area,
but Jonathan grew up in this territory
and apparently knew it well.
His knowledge of the surroundings
provides another practical lesson:
Whatever theocratic assignment
we may be given,
putting forth time and effort
to get to know the terrain,
so to speak,
will contribute to our effectiveness.
When we show interest
in our assigned work,
we become even more effective
fellow workers of Jehovah.
Let’s read as Jonathan prepares
to take action against the Philistines.
First Samuel 14:6 states:
“So Jonathan said to his armor-bearer:
“‘Come and let us cross over
to the outpost of these uncircumcised men.
“‘Perhaps Jehovah will act in our behalf,
for nothing can hinder Jehovah
from saving by many or by few.’”
What contributed
to his confidence in Jehovah?
Recall that he put faith
in Jehovah’s reassuring words
through the prophet Samuel:
“Do not be afraid. . . .
For the sake of his great name,
Jehovah will not abandon his people.”
He experienced Jehovah’s support
when he struck down
the Philistine garrison at Geba.
Jonathan could also
think back on Israel’s history.
He could reflect
on how Gideon and his 300 men
were victorious over 135,000 Midianites.
He could meditate
on Samson killing 1,000 Philistines
with the jawbone of a donkey.
Such examples
would bolster his confidence
that he was working
with the Almighty God, Jehovah.
We too can meditate on fellow workers
of God recorded in the Scriptures
as well as published life stories
of modern-day faithful servants.
Such examples
reinforce our faith in Jehovah
as we rely on him for success.
Another lesson comes from the response
of Jonathan’s armor-bearer
at 1 Samuel 14:7:
“At this his armor-bearer said to him:
“‘Do whatever your heart impels you to do.
“‘Turn wherever you wish,
and I will follow you
wherever your heart impels you.’”
It is unlikely that the attendant
would have initiated
this challenging mission on his own.
Jonathan’s confident lead was a positive,
motivating influence on the man.
What happens today
when elders and overseers
take the lead and display zeal
in Jehovah’s work like Jonathan?
Others in the congregation are also
motivated to action by their fine example.
Let us now read verses 8-10:
“Then Jonathan said:
“‘We will cross over to those men
and reveal our presence to them.
“‘If they say to us,
“Stand still until we come to you!”
“‘we will stand where we are
and not go up to them.
“‘But if they say, “Come up against us!”
“‘we will go up, because Jehovah
will give them into our hand.
This will be our sign.’”
Jonathan once again demonstrated
humble reliance on Jehovah.
Later in Second Samuel,
Jonathan is described
as “swifter than the eagles”
and “mightier than the lions.”
However, these qualities
and abilities did not cause him
to be self-reliant or overconfident.
He sought Jehovah’s direction
by means of a sign.
What a powerful reminder for us!
Regardless of any natural abilities,
acquired skills,
or experience we may have,
the key to success is seeking
Jehovah’s guidance and support.
We seek his direction
through specific prayers,
Bible reading and meditation,
and applying direction
from “the faithful and discreet slave.”
We also consult
with longtime faithful brothers and sisters
who can share their rich experience
as God’s fellow workers.
What else can we learn
from Jonathan’s account?
Picking up at 1 Samuel 14:12,
Jonathan and his armor-bearer
advance toward the Philistines.
From their elevated location,
the Philistines shout to them:
“‘Come up to us,
and we will teach you a lesson!’
“At once Jonathan said to his armor-bearer:
“‘Follow me, for Jehovah will give them
into the hand of Israel.’”
Jonathan had requested a specific sign,
and he got it.
But it meant advancing
up a steep and treacherous incline
right into enemy hands.
Someone lacking complete trust
in Jehovah might have said,
“Before proceeding,
perhaps we should ask for another sign,”
but not Jonathan.
Without hesitation,
he told his attendant to follow him
because Jehovah would give
the enemy into their hand.
When we receive Jehovah’s direction,
we should without hesitation
put our hearts into the work,
confident of Jehovah’s backing.
What happened next?
First Samuel 14:13, 14 reports:
“And Jonathan climbed up
on his hands and feet,
“and his armor-bearer was behind him;
“and the Philistines began
to fall before Jonathan,
“and his armor-bearer was putting
them to death behind him.
“In the first attack that Jonathan
and his armor-bearer made,
they struck down about 20 men.”
Even after receiving
a clear sign from Jehovah,
it took great effort.
They had to ‘climb up
on their hands and feet,’
exerting themselves
vigorously over rugged terrain.
The lesson?
Even when we receive clear direction
and are ready to obey,
carrying out our assignments
will not always be easy.
We have to exert ourselves vigorously,
being willing to work hard
with all of our mind, heart, and strength.
How did the Philistines react to seeing
Jehovah’s support for his people?
First Samuel 14:15 reads:
“Then terror spread in the field camp
“and among all the people of the outpost,
“and even the raiding parties were terrified.
The earth began quaking,
and a terror from God ensued.”
The earthquake Jehovah caused
melted the Philistines’ hearts.
Soon, the Israelites, even those
who had previously fled in fear,
joined the victory battle
over the Philistines.
Likewise, when we put our hearts
into theocratic assignments,
Jehovah, our best Fellow Worker,
will always come through with whatever
we need to accomplish his will.
But there is another lesson to be learned
from this exciting Bible account.
During the height of the battle,
King Saul gave an unwise order saying:
“Cursed is the man who eats
any food before the evening
and until I have taken
vengeance on my enemies!”
Jonathan, however, was not aware
of his father’s order
and ate some wild honey
that he had found.
How did Saul react when he discovered
that his own son had disobeyed him?
First Samuel 14:43, 44 tells us:
“Then Saul said to Jonathan:
“‘Tell me, what have you done?’
“So Jonathan told him:
“‘I merely tasted a little honey
on the tip of the staff in my hand.
“Here I am!
I am ready to die!’
“At this Saul said:
“‘Thus may God do and may he add to it
if you do not die, Jonathan.’”
Imagine, after all that Jonathan had done
in risking his life in behalf of his people
and seeing Jehovah grant so much success,
he is now being condemned
to death by his own father.
How his heart must have sank in disbelief,
disappointment, and sadness!
Would Jehovah now abandon
his loyal fellow worker?
First Samuel 14:45 reads:
“But the people said to Saul:
“‘Should Jonathan die
“‘—the one who brought
this great victory to Israel?
“‘It is unthinkable!
“‘As surely as Jehovah is alive,
“‘not even a single hair of his head
should fall to the ground,
“for it was with God that he acted this day.’
With that the people rescued Jonathan,
and he did not die.”
Jonathan’s success
provided undeniable evidence
that he was truly Jehovah’s fellow worker.
Jehovah, who had been
at Jonathan’s side the whole time,
saw everything that had happened
and would not allow his loyal worker
to die at Saul’s hands.
How comforting to know that when we
faithfully carry out our assignments,
he will never forget our zealous efforts!
If someone as close as a father
fails to see and appreciate
the work we do in Jehovah’s service
or even turns against us,
Jehovah will never forget our work.
He will always be there to guide,
support, protect, and bless us.
What a faith-building account
we’ve considered
in 1 Samuel chapters 13 and 14!
Why not take the time
to read these chapters for yourself?
You’ll be moved to imitate
Jonathan’s excellent example of loyalty,
courage, and obedience.
We want to be described
just as Jonathan was at 1 Samuel 14:45:
“For it was with God
that he acted this day.”
By continuing
as industrious fellow workers with Jehovah,
we are assured
that ‘through faith and patience
we will inherit the promised reward.’