Welcome to JW Broadcasting!
Here’s what we
can look forward to in our program:
What if your courtship
reveals problems you didn’t expect?
Part 3 of the Preparing for Marriage series
will show us how we
can “calculate the expense”
when considering marriage.
We go to Australia
to meet Viv and Ann Mouritz.
Their life of full-time service
has taken them around the world.
What advice do they have
for those who are deciding
what form
of sacred service to pursue?
And we’ll enjoy
a music video that highlights
the theme of our program.
It will encourage us to settle differences
with our brothers and sisters
and to forgive one another.
This is the October 2016 edition
of JW Broadcasting!
We begin with a report from Ukraine.
In 2014,
political tensions in eastern Ukraine
boiled over
into a full-blown military conflict.
Within months,
over 7,600 Witnesses
needed to flee the area
to seek refuge.
Others sheltered in their homes.
How did our brothers
survive physically
and spiritually
through the fighting?
Relief was organized
from hundreds of miles away
at the branch office in L’viv.
In the following interviews,
our brothers and sisters
describe the love and care
they received from the organization
and from each other.
It happened that the hostilities
started without warning,
and the brothers needed to flee quickly.
There was not enough food;
there was nothing in the stores;
there was a lack of medicine;
there was no water,
no electricity.
It was scary.
There was no stability at all.
We did not know what to do.
Should we stay, or should we leave?
There were triplets;
they were seven years old.
As soon as they
got into the shelter,
they started singing
a Kingdom song.
The adults
also joined them in singing,
and because of that,
we couldn’t hear the explosions
that were happening outside.
True, we ran out of foodstuffs,
and we had no money.
But I knew we would be able to get by.
God would not let us die of hunger.
Because the shelling was happening
so often, it was impossible
to conduct our usual meetings.
We also couldn’t organize the ministry
in the normal way.
It was just too dangerous.
When we received the first reports
about the unrest in the east,
our Branch Committee gathered
and we prayerfully analyzed
the situation.
We asked Jehovah for wisdom
—how to act,
how to help our brothers
to be spiritually and physically safe.
We were also sending regular
update reports to the Governing Body.
More than 156 tons of food
and 21 tons of clothing donated
by local brothers have been distributed
to fellow believers
and also to some non-Witnesses.
We had been told
that we would be receiving
about five tons of relief supplies.
So we were astounded
when instead of 5 tons,
we received 15 tons!
It was lovely to find little notes
that our brothers
and sisters had written
and included in the packages.
Brothers from neighboring cities responded
and offered their homes,
provided foodstuffs
and, more importantly,
their brotherly hospitality.
So we are ready to make sacrifices,
to adjust our schedules,
and to even take time
out from our families
to render practical help
to our brothers.
For example,
beginning at 6 a.m.,
I would visit
the brothers and sisters
and bring them
the things that they needed.
So during two and a half months of war
and two months of reconstruction,
I rode my bicycle
6,500 kilometers.
The local elders from Slavyansk
organized small congregations
and regularly conducted meetings
to support them spiritually.
Major repairs
have been carried out on 20 houses
of brothers and sisters,
and minor repair work
was done on 72 houses
and apartments.
We prepared two more programs.
This time, not only
for the congregations in the war zone
but for the whole country of Ukraine,
even for Russia and Belarus.
We even had 325,000
in attendance.
An interesting experience
was the response of the people
who were not Jehovah’s Witnesses.
They belong to another religion,
yet they said:
“You are the only ones
that really care.
Your genuine love
is shown by your deeds.”
This is what makes us different
from all other religions.
This unselfish love
shown by our brothers
did not go unnoticed
by my husband and my son.
My husband
started studying the Bible,
and he regularly attends
the meetings now.
Recently, he enrolled
in the Theocratic Ministry School.
I experienced this love personally,
and I started studying
the Bible again with the brothers.
Now I am preparing for baptism.
Unfortunately,
one of our sisters was killed.
I realized that a person can lose
—lose everything, but that
is really nothing
compared to losing your children.
The brothers and sisters listened to us.
We cried together.
I just can’t put it into words.
It is as if Jehovah
is holding you in his arms
—he doesn’t let you fall—
as if he is saying to you:
‘Don’t let go, my dear one.
I’m helping you.
I’m supporting you.’
With Jehovah there are no borders
between nations.
I could see
that this was the true religion.
We continue to pray
for our brothers in Ukraine.
We’re confident
of Jehovah’s love for them,
and we know he’ll sustain them
through any tribulation.
Our worldwide brotherhood
is truly special.
When our brothers are in need,
we want to help
in whatever way possible.
It also brings us great joy
to be with our brothers
—whether at the meetings,
in the field service,
or on other occasions.
We love our brothers
and enjoy spending time with them.
At the same time,
because we are all imperfect,
our love and unity will be tested.
We may have our feelings hurt,
or we may hurt
the feelings of others.
That brings me to the theme
I would like to discuss
with you
in this month’s program,
“Settling Differences
Brings Jehovah’s Favor.”
It is based on Matthew 6:14.
Let’s read
this important verse together.
Right after teaching
his disciples how to pray,
Jesus says in verse 14:
“For if you forgive
men their trespasses,
your heavenly Father
will also forgive you.”
To what extent do Jesus’ words
affect how Jehovah
views what we do each day
in our worship to him?
Consider this:
You’re concluding
your day in prayer.
You pray for Jehovah’s name
to be sanctified.
You pray
for his Kingdom to come.
You ask that he bless
the Governing Body
and the brothers taking the lead.
You share with him
a few matters
of personal concern.
And then you say: “Jehovah,
“I know I am imperfect,
“and I sin against you often.
“Please forgive me
for my sins.
“Let me stand before you
in a clean
and approved state.”
Now the question is,
Has Jehovah heard
your heartfelt request?
Will he forgive you?
Well, what did Jesus say?
Look again at verse 14:
“For if you forgive
men their trespasses,
your heavenly Father
will also forgive you.”
Did you notice
Jesus’ use of the word “if”?
That tells us that forgiveness
is not automatic.
It comes with a condition, or price.
What price?
According to Jesus,
‘if we forgive others,’
the condition has been met;
the price has been paid.
What will Jehovah do for us?
Jesus said:
“[He] will also forgive you.”
Really, though,
is it fair or reasonable
for Jehovah to say to us,
‘Only if you forgive others,
then I will also forgive you’?
Well, suppose you
get very sick and lose your job.
You’re unable
to pay rent for many months.
Your situation is desperate.
You have very few,
if any, options.
You worry about your wife
and your children.
Say you go to the owner
of the house and ask
if he would give you time
to get back on your feet.
Once you get better
and are able to work again,
you will do everything
within your power
to pay him what you owe.
He tells you not to worry.
He understands your situation.
He will cancel your debt,
and you do not have
to pay him any rent
until your situation improves.
In fact, he’ll cover
your monthly expenses
until you are able
to care for your family.
How would you feel
about what he has done,
and would this affect
how you treat others?
Well, because of our sinful nature,
we are all in debt to Jehovah
—deserving of death.
We are unable
to cover our expenses.
But when we go
to Jehovah in prayer
and beg for his help,
in his great mercy and kindness,
he tells us not to worry.
He has given the life
of his Son to pay our debt.
And on the basis of that sacrifice,
He is willing to cover our expenses
—the sins we commit daily—
and to extend forgiveness
to us until we are able
to get back on our feet,
when we reach perfection
in the new world.
So think again about those
simple yet powerful words
of Jesus at Matthew 6:14:
“For if you forgive
men their trespasses,
your heavenly Father
will also forgive you.”
Is that fair?
Is that reasonable?
Is it realistic?
Without a doubt!
In fact, settling differences,
or forgiving others freely,
is one of the best ways to imitate
Jehovah’s compassionate
and merciful nature.
What can help us
to settle differences quickly?
The first thing
we should do is to try
and let love cover
over the wrong.
Can I just forgive and forget?
If we are able to do so,
this is a beautiful way to maintain
the congregation’s peace and unity.
But if we’re struggling
to forget the wrong,
there are two scriptures
that are especially helpful
in this matter
of settling differences.
They are Matthew 5:23, 24
and Matthew 18:15-17.
Keep in mind that these texts
are not referring
to the same scenarios,
nor are they to be applied
in the exact same way.
Matthew chapter 5
has a broader application
and can be used to bring peace
in most situations.
Matthew chapter 18
has a more limited application
and applies to specific situations
that are more serious in nature.
Now let’s consider the first text,
Matthew 5:23, 24:
“If, then,
you are bringing your gift to the altar
“and there you remember that
your brother has something against you,
“leave your gift there
in front of the altar, and go away.
“First make your peace
with your brother,
and then come back
and offer your gift.”
To truly capture
what these two brief verses mean
for you and me today,
we have to understand
what Jesus’ words meant
to his first-century Jewish listeners.
Picture the scene in your mind
as we transport ourselves
into the city of Jerusalem
some 2,000 years ago.
It is during one
of the annual festivals.
There are tens of thousands
of people in the city.
You are there to make your sacrifice
—a beautiful lamb.
The best one you have.
It’s clean and unblemished.
You take the lamb
through a series of courts
all the way
to the Court of Priests.
It has taken you
most of the day to get there.
Now you’re ready
to put your hands on that animal
and offer a prayer for forgiveness,
and then you remember something.
What?
Verse 23 reads:
“If, then, you are bringing
your gift to the altar
“and there you remember
that your brother
has something against you,”
Now you think:
‘My brother
‘does have
something against me!
‘The last time I saw him,
‘he greeted
everybody else but me.
‘He was upset.
But what is it?
‘I don’t remember
doing anything.
‘He is so sensitive!
He’s always upset
with something.’
Did Jesus
have all of that in mind
when he said
what he did in verse 23?
No!
He did not go into detail
about what
that “something” might be.
He doesn’t say
who is right or wrong.
He doesn’t make a comment
about whether
someone is too sensitive,
always getting upset,
never satisfied,
difficult to get along with.
Why not?
Because the reason
behind the “something”
is not the important thing.
What is the important thing?
That the peace
has been disturbed.
There is a difference
that needs to be settled.
The lack of peace
between brothers
could affect their relationship
with Jehovah.
That is important!
So what should be done?
We see the answer in verse 24:
“Leave your gift there
“in front of the altar,
and go away.
“First make your peace
with your brother,
and then come back
and offer your gift.”
That animal sacrifice
is important too.
There’s no doubt about that.
It represents worship to Jehovah
—like going to the meetings,
in the field service,
sharing in family worship.
But according to Jesus,
what is more important?
It is settling the difference
—making peace
with our brother first.
Then we will be
in an acceptable position
to offer our gift
of worship to Jehovah.
Yes, settling differences
will bring Jehovah’s favor.
But when can we apply
the principle of Matthew 5?
Whenever there is
a difference to be settled.
Perhaps our brother
misunderstood what we said or did.
Or maybe he didn’t misunderstand
—maybe we did give him
a valid reason to be hurt.
Regardless, we notice
that he has something against us.
In that case, we make peace.
We can also use
the principles of this text
when we are hurt
or have something
against our brother.
We can take the initiative ourselves
to settle misunderstandings,
to resolve differences,
and to make peace
with our brother.
Again, Jehovah blesses
such a spirit.
Now, open your Bible
to Matthew chapter 18.
We mentioned earlier that it has
a more limited application.
How so?
Notice verse 15:
“Moreover,
if your brother commits a sin,
“go and reveal his fault
between you and him alone.
If he listens to you,
you have gained your brother.”
Here Jesus says,
“if your brother commits a sin.”
That is much different
than just having
“something against [us].”
We are talking about a situation
that is much more serious.
What situation?
The revised
Organized to Do Jehovah’s Will book,
page 136, explains
that it “involves financial
or property matters,
“such as failing to repay a loan
“or committing fraud.
“Or the offense
might be slander,
which seriously affects
someone’s reputation.”
Of course,
they are sins that could be resolved
between the individuals concerned
but are also serious enough
to merit expulsion
from the congregation if not settled.
Before we start applying
Matthew 18:15,
we should first consider
whether it is really necessary
to pursue the matter.
Could we simply
forgive the individual
for what was done
or even take the loss
if it were a financial matter?
That is a personal decision.
If we decide to pursue the matter,
what do we do?
Jesus helps us in verse 15,
when he says
that we reveal his fault
between the two of us alone.
We do not discuss
the matter with others,
attempting to get them
to side with us.
We do not go
straight to the elders
and try to get them
to solve the problem for us.
No, we try to resolve
the matter between us.
And since our goal
is to settle the difference,
maintain our relationship
with Jehovah,
and help our brother do the same,
we make repeated efforts
to speak with him
when our initial efforts
are unsuccessful.
Keep in mind
that Jesus did not say:
“Go only once
and reveal his fault.”
When applying this first step,
make it clear
that your motive
is to ‘gain your brother.’
Also, it would be helpful
to clearly state
that you are applying
the first step in settling differences
as outlined by Jesus
at Matthew 18:15.
Of course,
this would be stated in a kindly,
nonthreatening manner
but still in a way
to show the seriousness
of getting the matter settled.
What if the first step
in gaining your brother
is unsuccessful?
Notice verse 16 explains step 2:
“But if he does not listen,
“take along with you
one or two more,
“so that on the testimony
of two or three witnesses
every matter
may be established.”
Yes, we talk with him
in the company of one or two more.
Would that be our best friends?
No.
The whole purpose
is to ‘gain our brother.’
Teaming up with two
of our best friends
could alienate our brother.
Instead, it makes sense
that we would choose
other mature Christians.
How would mature Christians
be helpful?
Well, are we
misunderstanding things?
Could they help him
to reason about the matter?
Could a solution be found?
Having spiritually
mature witnesses there
may help to resolve the matter.
Generally, applying steps 1
and 2 will result
in gaining your brother
and preserving the peace
of the congregation.
If he does not respond
to these repeated efforts
to help him, then what?
You have a decision to make.
Are you willing
to forgive your brother,
even take a loss
if a financial matter is involved?
If you choose
to pursue the matter further,
listen to Jesus’ words recorded
at verse 17:
“If he does not listen to them,
“speak to the congregation.
“If he does not listen
even to the congregation,
“let him be to you
just as a man of the nations
and as a tax collector.”
At this point,
the body of elders
representing the congregation
will get involved.
They will review
the facts of the case and determine
if a judicial committee
should be appointed.
Happily, though,
these situations are rare,
and matters
are often resolved peacefully
before reaching
such a serious point.
Think back again
to that heartfelt prayer to Jehovah.
Has Jehovah heard
our sincere requests?
Will he forgive?
Well, at this moment,
if you realize there is a difference
with your brother
that needs to be settled,
pray to Jehovah about the matter.
Ask him to help you see
beyond the emotion
and make peace.
Do not let any more time go by!
Once we have followed
the simple steps outlined by Jesus
and have forgiven others,
the condition has been met;
the price has been paid.
Then what will Jehovah
do for us?
Jesus said:
‘He will also forgive us.’
As a result,
we will gain the peace of mind
that comes with a clean conscience,
knowing that we have
Jehovah’s favor and blessing.
We can then
make a valuable contribution
to the beautiful,
united brotherhood
that we are privileged
to be a part of.
There are more lessons
in Matthew chapter 18
that teach us how to maintain peace
and unity with our brothers.
Just as important
as settling differences,
Jesus cautioned against becoming
a cause for stumbling.
At a Bethel morning worship,
Brother Stephen Lett described
three ways
we can avoid stumbling others.
Now, this word picture
of someone being stumbled
is quite vivid, isn’t it?
We’ve all seen someone stumbled.
In fact, we’ve all stumbled
ourselves at times,
and there are varying degrees
of consequences.
For example,
a person can stumble,
quickly recover,
and continue
almost uneventfully down the path.
Or a person can stumble,
fall, break a bone,
eventually they recover
—but only after extensive therapy.
Then again, a person can stumble,
fall, hit his head,
never recover
—becoming a casualty.
Well, the situation is similar
when one is stumbled spiritually.
He can recover quickly,
maybe recover over time,
or he may never recover
—becoming a spiritual casualty.
So we cannot know
the ultimate outcome
for someone who is stumbled.
So no wonder we’re cautioned
to be very careful
to never be any cause
for stumbling.
Open up
to Matthew chapter 18,
and here’s
an especially powerful scripture
in this regard.
Matthew 18:6, Jesus says:
“But whoever stumbles
one of these little ones
“who have faith in me,
“it would be better for him
to have hung around his neck
“a millstone
that is turned by a donkey
and to be sunk in the open sea.”
Well, with graphic language,
Jesus describes
how that if we cause someone
to become a spiritual casualty,
we could actually bring
eternal doom
upon ourselves.
But now, here’s a question,
What could we do
to cause someone to stumble?
Well, interestingly,
there are several similarities
between causing someone
to stumble physically
and causing someone
to stumble spiritually.
Let us discuss three.
Now one, pushing someone
could cause them to stumble,
especially if they’re on uneven terrain,
if you think about it.
And this is true
physically and spiritually.
But think about Jehovah
for a moment.
He could push any of us,
couldn’t he?
He could force us to serve him.
He certainly has the power,
but he never uses it that way.
Instead, he invites, he encourages;
and he explains the blessings,
the curses,
depending upon how we decide.
But it’s up to us, isn’t it?
For example, at Isaiah 48:18,
Jehovah says: ‘If only
‘you would pay attention
to my commandments!
‘Then your peace
would become like a river
and your righteousness
like the waves of the sea.’
Beseeching, but not forcing.
Now think about it,
if Jehovah doesn’t force,
he doesn’t want us
to force either, does he?
For example, parents
need to be very careful
they don’t just simply push
their children to serve Jehovah.
But rather, lovingly,
beseechingly like Jehovah,
try to reach the heart,
and of course,
clearly show them the blessings
that will come their way
if they do.
Another example,
elders should never try
to push Jehovah’s sheep.
I heard an experience
about an elder, during his part,
asked the brothers
for a show of hands
how many were going out in service
the next morning.
Well, only a few raised their hand.
He proceeded
to scold the congregation
that more should be going out.
Well, he then unwisely asked
for another show of hands.
You guessed it
—fewer raised their hand
the second time.
Take another example,
those who conduct Bible studies
should not just try to push
their students to do the right thing.
“You’ve got to quit smoking!
You’ve got to get rid of those idols!”
No, not with external pressure,
but by motivating their hearts,
you motivate your students.
Or take another example,
none of us
should try to push schoolmates,
workmates, or relatives
to accept the truth.
A pushing approach,
shoving approach
—even though motivated with sincerity—
has actually resulted
in people being stumbled
away from the truth
for many years.
It makes me think of the story,
or the saying,
that when a person
first learns the truth,
you should lock them up
for about six months
to contain, or minimize,
the damage they do.
Well, that saying is totally erroneous.
You shouldn’t lock that brother up;
you should follow that brother.
See, that brother has zeal,
doesn’t he?
But it’s true,
we probably do need to help him
to properly channel that zeal,
so that he doesn’t try
to force his relatives
or others to accept the truth
that he is so excited about.
But now, what is the second thing
we can do to cause someone
to stumble?
Placing an obstacle in their path.
Now again, this is true
physically or spiritually.
And if you think about it,
whether we put
that stumbling block there intentionally
or unintentionally,
the result is the same, isn’t it?
As mentioned
in today’s Watchtower comments,
wholesome speech and upright conduct
can help us to avoid
ever being a cause for stumbling.
In contrast, unwholesome speech,
unclean conduct,
can easily stumble ones inside
or outside the congregation.
But now, what about in an area
where we have a Scriptural right
to do something?
Now, surely exercising that right,
if it stumbles someone,
we can’t be held accountable
for that, can we?
Well, open up
to 1 Corinthians chapter 8,
and here
—very interestingly—
this scripture
answers that question.
1 Corinthians 8:9,
it says:
“But keep watching
“that your right to choose
“does not somehow
become a stumbling block
to those who are weak.”
Isn’t that interesting?
Even our right to choose,
if it would stumble someone,
we wouldn’t exercise that right
according to this scripture.
The apostle Paul,
in verse 13 of that same chapter,
he said he
wouldn’t even eat meat ever again
if it stumbled his brother.
Well, like Paul,
are we willing
to forgo our rights regarding,
for example,
wearing a beard,
wearing heavy makeup,
using alcohol
—as just a few examples—
if exercising that right
might even possibly stumble someone?
But now,
what’s the third way
we could cause someone to stumble?
Failing to warn him
about a potential trip hazard.
We could call this
the sin of omission.
And again,
it applies physically and spiritually.
As a physical example,
let’s say we see the floor
has just been mopped,
and an unsuspecting person
is approaching that wet area.
Now will we warn them?
If we don’t warn them
—they fall, hurt themselves—
would we not share
some responsibility?
Well, similarly,
with spiritual application,
Galatians 6:1 tells us
that if someone “takes a false step”
before he’s aware of it,
what are we supposed
to try to do?
“Try to readjust” such a person,
but then it adds:
“In a spirit of mildness.”
Don’t push him!
But try to gently, lovingly warn
and readjust that person.
So there we have three areas
in which we must be careful
we never contribute
toward someone being stumbled.
We don’t push others
to serve Jehovah.
We strive to never,
even unintentionally,
put a stumbling block in their path
—for example—
by insisting on exercising
our personal rights.
And number three,
we never fail to lovingly warn
one whom we see approaching
a potential trip hazard.
Rather than being
any cause for stumbling,
we want to be
a force for good, don’t we?
Helping others to stand firm
and even helping ones get up
if they have fallen.
None of us want to cause
our brother to stumble,
but it can happen
if we’re not careful.
Why not recall the three ways
Brother Lett listed
to avoid stumbling others?
You can then examine
how you’re doing as a parent,
an elder, a Bible teacher,
or as a fellow worshipper
in the congregation.
The effort we make toward unity
is always worthwhile.
We want only joyful memories
of the years spent
working side by side
with our brothers and sisters.
That’s the way
Sister Esther Lozano looks back
on 73 years
of special full-time service.
Well, everybody here
calls me Honey, but my name
is Esther Lozano.
And I was born in Fresno, California,
in 1919.
I was baptized in 1935,
and I’ve thoroughly enjoyed
my service to Jehovah.
I became a special pioneer,
and then they called me to Gilead.
I was in the fourth class of Gilead.
That was in 1944.
When I left my assignment as a special,
I didn’t even know how it was to study,
but this was beautiful
how Gilead prepared us
for what was in the future.
Right after Gilead,
we went to Brooklyn Bethel for two years
—Esther Lopez and I—
then I was sent to Mexico.
I came in 1947,
and I’m still here.
So that makes more than 68 years
I’ve been in Mexico.
When I arrived,
there were 7 Bethelites,
and there were 22 missionaries.
We all lived right at the branch;
it was a branch-missionary home.
The progress in Mexico
really is because of the families
being united.
And when you get
the husband and wife together,
then the whole family
comes in the truth.
In 1961, Sister Esther Lozano
preached to our grandparents.
My grandfather first got interested
through the book
From Paradise Lost to Paradise Regained.
When I placed the book
with his wife
and she gave it to him,
he decided that that’s what
he was looking for.
He said,
“Well, when can I be baptized?”
Three visits later,
a study was started
with the entire family.
And the oldest son was only 13.
He said,
“I’m getting baptized too!”
About a year ago, he came
and brought me a letter
and told me how happy he was
that I had gone to their home
and preached to them.
And that was
a happy experience of my life.
Today, in our family,
we are 23 Witnesses
spread over four generations,
and now my brother
and I are serving here
at the Central America branch.
Oh, I forgot to talk about my husband.
He was the branch overseer at that time.
We were there
in the same branch for five years.
We got to know each other,
but I didn’t pay attention to him
because I was always in the service.
And so,
I don’t know when he decided
he wanted to get married
because I know
that wasn’t his goal in life.
And so I wrote Brother Knorr
and asked him if he was surprised
to hear that we
were going to be married.
Then he did write me back
and also said,
well this is what he said in the letter:
‘You’re always jolly
and talkative when I’m around.
‘On the other hand,
‘Brother Lozano is so quiet.
‘I must say,
it is an interesting combination.
‘Both of you together
can serve him and aid
one another in your true worship.’
This is one of my greatest treasures,
having that letter from Brother Knorr.
Then when Rudy died,
I didn’t dwell on that.
I remembered
I made my dedication to Jehovah,
and I know that he would want me
to put that first in my life.
So I did not really suffer
that much about his death
because I became even more involved
in theocratic activities.
I’m in the Correspondence.
But I’m at work
about an hour and a half in the morning
and an hour and a half
in the afternoon
and the rest of the time
I’m studying here in the room.
I’m so pleased that I’m still able
to go to the morning text,
and I have a part in the service.
I have two studies
that I conduct every week.
It’s such a pleasure
to be with people
that have dedicated
their lives to Jehovah.
And that’s what makes me happy
because I know
Jehovah counts them
as his precious sons and daughters.
I don’t know why,
but many of the missionaries
have come up to me and told me
that I’ve been
an encouragement to them,
and really,
they are the ones that encourage me.
It’s because I had
such beautiful examples
to follow in all these years.
And all I can say
is thanks to Jehovah
for this great privilege
of serving him.
Sister Lozano is a beautiful example
of sticking to your assignment
and building
close bonds of friendship.
Did you notice
another blessing she enjoyed?
It was finding a marriage mate
who shared her goals
for full-time service.
Of course,
not every courtship leads to marriage.
If you’re dating,
can you look past your emotions
to honestly see the differences
and flaws
in your potential mate?
Can you accept these?
Or are they serious enough
for you to end your courtship?
That’s the situation
depicted in the third
and final part of the series
Preparing for Marriage.
Well, the big day finally arrived.
After all those months of preparation,
it was just as I imagined.
Oh wait!
That’s not me.
That’s me.
As I watched my sister
get married that day,
I couldn’t help
but think about my own future.
When I began dating Shane,
everything was perfect.
We spent a lot of time
talking on the phone.
Everything just naturally
seemed to click.
I was convinced he was the one.
But over time,
I started to notice some things.
I was starting to see patterns.
And they didn’t seem
to be getting better.
I wasn’t even sure
our goals were the same anymore.
I felt alone.
But thankfully, I wasn’t.
My mom kindly asked
how things were going,
so I told her.
“Maybe he’s not the one,”
I told her.
I thought she was going to tell me
which way I should go,
but she didn’t.
Instead, she reassured me
that if he wasn’t the one,
I was going to be OK.
They reminded me about what Jesus said
when building a tower.
“For example, who of you
wanting to build a tower
“does not first sit down
and calculate the expense
to see if he has enough
to complete it?”
I realized that I was about to enter
into a building project of my own
—my relationship with Shane—
and I too needed
to “calculate the expense”
before I commit to it.
They encouraged me
to talk to Shane
and tell him about the things
that were concerning me.
So I did.
And my mom was right.
I was OK, more than OK, really.
Shane and I decided it was best
to break off the relationship.
And some years later,
I found someone
that loves Jehovah as much as I do,
and I love him with my whole heart.
Our sister wisely compared
her relationship
to a building project.
She “calculated the expense”
of any traits she saw
during their courtship
—well before they
could become problems in a marriage.
Of course,
we shouldn’t expect
perfection from our mate,
but working through matters
during courtship
is another opportunity
that Jehovah provides
to settle differences in peace.
There’s something common
to every successful marriage
between two Christians.
It is their putting Jehovah first
and supporting
each other’s personal dedication to God.
This is certainly true
with Viv and Ann Mouritz,
serving
in the Australasia branch.
They’ve been married
for 65 years
and have
a combined 131 years
in full-time service.
Listen to their advice
for younger ones
deciding what to do
in Jehovah’s organization.
I started pioneering
in November 1948.
That’s a while ago now.
And that’s what I thought
I would do—pioneer.
So I said, “Well, Jehovah,
if I do what you ask me,
“I accept whatever assignment
you give me,
“and I’ll just go
where you send me,
and I won’t seek an assignment,
but I won’t refuse one.”
That’s all I intended to do
as far as I knew,
but then I had only been pioneering
about a year
when I got this envelope,
and the letter said:
“Please fill in the enclosed form.”
It was an application for Bethel,
and I thought,
‘Goodness, I didn’t think of Bethel.
I told Jehovah I’d go where he sent me,
so don’t argue, just do it.’
I was working in the printery
cleaning out old ink tins
and making schedules
for printing and so on.
And then I got to work
on the press too,
but I wasn’t there very long
when they moved me to the office.
Well, you learn a lot in Bethel.
You learn how to live
with your brothers,
which you’re not used to.
You learn about Jehovah’s organization
—you see how it operates.
I had the privilege of working alongside
brothers who had lots of experience.
I got assigned
to Metropolitan Congregation.
That’s where Ann was.
Yeah, we got married
in October 1951,
and two weeks later,
I started pioneering.
I was 20 at that time
when we started circuit work,
and I’d only pioneered for a year;
so of course I was very worried
and scared about having to witness
with sisters
that had pioneered for years
and some of them even of the anointed.
I cried halfway to Melbourne.
We got very close
to the brothers and sisters
and especially to the children,
so we really loved that.
And then we
got the opportunity to go
to New York
to the international convention
in 1958.
When the Society found out
we were going, they sent us
an application for Gilead,
and we thought, ‘Oh, my goodness.
How can we do that?’
So we said,
“Well, we don’t say no.”
After the ‘58 convention,
we were assigned to special pioneer
in Canada for six months.
Brother Knorr said
we were in cold storage,
so there were about 40 of us
from British Commonwealth countries.
So that was a good experience too.
We saw winter for the first time.
I did, anyway.
And we took pictures
of snow and ice and icicles
to show in our assignment when we
got into India or Africa or somewhere.
And Jehovah had a sense of humor;
he sent us to Finland.
Well, the schooling you get from Gilead
or the other schools
helps you to see Jehovah’s organization
and how it works.
We didn’t know a lot about Finland
except that we knew it was cold
and clean
and a long way from Australia.
Being so far from Australia,
we knew that we
wouldn’t be able to get home
to see our families,
not for a long, long time.
When we moved into Finland,
the brothers
in Russia and those countries
were under ban.
They needed spiritual food,
and so it had to be supplied to them.
So we used to send people in as tourists,
and they would meet
the brothers there
and deliver the food to them.
Without Jehovah’s blessing
and his spirit,
we couldn’t have done it at all.
It’s amazing to think
that the amount of spiritual food
that got in there,
they translated it,
and they made it available.
And we did that for over 20 years
without any mishaps.
It couldn’t happen
without Jehovah’s blessing.
Leaving Finland was not easy,
of course.
We had mixed feelings,
but, actually,
I saw Jehovah’s hand
in the assignment
because we really got back
to Australia
at a time when my parents
were needing help,
so we didn’t have to leave Bethel
or full-time service
to give that help.
We were asked
to go to Russia in 1999.
That turned out
to be two and a half years.
I was a little apprehensive
about going to Russia,
but it was really one of the most
memorable assignments
we’ve ever had.
In Russia, the brothers
were not used to house-to-house work
because of all the years under ban.
And that was quite different
because you go to the door;
you can’t just strike up a conversation.
The person wants to know
why you are there.
And you can’t make
a return visit on someone
you met on the street
—well, you don’t know
where he lives.
If you’ve called at his house, you do,
and you can make a return visit.
The brothers saw
the advantage of that.
But they had to learn.
It was a new thing.
Circuit overseers had to learn
how to visit congregations,
and Polish brothers came in
and helped a lot with that
—did circuit work—
but they too had to learn.
So it was a big change for them
to come from working
under ban all their lives
to now working the way
the rest of the world does.
The best decision I ever made
was to put my life
in Jehovah’s hands,
and to say, “You decide
where I go and what I do.”
I’ve had the feeling all along,
and it’s proven true so far,
that everything I have done
has been training for something else.
So, what I’m doing now
is still training.
It must be for the new world
because I haven’t got
much time left in this one.
What will it be?
Well, who knows?
So my recommendation
to everyone is:
Don’t decide for yourself.
Let Jehovah do it.
Brother and Sister Mouritz
always looked to Jehovah
for their assignments.
For Brother Mouritz,
that’s meant serving
on the Branch Committees
in Finland, India,
Russia, Poland, Ukraine,
and Australasia
and the privilege of making visits
to more than 70 countries
as a representative
of world headquarters.
We can certainly pursue
any form of service
that our circumstances allow.
But when we pray
for Jehovah’s direction,
we rely on him to send us
where it benefits his organization
and ourselves the most.
The willing spirit
to do Jehovah’s will
is shared by Bethelites
who have received
new assignments in the field.
Adjustments in the work at Bethel
have put greater emphasis
on the preaching work.
More resources,
including experienced Bible teachers,
are being directed
to the busy harvest.
In this report
from the South Africa branch,
we hear from loyal ones
who are supporting theocratic direction.
On September 23, 2015,
it was announced
at all branches that
the Governing Body was requesting
all Bethel families to reduce in size.
For me personally,
when they made that announcement
on Wednesday, September 23,
that was exciting.
It was—
I knew it was momentous.
When the announcement was made,
tears welled up in my eyes
because I realized how close we are
to the end.
And I remember just closing my eyes
and saying to Jehovah,
“Whatever you want, we’ll do.”
When I received news of my reassignment,
initially I was numb.
When I got the news
about my reassignment,
I was so scared in the beginning.
It caught me off guard.
I wasn’t expecting it.
We were quite shocked and sad,
but we were encouraged by the brothers
at Bethel and also in the congregation.
The direction from the Governing Body
was that we were being reassigned
as regular pioneers.
We signed the forms for pioneering
that very Thursday.
For me, I’ve always appreciated
the scripture at 1 Samuel 12:22
where it states there:
“For the sake of his great name,
Jehovah will not abandon his people.”
I don’t want to forget my Bethel time,
because it was lovely,
but I want to stretch forward ahead
to pioneering and really enjoy it.
We prayed specifically for a place
that is going to help us
to be as simple
as possible so that we can focus
our attention to the ministry.
All that I’d love to say
to everyone who has been reassigned
is that Jehovah is our Father,
and he will never relinquish
his responsibility as a Father.
He will take care of us.
We are losing four couples
from our congregation.
And I would like to tell
the congregations
where they have been assigned to
that they are getting
real spiritual people
and that they are
really going to be an asset
to their congregation.
I just want to also thank
the brothers in the congregation
where we are going to
because they organized
secular work for us
and also, as Bonnie mentioned,
accommodation.
So they made it easier for us
to look forward to our assignment.
But we know this,
of course, comes from Jehovah.
And so the Branch Committee said,
“Well, we have to move quickly with this.”
We asked the family,
“Please, give us two,
three weeks to work things out,”
and that is what they appreciated.
Congregations phoned in.
The Bethelites were offered jobs.
They were offered accommodation.
Our congregation is delighted
having two young Bethelites
coming and joining us.
Our congregation
has quite a number of young people.
We can already see that
it’s going to benefit them quite a lot.
We’ve actually assisted them
in getting a place
where they could stay,
and also we’ve assisted them
to settle in
and be part of the congregation.
Welcome to our new home!
We’ve been here
a little over a week now.
The brothers helped
to paint the house,
to put tiles on,
to clean the entire place.
So they really did
a lot of work in our behalf.
Also, memories
of our friends from Bethel.
It was about six months ago
when we enjoyed pioneer school.
Thanks to our brothers,
we were able to find employment.
Jehovah has been
answering our prayers,
and sometimes
he has been answering
our concerns
even before we even pray about it.
No doubt,
these extraordinary experiences
in South Africa
are mirrored all over the world.
The love we show
to each other is a reflection
of Jehovah’s great love
for each of us,
and we thank him to be a part
of this amazing brotherhood.
The Governing Body
deeply appreciates
the brotherhood’s loyal response
to theocratic direction.
Change is not always easy,
but it helps when we look
at Jehovah’s blessing
on new spiritual provisions
and adjustments to the work.
Letters of appreciation
from our brothers
add to the Governing Body’s confidence
that Jehovah
is directing his organization.
A sister from the United States
wrote this about JW Broadcasting,
“Often the programming seems like
a direct answer to a prayer.”
After a particularly difficult day,
she added:
“What did I find today at home
for me like a present from Jehovah?
The March [2016] broadcast
. . . dealing with discouragement.”
After watching
the January 2016 broadcast,
a family from Austria wrote:
‘Our eldest son is serving
in the branch in Selters, Germany.
‘We are very proud of him,
but we terribly miss him.
‘So we love the new song,
“I Give You My Best.”
‘It’s heartwarming
that you know our feelings
and value our offers.’
Jehovah is certainly giving us
what we need
when we need it.
And it comes to us
in such variety.
This next music video,
for example,
fits well with our discussion
on settling differences.
It begins with a situation
between a young mother
and her mother-in-law
and reminds us
to “Forgive One Another.”
Yes, you had the best of intentions.
Kindnesses too numerous to mention.
But thoughtless words
just cut me to the heart.
Then, as a tear appears, I see.
Things aren’t what they seem to be.
Before the sun slips from the sky,
Let’s be sure we both see eye to eye.
We’ll forget the things we said,
And, please, let’s forgive.
Sisters today, sisters we’ll stay.
Getting along is not always easy.
Angry words can bring you down, believe me.
Then you find a reason to forgive,
And now you realize it’s true;
Letting go’s the thing to do.
Before the sun slips from the sky,
Let’s be sure we both see eye to eye.
We’ll forget the things we said,
And, please, let’s forgive.
Brothers today, brothers we’ll stay.
Not one thing said or done can break us up.
Love’s a bond of unity.
Cancel the debt; forgive and forget.
That’s the way true friendship should be.
Before the sun slips from the sky,
Let’s be sure we both see eye to eye.
We’ll forget the things we said,
And, please, let’s forgive.
Here in our hearts, that’s where it starts.
Bonded in love, forgiving one another.
Did you see two critical areas
where we need to be forgiving?
It was in the family
and in the congregation.
We’ll always have reasons
in this imperfect world
to forgive.
Look for the opportunities
in your life
to imitate Jehovah
and forgive others.
As we conclude our program,
we take you on a visit
to world headquarters
in Warwick, New York.
The Bethel family
has been moving
into their new work areas.
More than 25,000 brothers
and sisters
worked on the construction
of the facility.
It was a united effort
by temporary volunteers,
construction servants,
Bethelites, construction groups,
and volunteers
who previously worked
on Kingdom Hall projects.
Earlier this year,
workers were making
final preparations for the arrival
of world headquarters staff.
When open for tours,
visitors will enjoy
the historic Bible display,
a visual history exhibit
of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
and an interactive museum
explaining how Jehovah directs
his organization today.
We thank Jehovah for all
who helped to complete
the new world headquarters.
That includes
the thousands of volunteers
but also the millions
of you dear brothers and sisters
who support the worldwide work
with your regular donations.
We send you our love
and pray for Jehovah
to bless
our united brotherhood.
From Brooklyn, New York,
this is JW Broadcasting!