When we think of Acts 1:8,
we think of this challenging assignment
that the apostles were given,
and we can only just imagine
them thinking about
the other promise of “power”
and “holy spirit” being with them.
They certainly would need that to go
“to the most distant part of the earth.”
When we think back
to the first century,
we think of ones such as
the apostle Paul, Barnabas, Timothy,
and many others
who literally tried to go
as far as they could
to reach various territories.
If we take our Bibles
and turn to the book
of Romans 15:23, 24,
we see summarized here
the apostle Paul’s viewpoint
with regard to this.
Romans 15:23:
“But now I no longer have
untouched territory in these regions,
and for many years
I have longed to come to you.”
And that’s the brothers in Rome.
“Therefore, when I journey to Spain,
I hope that I will see you.”
So Paul was very concerned
about going to untouched territories.
Well, in recent times,
we can say the same
is true of Jehovah’s people,
whether it be the Gilead missionaries
who have been sent out
or other missionaries even prior
to the time of Gilead
being established.
Or we think of the brothers
who have moved to other countries
to serve where the need is greater
or perhaps those who
have gone out to unassigned territories
or helped in areas
where very few people
get the opportunity
to hear the message.
When we hear
those experiences,
we certainly are encouraged
by them, aren’t we?
But perhaps we
could think this morning
about just one of the aspects
of the history in the past.
It’s something referred to
in the March 2016 Watchtower,
in the “Questions From Readers.”
You remember this was discussing
the valley of dry bones
in Ezekiel 37.
It spoke about
the gradual restoration
of true worship,
and it made the comment
there that in the Scriptures,
it speaks of a “rattling” noise.
And The Watchtower
made this comment,
it said that even
prior to the time of the end,
there were some
faithful individuals
who stood up
in behalf of true worship.
Then it said:
“Some of them endeavored to produce Bibles
in the languages of the common people.”
So let’s just think
for a few moments about some of those
—perhaps less than 100 years
before the time that Brother Russell
started The Watchtower—
and how many
of those were motivated
to go to distant parts
of the earth
to translate the Bible
and help others there.
For example,
in the year 1793,
a man by the name
of William Carey
was a British shoemaker.
And this shoemaker
was very impressed with the words
recorded at Matthew 28:19, 20.
He felt strongly that all Christians
should follow that command.
So his goal was to go to India.
And he arrived in India
and faced all sorts of problems
—eventually his wife died,
his son died as well,
he had to take
a job planting indigo.
But this man, within 21 years,
with the help of some others,
was able to translate the Bible,
well, parts of it,
in 36 languages.
Then in 1797,
another man,
Henry Nott,
from England
was a bricklayer.
And he and quite a number
of others arrived in Tahiti.
Now, four of those on that ship
were noted to be pastors,
but they had
no formal training whatsoever.
Henry Nott hadn’t had
a very good education.
He was a bricklayer;
he just had the basic education.
But this very faithful man
decided to learn Hebrew and Greek
and translate the Bible into Tahitian.
And he learned Tahitian very quickly,
and in 1835,
after 30 years of translating,
it says that he put down his quill
and the Tahitian Bible, which,
incidentally, uses Jehovah’s name
in both the Hebrew
and the Greek sections of the Bible.
Then 1807,
Robert Morrison
—a man who was determined
to translate the Bible into Chinese.
He arrived in China to find out
that if anyone
taught a foreigner Chinese,
there was a death penalty.
So he remained indoors
for a couple of years
while he learned
the Chinese language.
And then when he
started to translate the Bible,
he found out the emperor
had stated there would be a death penalty
for anyone who printed
Christian literature in that country.
Well, in 1819,
Morrison completed
his version there of the Bible.
In 1812,
Judson, an American,
along with his wife,
left America
just after two weeks
of marriage and,
in 1813,
arrived in Burma,
which is now known
as Myanmar.
And his determination
was to translate
the Bible into the local language,
which was very hard there.
There was no dictionary;
there was no one
that could actually teach him,
and yet he set
to learning the language.
He had a period of time
where he was in prison
with three pairs of iron fetters
attached to his body.
And he was very concerned
about his Bible manuscript
that he’d been translating,
which was hidden
in the earth under his home.
His wife eventually brought it
to him in prison.
It was hidden in a pillow.
Well, this man,
by 1835,
had the Bible translated
into the local language there.
But not all of these
were white missionaries
from either America or England.
When the message
reached the Pacific, for example,
many local persons
—Polynesians—
were very determined to go
to other islands within the Pacific
to spread the message.
An example of this is in 1823.
A man,
a Polynesian by the name of Papeiha,
was determined to get
the message in Rarotonga,
in the Cook Islands.
So the mission ship arrived there;
the two missionary couples
from overseas,
white missionaries,
were put ashore.
There was a misunderstanding
with a drunken king,
which resulted in them
being beaten up,
all their possessions
being stolen,
and them fleeing back
to the ship.
But Papeiha was determined
to take the Gospel message
to those islanders.
So it’s reported that he said
that he would swim ashore
and that he called out:
“Ko Jehova toku tiaki!
Tei roto au i tona rima!”
which translated means
“Jehovah is my shepherd!
I am in His hand!”
And holding a book
with some translations
of the Bible in Tahitian,
he jumped overboard,
swam ashore,
and started preaching
to the local people.
Well, you can’t help
but admire that enthusiasm.
The conditions
that these missionaries met
were very, very difficult,
very primitive conditions.
In one country,
the missionaries lived in villages
where people
still practiced cannibalism and,
in many cases,
when the chief died,
all his wives were executed
at that point and buried with him.
So in the midst
of these conditions,
these men translated
the Bible and, in many cases,
used Jehovah’s name
not only in the Bible
but in their personal writings.
What kept them going?
What helped them to go
to these distant parts of the earth?
Well, a book on the history
of the missionary work in the Pacific
makes this interesting comment.
It says:
“Strong faith in Jehovah
often overcame fear and despair.”
What an interesting thought.
Well, the obvious question is,
Were these ones anointed?
The answer obviously is,
We don’t know.
But we do know
that Jesus said in Matthew 13
there would be
wheatlike “sons of the Kingdom”
right down through history.
And if some of them
were involved with this type of work,
I’m sure we wouldn’t be surprised.
And in the future,
we will no doubt find out
if they were involved
with that work or not.
But what about us today?
Well, does it mean we
have to all leave our Bethel homes now
and go to the most distant parts
of the earth?
Well, remember,
in Acts 1:8,
Jesus was speaking to people
there in Jerusalem,
and you may already be living
in one of the most distant parts
of the earth
when you view it
from Jerusalem’s viewpoint.
But the main thing is,
wherever we are
—if we can reach out
and go somewhere else
or whether we can preach
within our own territory—
if we follow the example
of these faithful ones,
we’ll be sure to try
and reach out to persons
who have not had
the opportunity to hear the truth,
whether near or far.