The trunk of the African elephant
is an impressive multitool.
It is both flexible
and strong.
It can pick up a blade of grass
or uproot a tree.
Some elephants can use
their trunks to feed themselves
around 270 kilograms (600 lbs)
of vegetation
every day.
With their trunks,
they can suck water like a straw,
spray like a fountain,
and swim with a snorkel.
The trunk can give a gentle touch,
give a strong push,
or sound a warning trumpet.
Engineers admire
the elephant trunk’s remarkable flexibility.
This comes from having no bone.
Instead, it contains
about 150,000 muscle units
—an incredible marriage
of strength and structure.
Inspired by the elephant’s trunk,
researchers are designing robots
for the future with greater flexibility.
Industrial design
often can be made better by copying
the perfectly beautiful solutions
in the natural world.
What do you think?
Did the elephant’s trunk evolve?
Or . . .