‎This morning I thought I’d discuss the matter
‎of how a proper view of discipline
‎keeps us close to Jehovah.
‎Now, in the context of today’s text
‎about Jehovah correcting
‎to the proper degree,
‎he’s talking to his people
about being brought back to their land.
‎He was not going to exterminate them
or leave them,
‎and it helps us to appreciate
that he wanted them
‎to keep their relationship with him.
‎Now, today we receive
discipline in various ways.
‎It might be from personal Bible study.
‎And I was excited this morning
‎(I don’t know when it happened,
maybe last night)
‎to see that we have in JW Library®
‎where we can put our personal notes,
‎and I got started with some already.
‎So that’ll be like thoughts
or discipline from Jehovah
‎that is just between him and ourselves
‎—a very beneficial and wise way
to go when it comes to discipline.
‎It keeps us from veering off
in our relationship with him.
‎It might be something
we read in a publication;
‎might hear in a talk at a meeting,
at an assembly,
‎or convention;
something in a JW Broadcast
‎—various ways, any number of ways
Jehovah will discipline us.
‎And we need to remember
‎that he does it
so that we remain close to him.
‎The problem is discipline
is not easy to take.
‎It requires humility.
‎And the proper view of discipline
is found here in Proverbs chapter 3,
‎and this gives us the Scriptural basis
‎to have this proper view of discipline
‎that’ll keep us close to Jehovah God.
‎Now, notice verses 11 and 12
of Proverbs chapter 3:
‎“My son, do not reject
the discipline of Jehovah,
‎“and do not loathe his reproof,
‎“for those whom Jehovah loves
he reproves,
‎just as a father does a son
in whom he delights.”
‎So how might we reject
the discipline of Jehovah?
‎Well, put yourself
in a position of being counseled.
‎It’s come to the point
where overseers and elders
‎have had to sit down with you.
‎Now, for some,
as soon as the counsel begins to flow,
‎there’s this quickness to be upset,
‎to justify, to feel picked on.
‎Well, Jehovah is saying, ‘Don’t reject this.’
‎If they’re using the Scriptures
and thoughts from publications,
‎view it as coming from Jehovah
so that we can stay close to him.
‎Now, to give you an idea,
‎sometimes reading something
will bring us close to Jehovah,
‎especially if we veered off
and didn’t even realize it.
‎I’m going to go way back
to some examples
‎of Jehovah’s sheep
reading something in The Watchtower,
‎and it just disciplined them
so that they could get close to Jehovah.
‎And it goes way back to 1982,
‎and it had to do with TV serials,
or soap operas.
‎Some are saying,
“Well, that’s a long time ago.”
‎Well, the fact is nothing has changed.
‎Some of these soap operas
are still on that had the name
‎that they had in 1982.
‎They still have it.
‎So many readers
personally benefited from the counsel.
‎The counsel still applies
that was found there.
‎But I think it’s very touching
and commendable
‎for the ones who read that
that they recognized it.
‎It impacted their relationship with Jehovah,
‎and they wanted to get close to him.
‎Now, the cover on The Watchtower was
‎“TV Serials—Can They Corrupt the Heart?”
‎And in the opening article, we did say:
‎“Millions of women and men of all ages,
‎races and backgrounds
will rarely miss a show.”
‎Well, now you can record them
and have them anytime that you like.
‎It’s still an ongoing problem
and an issue for a true Christian,
‎a worshipper of Jehovah,
to make sure we’re not being corrupted
‎by soap operas, or TV serials.
‎Now, after the articles came out,
‎we had some write in
to explain what happened to them.
‎And so months later,
after this 1982 issue of The Watchtower
‎(that was December 1),
‎we went
to the ’83 Watchtower, December 1,
‎and here’s the response
from some of the readers.
‎And I found it very commendable.
‎I think you’ll appreciate the humility
because it takes humility
‎to accept and have
the proper view of discipline.
‎So one of the dangers
‎that the brothers
were warned about is that
‎you can get emotionally attached
to the characters in the show.
‎So here’s what one wrote:
‎“I had grown up
watching this one soap opera
‎“and the character ‘Julie’
was just like my ‘friend.’ . . .
‎“One day ‘Julie’ had an accident
‎“that left her beautiful face
badly scarred . . .
‎“I was in front of the TV set every day
‎“to make sure
she was going to pull through.
‎“That night as I was saying my prayers,
‎“before I even thought
what I was saying,
‎I prayed,
‘And Jehovah, please bless Julie.’”
‎Well, she admits:
“‘I was shocked.
‎“‘[She should’ve been.]
‎“‘This plea to Jehovah for Julie
had come from my heart!’
‎“Realizing how involved
she had become,
‎“she stopped watching these programs.
‎“She wrote: ‘If all readers
‎“‘will take your article
on TV serials to heart,
‎“‘they will feel a real sense of freedom,
‎since our own everyday problems
are enough to cope with.’”
‎So, you see, our sister
had the proper view of discipline,
‎and she was able
to keep close to Jehovah.
‎Now, another one,
after expressing appreciation, wrote:
‎“I realized that I was ‘addicted’
to soap operas,
‎“and that I had to do something about it.
‎“I wondered, too, if my relationship
with Jehovah could be affected.
‎“How could I have ‘them’ as friends
‎“and also be a friend to Jehovah?
‎“I had to quit all at once
‎—it was the only way,
and how hard it was!” she admits.
‎So, what did she
have to do to break free?
‎She had to unplug her TV.
‎She’d go outdoors
and work in the garden, call somebody
‎—anything to stay busy
so that she wouldn’t go back
‎to watching those soap operas.
‎She took time for personal Bible study
‎—that’ll keep you close to Jehovah—
‎preparing for her meetings,
and other spiritual things.
‎And then she confesses:
“How much better I felt!
‎“It has been over two years now
[from this last writing]
‎“since I have seen
those so-called friends.
‎“I must admit
that at times I still wonder
‎“what is going on with them,
but I fight it. . . .
‎Perhaps many others
who have not yet broken free will now.”
‎She says:
‘Thank you, Jehovah and you brothers,
‎for exposing
this “good-for-nothing thing.”’
‎Then, finally, this third one says:
‎“I cried when I read the articles,
‎“for I discovered that my heart
was no longer complete toward Jehovah.
‎“I promised my God
‎“that I would no longer be
a slave to these serials
‎“and asked him to help me
to get out of my home
‎“on the day of the program. . . .
‎“Two days later,
I was invited to attend a Bible study
‎“on the very day and time of ‘my’ serial.
‎“I happily accepted. . . .
‎“[and notice] I now feel
closer to Jehovah,
‎“and my relationship with him
is more intimate.
‎How good Jehovah is
to discipline us through his Word!”
‎Yes, she had
the proper view of discipline.
‎Now, finally,
let’s look in Hebrews chapter 12,
‎and we appreciate
these sincere comments
‎and the counsel there certainly applies.
‎Any kind of entertainment
‎that has that corrupting influence
‎would be avoided by a true Christian.
‎So here at Hebrews chapter 12,
‎notice verse 11:
‎“True, no discipline seems
for the present to be joyous,
‎“but it is painful;
‎“yet afterward, it yields
the peaceable fruit of righteousness
‎to those who have been trained by it.”
‎So discipline is painful,
‎but “the peaceable fruit
of righteousness”
‎makes it worth it
to have a proper view of the discipline
‎and to accept it humbly
‎so that we can remain close
to our precious Father, Jehovah.