Welcome, brothers and sisters.
This is a historic moment!
Our studio has moved
and is now located only minutes
from the new world headquarters complex
at Warwick, New York.
And this first program
from our new studio
will bring you
many spiritual gems.
First, what obstacles
have been overcome
so that common people
can read God’s Word?
In this exciting documentary,
we will see the courage shown
by William Tyndale of England.
What helped two fierce enemies
to become close friends?
The uniting power
of the Bible is evident
in this account.
And what can we learn
from the apostle Paul
that will improve our ministry?
We will find out as we join this family
during their Family Worship evening.
This is the January program
of JW Broadcasting!
As Jehovah’s Witnesses,
we truly love the Bible.
Why?
Because we know it is God’s Word.
That’s why we love reading it,
we love studying it,
and we love learning about its history.
When we pause
for a moment and reflect on
the many efforts that have been made
through the centuries
to hinder and even stop
the distribution of the Bible,
it becomes obvious
that its Author, Jehovah,
has been personally involved
in preserving
and making known
his precious Word.
This is very much
in harmony with the thought
in Isaiah 40:8:
“The green grass dries up,
“the blossom withers,
but the word
of our God endures forever.”
With that in mind,
I’m happy to speak
with you this month
on a theme
that’s very close to my heart:
“The Word of Our God Endures Forever.”
The more we come to appreciate
the value of God’s Word,
the more we’ll be moved to read it
and, even more important,
to apply it in our lives.
Jehovah gave us an outstanding gift
when he inspired
faithful men
to record his precious Word.
It’s through the pages of God’s Word
that we learn
just how much God loves us.
Thus, his Word contains
guidance on how to live.
It outlines his purpose
in creating us.
It gives us his precious promises
for life everlasting
in peace and happiness.
No wonder the apostle Paul
was inspired to write
at 2 Timothy 3:16, 17:
“All Scripture is inspired of God
“and beneficial for teaching,
for reproving,
“for setting things straight,
for disciplining in righteousness,
“so that the man of God
may be fully competent,
completely equipped for every good work.”
Of course, Satan the Devil
does not want people to have access
to these precious truths
from our heavenly Father, Jehovah.
It’s no surprise
that there have been many obstacles
to making the Bible available.
While Satan may not have been
directly behind all of these,
he certainly
has made use of them.
What are some
of these obstacles,
and how have they been overcome?
Let’s consider the first obstacle:
language barriers.
The first 39 books of the Bible,
which are often called the Old Testament,
were written primarily
in the Hebrew language.
These books were known
by Hebrew-speaking servants of Jehovah.
However, as time went on,
particularly after
the destruction of Babylon,
many Jews established communities
in other nations of the earth.
Many of these Jews spoke Greek.
They no longer used Hebrew.
That meant that many Jews
no longer had access
to the Scriptures in a language
they could understand.
Consider what had happened.
As Alexander the Great conquered
more and more
of the then-known world,
Greek gradually became
the common language
of commerce and government
throughout his empire.
If the Bible
was to be understood
by the Jews and by Jewish proselytes
who were scattered throughout
this vast Greek-speaking territory,
it needed to be translated into Greek.
Beginning in about the year 250 B.C.E.,
the Hebrew Scriptures began
to be translated into Greek.
In time, that Greek translation
came to be known
as the Septuagint.
It was widely and frequently used
by the Christians
in the first century who spoke Greek.
In fact, the writers
of the Christian Greek Scriptures,
which is often called
the New Testament,
frequently quoted directly
from that translation.
So that obstacle had been overcome.
But there were many more
language obstacles ahead.
As the Roman Empire
began to flourish,
Latin replaced Greek
as a common language.
Now it was necessary
to translate the Bible into Latin.
Some Latin translations
of the Bible books began to appear.
But it was in the year 405 C.E.
that Jerome completed
the definitive Latin translation
of the Bible.
It came to be known
as the Latin Vulgate.
Jerome’s translation
would become
the standard Bible
used by Christendom
for the next nearly 1,000 years.
However, Latin soon became
the language of the learned and the elite,
so the common people
could no longer understand
the Bible’s message.
During that long period,
there were sincere men
that translated portions of the Bible
into some additional languages,
but these translations were,
of course, all made by hand.
Such handwritten copies of the Bible
were rare and expensive.
Therefore,
access to the Bible in vernacular,
or common languages,
was very limited.
But language was not
the only obstacle
that threatened to prevent
the distribution of God’s Word.
Consider a second factor:
direct opposition
to Bible translation and distribution
from religious leaders.
That opposition
started to increase in 1229
when the local church
Council of Toulouse decreed:
“We prohibit also
that the laity should be permitted
to have the books
of the Old or the New Testament.”
In 1234,
the Council of Tarragona decreed:
“No one should possess the books
of the Old or the New Testament
“in the vernacular [language],
“and if anyone possesses them,
“let him deliver them, within eight days
“from the promulgation of this decree,
to the local bishop,
so that they may be burned.”
Thus, during
a very long period in history,
there was limited access to the Bible
in the languages
spoken by common people.
But did that mean
that the Word of God
would not continue to endure?
Neither language barriers
nor opposition from religious leaders
could stop God’s Word
from being made known.
Even in those dark times,
there were individuals
who loved God’s Word
and who worked hard
to translate it
and to make it available to others.
Consider John Wycliffe
and his followers
who were called the Lollards.
John Wycliffe and his associates
completed the translation
of the Bible
into English
about the year 1382.
They eagerly
hand copied the translation
and then traveled
from village to village
reading the Bible
to the common people.
Despite tremendous opposition
from the church,
Wycliffe and his followers
made the Bible available
to many honesthearted people
in the English language.
After Wycliffe died in 1384,
great opposition
came to his followers.
Many had land
and property confiscated.
Others were burned
at the stake.
In response to the work
of Wycliffe and the Lollards,
in 1408,
Thomas Arundel,
Archbishop of Canterbury, declared:
“We therefore decree and ordain
“that no man shall, hereafter,
by his own authority,
“translate any text of the Scripture
“into English,
or any other tongue,
. . . upon pain
of greater excommunication.”
Did such opposition
wipe out efforts
to translate and make
the Bible available?
Absolutely not!
The work of Wycliffe
and his associates
stimulated interest in the Bible
throughout England
and even as far as central Europe.
Religious leaders were not able
to silence the Word of God.
In fact, within just a few decades
after Wycliffe’s death,
two factors
led to a tremendous increase
in the availability
of the Bible.
The first,
about the year 1454,
was the development
of printing with movable type.
This invention would
in time allow for the printing
of large quantities
of Bibles in many languages.
The second factor was
the compiling and printing
of the Hebrew and Greek
original language text
of the Holy Scriptures.
This allowed many translators
to have access
to the original language texts
so that they then could produce
high-quality translations
in their own languages.
What was the result?
In the 1500’s across Europe,
fresh translations
were made and printed
in vernacular,
or common languages,
including German, English, Italian, French,
Dutch, Czech, Danish, Swedish,
Spanish, Slovenian, and many others.
However, opposition continued.
Bible translators were frequently hounded
by the Inquisition,
and some translators like
William Tyndale and John Rogers
were even put to death
for their work.
Nonetheless, the Word of God
continued to endure
and be made available
to more and more language groups.
By the early 1800’s,
Bible translation
began to speed up.
Bible societies
and intrepid translators
began to work
in many parts of the earth
so that the Bible began
to appear in languages
of Asia, Africa,
the Pacific islands,
as well as in indigenous languages
of the Americas.
From 1800 to 1899,
some portions of the Bible
were translated
into some 400 languages,
and from 1900 to 1950,
more than 500 languages
were added.
Consider what has been accomplished
with the New World Translation.
As of this month,
the New World Translation
has been produced
in whole or in part
in 149 languages,
with an additional
37 languages approved.
It’s obvious
that neither language barriers
nor opposition
from religious leaders
was able to stop
the distribution of God’s Word.
Jehovah has protected it
through the ages.
It’s just as Psalm 12:6, 7 says:
“The sayings of Jehovah are pure;
“they are like silver refined
in an earthen furnace,
“purified seven times.
“You will guard them, O Jehovah;
“you will protect each one of them
from this generation forever.”
Yes, Jehovah
has protected each one
of his precious sayings
down through the ages.
But consider a third obstacle.
Although the Bible is now available
in whole or in part
in almost 3,000 languages,
many people are no longer interested
in reading it.
In our modern age,
people have become
increasingly skeptical and irreligious.
Scientists have extolled
the theory of evolution
and have made it appear intelligent
to doubt the existence of God.
At the same time,
secular philosophy has encouraged people
to make life decisions
according to what feels right to them.
What is the result?
A world where people
are often guided
by their own selfish, fleshly desires.
Instead of leading to happiness,
many people are left
feeling empty and dissatisfied.
How is this third obstacle overcome?
Around the world,
people are opening
God’s Word, the Bible,
and reading it
for themselves.
They’re recognizing
that its thoughts
are not simply human wisdom.
As they apply
its principles in their lives,
they find
contentment and joy.
They develop
self-respect and dignity
from living according to
the upright moral standards
outlined by our Creator.
As Psalm 119:97-100 states:
“How I do love your law!
“I ponder over it all day long.
“Your commandment
makes me wiser than my enemies,
“because it is with me forever.
“I have more insight
than all my teachers,
“because I ponder over your reminders.
“I act with more understanding
than older men,
because I observe your orders.”
What a powerful proof
that the Word of God endures forever.
While the advice of human philosophers
is frequently flawed,
the Bible’s counsel works.
If we apply it,
it can help us either
to overcome or to cope
with any problem
or situation that we may face.
What is more,
by explaining
God’s purpose for the future,
it gives us a solid hope
this earth will be restored
to the Paradise
that it was
when it was first created.
It will be filled
with peace and righteousness.
What a wonderful gift
Jehovah gave us through the Bible!
Yes, languages barriers,
opposition from religious leaders,
and even
an increasingly irreligious world
cannot stop God’s Word.
How can you be part
of the evidence
that the Word of God
endures forever?
Read it every day,
study it,
meditate on the deep thoughts
that it contains,
and then apply
those priceless teachings in your life.
In this way,
not just on the printed page,
not just on the library shelf,
but in our minds,
in our own hearts,
in our own lives
the Word of God
will truly endure forever.
Now, let’s get better acquainted
with one of the individuals
we just mentioned
who truly loved God’s Word.
In the 16th century,
English scholar William Tyndale
had to endure harsh persecution
in order to translate the Bible.
But he was convinced
that the Bible had to be translated.
You will notice
that this brief documentary
has been designed also
to appeal to people
who are not
Jehovah’s Witnesses,
as it will later
be made available
on our official website,
jw.org.
In the autumn of 1536,
William Tyndale was led from his prison cell,
in the castle of Vilvoorde,
to the site of his impending execution.
There a post had been prepared for him.
Tyndale was chained to the post,
strangled to death,
and then his body burned
before the onlooking crowd.
His crime?
Tyndale struggled to reconcile
the teachings of the church
with his own studies of the Bible.
William Tyndale died
with his faith intact
that the Bible
is the Word of God.
William Tyndale
was the first person to seek
to translate the Bible
from the original languages
into English.
Tyndale was born
in the late 15th century.
He was born
in the area of Gloucestershire
but had a chance to go to Oxford
and became a priest.
In the 15th century,
there was a lot of resistance
—the idea that the Word of God
could just simply be accessible
by the general people.
People knew the Latin Bible from church,
which was interpreted by the priest for them.
They never had direct access
to the Bible themselves.
Tyndale was not allowed
to do this translation in England.
He went to the Bishop of London
asking for his permission
to translate the New Testament
from the Greek
—the original text—
into English
but was not given that permission.
Such was the opposition
to Bible translation
that Tyndale later wrote
that there was
no place to do it in all England.
And so with the help of merchants
sympathetic to his cause,
Tyndale fled to Germany
where he could more easily work
on his English translation
of the New Testament.
By 1525,
his translation was complete
and ready to be printed.
The British Library in London
holds the answer
to what happened next.
Dr. Karen Limper-Herz,
a lead curator at the library,
is going to help us find out.
So we are looking
at a unique copy of the first edition
of Tyndale’s New Testament,
printed in Cologne in 1525.
The Cologne Fragment
is the only known copy
of what exists of Tyndale’s first edition
of the New Testament.
The fact that it is a fragment
shows that it was a dangerous thing to do.
The printer had too much to drink
and mentioned that he
was printing
this pro-Lutheran English New Testament
for somebody called William Tyndale.
The authorities found out about it,
and the print shop was raided.
Tyndale and his partners ran
—and this is all that survives today—
and they went down the Rhine
a bit further to Worms.
So the fact that they didn’t get much further
than part way through Matthew
is quite indicative
of how dangerous it was.
The first complete copies
of Tyndale’s translation
of the Christian Greek Scriptures
were finally printed
in the city of Worms in Germany
in 1526.
Around 3,000 or more
of these books were produced.
After leaving Germany,
Tyndale moved to Antwerp.
This bustling city
was ideal for Tyndale.
It had a thriving printing industry
and its busy port
made it easy for his books
to reach readers in England.
Professor Guido Latré
has kindly offered to show me
around the very streets that Tyndale
would have walked himself
some 500 years ago.
What he saw around him here
were ordinary people
having access to the Bible in Dutch.
He wanted the same
for his own folk in England.
If you wanted to smuggle Bibles
on a large scale into England,
this was Northern Europe’s biggest seaport.
You can’t easily smuggle
a big volume and a big format.
So tiny loose leaves
that were taken to places like this
—these underground cellars,
the warehouses—
and between the leaves
of larger books
that were not forbidden,
the tiny leaves of Tyndale’s translation
would have been hidden.
In London,
someone would have recognized:
‘Aha!
These are the stacks that are marked.
‘I must have a look at these
and find the loose leaves
of Tyndale’s Bible.’
There were about 30,000 copies
of Tyndale’s Bible available
by the end of his life.
This was a brave man
and a big man in terms of courage
and in terms of investment of time.
And the risks he took
are not to be underestimated.
William Tyndale was imprisoned here
in Vilvoorde,
just north of Brussels.
As he languished
in prison for over a year,
he no doubt contemplated the cruel death
that inevitably awaited him.
Tyndale is often renowned
for his influence on the English language,
but his work was more than
that of just scholarly ambition.
Tyndale loved the Bible.
Maybe it can be said of him
that he shared the feelings of the psalmist
who spoke of God’s Word
and said:
“How I do love your law!”
Despite intense opposition,
the Bible and the wisdom in it
survives to this day,
a faithful transmission
of the original writers’ words.
No wonder so many have placed
such value on the Bible.
You’ll be happy to know
that later this month
an extended version
of this documentary
will be made available.
It contains
additional examples of individuals
who risked their lives
to spread God’s Word.
The video is called
They Valued the Bible
and will be released
on Video on Demand
under the heading
“The Bible.”
Knowing that Jehovah
is personally involved
in preserving
and making known his Word,
we can be confident
that the Bible
is the only true means
of drawing close to him.
As a child,
David Sibrey, from England,
had not read the Bible.
Instead, he had been taught
traditions of men.
What helped him see the truth?
I was born in 1930.
We lived in Littlehampton,
which was a seaside town,
a very pleasant little place,
quiet place.
I would like to walk
in the countryside.
Nature intrigued me.
My interest was in what I saw
rather than what I read.
Well, in 1939,
war broke out, and our road
became the second line of defense.
And then, of course,
you get the aircraft.
Well, there was a young boy
(younger than myself),
and one Sunday morning
an air raid took place,
and the house
where he was living
was destroyed,
and he was killed.
But I remember
saying to my mother,
“Why did he have to die?”
And her answer was:
“Well, he’s in a better place.
He’s with God in heaven,”
which didn’t quite
add up to me.
I couldn’t understand
how God
could be responsible
for his death,
which meant
He was responsible for war.
So it was—
The whole thing was depressing;
perhaps put it that way.
As far as religion was concerned,
I accepted it was there,
but I couldn’t understand
how it fit in with what was going on.
There was a gap somewhere,
and I couldn’t, I couldn’t, plug it.
Every time you went to church,
you had a hymnbook
and a prayer book,
but a Bible was something
you had personally.
And the only time
I ever opened it
was when I began to study
with Jehovah’s Witnesses.
I was 17 or 18 years of age
when I started.
A brother named Joe Gladwin
called upon me.
I knew nothing about the Bible.
The fact that he said it,
fair enough.
He said it was in the Bible, OK.
But what do other people say?
I decided to look for myself.
I realized that what Joe
was telling me was right.
He showed me
that the Bible was true.
I began to see that the Bible
told me things
that I had never known.
Over the years,
I’ve been privileged
to collect so many
different translations of the Bible.
Reading through the different translations,
it’s clear that God’s Word never changes.
I got baptized
at the age of 20 in 1950.
Over the years,
I’ve served first of all as a pioneer.
From then I came to Bethel.
Moving from Bethel
to the circuit and district work,
and then finally,
coming back to Bethel for the Writing Desk.
The assignments I’ve had
have strengthened my conviction
not only that Jehovah
is giving direction and his spirit
can enable us to do
whatever he wants us to do
but that the organization has grown and,
with the development
of the Governing Body’s direction,
is an organization
which is second to none.
And, therefore,
staying with it is the logical thing to do.
In my life,
I looked in many places
for answers
to life’s questions,
but only the Bible
has provided answers.
I am so thankful
that Jehovah continues to teach us.
Brother Sibrey’s appreciation
for the Bible is heartwarming.
Do you remember how
we can personally demonstrate
our appreciation
for the Word of God?
By reading,
studying, and meditating
on the deep thoughts
that it contains
and then by applying
those inspired teachings
in our lives.
When we do that,
we allow the holy spirit
to affect our inner being,
to shape our desires
and objectives in life.
However, what if someone
has harbored resentment
against his fellow man
for years,
perhaps to the point
of wanting to kill that person?
What can God’s Word do
in such a serious circumstance?
Remember the words
of Hebrews 4:12:
“For the word of God
is alive and exerts power
. . . and is able to discern
thoughts and intentions of the heart.”
Yes, Jehovah
has preserved the Bible
so that we can benefit
from the power of his Word.
Vladimir Olkhov
and Valery Zaporozhsky,
who are from Russia,
were the fiercest of enemies,
yet they experienced
that power firsthand.
I was the ringleader of a criminal gang.
We extorted money,
put people out of business,
threatened them,
dragged them away.
And they would hand over everything.
People were afraid of me,
and I liked it that way.
I never forgave anybody.
If someone wronged me,
I would say:
“Throw one stone at me!
I’ll bury you in a mountain of rocks!”
In 1993,
I was working for the police.
They assigned me to gather information
about a gang
whose leader was Vladimir Olkhov.
One time, when committing a crime,
they caught me at the scene.
I swore revenge on everybody involved
with my arrest.
During interrogations,
I did everything
to humiliate Vladimir
and tried to break him.
We just hated each other!
I told Valery,
“Just remember:
“Sooner or later
I’m getting out of prison
and then you’re a dead man!”
I thought to myself:
‘For a start,
‘I’m going to blow up his car.
If he doesn’t understand,
then I’ll just eliminate him.’
His threats sounded so serious
that I started to fear for my life.
I decided to have my friends
and acquaintances
make his life behind bars unbearable
and to make sure
that he would never get out.
I saw that one of my cell mates
had a pocket New Testament.
I asked him if I could read it.
Seeing my interest in spiritual things,
someone gave me a Watchtower magazine.
When I started reading the magazine,
I realized that there are
other people out there—real people.
There’s a totally different way
of life to be had, even now,
and with such prospects.
I was just stunned.
Then I found another five magazines
around the prison.
I devoured them as well.
And I became thoroughly convinced
that I had found the truth.
When my wife was first allowed to visit me,
I told her right away,
“I’ve found the truth!”
My wife made pretty fast progress
and was baptized two years later.
Her support was invaluable.
She would visit me,
constantly encouraging me
to be faithful
and remain loyal to God.
In 1993,
Jehovah’s Witnesses visited me.
I agreed to a Bible study,
but the truth didn’t touch my heart.
One time, Jehovah’s Witnesses
invited me to a gathering,
and there they told me that Vladimir Olkhov
—that criminal—
was about to get baptized
and become one of Jehovah’s Witnesses.
I was cut to the heart!
When I got home,
I burst into tears.
I realized that I had to make
spiritual progress.
Because if he,
in his circumstances,
could do it, then I could do it.
That very moment,
I prayed for the first time in my life.
I was released in October of 1997.
After I was released,
the brothers organized a gathering.
They invited me to this gathering.
I remember
that as I was approaching the place,
I suddenly realized this is where
I once conducted a search!
And then Valery walked into the room.
We just hugged each other
and burst into tears.
And I saw in his eyes
a completely different look,
not like before
—it was a kind look.
It brought tears to my eyes.
It was like a big weight
was lifted from my chest.
‘My brother!’
We begged one another for forgiveness.
On the 23rd of November 1997,
I was baptized together in the same pool
as my new friend Valery.
We really became the best of friends.
And now we serve as elders
in the same congregation.
My wife and I often talk about
what would have happened to us
if we had not started to study the Bible.
Probably we wouldn’t even be alive now.
We’ve kept our family together.
Even better,
we now have a spiritual family
in the Christian congregation.
And my former enemy
is now my brother and best friend.
More importantly, we’ve developed
a close relationship with Jehovah.
Only God is able to change the thinking
of such bitter enemies as Vlad and I were.
And I eagerly look forward to the day
when everything that divides people
will be gone forever.
Do you see
one reason why Jehovah
did not allow his Word
to be obliterated?
He knew the benefits
you and I would reap
from having access to the Bible.
Its message is so powerful,
it could help Vladimir and Valery
to change their lives
and even become close friends.
While very few of us have taken part
in the translation of the Bible,
all of us can share it with our neighbors
and help them to gain
accurate knowledge of Jehovah.
In the following dramatization,
note some of the theocratic activities
that this family enjoys
and what they had to do
to become so zealous.
OK, OK.
We already know
how this story is going to end.
No real surprises there.
So the real question is,
How did we get here?
For the record,
I never thought our ministry
really needed help.
My wife and daughter
were both regular pioneers.
My son was a solid publisher.
And while my schedule
didn’t let me pioneer yet,
I was trying to do
all I could to support them.
I always assumed
the best support I could provide
was just being out with them
as much as possible,
but I quickly realized more was needed.
Our Field Service Group Overseer
had been making a real effort
to work in the ministry with us
regularly the last few weeks,
and he kindly mentioned
he’d noticed a few challenges.
While our service time was great,
he pointed out that our return visits
were slowly dwindling.
And other than the studies
I had with the children,
no one in the family
was conducting a Bible study.
I asked him
what we could do to try
and improve
the quality of our ministry.
He showed me Romans 15:19,
highlighting Paul’s words:
“I have thoroughly preached
the good news about the Christ.”
He suggested
on our next Family Worship night
studying Paul’s ministry and seeing
what we could learn from his example.
As we looked at Paul’s ministry,
we realized
to be more productive
we needed boldness.
Ephesians 6:19 says:
“Pray also for me,
“that the words may be given to me
when I open my mouth,
“so that I may be able to speak boldly
in making known
the sacred secret of the good news.”
Rina also noticed how Paul
reasoned persuasively with people.
And Keiko liked how he found
common ground with those he talked to
—even referring to a pagan altar
to an unknown god
as a way to direct
the conversation to Jehovah.
Finally, Haruto noted how 2 Timothy said
Paul was
“a workman with nothing to be ashamed of,
handling the word of the truth aright.”
So he was skilled in using the Scriptures
with those he witnessed to.
See, I told you.
You already knew
how this was going to end.
I started auxiliary pioneering.
We now have a number of return visits
and a few progressive Bible studies.
But how did we get here?
We learned from the example of Paul
and how he
“thoroughly preached the good news.”
The group overseer
could’ve simply listed
what changes were needed
to improve the family’s ministry.
Instead,
he directed the father
to a specific principle
found in the Scriptures.
After all,
it is only God’s Word
that “is inspired . . . for teaching.”
Bible translations
in common languages
started to spread
across Europe in the 1500’s,
but it took much longer
for more remote places
to receive the Bible.
It was in 1766
that the complete Greek Scriptures,
or New Testament,
was first published in Greenlandic
—a language spoken today
by about 50,000 people.
In August of last year,
I had the privilege of serving
a regional convention in Greenland,
which is overseen
by the Scandinavia branch.
Greenland is the neighbor
to the north of Newfoundland,
where I pioneered for 11 years.
So it was a wonderful experience
to go there and meet our brothers.
Some 400 brothers and sisters
traveled at their own expense
from all over Scandinavia to support
the convention in Greenland.
Although Greenland is a land
covered by large ice caps,
there are many warm hearts
yearning for the truth.
I think that Jesus had Greenland in mind
when he spoke about preaching
to the most distant part of the earth.
My name is Arne Mattsson.
My wife, Karin, and I have lived
in Greenland for more than 34 years.
We have traveled all over the country
preaching about God’s Kingdom,
and we have had
some fantastic experiences.
In the 1950’s, two young special pioneers
came to Greenland
as the first publishers.
They traveled by boat
from town to town
carrying just tents
and simple equipment.
They had to endure
the cold weather,
face resistance
from the local ministers,
and even fight with sledge dogs
that took their food.
But they laid the groundwork
for the great effort
that has been made
to preach to all in this country.
In the 1960’s and ’70’s,
many families
moved here from Denmark
to help with the preaching work.
I remember how I,
as a teenager in 1971,
moved from Denmark
to Greenland with my family.
It was not easy
to learn the language,
but the brothers and sisters
from Denmark did their best,
and it had a good effect
on the territory.
In 1973, The Watchtower began
to be published in Greenlandic.
Just to pronounce the name,
Napassuliak’ Alapernaerssuivfik,
was a challenge.
But it has been a popular magazine
in Greenland ever since.
Once, we met a couple
who for many years
had received copies of The Watchtower
when publishers visited their settlement.
They told us that they often felt depressed
when they woke up in the morning,
but when they read the magazine,
they felt better.
And they would read
the same copies over and over again.
When the temperature drops
and the snow falls,
the landscape gets covered
by a beautiful white blanket for half a year,
so the publishers
make good use of the summer.
Some towns and settlements
only seldom receive a witness.
There are no roads between the towns,
but we reach isolated areas by boat.
When someone shows interest
in our message,
the contact
is maintained by phone.
Many have great respect for the Bible,
and so My Book of Bible Stories
has found its way into many, many homes.
Over a period of 24 years,
Karin and I have sailed so much
that it equals a trip
twice around the globe.
This has cost a lot of effort and money,
but with Jehovah’s blessing,
we have been able
to continue year after year
preaching to the distant parts
of Greenland.
The preaching work here
is a great experience.
People are attentive and kind.
But it took a long time
before the first native Greenlander
was baptized
—actually 18 years of zealous preaching.
Today, there are
more than 150 publishers
in 5 congregations.
Jehovah has really blessed
the work that has been done here
for more than 60 years.
In August 2016,
a very special convention
was held in the capital of Nuuk.
Brothers and sisters
from all over Scandinavia
traveled all the way
to attend the convention.
We were very encouraged
by the visit of a member
of the Governing Body,
Brother Mark Sanderson,
who gave us
some faith-strengthening talks.
I think it’s a great privilege
to be able to understand the truth.
It’s amazing that Jehovah
gave his attention
to an insignificant human like me.
When I started to follow
the Bible’s unique teachings
and principles,
I clearly understood
how it would benefit my own life.
After this convention,
even though we live in small towns
far away
from the rest of the world,
we feel closer than ever before
to the worldwide brotherhood.
The peak attendance
at the convention was 614
—the largest ever in Greenland.
Our brothers
from other parts of Scandinavia
who attended
the convention also took part
in a campaign
inviting interested ones.
In only two hours,
the whole capital city of Nuuk
was covered.
It was a wonderful witness!
And speaking of witnessing
in “the most distant part
of the earth,”
you’ll be happy to know
that Brother Geoffrey Jackson
of the Governing Body
recently explained
in a morning worship
how the Bible was translated
into numerous languages
in the 19th century.
That segment is now available
on Video on Demand.
It is entitled
Reaching “the Most Distant Part.”
And later this month,
a beautiful segment
from the 2011 annual meeting
will be posted
for your enjoyment.
It is an interview
with five widows
of Governing Body members.
The sisters relate
how they learned the truth
and share treasured memories
from their many years
of faithful service.
This segment is entitled
Interview With Faithful Sisters
—Widows of Governing Body Members
and will be available
on Video on Demand under the
“Interviews and Experiences” category.
Do you agree that Jehovah gave us
an outstanding gift in his Word?
He not only gave us the gift
but also made sure time and time again
that it was preserved for our benefit.
Individuals we met earlier in the program,
such as Brothers David Sibrey,
Vladimir Olkhov,
and Valery Zaporozhsky,
have all seen
the effects of the power
that God’s Word exerts
and the guidance it provides.
We also saw that the Bible
is “beneficial for teaching”
and “for setting things straight,”
as we watched a family
learn how to improve their ministry
by following the example
of the apostle Paul.
Yes, God’s Word has endured
and will continue to endure forever.
As you know,
on April 3, 2017,
our museums in Warwick
will open to the public.
In addition
to our enlarged gallery entitled
“The Bible and the Divine Name,”
we will also have
a new gallery on the theme
“The Word of God Endures Forever.”
Please come and visit.
You’ll be happy to see
a wonderful collection of Bibles
that illustrates the points
we have discussed in this broadcast.
The psalmist was inspired to write:
“How I do love your law!”
And we agree.
We love Jehovah
and we love the Bible
and so have millions
throughout the centuries,
including those who were used
by Jehovah to preserve his Word.
With these thoughts in mind,
let’s enjoy
this month’s music video entitled
Your Word Endures Forever.
They looked up at the stars
With godly fear in their hearts.
They thanked their God up above
For revealing to them His love.
So You gave them your name,
A Kingdom hope to proclaim.
They’re words preserved for our day.
They’re faithful words to show us the way.
They loved you from their heart,
And they were proud to play their part—
Approved by you to preserve your Word,
Wrote it down so you would be heard.
Your Word endures forever,
And your sayings are, oh, so deep.
The good news you declare
is a breath of fresh air,
And your sayings I just want to keep.
Oh, whatever Your enemies tried,
They could not silence You.
Your loyal ones who loved your Word
Kept their faith, integrity too.
And when they tried to ban their Bibles,
They were prepared to give their lives.
For so strong was their faith
and the witness they gave,
Not one of your words was erased.
And so your Word endures forever,
And your sayings are, oh, so deep.
The good news you declare
is a breath of fresh air,
And your sayings I just want to keep.
And you told us your name is Jehovah.
In your Word it’s plain to see.
So your name will endure,
All your words will come true,
And we’ll praise you all of our days.
So your Word endures forever,
And your sayings are, oh, so deep.
The good news you declare
is a breath of fresh air,
And your sayings I just want to keep,
All of my days.
A beautiful song, indeed!
We would like to conclude
this program
by sharing these greetings
from our brothers and sisters in Mali.
Mali is located in western Africa,
reaching well into the Sahara Desert.
The northern part of the country
is hot and covered with sand,
but the southern region,
which is watered by the Niger River,
is green with forests and vegetation.
The Witnesses in the country
have a huge task,
as the ratio
of Jehovah’s Witnesses to population
is about one publisher
to 59,000 residents.
Also, the distances are tremendous.
The approximately 300 publishers
cover an area more than twice
the size of the country of France.
Mali is one of the hottest countries
in the world,
so some groups and congregations
hold their meetings outdoors
under the cool shade of a tree.
Although the official language
of the country is French,
most people better understand
the local language Bambara.
Thus, most meetings are either
held or interpreted in Bambara.
Recently, language classes
were held in Bomu,
which is another local language.
Also, the seven publishers
of the American Sign Language group
have been assigned to witness
to the more than
350,000 people in Mali
who have
a hearing impairment.
Last year, the total attendance
for the Memorial
was over 1,100 people.
One man who received an invitation
walked three kilometers,
or almost two miles,
to attend the Memorial
despite having
a physical challenge with his foot.
He is now regular at the meetings
and is making good progress.
Recently, a new Kingdom Hall
was built in the capital city.
Municipal and state authorities,
neighbors, and many passersby
have been amazed
at what they have seen,
and they have praised
the brothers working on the project.
Our brothers and sisters
in Mali send us their love.
We love them,
and we love all of you.
This is JW Broadcasting
from the world headquarters
of Jehovah’s Witnesses.