Greetings!
We’re so happy you could join us.
It’s a new service year
and a new monthly program.
And look, we have a new cohost,
Brother Seth Hyatt,
affectionately known as Rocky.
Now, Rocky, what can the friends
have to look forward to?
You can look forward
to this dramatization
where we meet a sister who is
on the brink of losing
her joy in the ministry.
What does she need to do?
We will all benefit
from the very practical application.
And we’re also going to see
an amazing video
from the Art Department
at world headquarters.
What do they do?
And how do we benefit from their work?
This segment is going
to answer those questions.
In some countries in Europe,
congregations are involved
in witnessing at truck stops.
This has proved to be a very productive way
of reaching individuals
who spend most of their time
away from home.
So if you’re a first-time viewer, welcome.
If you’re a regular viewer, welcome back.
This is the September program
of JW Broadcasting!
Have you enjoyed studying the book
Imitate Their Faith as much as I have?
It’s a wonderful book,
isn’t it?
And I was particularly captivated
by the introduction.
There was a point in the introduction
that encouraged us
to use our imagination
when we’re reading the Bible:
to see the sights,
to hear the sounds,
to smell the aromas,
to try to capture the feelings
of the individuals
that we are reading about.
Now, of course, we don’t want
our imagination to run away with us,
but at the same time,
we do want to get
a solid mental picture
of what we’re reading.
And that’s what I’d like
to talk to you about today.
When you’re reading the Bible,
try to get the whole picture.
Now we’ll use a couple
of well-known Bible accounts to illustrate.
Have you been raised
in a stepfamily or a blended family?
If you have,
did you know that you have
something in common with Joseph,
the son of Jacob?
Joseph was raised
with ten half brothers
in a large blended family.
So now you want to try to view
this family as a composite.
You want to try to figure out
how did people mesh
or how did they clash
within this family.
What would you do?
Well, you might start by writing down
some of the characteristics
of the individual members
of the family.
What about Joseph’s half brothers
and Joseph himself?
What do you know about them?
What about Judah,
Simeon, Levi,
Dan, Naphtali
—what do you know?
So write down
their characteristics,
and try to figure out
how they might get along.
Sometimes there is
one individual incident
that’s recorded in the Bible,
but we mustn’t forget:
People’s actions
have a way of affecting other people.
So when you read
about a certain incident in the Bible,
try to imagine who
might have been affected by that incident.
Take an example.
In the book of Genesis,
we read that Jacob’s son Reuben
committed sexual immorality
with Bilhah.
Well, that had an effect
on other people without doubt.
Who was Reuben?
He was Leah’s oldest son.
Who was Bilhah?
Rachel’s handmaiden.
Do you think that there might have been
a little animosity or tension
between Leah and Rachel sometimes,
especially when you consider
how their marriages started out?
There may have been.
And it may be
that the attitudes of the women
had some bearing on the attitudes
of their sons as well.
So you take all of these things
into consideration.
Now, Bilhah had two sons,
Dan and Naphtali.
How do you think
they felt when they learned
that their oldest brother,
or half brother,
had committed fornication
with their mother?
So there could have been
tension there.
And this all goes into the mix
when we’re considering
the family as a composite.
Now, do you picture
Joseph at age 17
with ten much older half brothers,
maybe in their 30’s,
some old enough to be his father?
Not true.
The truth is that there was only
a seven-year age difference
between Joseph’s oldest brother,
Reuben, and Joseph himself.
In fact, 11 of Jacob’s sons
were born
during the seven-year period
when Jacob
was working for Laban.
Eleven sons in seven years,
how is that possible?
It’s easy, when you remember
that Jacob had two wives
and two concubines,
or secondary wives.
So there didn’t have to be
a nine-month interval
between the birth
of the children.
In fact, some could have been born
just about at the same time;
they could have been
the same age.
So when Joseph
was sold into slavery at age 17,
his oldest brother
was no more than 24.
Some of his brothers were only
a year or two older than Joseph himself.
So we’re talking
about a group of young men
in their late teens
and early 20’s,
and this might explain
some of the hotheaded reactions
that some
of those young men had.
Well, so much for the boys.
What about their father, Jacob?
What can we learn about him?
A lot.
For one thing,
he was a spiritual man.
Now, this is something
for you young brothers and sisters
who are contemplating
marriage to think about.
Jacob was willing
to go to any length
to keep his relationship
with Jehovah intact.
Let’s take an example:
Genesis 29:18.
You can follow along
on the screen as I read this.
And we’re talking
about marriage here.
Genesis 29:18.
It says:
“Jacob had fallen in love with Rachel,
“so he said:
‘I am willing to serve you seven years
for your younger daughter Rachel.’”
Now what’s the takeaway?
Jacob didn’t marry
the first person who came along,
maybe some pagan woman.
He didn’t say,
‘Well, seven years is too long to wait.
I’m going to find some Philistine woman,
and I’ll marry her.’
He was willing to wait
so that he could marry someone
who would join him
in the worship of Jehovah.
And you young folks,
if you are willing to wait,
you can be sure that you will have
Jehovah’s blessing as well.
Now Jacob was apparently also
a bit of a romantic.
Notice verse 20.
It says:
“And Jacob served seven years for Rachel,”
but notice this,
“but in his eyes
they were like just a few days
because of his love for her.”
Now, isn’t that poetic?
Jacob may have learned
to treasure his wife
by observing his parents,
Isaac and Rebekah.
It appears that they
had a strong marriage.
Just notice what we read
at Genesis 26:8,
Genesis 26:8.
It says:
“After some time had passed,
“Abimelech king of the Philistines
was looking out of the window,
and he saw Isaac,”
that’s Jacob’s father,
“displaying affection
for Rebekah his wife.”
So it appears
that Isaac and Rebekah
had a warm relationship,
a good marriage.
Now, what else
can we learn about Jacob?
There’s an interesting detail recorded
in chapter 25 and verse 27.
It says:
“As the boys got bigger, Esau,”
Jacob’s brother,
“became a skilled hunter,
a man of the field,
“but Jacob was a blameless man,
dwelling in tents.”
So Jacob liked to dwell in tents.
That might explain
the strong bond that developed
between Jacob and Joseph,
who was his youngest for many years.
Now although Jacob
liked to dwell in tents,
he was by no means a sissy.
He was a strong man,
but he was a spiritual man.
That’s something
for you young brothers to take away.
You want to be strong,
we know you do,
but spirituality
should come first.
One time, spiritual Jacob
gave his sons a beautiful lesson
on how to settle
a difference with a family member.
We read about it
at Genesis chapter 32.
And I think all of us can learn
from his example.
We learn at Genesis 32
that Jacob’s brother, Esau,
was coming to see him.
Now, they hadn’t seen
each other for 20 years,
and to say that their parting
had been difficult is an understatement.
The fact is that when they separated
more than 20 years earlier,
Esau had vowed that one day
he was going to kill his brother;
now he was coming to see him.
Now, why was he
so angry with Jacob?
It’s because Jacob had received
a blessing from their father,
and Esau was not happy.
So Esau arrives,
and 400 men are with him.
Why 400 men?
Well, the Bible doesn’t say.
But it could be
that he was trying to show
how important and prominent
he had become.
How did Jacob react?
Did he try to go tit for tat?
Did he try to show how important
and prominent he had become
with all of the blessings
he’d received?
Did he reopen old wounds?
Did he argue with his brother?
Did he say,
‘You know I was right all along,
and you, Esau,
you have been wrong’?
Did he demand an apology?
No.
There was a lot that Jacob
could have bragged about.
No question about that.
There was no doubt that Jacob
had Jehovah’s blessing.
Early on,
we read that an angel of Jehovah
had appeared to him
and said:
“I am Jehovah
“the God of Abraham your father
and the God of Isaac.
“The land on which you are lying,
“to you I am going to give it
and to your offspring.
“I am with you,
“and I will safeguard you
wherever you go . . .
I will not leave you.”
Well, that’s quite a blessing,
isn’t it?
But there’s more.
For a portion
of the previous night
—that is, the night before Esau
and Jacob met up—
Jacob had wrestled with an angel,
and as a result,
he had managed
to receive another blessing.
But Jacob didn’t flaunt
his blessings.
Instead, he humbled himself.
In fact, he even bowed down
seven times before his brother
in front of his wives
and his 11 sons.
So Jacob settled
any lingering difference with Esau
not with his fists,
not with a bragging tongue,
not with a weapon,
but humbly,
like a real man
—like a real, spiritual man.
In contrast,
how did Jacob’s ten sons
settle their difference
with Joseph?
Like a bunch of cowards.
It was 10 to 1
against Joseph.
First, they decided
to kill their brother,
and then they delivered him
up into slavery.
Those jealous young men
didn’t learn a thing
from their father’s
excellent spiritual example.
Well, if you’re on the outs
with a member of your family,
if you had
a serious difficulty with someone,
could you try to settle the matter
peacefully as Jacob did?
If the person tries to apologize,
be gracious about it.
Don’t make it difficult
for him to apologize.
Don’t dredge up
all of the unnecessary details
about the past.
You may be in the right,
as Jacob was,
but isn’t the important thing
to make peace?
Jehovah loves the peacemakers.
Well, what else
do we learn about Jacob?
We learn that he wasn’t
his father’s favorite.
Let’s look
at Genesis chapter 25,
verse 28.
“And Isaac loved Esau
“because it meant game in his mouth,
whereas Rebekah loved Jacob.”
Now, this story may resonate
with many of you out there,
especially if you’ve grown up
in a large family
or perhaps you’ve had
a number of brothers and sisters.
Now, we know
your parents claim
that they always treated
all of you the same,
that they never ever
had a preference.
But ask the kids,
Was there anyone in the family
who was the favorite?
They all know.
‘She was!’
They know this.
The parents don’t realize it,
but they are giving preferential treatment.
And so this happens,
and it can be disconcerting at times.
Imagine this scenario:
Imagine that you have a couple
who have two children, two sons.
One is a pioneer.
He has never given his parents
a moment’s grief.
The other
never accepted the truth,
but he has done well
in business,
and as a result,
he has been generous to his parents,
and the parents are grateful,
very grateful.
And the pioneer
often hears the parents bragging
about the successes
that his brother has had in business.
Well, the pioneer can’t help
the parents materially very much,
and so he feels that there’s
a bit of partiality there.
Is it hurtful?
Yes.
That is life.
It’s chemistry.
It’s just chemistry.
But the pioneer needs to realize
that Jehovah God
appreciates his work.
His heavenly Father
loves him very much
for the work
that he is doing for His name.
Now, Jacob must have known
that Isaac loved his brother
more than he loved him.
And perhaps he vowed
that when he had children,
he would treat them all the same.
Well, if he did,
he didn’t keep that promise, did he?
Everyone knew
that Joseph was the favorite.
Well, have you noticed what we had to do
to make a composite of this family?
We had to read
from several different chapters of the Bible
—Genesis 25, 26, 28, 29, 32.
You can’t always get
a complete picture of an incident
by reading just one chapter,
just by reading the chapter you are reading.
Sometimes you have to extract details
from other chapters of the Bible.
Now let’s consider
one more example
where getting the complete picture
can enrich our understanding.
This is going to be
a shorter one.
We’re going to consider
the story of Naaman.
Now, you remember the story.
At 2 Kings 5:1,
we learn that Naaman
was the chief of the army
of Ben-hadad II,
the king of Syria.
But he was a leper.
Now Ben-hadad learned
that there was a prophet in Israel
Elisha who could heal him
of his leprosy.
And so he told Naaman
that he should go to Israel
and go to the prophet
and get healed.
And so word was sent
to the king of Israel by letter,
and the king of Israel was asked
to send Naaman to Elisha.
Now, when you think of it,
this was a strange request
because Israel and Syria
were often at odds.
Sometimes there were
wars between them,
and now, here you have
the king of Syria sending his general,
the one who is going to head
the army against Israel,
and saying: ‘Well, I’d like my general
to be a more effective general.
Could you please make sure
that he gets healed?’
Well, somehow,
he’s sent to Elisha
and Elisha kindly heals Naaman
and Naaman becomes
a worshipper of Jehovah.
Well, we can imagine,
remember we’re talking
about using our imagination,
we can imagine
that when Naaman returned to Syria,
Ben-hadad had lots of nice things
to say about Elisha.
So then, everyone lived
happily ever after, right?
If we didn’t read on,
we might think so.
But that’s not
the end of the story.
In the next chapter,
chapter 6,
we learn that Ben-hadad
declared war against Israel.
Now, if Naaman
was still the chief of the army,
he’d be in an awkward position.
Was he going
to lead the armies of Syria
against fellow worshippers
of Jehovah?
But it gets worse.
Ben-hadad learns that Elisha
is revealing the Syrians’ war strategies
to the king of Israel,
so he sends a large army
to capture Elisha
—the very man who
had healed his general.
So much for gratitude.
Now, it’s interesting
that Naaman is not mentioned
as being at the head
of those armies.
Did he get out of it somehow?
Don’t ask me.
If he’s resurrected,
you’ll have to ask him.
What lesson can we learn?
That the gratitude of the world
is fleeting.
Some of us may get excited
if there’s a favorable article
about Jehovah’s Witnesses
in a newspaper
or if some TV personality
makes a kind statement about us.
But what did Jehovah God say?
Genesis 3:15:
“I will put enmity
between you and the woman.”
So Jehovah’s organization
and Satan’s organization
are always going to be at odds.
Bible reading isn’t a chore.
It’s a joy.
Get the whole picture
of what you’re reading,
and you’ll enjoy it even more.
We wish you all
Jehovah’s rich blessing
as you continue
to enhance your appreciation
for this sacred volume.
And now, let’s turn to Rocky.
I think Rocky
has some practical application to share.
Thank you, and as David mentioned,
there is a close connection between joy
and how we handle our Bible reading.
In this dramatization,
we meet a pioneer sister
who did everything just right
but still felt
that her motivation was declining.
Whether you pioneer or not,
notice the importance
of properly digesting
our vital spiritual food.
That’s my roommate, Camille.
And, well,
that’s me.
I haven’t felt like myself recently.
I started regular pioneering
a couple of years ago.
At first, I was really zealous.
But somewhere down the line,
I lost that good feeling.
Soon, I was losing my joy
for almost everything.
I honestly didn’t know
what was wrong.
It wasn’t like I was doing
anything bad.
I thought,
‘Maybe I’m just tired.’
But it wasn’t getting better.
I tried to assess
what was going on with myself.
I felt love for Jehovah.
I felt love for the congregation,
but I felt unmotivated in my service.
I felt like something was missing.
As my enthusiasm waned,
my meeting attendance suffered too.
Thankfully, the loving elders
in my congregation noticed,
and help was on the way.
The brothers visited
to see how I was doing.
They really listened to me,
and they asked about
my spiritual routine.
Well, I read the Bible every day,
but, I admitted,
I’m not a natural study person.
They reminded me
about the example of Mary,
Jesus’ mother.
At first, I didn’t see the link,
but as we read from the Bible,
it became more clear.
Mary was known
for being a faithful woman.
But what kept her faith strong?
The Bible account said
that Mary paid careful attention
to words that had
deep spiritual meaning
and later took time to meditate,
“drawing conclusions in her heart.”
By meditating on spiritual things,
Mary strengthened her faith
and zeal for serving Jehovah.
I understand now.
I was reading spiritual food,
but I wasn’t taking time to digest it,
so it wasn’t sinking
down into my heart.
As a result,
I was on a direct path
to spiritual burnout
if I didn’t change something quick!
I began by taking control
of my busy schedule.
I made it a priority
to start my day with Bible reading.
I sought out quiet places
where I could meditate on what I read.
Meaningful Bible study reinvigorated
my passion for serving Jehovah,
and prayerful meditation
helped me to refocus.
Over time,
making these changes
helped me to find joy
in my service to Jehovah again.
The Bible says when we make time
to read and meditate on spiritual things,
we will become
“like a tree planted by streams of water,”
with foliage that never withers.
And everything we do will succeed.
Did you notice that our sister
read the Bible every day?
But that alone did not give her
the spiritual sustenance she needed.
We don’t want our Bible reading
to become an automatic process.
What does that mean
—automatic process?
Well, breathing, walking,
or perhaps, riding a bicycle
are things many can do
without even thinking.
They become automatic processes.
To some extent,
this is also true of reading.
So, what can help us
develop the art of meditation?
When you finish reading a passage,
you might pause
and ponder over what you have just read
to be sure
that you understand it correctly.
Ask yourself:
‘What does this
teach me about Jehovah?
‘How can I apply this in my life?
Or how can I use this
in my field ministry?’
You should always make sure
to apply what you read.
And remember,
reading in a stress-free environment
with few distractions
helps our concentration.
But what if our attention span is short
and our mind starts to wander quickly?
Starting out with shorter study sessions
and gradually lengthening them
have helped some.
Our goal should be to linger in study,
not to rush through it.
That’s when our spiritual food
becomes the refreshment we need.
Some excellent tools
when meditating are the illustrations
and photographs
we find in our publications.
Take the Bible account
found in Daniel chapter 5 as an example.
It reads: “That very night
“Belshazzar
the Chaldean king was killed.
“And Darius the Mede
received the kingdom;
he was about 62 years old.”
Using other scriptures
that provide additional details,
including prophecies about the event,
the Art Department
at world headquarters
was able to paint a vivid picture
of what it may have been like that night,
when the Medo-Persian soldiers
waded through the Euphrates River
and entered the city of Babylon
through its open gates.
Now, we know that looking up
illustrations in our literature
can be a helpful tool when meditating.
But why is that the case?
Let’s go behind the scenes
of the Art Department and find out.
A visual aid often makes
a clearer
or more lasting impression
on the mind than does the spoken word.
Under the direction
of the Writing Committee,
the Art Department
has enjoyed
the privilege of designing
and illustrating Bible literature
for almost 40 years.
The department was established
sometime before 1976.
But a small team of artists
had been working
on illustrations and typography
from as far back
as the “Photo-Drama of Creation.”
The work of publishing Bible literature
has seen many changes.
Now there are EPUBs, interactive PDFs,
Web design, and HTML content,
all of which require new skills
as well as close collaboration
with many other Bethel departments.
The Art Department
is structured into teams.
Each team is made up
of designers, photographers,
illustrators, prop and set makers,
costume and makeup artists,
as well as production workers.
The team lead and the scheduler
work directly
with the Writing Department contact
known as a compiler.
After receiving
an early version of the text,
the three brothers discuss
the purpose
and possible look of the design.
All on the team
are invited to collaborate
as concepts are developed.
Each member contributes
to the overall design of a project.
Before any production work is started,
concepts are sketched and developed.
These sketches become a blueprint
that helps the team
understand the concept,
plan the resources,
and ensure
that the project stays on track.
Who is the target audience?
How will this publication be used?
The design should be clear and simple.
And it needs to work in all languages.
This is no small task.
When the design is ready,
the compiler presents a mock-up
of the publication
to the Writing Committee.
The committee reviews the design
and makes any needed adjustments.
After the concept is approved,
production begins.
Around the world,
there are many photographers
who work part-time to assist
in providing images.
Photographs are also taken in our studio
and other locations.
These images help give our publications
an international look.
Accuracy is vital.
A researcher provides
historical references and inspiration.
Hair, makeup, and costumes
are designed to depict
the time period and region.
Props, set design, and lighting
provide the right look and setting.
When combined,
each element helps tell the story
and capture the imagination of the viewer.
Sets are also built in 3D programs.
They can be used as art source
or as final illustrations.
Whether painted digitally
or with traditional materials,
the artist renders the illustration
in a style suited for its final use.
When design meets illustration,
infographics are born.
After final approval
by the Writing Committee,
files are sent to the printeries
and to the website
or used to create other digital versions.
In order to reach the hearts of those
who read a Bible-based publication,
hands and hearts
have to be involved in its creation.
Those of us in the Art Department
consider it a privilege to give support
to the most urgent of all work
—preaching the good news.
Did you notice
the answer to our question,
Why can looking up illustrations
in our literature be helpful?
As the narrator said, “A visual aid
“often makes a clearer
or more lasting impression on the mind
than does the spoken word.”
But on top of that,
illustrations
can help a story come alive.
They help us
envision an event before our eyes
and thus deepen our appreciation
for Bible truths
and ultimately for Jehovah God.
While illustrations and photographs
can be a great complement,
it’s the written Word, God’s Word,
that is the source
of the spiritual food.
But what if we face a situation
in which we have access to nothing?
We are not allowed
to have a Bible,
no literature with illustrations,
no videos,
and no audio recordings.
What do we do?
Our recollection
of what we have read in the past
can keep our spirituality intact.
One of our brothers from Russia
faced such a situation.
Notice what helped him.
The year was 1963.
I was 36 at the time.
The KGB searched my home
and found some Bible literature
and some publishers’ field service reports.
So I was sentenced
to five years of imprisonment
for being an organizer.
That was the third time
I had been imprisoned.
Some brothers and sisters
and I went to the court
to support Brother Vladimir.
When he saw us,
he clasped his hands
and declared,
“Everything is fine!”
A KGB officer told me
that the only reason
I hadn’t been imprisoned
was because I had six children.
But Vladimir was single.
I was just glad
that they had arrested me and not him,
because I didn’t have a family.
In the camp, I didn’t have a Bible
or any Bible literature at all.
All I had to keep me going
was the knowledge I already had.
We prayed for him,
and we sent greetings
and encouraging messages
to him through his relatives.
Due to the strict censorship
in the camp,
we were not allowed
to write anything spiritual in our letters
to encourage each other.
If we did,
the letters were confiscated.
But I really wanted to send Brother Mikhail
something encouraging.
I was growing flowers
with a group of inmates in the camp.
So instead of a sending him a letter,
I decided to send him
a bouquet of flowers.
Vladimir’s sister Olga came to our home,
and she brought me a beautiful bouquet
of flowers from Vladimir.
I couldn’t believe
that I had received fresh flowers
from behind a barbed-wire fence
—from inside the camp.
I was so touched
by his act of kindness
that my heart moved me
to write down some verses,
a poem,
which I called “The Bouquet.”
My relatives came
and visited me in the prison
and delivered to me the poem.
I kept the poem
in a very secret place.
It could have been confiscated,
and I could have been punished
because it was about God.
After Vladimir was released from prison,
well, he told me that my poem
had really strengthened him
and that he had often taken it out
of its secret hiding place
to read it over and over again.
If it hadn’t been for the support
I received from Jehovah
and the prayers of friends,
it would have been much harder
for me to serve my time.
The poem that I had received
helped me not to feel
separated from my friends
and, most importantly,
from Jehovah.
So many years have now gone by.
But we have remained firm
through the difficult times,
and we continue serving Jehovah.
Lately, Vladimir and I have been trying
to keep in touch by phone,
but we haven’t seen each other
for seven years.
I would really love
to see Vladimir again.
He doesn’t know
that I’ve decided to go and visit him.
I hope that he likes the surprise.
“I see these flowers,
grown by hands
“Hardened from work
that prison demands.
“My friend has sent a bouquet.
“Prison three times
prevented our meeting,
“But you found a way
to convey a greeting.
“My joy now moves me to say:
“‘Greetings, my brother,
with all of my heart.
“‘You gave me strength,
although we’re apart.
“‘While you have
countless trials withstood,
“‘You’ve strengthened me
as best you could.
“‘Greetings, my friend
on that narrow road,
“‘You were always with me
through hardships untold.
“‘We worked so hard
for spiritual treasure.
“‘Blessed we were
for sticking together.
“‘Cruelly, my friend,
you were taken from me
“‘When they tried
to break our integrity.
“‘But God stood by us
and helped us to cope.
“‘Conquer the evil, we did,
for our dear Kingdom hope.
“‘How grateful we are
and always will be
“‘For spiritual vision
by which we can see
“‘The crown of life
promised to those
“‘Who stay on the loyal course
they chose.
“‘How much you’ve endured,
long-suffering friend.
“‘But Jehovah’s mercy
will never end.
“‘On a paradise earth
our hands will unite,
“‘Planting more flowers
to gladden His sight.
“‘Christ Jesus will heal us
during his reign,
“‘So no trace of sin
will ever remain.
“‘And far from the trials
that we overcame,
Forever we’ll praise
Jehovah’s great name!’”
True friends are such a blessing
from Jehovah,
and you don’t really know
who they are until disaster strikes.
During my whole life,
walking in the way of the truth,
I have often thought
about the words of Psalm 119:63,
where it says:
“I am a friend of all who fear you
and of those who keep your orders.”
Our serving side by side
in the Kingdom work
has strengthened our friendship.
It is only that sort of friendship
that will last forever!
What a beautiful friendship!
Our brotherhood truly is
a blessing from Jehovah.
Brother Mikhail Savitsky spent many years
as a circuit overseer,
helping the Kingdom work progress
in Siberia, northern Caucasus,
and the countries
of Georgia and Armenia.
In 1992, he had the privilege
of being one of those
who signed the documents that confirmed
legal recognition of our work in Russia.
However, we regret to inform you
that some time
after this segment was produced,
Brother Vladimir Varkholik
fell asleep in death.
He was 88 years old
and had served Jehovah faithfully
for over 59 years.
At the time of his death,
he had served as a pioneer
for some 26 years
and as an elder
in the congregation for 43 years.
From his interview,
you can clearly see the faith
that kept his spirituality strong
through 12 years of imprisonment.
And he is a good example for us.
Did you notice one aspect
of his circumstances while incarcerated?
He said:
“In the camp,
I didn’t have a Bible
“or any Bible literature at all.
“All I had to keep me going
was the knowledge I already had.”
That could happen to us.
When persecution starts,
we need to be prepared.
That’s one reason
why it is so important
not to neglect
our study of the Bible
while we have the opportunity.
Now, back to David.
Thanks, Rocky.
We’re truly sorry to hear about Vladimir.
But one thing is certain,
we know that Jehovah God will not forget
the love that he showed for His name.
That was a moving interview indeed.
Well, back in June,
a number of new Kingdom songs
were released electronically,
but one was missing—number 151.
Now, you noticed that, didn’t you?
I know you did because nothing escapes
the eagle eyes of you brothers and sisters.
Well, here it is, number 151.
It’s entitled
“The Revealing of God’s Sons.”
And it reminds us
that the time is getting near
when the anointed
will hear the final call.
Let’s listen.
The time is near when God reveals
His faithful chosen ones.
In heaven they will rule with Christ
As mighty spirit sons.
The sons of God will be revealed
Along with Christ, their Lord.
They’ll join him in his victory
And share in his reward.
And soon the last remaining ones
Will hear his final call.
The King of kings and Lord of lords
Will then collect them all.
The sons of God will be revealed
Along with Christ, their Lord.
They’ll join him in his victory
And share in his reward.
And then with Christ, these sons of God
Will wage the final war.
The joyous marriage to the Lamb
Will last forevermore.
The sons of God will be revealed
Along with Christ, their Lord.
They’ll join him in his victory
And share in his reward.
Don’t you think that was
a beautiful song, Rocky?
Absolutely!
That was one beautiful song.
You know, I really do appreciate
the Watchtower chorus.
Only two or three of them
have professional training,
and the rest have got where they are
just through hard work.
So this is something
that all of us can keep in mind.
Practice, practice, practice singing.
And then when you
get to the Kingdom Hall, sing out.
And it’s a very timely song,
considering how close we are to the end.
And I’m sure all of you agree that the closer
we are to the end of this system of things,
the more work there is
in the field ministry.
But there are individuals whom we
rarely find home due to their secular work.
In Europe, our brothers
and sisters have found a way
to reach one such group.
Every year, thousands of truck drivers
from all over the world
crisscross the European continent.
They work hard to make ends meet
for their families
but often have to spend
weeks away from home.
Jesus and his apostles
approached people wherever they were.
It is this same spirit
that must motivate us.
By trying to reach truck drivers
wherever they can be found,
we can make sure
that everyone receives a witness,
even those who would
otherwise be missed.
We live in the Rotterdam area
which has a lot of truck traffic.
We cover our regular territory
once every three months,
while these truck drivers
are hardly ever reached.
We noticed that 300,000 trucks
crossed France every year.
Thus, it was necessary to explore
this formidable potential for the ministry.
Many truck drivers use truck stops
to take a short break
or even spend the night there.
That’s ideal for preaching.
While we are parked here, resting,
we are cleaning the trucks;
we are washing our clothes
because there is no laundry here;
and also we do our cooking.
One day on my way to France,
I had to stop in Austria
to swap drivers.
My colleague went to the bathroom,
and I was alone.
At that moment, a Witness came
and offered me a magazine.
Much effort is being put into reaching
truck drivers in an organized way.
We made sure all truck stops
were mapped
and organized schedules so that pioneers
can preach in this territory
at least once a day.
Publishers will encounter
many different nationalities and languages.
The language barrier
is one of the biggest challenges.
On any given morning,
you can encounter
up to ten different languages:
Romanian, Russian, Polish.
When I looked at the magazine,
I saw that it was a Watchtower,
but I thought it was in German.
I told this brother
that I did not speak German.
Then he had a look at my license plate
and saw that it was Romanian.
He again offered me
the magazine and told me:
“It is Romanian.
It is for you.”
When I saw it,
I was very happy.
I took the magazine
and was very glad.
Of course, we don’t speak in tongues
like the first-century Christians did.
But jw.org makes us feel like
we can preach in any language.
We need to go further
than just distributing publications.
We need to be real teachers,
and to do that,
we can make use of the videos.
A driver had his Bible
wide open on his dashboard
and literally cried when he watched
the video Why Study the Bible?
Since truck drivers spend
most of their time on the road,
it is a real challenge to follow up
on those who have shown any interest.
It’s very difficult to do return visits
or to start Bible studies.
You just don’t know when you will meet
a truck driver again.
So we try to get their e-mail addresses
as soon as possible.
The results were remarkable.
For example, in the last service year,
about 100,000 magazines were placed,
100 Bible studies were started,
and 4,000 videos were shown.
Experience shows
that even if it’s not possible
to obtain an e-mail address,
the slightest witness given
can have a great impact.
In time, I returned to Romania.
I started a Bible study,
progressed spiritually, got married,
and now I am
an unbaptized publisher.
The brother that first
contacted me has no idea.
Hebrews 6:11 invites us all
‘to show industriousness’ in our ministry.
The more you invest in
this form of ministry,
the more fulfillment you get
from the positive response of the drivers.
It is a good thing
to preach the good news at truck stops
because all drivers need to feel God’s love,
to see that God really cares for us.
And like me,
they can make changes in their lives.
And they need to see that Jehovah
has promised a future paradise
and how this will affect them
and their families.
What great results
came from this preaching initiative,
and what a delight to see
how many of the publishers
used our videos while witnessing!
Although videos can be great tools,
we all must continue
to develop our teaching skills
and our ability to reason
from the Scriptures.
The brothers witnessing
at truck stops did just that,
and the results
speak for themselves.
You will be happy to know that one
of the truck drivers who was interviewed
Ion Bolbotina from Romania
was recently baptized
as one of Jehovah’s Witnesses.
It is beautiful
to see how our efforts
in the ministry
are blessed by Jehovah.
Sister Margarita Königer has seen
the growth of the Kingdom work
all her life.
She has served
as a missionary since 1966,
and we met her in Hungary,
where she has now served
for about nine years.
In the 50 years
since she graduated from Gilead,
Sister Königer has learned
seven languages
and has served
in five different countries.
And recently,
she received a new assignment
—the Chinese field
in Munich, Germany.
Daily reading
and meditating on God’s Word, the Bible,
has given her
the strength she needs
to continue with joy
in her missionary assignment.
The same is important
if you’re young.
Taking the time
to properly digest spiritual food,
by enhancing your Bible reading,
can teach you to make good decisions.
For example,
whom should you choose as friends?
Pay special attention to this music video
entitled Where I Belong,
which will help you choose
the best friends possible.
Now everyone, it seems to me,
Knows just the place he wants to be.
I know what’s right; I know what’s wrong;
And, yes, I know where I belong.
It feels so good, so good to know
Where I should be, where I should go
To find good friends and company
Who build me up and care for me.
Yes, here in my heart
The feelings are strong.
Jehovah, it’s you
Who’ll help me get through
And show me where I belong.
My heart is sure, it’s clear to me,
I’m standing where I want to be.
I read God’s Word. I make it live.
It moves my heart. What can I give?
And now I know; yes, now I see
Where real friends are; that’s where I’ll be.
They’re all I want; they’re family;
Jehovah’s gift with love to me.
Yes, here in my heart
The feelings are strong.
Jehovah, it’s you
Who’ll help me get through
And show me where I belong.
What a fine young man!
And he made the right decisions.
He decided he belongs
in Jehovah’s organization.
And did you notice his habit?
He read the Bible regularly,
brought it with him on the trip,
meditated about what he read
—both after reading
and also when out in the ministry.
He took the time to grasp
the wonders of Jehovah’s creation,
and we need to do the same.
We need to enhance our Bible reading
—visualize what we read
and try to get the whole picture.
And the organization
has given us many fine tools
to visualize our Bible reading,
such as the illustrations
in our publications, audio dramas,
and dramatic Bible readings
and videos.
Make full use of them,
and meditate about what you learn.
Thanks, Rocky,
I agree with everything you’ve said.
Well, as of September the 1st,
members of the Bethel family
have been moving
from Brooklyn to our new headquarters
at Warwick, New York.
Now, if you’re listening in from Britain,
that’s Warwick to you.
Warwick or Warwick, it’s the same place.
Tomato, tomato.
And we’re very,
very happy about this move.
It’s a tremendous project
to move the entire Bethel family
from Brooklyn to Warwick,
and it’s going to take some time.
So we know you’re anxious
to see the property in person,
but we’re not going to be able
to get the property ready for tours
until April 3, 2017, that’s a Monday.
I’m going to repeat that.
We’re not going to be able
to open for tours
until Monday, April 3, 2017.
Now, if you
happen to be touring Wallkill
or Patterson between now and then,
it’s going to be a mighty temptation
for you to tiptoe
up to the property line in Warwick,
perhaps put some twigs
and branches in your hat,
climb a tree,
and see what you can see.
Please, don’t do it.
We’re working very hard
to get everything ready for you.
We want everything to be just right
when the facility is open for tours.
And here’s another interesting thing:
You are going to be able
to go online
and schedule a tour.
And so arrangements are being made
with the congregations and the branches
so that they’re going to be able
to do that.
So you’ll be able to avoid the rush.
We also wanted to take the opportunity
to mention that two new interviews
in the Viewpoints on the Origin of Life
video series
have now been posted.
You may remember this series
from the April program.
It’s about scientists
who have concluded
that life did not come about
by chance, but by design.
You will find these new interviews
in the “Interviews and Experiences”
category,
under the “Origins of Life” heading.
We’d like to conclude
with these greetings
from northeastern Bolivia,
in a region called Beni.
This area has a publisher ratio
of 1 Witness to 426 people.
Their territory consists
mainly of rivers and jungles.
The approximately 350 publishers
in the cities of Riberalta
and Guayaramerín
need to be innovative to reach
all corners of their territory.
For example,
under the direction of the local branch,
a Witness pilot
flies brothers to isolated populations.
In other cases, some communities
located on the banks of rivers
are reachable
only by boat.
Thus, preaching trips by boat
are arranged from time to time.
Some trips last well over a month.
But some parts of the territory
can be reached by motorcycle.
The brothers and sisters travel
up to four hours
to cover such territories.
The brothers and sisters in Beni
send their warm love, and so do we,
to all of you around the world.
Rocky, I’d like to thank you for doing
the heavy lifting for me during this program.
You’re a good brother,
you know that?
My privilege.
He’s a good brother.
And this is JW Broadcasting
in Brooklyn, New York.