The scripture that we are highlighting today
is 1 Timothy 5:2,
which instructs Christian men
to treat “older women as mothers, . . .
“younger women as sisters,
with all chasteness.”
Of course, the reverse is also true:
Christian women
should treat older men as fathers
and younger men as brothers,
with all chasteness.
This is taken from the Watchtower  article
entitled “We Can Remain Chaste,”
one portion of which discusses the matter
of flirting with the opposite sex.
My discussion is going to focus
on keeping one’s ego in check.
Now, what are
the connections between chasteness,
flirting, and ego?
Well, let’s start with chasteness,
that is, purity in thought and action.
And it means “being free from all taint
of what is lewd or salacious,”
that is, what arouses or appeals
to sexual desire or imagination.
And one way to maintain our chastity
is to avoid the practice of flirting.
And what is that?
Well, flirting means ‘behaving amorously
without serious intent.’
Such a person signals romantic interest
with no intention of marriage.
It may involve
an inappropriate remark, a look,
a touch, the tone of voice, a coy smile,
even the way one dresses,
stands, or carries oneself.
Some single people flirt with each other
or with married folks.
Some married people flirt with single people
or with other married people.
And in this degenerate world,
men flirt with men,
and women flirt with women.
But it’s inappropriate for single people
to send romantic signals
to each other just for amusement,
and it is morally wrong for married people
to direct that kind of attention
to a person outside of their marriage.
Interestingly, an attorney
who practices family law reported:
“I talk to plenty of people
who are going through divorce.
“In most cases, these marriages are ending
“because someone had an affair,
and in all of those cases,
the affair started out
as just a little harmless flirting.”
Of course, flirting is not harmless.
To intentionally toy
with the feelings of others is cruel.
It can arouse wrong desires and expectations
that may result in a lot of emotional pain.
It can also lead to worse things:
fornication or adultery.
It’s no wonder that it has been said
that flirts make poor friends
and worse marriage mates.
Well, in the world,
flirting is viewed as a sport,
and it’s done
to increase one’s own self-esteem.
Now, that’s where ego comes into the picture.
Ego is “the sense of one’s own worth.”
One source on the subject of flirting says
that it is a gigantic ego boost, an ego trip,
because the flirt is doing something
for his or her own gratification,
to make himself or herself feel better.
But there’s something the apostle Paul wrote
that can balance our thinking
about this trait of self-esteem
that imperfect humans
tend to take to an extreme.
So let’s turn to Romans 12:3
and see what Paul has to say,
Romans 12:3;
he wrote:
“For through
the undeserved kindness given to me,
“I tell everyone there among you not to think
“more of himself than it
is necessary to think,
“but to think so as to have a sound mind,
each one as God has given
to him a measure of faith.”
Well, self-esteem is defined
as “confidence and satisfaction in oneself,”
and it can range
from self-respect to self-conceit.
Some people have too little of it;
some people have too much of it.
So Paul wrote:
“I tell everyone there among you.”
And what he tells us is how
to avoid either extreme
of thinking too much or too little
of our worth in God’s eyes.
And Paul pinpointed exactly
where the problem lies
because three times in the verse
he used the phrase “to think.”
He wrote that a person
is “not to think more of himself
than it is necessary to think,
but to think so as to have a sound mind.”
So it matters how one thinks
about himself or herself.
Consider the person
who has too little self-esteem.
Now, Paul said it is necessary
to think something of ourselves.
It was never intended
that modest, moral Christians
had to develop an inferiority complex.
Our dedicated relationship with Jehovah
makes each of us
precious and desirable to God,
and we should really believe that.
So the one with low self-esteem
is not thinking enough
of the right things about himself.
And what Paul wrote two verses earlier
in Romans chapter 12 can help.
So let’s look at verse 1 of Romans 12:
“Therefore, I appeal to you
by the compassions of God, brothers,
“to present your bodies
as a living sacrifice,
“holy and acceptable to God,
a sacred service with your power of reason.”
Now, doesn’t that describe
what we are endeavoring to do?
Haven’t we dedicated our lives to Jehovah?
Aren’t we striving to live holy lives?
Aren’t we performing sacred service
and making sacrifices
for the sake of the Kingdom?
Certainly.
And all that is most acceptable to our God.
Our lives have real worth in Jehovah’s eyes,
so no one should have to resort
to frivolous flirting to boost their ego.
Now, consider the person
who has too much self-esteem.
In his efforts to gain self-confidence,
he has overshot the mark
and has crossed the line
between cultivating
self-respect and arrogance.
He’s overestimated his own worth
and thinks too highly of himself,
and he may behave
in an unpleasant way toward others,
as does the uncaring flirt.
Well, Paul said something
that applies here too
at Romans 12:16,
verse 16:
“Have the same attitude
toward others as toward yourselves;
“do not set your mind on lofty things,
but be led along with the lowly things.
Do not become wise in your own eyes.”
So it’s important that we have a healthy,
balanced view of our own worth.
And remember, it is the way of our thinking
that Paul was cautioning us about,
because that governs
whether our self-esteem is in balance or not.
No wonder that Paul said that we ought
“to think so as to have a sound mind,”
that is, to have thoughts that are based
on a true premise about ourselves.
Since it always helps
to look at the example of Jesus,
let’s do that, in this case,
by turning to Philippians chapter 2,
Philippians 2,
beginning with verse 5;
it says: “Keep this mental attitude in you
“that was also in Christ Jesus,
who, although he was existing in God’s form,
“gave no consideration to a seizure,
namely, that he should be equal to God.
“No, but he emptied himself and took
a slave’s form and became human.
More than that, when he came as a man,
he humbled himself.”
Well, in every facet of his life,
Jesus’ sound mind kept
his self-esteem in perfect balance.
He never had too little or too much.
He never thought more
of himself than was necessary to think.
We can never imagine Jesus
trying to boost his ego
by flirting with Mary and Martha
or with any other woman
who was in his company.
Paul said, ‘keep this mental attitude in you’
—Jesus’ mental attitude.
We should think the way Jesus thinks.
Now, note the context
in which we find this admonition
in Philippians 2
by reading verses 3 and 4:
“Do nothing out of contentiousness
or out of egotism,
“[one Bible says: “Never act
“from motives of rivalry or personal vanity”]
“but with humility consider
others superior to you,
“as you look out
not only for your own interests,
but also for the interests of others.”
So we keep our egos in check,
we stay clear of any speech,
dress, or flirtatious actions
that could be viewed as provocative,
and we thus maintain
our chasteness toward everyone.