Now, there are many reasons
why all of us want to cultivate humility,
but what would you say is the foremost reason?
Well, let’s get the answer from James 4:6
—the “b” part.
It says:
“God opposes the haughty ones,
“but he gives undeserved kindness
to the humble ones.”
So if we don’t have humility,
Jehovah is going to oppose us.
If we do,
he’s going to give us undeserved kindness.
Obviously, that’s the main reason,
even though there are many others,
we want to cultivate humility.
But as you know, once humble
does not necessarily mean always humble.
The Bible contains many examples
of ones who started out humble,
but somewhere along the way,
they lost their humility.
And you probably can think
of modern-day examples
of ones who lost their humility.
Now, in some cases,
perhaps they regained it.
But in other cases,
pride proved to be
their ultimate downfall.
But now think about this:
In a case of one who loses his humility,
does it just happen automatically?
Well, isn’t it true that in most cases
some situation develops in that person’s life
that proves to be a catalyst
that causes that person to lose his humility?
So this being the case,
let us discuss five situations
that could develop in our lives
and test our humility,
and if we’re not careful,
cause us to lose it.
Number one:
when we receive privileges
or added responsibilities.
In this regard,
let’s think for a moment about Hagar.
Now, the Insight book suggests
that she perhaps became
the maidservant to Sarah
during a time of great famine in Egypt.
So in that circumstance,
she would’ve been
very appreciative, very humble.
But now when she became
the secondary wife of Abraham
and found out she was pregnant,
then what happened?
Well, Genesis 16:4 says:
“When she realized that she was pregnant,
she began to despise her mistress.”
Yes, with her new honored status,
she lost her humility;
and appropriately,
Jehovah’s angel gave her some counsel.
The angel said:
“Return to your mistress
and humble yourself under her hand.”
Well, Hagar well illustrates
that a person who has had a good heart
can lose their humility
upon receiving privileges or authority
—an honored position.
But now let’s take
the second humility-testing situation:
when we receive success,
or achieve success, in some endeavor.
Now, let’s think about Uzziah in this regard.
In 2 Chronicles 26,
if you just scan down through verses 3 to 5,
it shows that he started out very humble.
He “was 16 years old when he became king,”
and in verse 4, “continued to do
what was right in Jehovah’s eyes.”
At the end of verse 5:
“During the time he was searching for Jehovah,
the true God made him prosper.”
So he started out well; he ruled well.
He was humble,
and Jehovah blessed him for many years.
But now look over at verse 16,
and you’ll notice
that it starts out with the word “however.”
And when the Bible uses that word “however,”
it means something changed.
“However, as soon as he was strong,
his heart became haughty to his own ruin.”
And then, as you know,
he even tried to go into the temple
and offer incense.
Now, what does that mean,
‘he became strong’?
Well, the Insight book explains
that he
“became famous for his military successes.”
So apparently these successes,
these achievements, went to his head
to the point that he thought
he could go into the temple
and usurp the duties of a priest.
He forgot that Jehovah
gave him those victories.
Now, that’s a lesson for us, isn’t it?
If we happen to achieve
success in some endeavor,
may we never forget
that the qualities and abilities
that enable us to achieve that success
came from Jehovah.
But now let’s get
our third humility-testing situation:
when we’re given counsel.
Now, Uzziah also well illustrates this point.
If you still have your Bible
open there, in verses 17 and 18,
when Uzziah went
into the temple to offer the incense,
you notice that it
describes how ‘Azariah the priest
‘and 80 other [and notice, it calls them]
courageous priests
went in there after him.’
They confronted him.
They tried to give him counsel:
‘You’re out of order.
‘What you’re trying to do,
only priests are to do.
You’d better go out of this sanctuary.’
Well, they tried to give him counsel,
didn’t they?
But how did Uzziah react?
Well, verse 19 tells us
that he “became enraged” at them.
‘Who are you to tell me what to do?
I’m the king.’
His pride became even bigger,
and Jehovah struck him with leprosy.
Now think about this:
Jehovah didn’t strike him
when he presumptuously first went
into the temple.
But only when he
pridefully rejected the counsel,
then Jehovah struck him.
Now, that’s a good lesson for us, isn’t it?
We have to be very careful
that we never become prideful
when we receive counsel.
And especially do we have to be on guard
if we think we have
more authority, perhaps more experience,
or more seniority
than the one giving us the counsel.
Let’s get our fourth humility-testing situation:
if we happen to come into material prosperity.
Maybe we get an inheritance,
or somehow we come into material prosperity.
Well, what happened to the Israelites
when they entered
the “land flowing with milk and honey”?
Well, the Bible tells us,
and Jehovah is speaking at Hosea 13:6.
Jehovah says:
“They were satisfied with their pastures,
“they were satisfied
“and their heart became proud.
And so they forgot me.”
Well, that’s a sobering lesson, isn’t it?
If we happen to come into material prosperity,
we never want to allow that situation
to cause us to lose our humility
—no matter what our material situation.
Then we
must always humbly depend upon Jehovah
and not material things.
Well, let’s get our fifth,
our last one, humility-testing situation
(and it was talked about earlier
by one of our commenters):
when we receive praise.
Do you recall the account in Acts chapter 12
when Herod put on his royal raiment,
he sat down on the judgment seat,
he began to give a public discourse,
and the people shouted:
“A god’s voice, and not a man’s [voice]”?
Well, what happened?
An angel struck him dead;
he died; worms ate him up.
Why?
Because he didn’t give glory to Jehovah.
In stark contrast,
think about the account in Luke 18
when a ruler came up to Jesus
and called him “Good Teacher,”
and Jesus said:
“Why do you call me good?
Nobody is good except one, God.”
Well, we can learn
from those examples, can’t we?
When we receive praise,
there are two ways we can react:
Like Herod,
try to take the credit for ourselves;
or like Jesus,
we can give the credit to Jehovah.
We can do that in words
or at least in our heart.
Now, Proverbs 27:21 says:
“A person is tested by the praise he receives.”
And one way he’s tested
is when his humility is tested.
The Watchtower some years ago said this:
“Praise [will] show the quality of a man’s heart.
“Wise men do not seek praise
“nor are they puffed up by it.
“Vain men seek it
and weak men are inflated by it.
“If one can bear praise without injury,
“remembering that anything
and everything he has is actually from God,
that one is sterling in the eyes of Jehovah.”
Well, there we have five situations
that can test our humility
and, if we’re not careful,
cause us to lose it.
Do you have them?
(1) When we receive
privileges or added responsibility,
(2) when we achieve
success in some endeavor,
(3) when we receive counsel,
(4) if we happen to come
into material prosperity,
and (5) when we’re praised.
But you can probably think
of other situations that can test our humility.
The point is,
If we meet these tests successfully
and keep our humility,
with Jehovah’s help,
then Jehovah will never oppose us.
Rather,
we will continue to receive
undeserved kindness
from his generous hand.