Did Jesus explain to his disciples
how his perfect body came to be?
Did he take the time to do that?
We don’t know.
But what we do know is that how he used
that perfect body when he was on earth
has a profound effect
upon our relationship with Jehovah God.
When we meditate and think about that,
that’s what we want to focus on
in our discussion this morning.
But how did that body come about?
Let’s find out.
Let’s open our Bibles, please,
to Luke chapter 1,
Luke chapter 1,
and we’re going to look at verse 31.
Now, the angel Gabriel,
in speaking to Mary, he says:
“Look! you will become pregnant
“and [you will] give birth to a son,
and you are to name him Jesus.”
‘Pregnant, me?
I’m a virgin. How can that happen?’
Jehovah employed his holy spirit
in transferring the perfect life force
of his only-begotten Son
to the womb of Mary,
thus causing conception.
Jehovah would cancel out any imperfection
that would be passed on to the child,
thereby producing a genetic pattern
that was perfect from its start.
Imperfection was not going
to stop Jehovah’s purpose
from being accomplished.
He dealt with that;
he handled that.
Very interesting here, too,
in verse 35:
“In answer the angel said to her:
“‘Holy spirit will come upon you,
and power of the Most High
will overshadow you.’”
So again,
holy spirit is involved.
And in some manner,
Jehovah guaranteed that it would be a boy,
and then he assured that
that developing embryo would be shielded
from the taint of sin
and protected from any harmful force.
So there she has this baby boy.
She was a Jewish mother,
so no doubt Jesus would have had
some of the physical traits of Mary
—his Jewish mother.
However, we need to remember
that he was not another personality;
he was not another person.
He was the only-begotten Son,
and he was able to identify himself
as such in due time.
But now imagine Mary
giving birth to this little baby,
and she’s holding
this little baby in her arms.
Now, how many mothers
have said to us when
that baby is born
and they’re holding that baby,
and they say:
“Look at my baby. It’s perfect.”
But Mary was right;
she got it right.
She was the only one that could say,
“My baby is perfect.”
She didn’t have to count the toes
and the fingers and so forth.
She got it.
But the thought is that
though she didn’t
fully understand all the details,
she’s holding this body
and it’s this body
that for thirty-three and a half years
is holding the blood
that’s going to be poured out
in behalf of mankind
as a ransom sacrifice.
But before that blood
was going to be poured out,
Jesus was going to use
that body in a very special way.
He used his fleshly body
to honor Jehovah God.
So again,
understanding how
he used that fleshly body
to honor Jehovah
has a profound effect
upon our relationship with Jehovah.
Let’s see how.
Let’s open our Bibles now
to 1 Peter chapter 4.
First Peter chapter 4,
we’re going to read verse 1:
“Since Christ suffered in the flesh
[suffered in the flesh],
“you too arm yourselves
with the same mental disposition;
“because the person
who has suffered in the flesh
has desisted from sins.”
Let’s think
about this for a moment.
Christ suffered in the flesh
—that fleshly body.
This is directly related
to the issue of sovereignty.
His blood paid the ransom.
But why did Christ suffer
in the flesh?
Because he chose to use his fleshly body
to honor Jehovah;
he chose to use his fleshly body
to defend Jehovah’s sovereignty;
he chose to use that fleshly body
to prove that Satan is a liar.
He suffered in the flesh.
On Nisan 14, 33 C.E.,
Jesus allowed himself
to be arrested by a mob;
he allowed himself
to be subjected to an illegal trial;
he allowed his back to be torn by rivets
and scourged through a scourging
and to be nailed
—his hands and feet—to a pole.
He allowed that.
And this is why he said at John 10:17:
“This is why the Father loves me.”
‘The Father loves me.
‘Why?
Because I surrender my life.
‘No man takes my life from me.
I surrender it of my own initiative.’
Now,
that’s the example he set for us.
let’s look at verse 1 again.
This time we see
that “b” part where it says:
“Because the person
who has suffered in the flesh.”
So who is that?
That’s you;
that’s me;
we’re the person.
We suffer in the flesh;
we desist from sins.
Verse 2:
“So that he [you, me] may live
“the remainder of his time in the flesh,
no more for the desires of men,
but for God’s will.”
The fact that Peter draws attention
to suffering in the flesh for you and me
—this is what we’re expected to do.
We’re imitating Jesus Christ
by doing that.
So here we are
in this very special week of activity.
We think deeply
upon the ransom sacrifice;
we think deeply
about how Jesus used his life.
And we have opportunity to do that.
For example, some ask,
‘Why do we pass
the emblems on Memorial night?’
They say, ‘If in a large congregation
there are so many there,
‘wouldn’t it be more practical
‘if the servers just stood
at the end of the aisle?
‘And if someone wanted
to partake of the emblems,
‘they would just nod
or give a sign to the server
‘and he would give them
to that person.
Look at the time we would save.’
But that’s not the pattern
in the Scriptures;
that’s not what Jesus did;
that’s not the procedure
that was instituted.
We’re following the Biblical pattern.
But in addition to that
—in the actual passing of the emblems—
what does that do?
That deepens our appreciation
as we see the bread passed;
as we see the wine passed.
We are able to understand
the sacred things
that are discussed
even more so that evening.
And we’re able to get involved.
Our feelings get involved.
That event burns into our memory.
So this Friday
as those emblems are being passed
—as the bread is being passed—
now you might say,
‘But I’ve been to so many Memorials.’
And some in our family have been
to decades worth of Memorials.
But how about this Friday
we do something different?
We just—as that bread passes—
we just think;
we just take a moment to reflect
on what that bread represents.
And we ask ourselves:
‘Can I think of one way
‘that I can use
my body, my mind,
‘my energy
‘to better worship Jehovah God?
‘Is there one way
that I can do better?
‘To what extent
am I slaving for others
‘as Jesus Christ did?
‘Like Jesus Christ,
‘to what extent
am I pummeling my body
‘and leading it as a slave
‘even if it takes drastic measures
‘—at times with self-control—
‘to make sure
that I am giving an answer
to the one who is taunting
my heavenly Father?’
When we examine
the life of Jesus Christ,
it’s as if he said to the Devil,
it’s as if he declared:
‘You want to attack my Father?
‘You go through me.
‘You’re going to go through me
‘because I am Michael
(“Who is like God?”).
‘No one attacks my God.
‘I am the chief defender
of His sovereignty.
‘I am the champion of my God.
‘I am the chief vindicator of Him.
That’s who I am.’
And we take that same stance
—that same posture.
Someone wants to attack
our heavenly Father?
‘You want to attack
my heavenly Father, Devil?
‘You go through me;
you go through me.
‘And my integrity,
my obedience,
‘my faithful course,
you know what it will do?
‘It will embarrass you;
‘it’s going to push you back;
it’s going to humiliate you;
‘it’s going to disgrace you
because I am using my body
as Jesus Christ did
to honor my heavenly Father.’