Welcome to this month’s broadcast.
Here are just a few highlights
of what we will enjoy:
Has anyone ever angrily confronted
you about your beliefs
and you found yourself
struggling to respond?
You are not alone.
In this dramatization, we will learn
how Grayson faces this same challenge.
With the right circumstances,
some have enjoyed full-time service
while successfully raising a family.
What did they do to make that possible?
The Schiller’s life story
will help answer that question.
We will see the excitement and benefits
that come from attending pioneer school.
But these students are not pioneers;
they are all in Bethel service.
And we will learn ways
to manage our time
so that we can do
“the more important things.”
All this and more
on this edition of JW Broadcasting!
Many have found public witnessing
to be an incredibly productive way
to share the good news in their territory.
Often, when we think
of this kind of ministry,
we might imagine being on a busy street
or in some other urban area.
Let’s see what it’s like
when public witnessing
is done in a very different location.
In the book of Romans,
the first chapter, verse 20,
it talks about how you
can perceive Jehovah’s creative power
by what we see in creation around us.
When you’re in a national park
and you see the beauty of these parks,
you immediately think of that scripture.
We have individuals driving
from an hour and a half
to over three hours one-way
to share in this form of witnessing.
National parks generally have
what is called a freeness of speech area.
So that allows us
to be able to get permission
to go into the parks
to set up our carts there.
It’s just a nice place to come and relax,
and when people are relaxed,
they’re wanting to talk.
They already kind of have
a sense of closeness with God;
it kind of gets them thinking
about their spirituality,
and then when they see our cart
displayed so nicely about that,
it kind of draws them toward that.
You will find visitors
from all parts of the world.
Many cultures are represented.
And quite often,
we will have literature in their language.
There are many that benefit
from our work at the carts.
But especially noteworthy are those
who do not have access to Bible literature.
A Chinese couple came up, and they said,
“Thank you for giving us
the Bible in our language.”
That made our day.
It was fabulous!
They may not stop.
They may not talk to us.
But they see it,
and that registers in their mind
—that they’ve seen this
at an airport or in their city.
And now they’re going to look into it
or go to the website and wonder:
‘What was that all about?
What were those people doing there?’
We sit here sometimes
thinking we need to pinch ourselves
because it’s so beautiful
that we’ve been given the privilege
of doing the cart work
in a location like this.
Very soon,
these national parks will not just be
isolated places that we have to travel to
—the entire world will be that national park.
And what a joy it will be
when every single person alive
can enjoy that beautiful painting
that our Creator has made for us!
Jehovah’s qualities
can certainly be perceived
just by taking
the time to study creation.
So we can see the power
of giving a witness in a beautiful location
that naturally draws attention
to what Jehovah has made.
Of course,
permission from park authorities
is often needed in advance,
but this idea of buying out
time to appreciate something
takes us nicely
into our discussion for this month.
I would like to talk about a valuable asset
that every one of us possesses
—time.
It certainly is something
that is on our minds
as we go about our day’s activities.
Just think of how often
you look at a clock, your watch,
or your cell phone to check the time.
Why do we do that?
Probably to see
if we are ahead of time, on time,
behind time, or out of time!
But what exactly is time?
One dictionary says
it is “a nonspatial continuum.”
Another says
it is “the thing that is measured
as seconds, minutes,
hours, days, and years.”
To explain exactly what time is
in simple terms is nearly impossible,
and the Bible does not define it,
which may suggest that Jehovah knows
it is beyond our ability to understand fully.
But the Bible does discuss time.
It shows that Jehovah is very time conscious.
It speaks of time
as something that we should use wisely.
And it gives us
the amazing hope of living into infinity
—that is, endless time.
We do know this about time:
Every human has exactly the same number
of hours and minutes in each day.
Rich people cannot buy more hours,
and scientists cannot invent new minutes.
We can never recoup
the time we have wasted;
neither can we save it
to spend on another day.
Just think, we have exactly
the same number of hours
to use each day that Jesus Christ
had when he was on the earth!
And we can be sure
that no human used his time more wisely
than did God’s Son.
It has been said that time
is the most valuable thing
a human can spend.
And so it is up to us
how we will use the time
that is at our disposal.
In this regard, there is a Bible principle
that gives us good direction,
a principle that was shared
with us by the apostle Paul
at Philippians 1:9, 10.
He wrote in verse 9:
“And this is what I continue praying,”
and in verse 10,
“that you may make sure
of the more important things.”
Therefore, the theme of this month’s program
is “Make Time for
‘the More Important Things.’”
This presents us with a two-fold challenge.
First, we have to determine
what are the more important things of life.
In the scripture we just read,
some Bible translations say
“have a sense of what is vital.”
So we must distinguish
between activities that are merely trivial
and those that really matter.
In addition to the obligation
to work to support one’s family,
to care for necessary household chores,
and to look after one’s children
or aging parents,
we have many important things
of a spiritual nature
that deserve our full attention:
reading and meditating on God’s Word,
studying the Bible personally
and in family worship,
preparing for and attending
congregation meetings,
caring for any responsibilities
that we have in the congregation,
and participating in the Christian ministry.
Besides all of that,
who does not want some time to rest,
to exercise, to work in the garden,
to enjoy some recreation,
or to visit with family and friends?
Have you ever felt that you did not have
enough time to do all those things
—that you have difficulty
fitting all the spiritual activities
into your busy life?
As much as we might like to,
we cannot add an extra hour to our day
or another day to our week
to accomplish more things.
So we have to be selective
about how we spend
the time that we have.
We will get the most accomplished
if we prioritize
the things that really matter.
And what does that mean?
To prioritize means to decide
which tasks are more important
and to do them first.
In other words,
decide what must be given attention
prior to other things.
There is a Bible proverb
that nicely illustrates
the importance
of prioritizing life’s activities.
Proverbs 12:11 states:
“The one who cultivates his land
“will be satisfied with food,
“but the one pursuing worthless things
is lacking good sense.”
What a clear warning that is for a farmer
not to fill up his day
with worthless endeavors
and waste the precious time that he
should be spending working in his field!
Likewise, a Christian
who diligently cultivates his spirituality
can be confident of Jehovah’s blessing,
whereas a person
who is distracted by worthless activities
puts his relationship with God in danger.
How can we avoid that?
By not taking valuable time
away from spiritual pursuits
to spend on the things that distract us
from serving Jehovah whole-souled.
For example, when it comes
to communicating with others,
what should take priority?
Starting our day
by giving Jehovah praise and thanks
in prayer for another day of life
or telephoning an old friend to catch up
on the latest news in his or her life?
There’s nothing wrong
with talking to a friend.
But we need to make sure we take the time
to talk to our very best Friend, Jehovah.
Obviously, it is more important
to communicate with our heavenly Father,
so praying to him should be a priority.
The apostle Paul had more
to say about time management.
At Ephesians 5:15-17, he wrote:
“So keep strict watch that how you walk
“is not as unwise but as wise persons,
“making the best use of your time,
“because the days are wicked.
“On this account stop being unreasonable,
“but keep perceiving what
the will of Jehovah is.”
Now we can address
the second part of our challenge:
to make ample time to care
for the more important things of life.
What does Paul’s counsel
to ‘make the best use of your time’
actually mean?
Literally, in Greek,
it means to ‘buy out the appointed time.’
That implies buying time
at the expense of something else.
So it helps to analyze
how our time is actually being spent
and to see what adjustments are needed
so that we can buy out, or make,
time for the more important things.
If we ‘perceive what the will of Jehovah is,’
then we certainly will want
to use as much time as possible
to forge an ever stronger
relationship with him
and to share fully in sacred service.
Do you have definite periods set aside
for the spiritual activities of life?
For congregation meetings,
the schedule is set for us.
We know exactly when
our congregation meets
for its midweek
and weekend meetings.
We just have to be sure
that we do not let
anything else get
in the way of our attending
because the meetings are a priority.
Hebrews 10:25 says ‘not to forsake’ them.
For everything else
—reading the Bible,
preparing for meetings,
family worship,
field service activity—
we have to set our own schedule
and stick to it as part
of a good spiritual routine.
As an example,
what does your family do
most Saturday mornings?
Many families have the routine
of going in field service every Saturday.
Rarely is anything allowed
to get in the way of that routine.
For them,
Saturday morning is not the time
for music lessons,
dance classes, cooking courses,
working out at the gym,
or anything else
—it is their time for field service.
Having a routine like that
makes life easier for everyone in the family.
No one has to wonder Friday night
what is going to happen Saturday morning.
The decision has already been made
to go out in the ministry that day.
Otherwise,
if we leave it up to chance every week,
then it means
that 52 times during the year
we have to decide
whether to go in service on Saturday.
How much simpler it is
to make the decision once and for all
that we will use
that time slot for the ministry,
barring any serious,
unforeseen circumstances.
Of course,
given your family’s situation,
another day of the week may work better.
But you get the point.
Sharing regularly in the Christian ministry
cannot be left up to chance.
At Mark 13:10,
Jesus prioritized the ministry when he said:
“The good news has to be preached first.”
So if spiritual matters are going
to take precedence in our lives,
we first have to make them priorities,
and second,
make ample time
to care for those priorities.
That means setting aside
definite periods of time
to build up our spirituality
and to stay fully involved
in our worship and service.
Ecclesiastes 3:1 reinforces this thought.
It states:
“There is an appointed time for everything,
a time for every activity under the heavens.”
We have to decide
when that “appointed time” is
for each of our spiritual activities.
If we are having difficulty with this,
can we shorten the time
we spend on hobbies, recreation,
sports, social networking
and devote that time
to our Bible reading, family worship,
meeting preparation, or field ministry?
If we can, we will find it
to be spiritually refreshing
and invigorating.
This was the experience
of a family man that I know
who began preparing better
so as to participate each week
in the “Digging for Spiritual Gems” portion
of the midweek meeting.
He made time on Sunday evenings for this.
All in his family
and congregation have benefited
from the excellent points he has learned
as he does research
on the assigned Bible reading,
and he feels good because of it.
One married couple decided to eliminate
some of their hobbies and personal projects.
They even packed them up
and put them out of sight.
Why?
So as not to be distracted by those things.
They were nonessential activities
that they decided they could do without.
Likely, we could all benefit
from taking inventory of our lives
and limiting any unnecessary activities
that may be interfering
with our spiritual routine.
Imagine how rewarding that would be!
Just think, if we could buy out
30 minutes each day
from doing something
that is not essential,
that is about how much time it would take
to read the entire Bible in one year.
Or if we could buy out
an extra hour or two
each week for the field ministry,
think of how much more
we could accomplish
and how happy
that would make God and Christ,
as they see us making time
for the more important things!
Now, why have we felt
the need to spend this time
discussing how to manage time?
It is because of something else
that the Bible tells us.
First Corinthians 7:29 says
that “the time left is reduced.”
That certainly is true of the time
that is left between now
and the great tribulation!
This is not the time to neglect
the most important activity of all
—our worship of Jehovah.
Making time for what matters most in life
is something we all need to do
—even our young ones.
And that’s the focus
of this month’s music video
about the important things.
Ev’ry day brings decisions,
and we must choose
How will we spend our time
and live for the truth.
Now, there’s a time to laugh
and be with our friends,
But it can’t be all
we’re living for in the end.
We need to set time aside
for what’s most important—
Prayer, study,
and godly devotion.
Make Jehovah real,
’cause that’s really what matters.
Throw off those things
pulling us down.
Think about the future
and where we are now.
Let nothing take the place
of more important things.
Life sure can weigh us down
with bills to pay.
It can make us lose sight
and misplace our faith.
But our fam’ly needs us
back at home.
And if we want to be there to help
and watch them grow—
We need to set time aside
for what’s most important—
Prayer, study,
and godly devotion.
Make Jehovah real,
’cause that’s really what matters.
Throw off those things
pulling us down.
Think about the future
and where we are now.
Let nothing take the place
of more important things.
We need to set time aside
for what’s most important—
Prayer, study,
and godly devotion.
Make Jehovah real,
’cause that’s really what matters.
Throw off those things
pulling us down.
Think about the future
and where we are now.
Let nothing take the place
of more important things.
What a delightful song,
and what precious children
we saw in that music video!
Well, today we invited
two young people to join us in our studio.
This is Logan, and this is Aiden.
Thank you for coming.
Thanks for inviting us.
What did you think of that video?
I liked it
and that it showed a lot of families
doing stuff that involves Jehovah.
Good.
The one thing I noticed was
that they were all in a relaxed setting.
It was not like in a busy city.
They were at, like, the shore
where they were talking about the Bible,
and it was nice family time
that they were having.
Good observations, Fellas.
Now, three times in the chorus it said:
‘We need to set time aside
for the most important things.’
Then it mentioned three important things.
What were they?
Prayer.
Study.
Godly—
—devotion.
That’s it, very good.
Good things for all of us to remember,
wouldn’t you say?
Well now, my wife and I
are in the same congregation
with Logan and Aiden
and their families.
So I know
what excellent meeting attenders they are.
And what I really appreciate
is that you participate in the meetings
and you comment in your own words.
That’s very good and sets a nice example.
Keep it up.
Speaking of the meetings,
how do you like the midweek meetings
with all the videos that we see?
It gives a diversity.
It’s not always talks.
It gives, like, a break in the meeting.
Yes.
The videos are always great,
and they go with every talk
that the videos are for.
And you know, sometimes
we even show Caleb and Sophia videos
from the Become Jehovah’s Friend series.
Now, I’ve got to ask you,
Do you have an idea for a new Caleb video?
I think I have one.
Caleb is at school;
he gets asked to go
to a birthday party at someone’s house.
He goes home and shows his parents the card,
and they discuss what he should do about it,
and then he preaches at school.
But before he does that,
Sophia gives him a couple of pointers
on preaching at school and on boldness.
Good.
How about you Aiden,
do you have an idea?
Yes, I think a good idea would be:
A new kid comes to Caleb’s class,
and it is his birthday,
and he passes out the treats.
But Caleb says, “No, thank you.”
And then he bullies him
that he doesn’t get to have fun;
he doesn’t get treats at school.
And I think
he should discuss it with the family,
and then maybe he could tell the boy
why he doesn’t celebrate birthdays.
Very nice.
Well, I’m sure the Teaching Committee
of the Governing Body
will give some thought
to your recommendations.
We brought you to the studio
because we want you
to help me with a little experiment.
And this is an experiment
that some of our viewers have seen before.
And you’ve probably seen it, too,
because it’s mentioned in Volume 2
of the book Questions Young People Ask
—Answers That Work.
And the idea is to help us appreciate
how we can make time
for “the more important things.”
Now, let me explain
what we have on the table.
The two pails represent
one week in a Christian’s life.
The large rocks represent
the most important things
that we need
to accomplish during the week,
and all these little pebbles
represent the nonessential things of life
—recreation, playing games, playing sports,
going on the Internet,
working with social media,
our hobbies, taking music lessons.
They’re all fun things to do,
but, really, they’re not essential.
Now, our challenge is
to try to get all the big rocks
into the pail with the little pebbles.
So as I hand you each rock, Logan,
I want you to put it in the pail.
Now, this first one represents
the important things
that your father might have to do.
He works to support the family.
Maybe your mother
is a pioneer or has to work secularly.
Your mothers certainly have a lot of work
to do around the home caring for the family.
And you boys go to school
and have homework to do,
so that’s a big part
of your time, isn’t it?
Now, this rock represents
all the chores that everyone
in the family has to do at home:
cleaning, washing clothes, cooking,
caring for the yard,
the automobile, and so on.
That takes a lot of time.
This rock represents a third of your life
—sleeping.
Now, here are the most important things
—our spiritual activities.
For instance, when we read the Bible
and meditate on what we read
and when we do
personal study and family worship.
This one represents
all the time it takes for us
to prepare for, dress for, travel to,
and attend our congregation meetings
—midweek and on the weekend.
And this represents the time we spend
in the field service on the weekend.
Now, I didn’t tell you
that we can’t go above the top of the pail.
They don’t fit, do they?
No.
OK.
And when that happens in a person’s life,
some brothers and sisters
are tempted to decide:
‘Well, maybe I’ll skip
field service this week,’
or ‘Maybe I’ll stay home
from the meetings,’
or ‘Maybe I just won’t get
my Bible reading
and studying and family worship
done this week.’
But that’s a big mistake, isn’t it?
These are the most important things of life
—our spiritual activities.
So is there some way that we can get
all of this into our week’s schedule?
Here’s what we’re going to do now.
We’re going to put
the rocks in the empty pail.
So, Logan,
see if you can get them all in there.
Very good! They all fit.
Isn’t that nice?
We can get the more important things done.
But you know, we also want
a little time for recreation, don’t we?
So, Aiden,
let’s have you pour
the little pebbles into that bucket
and see how much
of that you can get in there.
You can put a lot more in.
Very good!
Look how much you got in there!
Now, you didn’t get them all in,
did you?
But that’s OK because the Bible tells us
we have to ‘buy out the time’
for the more important things.
So, no, we can’t spend all the time
that we may want to on recreation.
We want to get
the more important things done.
So, what have we learned
from this little demonstration?
Why weren’t we able to get
the big rocks in the pail the first time?
Aiden?
Because there was too much recreation.
That’s right.
Now, Logan, why were we able to get
all the rocks in the second time?
Because we put in the nonessential things
—like watching TV, playing video games—
in second.
We put that in last, didn’t we?
Good.
So that teaches us:
Put the more important things first.
And it all depends
on what we fill our pail up with,
or our life with, first.
Thank you very much for your help.
I appreciate that.
And keep up your good work
as Kingdom publishers,
and I’ll see you at the Kingdom Hall
at the next meeting.
With this illustration in mind—
Let’s turn our attention
to the Schiller family.
Is it possible to balance raising a family
with a busy spiritual routine?
And if circumstances allow,
can parents reach out for spiritual goals
—even full-time service?
Let’s listen to their answers
to those questions.
Sometimes people say:
“Well, you know, what was your secret?
How did you raise six kids?”
We got married September 16, 1972.
Two things started coming quickly
—spiritual privileges came along
and the children came along—
together.
I was made an elder
shortly after the elder arrangement
came into effect.
The kids were just part of all that,
and you might think
that sometimes they didn’t know it.
We were doing
substitute work with five children,
and I don’t think they
even knew what we were doing.
In 1989, we were pioneering,
and then we had the opportunity
to help out at Bethel,
maybe a week or two at a time.
About that time,
Patterson was starting up.
And we kind of recognized
that maybe we were getting too comfortable.
We went one time to Bethel and said:
“Hey, if you need a doctor out at Patterson,
why, we’d be available.
Or we could make ourselves available,
maybe.”
And wouldn’t you know it,
shortly after, we got a call,
“How quickly could you
sell your place and be up here?”
So we went to Bethel with six kids,
sold our house at a loss so we could do that,
and started a new life there.
So we learned pretty quickly:
Don’t turn down any privileges
—and especially not because we had kids.
When we went to Bethel,
the oldest one was 17.
Having children
kept my husband and me very humble
because as soon as you thought
you had something figured out,
each child needed
to be disciplined in a different way.
And as soon as you thought,
‘Boy, you know, I’ve got this figured out,’
you’re thrown a curve.
A challenge was
to keep doing the basic things.
You’d come home tired.
It would be so easy
not to have the family study
maybe one Monday.
It’s those basic, simple things
that I think kept us on an even keel.
I often think
of the illustration that Jesus gave
at the end of the Sermon on the Mount,
what he said about this foundation
that was washed away.
And Jesus never blamed the storm;
he blamed the foundation.
And so we recognize that any child anywhere
—in fact, even adults—
can get their faith tested.
So we tried to really make sure
they had a good foundation
that didn’t get washed away.
Prepare them,
let them learn how to deal with people
while they’re under your care,
and get them ready for life.
We got to thinking, ‘Other parents
require their kids to go to college,’
so we just required them
to pioneer for a year.
Any kind of education—
Any kind of secular education can teach you
how to have a skill so that you have a job.
But the Bible teaches you how to live,
and it teaches you principles
that you can live your life by.
And all of them kept pioneering.
You know, they did various jobs
to support themselves.
They cleaned; they worked at lumberyards;
they worked on roofing.
And none of them have
a complicated life that holds them down.
I wanted everlasting life
for my children,
and I knew I would have to give
them back to Jehovah.
We have to realize we don’t own our children
—Jehovah does.
And we have to respect that.
We’re not telling them what to do anymore.
We appreciate
and we’re very, very thankful
when our children,
as far away as they are
and as busy as they are,
take the time to communicate with us.
And I know you won’t remember this,
but I remember one time,
before you fell asleep at night,
I said,
“With all that you have done for Jehovah,
what would you like in return?”
Do you remember what you said?
You said three words, “All my children.”
In Deuteronomy it says:
“I have put life and death before you,
. . . and you must choose.”
So we can do what we can as parents
—some things good,
some things not so good.
In the end, each one had to make
his or her own decision.
And that’s why, again,
it was not any secret we had.
We’re so proud of what the kids decided
and how they turned out
because it was their decision.
I think that’s the thing that we’ve learned:
Don’t turn down opportunities.
Isn’t it wonderful to hear of ones
like Brother and Sister Schiller
who have offered their gifts to Jehovah?
Brother Schiller said
that it was doing the basic things
that kept his family focused spiritually.
So when opportunities came along,
he was able to do more,
which included pioneering,
substitute circuit work,
and using the medical training
he had already acquired
to volunteer
at the Patterson Educational Center.
Proverbs 10:22 says:
“It is the blessing of Jehovah
that makes one rich,
and He adds no hardship with it.”(Ftn.)
That certainly has proved true
for Brother Schiller and his family.
We can all agree that one of the ways
Jehovah provides spiritual riches
is through the training
we receive at meetings,
assemblies, conventions,
and even special schools.
Such training helps us to prioritize
and to do “the more important things.”
Over the past few years,
members of the Bethel family
have attended the Pioneer Service School.
Let’s see how the school has helped them
in their Bethel service
and in their ministry.
It was a really great privilege
for us as Bethelites
to be able to study for six days.
The Governing Body
giving us time to study more
about Jehovah’s qualities was tremendous
to help build our spirituality.
For many Bethelites,
this was like a gift from Jehovah
because they had never attended before.
In fact, one couple
who had been 50 years in full-time service
had never attended the pioneer school before.
I’d been invited twice before,
but unfortunately,
both times I wasn’t able to go.
I felt like Jehovah
was giving me a third chance,
and this time I wouldn’t miss it.
At first, you feel a little like,
this is strange;
you’re at Bethel;
you’re not out pioneering.
But then,
when you’ve gone to the school
and you’ve seen what the school
actually does for your ministry,
it was really—
You can see why the Governing Body—
It was such a kind gift for them
to give us this privilege of coming.
You’re surrounded by people
who have been pioneers for years;
some have been to Gilead;
some have been in the traveling work;
some have conducted
pioneer schools themselves.
It’s the best.
Even though they’re
in this spiritual environment,
they need to be upbuilt.
As Bethelites,
we go out in service
not as much as we did
when we were pioneering.
So being able to have
an effective use of our time
in the ministry makes a big difference.
You learn a lot about the field ministry
in pioneer school.
So in a month when 30 hours was an option,
I applied to auxiliary pioneer
and I also tried to participate
a lot in the ministry on weekends.
This way I was able
to prepare for the school.
I think that every Christian
needs to have goals,
and even for us serving in Bethel,
we need goals.
So the main thing I learned from the school
is that even while working in Bethel,
I can do more for the congregation
and make a bigger effort in the ministry.
After the pioneer school,
I realized I needed to cultivate
more humility in my Bethel service
and the field ministry.
Because there’s so much spiritual food
available at Bethel,
it can become easy to neglect personal study.
Listening to the deeply meditated comments
from the students
and the instructors really stimulated me
to also meditate more deeply.
During the school,
I had to study more than usual,
so I had to set aside more time for reading
so as to be well-prepared for class.
It was really practical for me
to improve my ministry,
and it was really nice
because with this new school,
we had a demonstration
of what we have to avoid
and what is good to do.
There was a demonstration
about what not to do on a Bible study,
and I saw myself doing some of those things.
So I realized that I really needed
to get better at conducting Bible studies.
I remember one demonstration that taught us
how we can witness informally
in a supermarket line, for example.
That demonstration
gave me more confidence
to witness informally.
In the school,
we learned a lot about Jesus
—how he was hardworking, zealous,
and showed genuine interest
in the people around him.
That example helped me
to be more hardworking and zealous,
as well as to be more approachable
to those whom I work with.
That’s why we’re here in Bethel
—it’s to support the preaching work.
So it doesn’t matter what assignment we have.
In a way, it’s connected to that.
The fruitage of the spirit
is good not just for the ministry
but it’s good for everything in everyday life
toward our brothers and sisters.
Love is such an important quality
for Bethelites.
I work in the Computer Department,
but I don’t treat computers with love.
But the school strengthened my determination
to treat my brothers and sisters with love.
Out of all the other schools I’ve attended,
this school had the most impact on my life.
In just one week,
it strengthens our faith,
widens our view of things,
trains our conscience,
and deepens our love.
It definitely
stimulated the pioneer spirit.
Even though we’re not pioneers,
it helped us to understand
the importance of the pioneer service
and how it contributes
to our overall joy
in serving Jehovah.
So that’s something
that we would never want to neglect.
We really appreciated
the emphasis that was placed on that
and how it also helps to keep
our close relationship with Jehovah.
Certainly, we can see
the blessings that have come
from making time
for that additional spiritual training.
Spiritual training at Bethel
also includes morning worship.
Many of you have expressed appreciation
for the morning worship programs
posted on JW Broadcasting.
Let’s listen to Brother Geoffrey Jackson
of the Governing Body
as he shows us how we
can maintain a faithful life course
like that of Abraham.
This morning I’d like you to imagine
for a few moments
that you’ve been asked to write
your life story for The Watchtower.
Well, once you get over the shock,
how would you go about doing that?
You’ve probably noticed with many
of the life experiences in The Watchtower,
usually the first paragraph,
have a defining moment in that person’s life.
For example, Brother Eric Beveridge,
who serves with us here in the United States,
he started off this way:
“‘I hereby sentence you
to six months in prison.’
“With those words ringing in my ears,
I was taken off to . . .
“[p]rison in Manchester, England. . . .
“I had just faced
one of the toughest tests of my young life
—I had refused to be conscripted
for military service.”
Or another brother, Brother Harley Harris,
who served as a missionary
in Ecuador for many years,
he referred to the date September 2, 1950.
He said: “We were at a circuit assembly,
surrounded by a mob.
“The mayor brought in the National Guard
to protect us from the unruly crowd.
“Soldiers with drawn rifles
and bayonets lined the street.
“Amid insults,
we walked to our cars and drove to . . .
“the remaining sessions of the assembly.
It was there
that I was baptized at the age of 14.”
Or another brother, Brother Don MacLean
—who serves
on the Branch Committee in Australasia,
a brother originally from Canada—
made this comment.
He started his life experience:
“There I sat, hour after hour,
“with one of the Royal Canadian
Mounted Police by my side.
“I was his prisoner.
“We were headed
for the prison camp at . . . Ontario, Canada,
“and it seemed
[that] the 1,500-mile train trip
would never end.”
Well, those certainly were defining moments
in the lives of those brothers.
What about you?
What is your defining moment?
Well, you might be thinking,
‘No one put a gun
to my head and said,
“Decide now whether
you’ll serve Jehovah or not.”’
But for many of us, there have been
defining moments in our lives.
Perhaps it’s the moment
you decided to serve Jehovah
or the moment you decided
to become a full-time servant.
Perhaps it involved some decisions,
such as selling a home,
selling a business,
deciding to move to Bethel,
or perhaps leaving your country
and going somewhere else.
Or it may have involved
certain tests or trials,
perhaps giving up
opportunities for education
or for lucrative job opportunities.
Well, whatever the case,
I’m sure most of us
have had some defining moments
in our lives that we remember
—the decisions that were made
that resulted in much good.
Let’s think for a moment
about the faithful man Abraham.
What was the defining moment in his life?
Well, if you take your Bibles
and turn with me to Hebrews chapter 11,
of course, here we see
the apostle Paul giving us an outline
or history of many
of the defining moments
in the lives of faithful ones.
At Hebrews 11:8,
it says of Abraham:
“By faith Abraham, when he was called,
“obeyed by going out to a place
“he was to receive as an inheritance;
he went out,
although not knowing where he was going.”
Yes, that was a defining moment
in the life of Abraham, wasn’t it?
He decided to obey Jehovah,
to leave Ur,
and to travel to a distant country
that he didn’t really know about.
But was that all that was involved
with Abraham receiving the reward?
No.
Let’s read on a little further in verse 9.
There it says:
“By faith he lived as a foreigner
“in the land of the promise
as in a foreign land,
“living in tents with Isaac and Jacob,
the heirs with him
of the very same promise.”
Now, this is not a defining moment, is it?
This is a course of faithfulness,
day in, day out.
So, what’s the point?
Well, in the case of Abraham,
we remember
that eventually he and his family
crossed the Euphrates River
and into the Promised Land
in the year 1943 B.C.E.
But he had to wait 25 years
before his son Isaac was born
and then another 60 years
before his grandsons
Esau and Jacob were born.
And eventually,
he died after being in the Promised Land
as a foreigner for about 100 years.
So, what’s the point?
Although there was
a definite decision he made
—a defining moment in his life—
that was backed up as verse 9 says,
by his faithfulness
—day in, day out—
serving Jehovah.
So the lesson we learn from that is
that it’s not just the defining moments
that define who we are.
Rather, those moments and those decisions
need to be backed up by faithful service.
Let’s be quite frank.
Many of the life experiences
that we read in The Watchtower
may have a very exciting first paragraph.
“Yes, they put a gun to my head.
“Make your decision.
“Will you die?
Would you be willing to die for Jehovah?”
But then,
when you read the rest of the article,
nothing really exciting
happened in that person’s life.
I’m sorry to say it.
That includes my life experience as well.
Why?
Because the majority of our lives
are not involved with defining moments
—exciting things that are happening.
Rather, they involve
our faithfulness to Jehovah.
So we can’t just rely
upon these defining moments and say,
“Well, I made this decision
to serve Jehovah;
I passed this test,
so everything is good.”
No, we need to continue
to back up those defining moments
with faithful service.
Remember that in the Scriptures,
there were many who had
defining moments in their lives.
Take, for example, Solomon.
He had a defining moment, didn’t he,
when he prayed to Jehovah
and he was praised for the fact
that he asked for wisdom rather than wealth?
But that wasn’t backed up by faithfulness.
Eventually, that defining moment in his life
really wasn’t as valuable as it could’ve been
because of his lack of faithfulness.
And what about Judas Iscariot?
Were there some defining moments in his life?
Obviously, he decided
to follow Jesus at one point.
And during that time,
when he faithfully followed Jesus,
no doubt, there were very exciting,
interesting things that happened.
But again,
those defining moments in his life
proved to be of little value
because of the lack
of faithfulness on his part.
So that helps us to understand
why the apostle Paul
said some very interesting points
just before he started this list
that he gives us in Hebrews chapter 11.
Let’s turn to Hebrews chapter 10,
Hebrews 10:35-39.
Notice, this is the point
that we should gain from this lesson.
Paul says starting in verse 35:
“Therefore, do not throw away your boldness,
“which will be richly rewarded.
For you need endurance,”
now, that reminds us of what Jesus said
about ‘the one who endures
to the end will be saved,’
“so that after you
have done the will of God,
“you may receive
the fulfillment of the promise.
“For yet ‘a very little while,’
“and ‘the one who is coming
will arrive and will not delay.’
“‘But my righteous one
will live by reason of faith,’
“and ‘if he shrinks back,
I have no pleasure in him.’
“Now we are not the sort
who shrink back to destruction,
but the sort who have faith
for the preserving of our lives.”
What a very positive comment that is.
So when we think of our life experience,
don’t be disappointed if you
don’t have some spectacular things
that you can mention as defining moments.
Remember, the important thing
is not just the decisions
that we make along the way
but the fact that we remain
faithful to Jehovah
day in, day out.
As Brother Jackson mentioned,
we might experience
a “defining moment” in our spiritual lives,
but real faithfulness is shown
in how we handle
smaller challenges day to day.
One example might be if someone
were to attack
our beliefs in front of others.
Have you ever experienced that?
Were you nervous?
Did you find it challenging to find
the right words to make a defense?
In the next video,
notice how the character of Grayson
deals with a similar situation.
It was one of those mornings
when everything seemed to be going right.
In fact, this whole year was going right
ever since I got baptized.
My family is closer than ever.
I’ve made some good friends
in the congregation.
I even started a Bible study.
It felt good to let go of my fears
and serve Jehovah with everything I have.
But things can change very quickly.
Uh, I’m sorry.
You know what?
I think I saw Grayson
over the weekend on Saturday.
I think he might be one of those people
that tells you about the Bible.
One of those, uh—
You’re saying Grayson is a Jehovah’s Witness?
Yeah.
Let me go ask him.
Hey, Grayson?
Hey, how’s it going, Ron?
Did I see you on Saturday morning
over on Main Street?
Yeah.
You know, I’m one of Jehovah’s Witnesses.
And what we do,
we go out and talk to people about—
I’m sorry.
I just don’t get it.
You’ll go knocking on strangers’ doors
to support your own religion,
yet you won’t stand and support this country.
Why don’t you people
get involved and make
a real difference for once?
I was really disappointed in myself.
I guess I hadn’t moved past
all my fears like I thought.
Later that night,
for family worship,
we sat down and discussed
our brothers who were in prison
for their faith.
Mom, why are they in prison?
They don’t want to fight;
they don’t want to kill people.
It really touched Aiden.
He was moved to pray for them that night.
His prayer touched my heart.
And with so much on my mind,
I couldn’t sleep.
So I decided to get up
and do some research.
I found some information
on the apostle Peter.
Despite his zeal,
he also struggled at times
with fear of man
like when he denied Jesus three times.
But eventually, he overcame that fear.
We strictly ordered you
not to keep teaching
on the basis of this name,
and yet look!
you have filled Jerusalem with your teaching,
and you are determined
to bring the blood of this man upon us.
We must obey God as ruler rather than men.
The God of our forefathers raised up Jesus,
whom you killed,
hanging him on a stake.
“Always ready to make a defense
“before everyone who demands of you a reason
for the hope you have”
—Peter focused on his hope,
not his fear.
Just like these faithful brothers
have been doing,
I want to be like them
and make Jehovah proud of me.
The next day I woke up,
and I was thinking about the apostle Peter
and our brothers
who were in prison for their faith.
And even though I was still a little nervous,
I felt ready to talk to Eric.
Hey, Ron, Eric.
Sorry I didn’t get a chance
to explain the other day,
but if you have a moment now,
I’d love to be able to talk to you.
I don’t want to hear it.
Sorry, Grayson.
And I thought that was it.
But it wasn’t.
Ron said he wanted to know more.
Maybe I’ll never completely
get rid of my fears.
But my love for Jehovah
and the example of his courageous servants
helps me to be ready to meet the challenge.
The other day I wanted to show you something.
What a practical example
of how taking time to meditate
on Biblical or modern integrity-keepers
can help us have
the courage to defend our faith!
This is just another example
of how making time
for “the more important things”
—such as prayer, study, and godly devotion—
can help us remain faithful.
Before we conclude our program,
let’s take a moment
and travel to the country of Hungary.
Situated in the center of Europe,
visitors to Hungary
can enjoy delicious food and wine
and see the beautiful great plain
known as the Puszta.
Water also plays a vital role
throughout the country,
with its abundant rivers,
lakes, and thermal springs.
There are more than 21,000 publishers
and close to 300 congregations.
They’re offering waters of truth to others,
often in spite of severe economic challenges.
In fact, during the last ten years,
the number of regular pioneers
has nearly doubled.
In 2016,
a pregroup
in the Lovari language was formed.
This language is spoken
by many Roma people in Hungary.
While none in the group
is a native Lovari speaker,
they’re willing to learn this language
to help these thirsty ones.
Additionally, this year,
nearly 30,000 foreign students
enrolled at various universities
in Hungary,
providing a very diverse territory
for those serving
in a foreign-language congregation
or group.
Our brothers and sisters from Hungary
are overjoyed to send
their love and greetings to all of you.
We send them our Christian love in return.
From the world headquarters
of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
this is JW Broadcasting.