Welcome!
This month we’ll focus on how
we can “serve Jehovah with rejoicing.”
As parents know, a child is a source
of great joy as well as challenges.
We’ll see how the good example
set by these parents
influenced their children.
When you think of God’s promised new world,
do images like these come to mind?
How do they make you feel?
We’re sure you’ll enjoy a glimpse
of the future in our new music video.
And we’ll learn how our joy is enhanced
when we express appreciation for our family,
for our congregation, and for Jehovah.
This is the February 2020 edition
of JW Broadcasting®.
To set the stage, we’d like to begin
with a few thoughts about the subject
“Serve Jehovah With Rejoicing.”
This is what we are told at Psalm 100:2.
But do you serve Jehovah
with rejoicing all the time?
I guess we all will agree
that at times it
can be difficult to be happy.
So, then, is it really important
to serve Jehovah with rejoicing?
And what does it really mean?
In other words, what is this joyful attitude
that Jehovah expects from us?
And what can we do to serve Jehovah
with rejoicing and maintain a joyful spirit?
How can we prove that it is important
to serve Jehovah with rejoicing?
You might think of our goal,
which is to reflect his personality.
At 1 Timothy 1:11,
he’s called “the happy God.”
So isn’t it logical that Jehovah expects us
to be happy in his service?
In Deuteronomy chapter 28,
we find a report
of God’s dealings with the Israelites.
Here Jehovah warned them
of what would take place
if they became disobedient
and lost their joy in serving him.
We read at Deuteronomy chapter 28,
beginning in verse 45:
“All these curses
will certainly come upon you
“. . . because you did not listen
to the voice of Jehovah your God
“by keeping his commandments and . . .
“because you did not serve Jehovah your God
“with rejoicing and joy of heart
when you had
such an abundance of everything.”
Jehovah took such good care
of the Israelites,
and yet they were not happy.
This attitude was something
he did not like at all.
So we see that serving Jehovah joyfully
is very important.
This was emphasized by what Jesus taught.
For example, in the Sermon on the Mount,
he helped his audience to understand
how to be happy.
At times, this part in Matthew chapter 5
is referred to as the nine happinesses.
Later, the apostle Paul
wrote about “the fruitage of the spirit.”
Joy is counted among the aspects
of the fruitage of the spirit.
Being joyful is important,
and by means of his spirit,
Jehovah helps us to rejoice in his service.
But is it realistic to expect
that we will smile all the time
and cheerfully sing songs the whole day?
Of course, this is not what Jehovah expects.
We all have different personalities
and express our happiness differently.
Also, there are moments in life
when we are sad and disappointed.
And Jehovah is fully aware
that some of us are not healthy.
Others might fight depression
and are therefore at times
just not able to express joy in this way.
And yet he loves all of us
and appreciates us very much.
So, then, what is the joy
that Jehovah expects from us?
What exactly is
this joyful spirit, or attitude?
Here in Deuteronomy,
the term “rejoicing” means
“the inner feeling
and the outward manifestation of joy.”
And we also read about the “joy of heart.”
The heart stands for
what we are on the inside.
This is the interior man and is displayed
in all his various activities,
desires, affections, emotions,
passions, thoughts, and so on.
And so we see that joy comes from within us.
Yet, does the joy we are talking about
depend on circumstances?
Let’s illustrate: I think it’s safe to say
that we all like sunshine.
However, how does the farmer feel
when he urgently needs it to rain
and he’s waiting and waiting?
He probably would be happier if he had rain.
In these last days, we rarely, if ever,
have perfect circumstances with no problems.
So I think we can all agree
that our joy in Jehovah’s service
is not based on circumstances.
And we’ve had here
on this program and in our publications
many examples of ones
who have maintained their joy
in Jehovah’s service
despite challenging circumstances,
like poor health or opposition.
So, then, what is it
that makes us a happy person?
To help us to open up
the scope of the answer,
would you be willing to join me
for a little experiment?
Please close your eyes for a moment.
Do you have your eyes closed?
So now think about an apple.
Now you can open your eyes again.
Let me ask you a question:
Did you think about a red apple,
a green apple,
or a yellow apple?
Why are you able to answer this question?
All I asked you to do
was to think about an apple.
The answer is, we think in pictures.
In fact, we think
of countless pictures every day.
And after we think about it,
it’s like we put
all of the pictures in a stack.
And then when we think
the same thought a second time,
it’s like we pull the picture out from below
and put it on top of the stack.
The longer that we do not think the thought,
the deeper the picture gets in the stack
and it becomes more difficult to remember.
Now, this stack of pictures
representing our thoughts
is our subconscious.
This stack of pictures makes up
our emotional state, or state of mind.
It determines whether we are sad or happy,
whether we are bored
or excited, and so forth.
Jehovah our Creator
is aware of this powerful connection
between our thoughts  and pictures.
Let’s please turn to 2 Kings chapter 6
to find one example
of how Jehovah made use of this.
Here we find the report
about the king of Syria
who wanted to capture Elisha.
How did his attendant feel?
Let’s see at 2 Kings chapter 6,
beginning with verse 15:
“When the attendant of the man
“of the true God rose early and went outside,
“he saw that an army with horses
and war chariots was surrounding the city.
“At once the attendant said to him:
“‘Alas, my master!
What are we to do?’”
The attendant was in fear.
He probably thought
about their defenseless position
and saw himself
already captured by the Syrian army.
Would Elisha be able to help his attendant?
Verse 16:
“But he [Elisha] said: ‘Do not be afraid!
For there are more who are with us
than those who are with them.’”
In other words, Elisha said:
‘Think of something else.
Think of the many that are with us.’
Did this work?
It seems that the attendant was not able
to focus on these reassuring thoughts.
He could not envision Jehovah rescuing them.
How did Jehovah help the attendant?
At 2 Kings 6:17, we read:
“Then Elisha began to pray and say:
“‘O Jehovah, open his eyes,
please, that he may see.’
“Immediately Jehovah
opened the attendant’s eyes and he saw,
“and look! the mountainous region
“was full of horses and war chariots of fire
all around Elisha.”
Jehovah helped the attendant with pictures.
The horses and chariots
captured his attention.
His thoughts now focused on the fact
that Jehovah
was with them and in full control.
Now, in his mind,
he already saw Jehovah’s victory,
and he was not concerned anymore.
He was happy.
What he saw influenced his thoughts
and changed his state of mind.
Thoughts are so powerful!
And how considerate Jehovah is!
Remember, in the end,
Jehovah did not need
any of these horses and chariots.
He saved Elisha and his attendant
by striking the Syrian army with blindness.
When we compare the emotions of Elisha
with his attendant, what made the difference?
The circumstances were exactly the same.
Their thoughts made the difference.
Now, what
does this have to do with our subject
“Serve Jehovah With Rejoicing”?
So far, we have established
that Jehovah expects us to be happy, right?
We have seen that our thoughts
can be pictures that influence
who we are and how we feel.
Pictures and thoughts are closely connected.
That’s why the apostle Paul at Romans 12:2
highlights the importance
of our thoughts when he says:
“Be transformed by making your mind over,”
or at Ephesians 4:23,
he emphasizes this by saying:
“And you should continue to be made new
in your dominant mental attitude.”
Both scriptures highlight that our thoughts
are critical and have a bearing
on our whole being.
Additionally, the apostle Paul knew
that we can change our thinking.
Please turn with me
to 2 Corinthians chapter 10,
and see what he recommends that we do.
Here at 2 Corinthians 10:5, he says:
“We are bringing every thought into captivity
to make it obedient to the Christ.”
Isn’t this exactly what we should do?
We control what we think.
We avoid occupying our mind
with thoughts that weaken our faith
or thoughts that undermine
our determination to serve Jehovah.
Remember, we said that thoughts
are like pictures that stay within us.
We cannot delete them,
and they will have an effect on how we feel.
But is there something else we can do?
Are you ready for a second experiment?
Please close your eyes again,
and do not think of an apple.
You can open your eyes again.
Were you successful
in not thinking of an apple?
If so, you probably had to force yourself
to think of something else.
We are made to think.
So the key to serving Jehovah with rejoicing
lies not just in avoiding negative thoughts
but also in thinking healthy thoughts.
Philippians chapter 4 lists a few of them.
We read in verse 8:
“Finally, brothers, whatever things are true,
“whatever things are of serious concern,
“whatever things are righteous,
“whatever things are chaste,
whatever things are lovable,
“whatever things are well-spoken-of,
whatever things are virtuous,
“and whatever things are praiseworthy,
“continue considering
[or “thinking about;
meditating on”] these things.”
By considering and meditating on
these healthy subjects,
we create pictures in our mind
that make it easier for us
to display our joy in Jehovah’s service.
Serving Jehovah with rejoicing
really depends on us.
Happiness does not depend
on our circumstances;
happiness comes
from doing things Jehovah’s way.
When we actively control our thoughts,
we add more pleasant pictures.
And even if in the past
we’ve experienced things
that make it difficult
to express happiness,
in time,
these unpleasant pictures
will be buried under thoughts
like those listed in Philippians chapter 4.
And gradually
our inner peace, contentment,
and happiness grows
and can be seen by others.
Jehovah, our happy God,
appreciates every little step
in this direction
because it’s important to him
that we serve him with rejoicing.
In our first video,
we’ll learn another way
to serve Jehovah with rejoicing.
You’ll recall that Jesus said:
“There is more happiness in giving
than there is in receiving.”
And isn’t it true
that when we give commendation, praise,
and words of appreciation to others,
we experience joy?
In the following interviews,
notice why some hesitate
to express appreciation.
We’ll see how they were helped by applying
lessons they learned from The Watchtower.
I work as a pioneer
and also as a commuter at Bethel.
I find this service to be very enjoyable.
However, because of my busy schedule,
at times I almost forget
to express my appreciation
to the brothers and sisters.
I wanted to express
my appreciation to my wife,
but I found myself
feeling bashful in doing so.
I knew something wasn’t quite natural.
Generally, expressing appreciation
is considered to be a virtue.
But I realized that I needed
some sort of stronger motivation.
Although all ten lepers
must have been grateful,
only one person returned to give thanks.
I suddenly realized
that even if I feel appreciative,
I might fail to express it.
Esau was an impatient man.
In contrast, David thought deeply
about how wonderful pure worship is.
I came to realize
that it is important to think deeply.
One sister was visiting
a very sick sister almost every day
to help her with shopping
and was looking after her very tenderly.
As I thought carefully
about why she was doing so much
and how she felt,
I felt deep appreciation well up in me.
Jehovah richly rewards us.
If Jehovah desires
to express his appreciation,
what kind of person am I
if I don’t show it from the heart?
Perhaps I might be thinking to myself
that I deserve to be appreciated,
since I am the one providing
for my family, aren’t I?
I started thinking
about how Jehovah wants to reward my wife.
That made me want to interact with her
with kinder words.
I feel that the way I look at her
and my facial expressions
are changing as well.
It gets easier
to resolve disagreements quickly.
I also feel that we are growing
closer and closer as a couple.
By expressing appreciation,
I feel very happy.
My relationship with brothers and sisters
within the congregation has gotten better,
and the bonds of friendship
between us are stronger.
I realized that the reason why
Jehovah encourages us
to express our appreciation
to others is for our happiness.
That drew me even closer to Jehovah.
Expressing appreciation
may not come easy for some.
As we saw,
we may be busy with our spiritual routine.
Perhaps we are shy.
We may need to make a special effort
to get to know our brothers better.
But what’s the result if we do?
We draw closer to them and to Jehovah
—and that makes us happy.
Being part of a loving family
can bring us great joy.
It also comes
with responsibilities as parents,
as children, and as siblings.
In the following dramatization,
we’ll see how three siblings decide
how to honor their elderly mother.
And please note how vital
good communication in the family is.
This wasn’t the first health scare with Mum.
And my brother and sister
were always quick to help out.
But this time was different.
She’d be here for at least another week
and then more long-term care.
We just weren’t prepared for that.
I should have accepted
more help when the friends offered.
I just didn’t want to be a burden.
Janice understood,
and she was wondering
how this might affect her Bethel service.
Terrance wished he lived closer
so he could do more.
We decided to pray, sleep on it,
and regroup after doing some research.
I shared the example of Joseph in Genesis 45,
where he told his father:
“You must dwell in the land of Goshen,
where you will be near me . . .
I will supply you with food.”
He didn’t let a long distance
get in his way of caring for Jacob.
He took practical steps
and made his care a priority.
Janice and Terrance too found great articles
offering solutions
such as asking for periodic help,
making more time to communicate with Mum,
or even getting a part-time nurse.
We weren’t prepared
for her situation to change so suddenly,
but Jehovah is guiding us
through each new challenge.
And with his help, we’re honoring Mum,
making her care our continual priority.
In this dramatization, we saw one way
that a family decided
to care for an aging parent.
Of course, situations will differ
from one family to the next.
Each must make a prayerful decision
based on their circumstances.
If you and your family are seeking
the right way to honor your elderly parents,
what can help?
Bible principles
and, as we saw in the video,
open and candid communication.
This, coupled with respect and love,
will help you make a good decision.
Now we’ll look at the joy and challenges
that come with raising children.
We’ll travel to Alaska,
in the United States,
to visit the Bode family.
Let’s see what we can learn
from the example
set by the parents, Dale and Nadja.
We were serving in a small town in Alberta,
and then we began having children.
When we moved to Craig we had four children.
And after living here,
we now have nine children.
You were given this trust,
and so as a parent,
you need to put the Kingdom first;
you need to set a good example;
you need to be at the meetings;
you need to be regular in field service.
We really believed
that we needed to love Jehovah first
in order to be
a good example for our children.
They helped us see that what would make
us happy were spiritual things.
My parents, more in action than in words,
taught us to seek first the Kingdom.
With nine kids,
it’s always going to be hectic.
You have extra children;
you have more excuses, perhaps.
Having nine children
is a challenge in a million ways.
Yeah, she had moments where she’d sit
in her rocking chair
and just look so  exhausted.
I remember one time
when it was time to go to the meeting,
but I was so exhausted.
And I thought of Isaiah 40,
where Jehovah says
that “those hoping
in Jehovah will regain power.”
So I figured that Jehovah wants me to do it.
He’s going to make me
strong enough to do this.
So I prayed, and I got ready.
It’s a scramble.
In Hebrews, we see the encouragement
to never forsake “our meeting together.”
My dad always spoke of that.
There was a time
that we had to travel in the wintertime,
maybe up to two hours to get to the meeting.
You’d come back to your home late at night,
you know, with all these kids
that are worn out—and yourself too.
Seeing the importance
that they placed on the meetings,
I was able to see
that you never take meetings for granted.
My parents always instilled in us consistency
in field service just like the meetings.
It was just what we did.
That wasn’t questioned.
We got up on Saturday morning,
and we got ourselves
out the door and in service.
We couldn’t simply
just be a backseat ornament.
We knew that we were there to give a witness.
From an early age,
we were really following the example
of our parents in showing interest in people.
So because of that,
we enjoyed being in the ministry.
It gave me a sense of purpose.
I had people to go visit in service.
I had to know what I was going to talk
to them about and have a plan.
In field service, we would often take breaks
for the sake of the children and ourselves.
It was important to have our children
enjoy field service—not push them hard
and be too rigid, and so forth.
I think about Proverbs 22:6
in the Byington translation
where it says to “give a boy
the start his course requires.”
They did that by putting the spiritual things
before the material things.
Jehovah helped us
to be the best parents we could be.
We failed at times, but I always knew
that Jehovah was the best Parent.
So if we could teach them to love Him,
then he would take over.
Well, we as a family were successful
because we did have Jehovah in our lives.
All our children
are doing very well in the truth.
And so we’re very happy about that,
and I’m sure it makes Jehovah happy.
You may not have nine children
—or seven or five or two—
but can’t all parents learn
a valuable lesson from the Bodes?
A very important lesson
was mentioned by one of the daughters.
She said,
“[Our] parents, more in action than in words,
taught us to seek first the Kingdom.”
Yes, despite the many demands
of a busy household,
Dale and Nadja put
the spiritual needs of their family first.
It was their example
that had a wonderful influence
on all of their children.
Next, we’ll hear from Brother Stephen Lett
of the Governing Body.
He spoke to the Bethel family
about an enemy of joy
and where to find the antidote to it.
Now, my theme is
“Guard Against Every Sort of Greed.”
Jehovah lovingly gave counsel
to Jeremiah’s secretary, Baruch,
to stop “seeking great things” for himself.
Now, what were those great things?
Well, we don’t know for sure,
perhaps prominence
or material things or both.
But what bad quality was developing
in Baruch’s heart that Jehovah saw?
Greed.
And the Insight book defines greed
as “inordinate or rapacious desire.”
The dictionary says it’s “a selfish, . . .
“excessive desire for more of something
(such as money) than is needed.”
So, in effect, Jehovah was telling Baruch,
‘Stop being greedy.’
And in an extended application,
Jehovah tells us the same thing.
Now, echoing Jehovah’s counsel to Baruch
is what Jesus tells us.
If you’ll open up to Luke chapter 12,
and let’s read our theme scripture here.
Luke 12:15
—similar counsel from Jesus—
Luke 12:15:
“Then he [that is Jesus] said to them:
“‘Keep your eyes open and guard [now notice]
“‘against every sort of greed,
“‘because even
when a person has an abundance,
“‘his life does not result
from the things he possesses.’”
Now, what makes it a challenge, though,
for us to “guard against
every sort of greed,” as Jesus counseled?
Well, our three great enemies.
In fact, let’s discuss each of these
and how it makes it a challenge.
Now, first, our imperfect flesh.
At Genesis 8:21, Jehovah said:
“The inclination of the heart of man
is bad from his youth up.”
And one form of badness is greed.
This tendency toward greed
becomes manifest very early.
For example, we see little toddlers
grab things and hold them tightly.
“Mine, mine, mine.”
That greed is starting to manifest, isn’t it?
When people look at a little toddler,
they may say,
“What a cute little boy,”
or “He has his mother’s eyes
and his father’s nose.”
But they never invariably say:
“Look at that little toddler.
What an unselfish little toddler!”
No, it takes a lot of effort
—doesn’t it?—
to teach that little one
to be unselfish like Jehovah.
But now, what about our
second great enemy, Satan?
What was Satan’s downfall?
It was greed.
He allowed a greedy desire for something
that belonged
to Jehovah alone to develop in his heart.
And what was that greed for?
Worship.
And he wants his downfall to be our downfall.
He wants to ensnare us in greed.
So he tries to magnify, intensify,
our wrong tendency to be greedy.
And if you think about it, how was Satan
able to entrap the perfect woman, Eve?
He entrapped her in greed.
He got her to crave, desire,
what belonged to God alone.
In effect, he said to her:
‘Eating of all the trees
of the garden minus one tree
‘is not good enough.
‘You should crave that one tree
that has not been given to you.’
In fact, let me, please, illustrate
how greedy Satan made Adam and Eve
—how greedy they were.
I’d like for you to imagine
that you have guests staying in your home,
and you say, “Now, I really want you
to make yourselves
at home while you’re here.”
You take them into the kitchen;
you open the refrigerator and say:
“There are all kinds of food here
“in the cabinets
—the pantry—
“everything you could imagine
that you would want to eat.
“It’s yours.
Help yourself.
Don’t even ask.”
But then you pull out
one little drawer, and you say:
“Now, I’ve set aside
some items for a later occasion.
“Please, this is very important.
“Do not eat from this one drawer.
“But you’ll find other items just like
“in this drawer
in the pantry and the cabinets.
You’ll have everything you need.”
Now, would that be overly restrictive?
Would that be
an unloving arrangement with your guests?
It’d be very generous, wouldn’t it?
And, in effect, that’s the arrangement
Jehovah made with Adam and Eve.
But now, back to the illustration:
If you came into the kitchen
and you found your guests eating
out of that one drawer
that you had not given them,
you’d be very upset, wouldn’t you?
And you’d probably view it as stealing,
and you likely would put
the thieves out of your house.
So that illustrates
how Jehovah felt and how Jehovah reacted.
But what a protection being content
with what was rightfully hers
would have been to Eve!
But now, what about
our third great enemy—the world?
We are relentlessly surrounded
by Satan’s world and his spirit,
called “the spirit of the world.”
We could say
that Jehovah breathes holy spirit
to influence his people
to act like him and to be unselfish.
But Satan, in effect, exhales
the stinky spirit of the world
that makes people
act like him in being greedy.
And one way Satan’s world
promotes greed for material things
is by relentless advertising.
People are constantly bombarded
with advertisements.
For example, here’s just an example:
They may bring out a shiny, new car;
it has about 12 coats of wax on it.
They have all these spotlights shining on it.
They bring in a camera
from all different angles
and, about this time,
a scantily clothed woman
comes strolling out to that automobile.
And you don’t even notice it, but there’s
soft music playing in the background.
As she opens the door and gets in,
a crescendo is reached
in the background music.
You’re made to feel like,
‘You poor, poor loser
if you don’t have that car.’
They don’t talk about the heavy payments
you’re going to have to make
or how many meetings you’re going to have
to miss to make those payments.
‘You poor loser if you don’t have that car.’
And similar advertising methods
are used very often
in promoting
many other gadgets and material things.
So, obviously, we have to fight hard
against the spirit of the world
so that we don’t allow it
to nurture greed in our hearts.
In fact, if we’re not careful,
our love for Jehovah
could be squeezed out
by love for money
and love for material things.
And if this happens,
rather than
conquering the world as Jesus did,
the world will have conquered us.
Now, it admittedly is a great challenge
to fight these three great enemies and avoid,
as Jesus counseled, “every sort of greed.”
But now, think of that—Jesus indicated
there’s not just one sort
of greed, one kind of greed.
Greed can take on
various faces, or manifestations,
but we’re to guard against all of them.
What would you say is the antidote
that can immunize us
against the poison of greed?
Well, is it not contentment?
For example,
one sort of greed we talked about,
greed for material things
—well, contentment will immunize us
against this terrible form of greed.
We’re familiar with 1 Timothy 6:8:
“So, having food and clothing,
“[and the footnote adds “shelter.”]
we will be content with these things.”
So contentment really protects us.
And, in effect,
that’s what Jehovah was telling Baruch;
he was telling him:
‘You have what you need.
‘Stop storing up great things,
or seeking great things.
Be content with what you have
and do more important things.’
And then he gave a powerful reason
why Baruch should do this.
Jehovah told him at Jeremiah 45:5:
“For I am about to bring
a calamity on all flesh,”
so if “you get the mastery over” this,
“I will grant you your life as a spoil.”
Well, the same applies to us, doesn’t it?
Jehovah is soon going to bring
a calamity on all flesh,
and so we need to be content
with what we really need
and ‘seek first the Kingdom.’
We’re just ‘temporary residents,’ aren’t we?
That’s what 1 Peter 1:17 says.
Now here’s an illustration
about a temporary resident.
I’d like you to imagine
that we rent a venue
for our regional convention.
Now, you may do a few things
to make the stay
more comfortable in that venue.
For example, you may do thorough cleaning;
you might do some touch-up painting;
you might repair
some broken toilets or light fixtures.
But you would never paint and plaster
the entire stadium inside and out.
You wouldn’t rip up the seats
and put all new seating in.
You wouldn’t tear out
the parking lot and put in a new parking lot
because you know
you’re just a temporary resident.
You’re going to vacate
that place after the weekend.
Now, unlike the illustration, we don’t know
exactly when we’re going to vacate,
but we know it’s soon.
So we keep it simple.
We’re just temporary residents.
Another sort of greed
is greed for prominence.
But being content
with how generous Jehovah
has been in giving us so many privileges
will protect us from this greed.
It would’ve protected Korah in Moses’ time.
Another sort of greed
is greedy sexual desire.
If we’re single or married,
being content
with what rightfully belongs to us
will really be a protection.
It would have protected David
from his sin with Bath-sheba.
Or there are other sorts of greed,
such as gluttony and drunkenness.
But the antidote
for all of these is contentment
—contentment with what is rightfully ours
that Jehovah has given to us.
And if we are successful
in guarding against every sort of greed,
then we’ll be on hand
to enjoy the marvelous time
when Jehovah will open his hand
and satisfy every proper
“desire of every living thing.”
Full-time service
is a special way to serve Jehovah
with a joyful heart.
But what happens to your joy
when you suddenly face a serious trial?
Jay and Elaine Humer,
you have been through this.
Thank you for being here today
to share your personal experience with us.
You’ve enjoyed
full-time service for over 40 years,
many of those years in the traveling work.
Yes, we’ve had
the wonderful privilege of both pioneering
and serving
in the traveling work for 30 years now.
And we really feel that Jehovah has been
very kind to allow us to serve him this way.
I remember
when I first filled out my application
for regular pioneering back in 1972,
and I thought this was my gift
to Jehovah—my sacrifice.
But after the many years
of the blessings and the privileges
and how Jehovah helped us
through some very difficult times,
what I thought was my gift to Jehovah
turned out to be his gift to me.
This is very encouraging.
Thank you.
Now, you mentioned “difficult times.”
Is there anything
in particular you can think of?
One of the hardest things
that we faced was about 20 years ago
when we experienced
seven deaths in just a six-month period.
This really was difficult because five
of those seven were family members.
Jay’s father died,
my aunt Alma (who brought me
into the truth) died, and my father died.
So it just seemed
like one layer on top of another.
We can hardly imagine how you must have felt.
Now, after such a Job-like experience,
what did you do in order
to regain your joy and happiness?
Well, it didn’t occur automatically.
We kept focused, of course,
on serving the friends
and working with them,
and that kept our thoughts
from constantly circling around our losses.
We also thought about the resurrection.
We focused on the resurrection hope
and, as we did,
it became like “the helmet of salvation,”
protecting our hearts and our thoughts
from the grief that we were going through.
And then, of course,
we shared our hope with others,
and that helped us to have it more
deeply engraved on our own hearts as well.
Thank you.
So now, may we learn
from you what you did in practical terms?
The most difficult of all
was about four years after that
when our beloved nephew Christopher
was killed
in an auto accident at the age of 17.
He and his parents
had lived with us in the same house
for a number of years
before we went on the road.
And we always looked
at Christopher like the son
that we would never
have on this side of Armageddon.
So his death was particularly tragic.
It was excruciating for all of our
family members, especially his parents.
Christopher was on his way
to the Kingdom Hall
to meet his papa
and his grandmother for field service,
and his car hit a patch of ice
and slid into an oncoming car.
He died instantly.
This was so difficult for us.
Our hearts were broken,
and our spirits were nearly crushed.
It actually rendered me speechless,
even to beg for the “groanings
unuttered” became very difficult.
I didn’t speak to Jehovah for three days,
but I was listening.
What do you mean by “listening”?
I remember when we were
all together as a family,
and my sister just happened to say
that Christopher had been cremated.
We were there
making arrangements for the funeral,
and it just hit me so hard.
It was just—it just hit hard enough
that I fell down, and I just cried.
I laid there on the floor, and I thought,
perhaps, maybe Mary
felt this way when she said:
‘Lord, if you’d only been here
this wouldn’t have happened.’
But as I laid there,
I could hear my sister say:
“Go get her Bible.
Read her her favorite scripture.”
And so Jay did.
He turned to Psalm 91,
a psalm that I had already memorized,
and now I began to hear Jehovah’s voice.
So was this listening
to Jehovah a onetime occurrence?
No, by no means.
I really had to now do my research.
So I searched
for every article on the resurrection,
I searched for every scripture on comfort,
and I meditated on the artwork
—the pictures in the publications.
I remember one particular scripture
that really touched my heart.
It was from Psalm 56:8.
And there it said:
“You keep track of my wandering.
“Do collect my tears in your skin bottle.
Are they not recorded in your book?”
And I thought about Jehovah
taking such notice of us
—keeping track, watching over,
even collecting every tear
and recording each of them.
That truly made me draw close to Jehovah.
So you continued to listen to Jehovah
by looking at comforting material
from the publications.
Was there any
specific article you thought of?
There was an article.
It was about a delicate flower
that had been bent over after a rainstorm
—the kind of cloudburst that would
send humans and animals running for shelter,
but not this flower.
Here it was intact,
bent over but unbroken and still rooted.
I thought about us in that same way.
The article said that we can no more
avoid losing a loved one
than this flower could
uproot itself and run for cover.
It had to endure.
But the article spoke
a great deal about hope and about faith.
Hope is our anchor, and hope
is our preserver of our spirituality.
And faith
—James 1:3 stated there that faith—
when it succeeds, we’re able to endure.
And so that’s exactly what happened.
It softened the grief.
And so like this flower,
we too would stand up and smile one day.
And we did.
I remember the first time I smiled inside,
and I thought,
‘Oh, Jehovah,
you truly are a healer of hearts.’
So did you do something else?
Now I started looking
for some of the artwork in the publications.
And one particular picture
I found was of a shepherd
who had gone into
a bramble bush and rescued a lamb.
He was lost.
He pulled him out, threw him
over his shoulders, and held onto him.
And I thought, ‘What a safe place to be
—such security!’
I decided to take the picture
and to print it out
and just enlarge it a little bit.
But what I didn’t see
on the publication page,
I saw when I enlarged it, and there
were scratches on the shepherd’s face.
And I thought about what
that shepherd had gone through
to go in the bramble bush and pull him out.
And then, I thought about Jehovah
as our Great Shepherd
and the lengths that he
went through to rescue us,
even at the cost of pain for himself.
Now I was listening and drawing close,
back to Jehovah.
So, then, what did you do
with these articles and the pictures?
So now I decided to print them all out
—the articles, the pictures,
and the scriptures—
and I displayed them
on my desk for quite some time.
But then I put them
in a big envelope (or like a file),
and I thought that was
Jehovah’s sympathy card to me.
We knew that we had to do something
so as not to be swept away by our grief.
It’s been said that grief is an arduous
journey, but one that we cannot avoid.
It’s not a place where we live
but a passage, as it were.
And we know that even though grief
never goes away, it does change over time.
That’s because Jehovah
made our hearts to heal.
And so, in time, that’s what we did.
Yeah, we sure did.
It’s not about the lack of faith;
it’s simply the price of love.
We loved Christopher, and we miss him.
It wasn’t like we were leaving him behind.
Sometimes that’s how you feel
when you lose a loved one.
But in reality, we know
that Christopher is in Jehovah’s memory.
And as the righteous God,
Jehovah never forgets his loyal ones.
Christopher was one of them.
So we’re confident
that we’re going to see him again.
And that’s what
helps us not to be, as it were,
always looking in the rearview mirror
but looking ahead to the time
when we will be with him in Paradise.
You know, Jehovah truly kept his promises,
and he carried us through that storm.
He gathered up the pieces
of our broken hearts and sealed them.
And even though this happened 17 years ago,
sure, we still have cracks in our hearts.
But we know for a certainty
that those one day will disappear as well
in the Paradise
when we welcome him back home.
And so, Jehovah
truly proved to be my stronghold,
my Father, and my Friend in a profound way.
We learned that Jehovah truly does
love us, cares for us, and protects us.
And because he is such a good Father,
our joy has come back
and we have had such a rich life.
So in all the years that we’ve had
the privilege of serving our God,
we’ve always found
that no matter what we give Jehovah,
no matter what sacrifices
we make for him, he always gives us more.
You cannot out generous
the most generous Person in the universe.
And so, just as he has
blessed us all these many years,
we are confident
that he will continue to bless us
as we transition to our next assignment.
Thank you so much for sharing
your personal experiences with us.
And may Jehovah
continue to be with the two of you
as you now continue
your full-time service as special pioneers.
And may you be able to apply
the principles that you have just mentioned
so that Jehovah
can continue to “guard your hearts.”
Thank you.
As we discussed earlier,
happiness does not depend
on our circumstances
but on our thoughts and our outlook.
And we can influence our thoughts
by what we picture in our mind’s eye.
We’ll see that beautifully brought to life
in our new music video entitled
The New World to Come.
Take a moment now and picture the scene.
Up ahead on the path are what seem to be
Children laughing at play
In a world free of the fears we once faced.
And taking care of this beautiful earth
Are a people that live by our Father’s words:
“Until the moon is no more”—
There is the peace we have been waiting for.
We will feel His love
Under the rule of His Son
In the new world to come.
Hope is a fire in our hearts.
Hope is an anchor that holds us firm.
Hope is a light that shines like the sun
As we see ourselves there
In the new world to come.
Take a moment now and think of a place
By the mountains and rivers or wide open plains.
It’s a place to call home.
And now walking in through your front door,
There is someone that you know
Holding out his open arms in hopes
Of a tearful embrace—
Feels like forever since you’ve been face-to-face.
Even death won’t stop
Our God’s outstretched love
In the new world to come.
Hope is a fire in our hearts.
Hope is an anchor that holds us firm.
Hope is a light that shines like the sun
As we see ourselves there
In the new world to come.
And ev’ry word from His mouth
Will do all for which He sent it out.
Jehovah’s will for this earth is
Fulfilling ev’ry living things’ last wish.
Hope is a fire in our hearts.
Hope is an anchor that holds us firm.
Hope is a light that shines like the sun
As we see ourselves there
In the new world to come,
In the new world to come.
You’ll probably want to listen
to that song again and again.
Or you might even want to sing it yourself.
Our hope is one of the things
we want to focus on.
And this will have an effect on us;
it will contribute to our being joyful.
Let’s conclude
this month’s program with a visit
to a truly beautiful part of the earth:
Martinique.
This island in the eastern Caribbean
measures just 50 miles
(or about 80 kilometers)
by 22 miles (or 35 kilometers).
Yet, Martinique,
nicknamed the Island of Flowers,
has stunning geographic diversity,
with beaches,
forests, rivers,
sugarcane plantations,
and rugged mountains.
The highest point is Mount Pelée,
infamous for causing
the deadliest volcanic eruption
in the 20th century.
When Pelée erupted in 1902,
nearly 30,000 people died
because they ignored the warnings.
This tragedy is often discussed
by our brothers in the ministry.
Today, more than 4,700 publishers
in 62 congregations
share the good news in eight languages,
including French, English,
French Sign Language,
Arabic, and Creole of Martinique.
They conduct more than 4,500 Bible studies
—nearly one per publisher.
Over one million tourists
visit this beautiful island every year
—many by cruise ship.
This presents a unique preaching opportunity.
The city of Le Marin
hosts 55,000 boaters annually.
Here our brothers preach
“sailboat to sailboat.”
This is the city of La Trinité.
A Creole of Martinique congregation
was formed here two years ago.
Today, the congregation has 91 publishers
and 10 regular pioneers.
They preach
in the countryside, the foothills,
wherever people can be found.
Our brothers and sisters
in La Trinité, Martinique,
send you
their warm Christian love and greetings.
From the World Headquarters
of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
this is JW Broadcasting!