Welcome to the June program
of JW Broadcasting.
As you likely remember,
Gilead graduations are now featured
as the monthly JW Broadcasting program
once every six months.
For this program,
we are excited to share with you
the first part of the graduation
of the 144th class of Gilead,
which took place on March 10, 2018.
This program features Scriptural talks
with intriguing themes.
We know you’ll enjoy
these thought-provoking discussions.
In coming weeks, be on the lookout
for Parts 2 and 3 of the Gilead graduation.
You’ll have an opportunity
to get to know some of the students better
during another heart-stirring episode
of The Inside Story.
But now, we invite you to enjoy Part 1
of the graduation
of the 144th class of Gilead.
You’ll see a picture on the monitors.
Take a look at it;
take a good look.
What’s the occasion?
I’ll give you a hint.
The picture was taken
75 years ago last month.
It’s a picture of the very first day
of the very first class of Gilead.
So 75 years ago last month
was the inception of Gilead.
Now, Gilead
—that’s an interesting word, isn’t it?
What does it mean?
Well, if you answer “Heap of Witness,”
it shows that you’re very familiar
with the 1984 edition
of the New World Translation.
The 2013 edition says “Witness Pile.”
Now, there can be a difference
between a heap and a pile.
Where I come from in Canada,
in the wintertime it gets very cold.
And to save on heating expenses,
many families heat with a woodstove.
And so you go to the backyard,
and you see
a very neat pile of wood stacked up.
They’re not careless about it.
In fact, some of them
are quite meticulous about their woodpile.
If you appreciate
the appearance of your home,
some of them are very artistic,
almost sculpted, these woodpiles.
And we’d never call it a heap
because with a heap you’d think of wood
that has just been carelessly strewn
right and left.
But no, this is a woodpile,
so something rather neat.
So why are we talking about a “Witness Pile”?
Well, what was it?
What was this “Heap of Witness”?
What was this “Witness Pile”
in the original meaning?
What purpose did it serve,
and why does it concern
you members of the graduating class?
It does.
In fact, it concerns all of us.
There’s a lesson that all of us can learn
from this “Witness Pile” called Gilead.
Let’s go to the origin,
back in Genesis chapter 31
—Genesis chapter 31.
Now, a little context:
The patriarch Jacob
was tired of being cheated
by his father-in-law, Laban.
And as we read the Scriptures,
we know that Laban
was kind of a shady character;
you wouldn’t want to buy
a used car from Laban.
And so Jacob got tired of being cheated,
and so he ran away
with his wives and his children.
Well, Laban ran after him.
And when he caught up with Jacob,
Laban and Jacob
made a covenant of peace.
Now, we’ll take up
the reading from verse 43.
So this is Genesis 31,
beginning with verse 43:
“Then Laban answered Jacob:
“‘The daughters are my daughters
“‘and the children my children
“‘and the flock my flock,
and everything you are looking at is mine.’”
It tells you what kind
of a person he was, doesn’t it?
Verse 44:
“‘Now come,
let us make a covenant, you and I,
“and it will serve
as a witness between us.’
“So Jacob took a stone
and set it up as a pillar.
“Then Jacob said to his brothers:
“‘Pick up stones!’
And they took stones and made a pile.”
And notice this:
“After that they ate there
on the pile of stones.”
So scholars tell us
that this “pile of stones”
must have been quite neatly arranged,
so that it would form a kind of a table,
and they had
their meal of peace on this table.
And, of course,
this was to serve as a monument.
It was to be a monument
of the covenant of peace
between Laban and Jacob.
Now, let’s carry on, verse 47:
“And Laban began calling it Jegar-sahadutha,
but Jacob called it Galeed.”
When the brothers
were picking a name for the school,
aren’t you glad
they didn’t go with Laban’s?
How would you students like to be graduates
of the Watchtower Bible School
of Jegar-sahadutha?
That would be a mouthful, wouldn’t it?
So they chose Galeed, or Gilead.
Verses 48 and 49:
“Laban then said:
“‘This pile of stones is a witness
“between me and you today.’
That is why he named it Galeed,
and the Watchtower.”
And isn’t it interesting
that both “Watchtower” and “Gilead”
are in the name of our school?
But what was the purpose
of the pile of rocks?
Verse 52:
“This pile of stones is a witness,
“and the pillar is something
that bears witness,
“that I will not pass
beyond this pile of stones
“to bring harm to you
“and you will not pass
beyond this pile of stones and this pillar
to bring harm to me.”
So this Gilead,
this “pile of stones,”
this “Witness Pile,”
was really a monument.
It was a symbol of peace and unity.
And anytime someone
would pass by that monument,
that “pile of stones,”
that “witness heap,” if you like,
they would be reminded of the need for unity.
Now, the unity between Laban and Jacob
didn’t come about automatically.
We read verse 43.
Did you notice
the accusations that Laban made
when he first encountered Jacob?
‘The daughters are mine;
‘the children are mine;
‘the flocks are mine;
everything you see is mine.’
Well, them were fighting words.
Jacob had worked very hard
for everything he got.
He’d worked for 14 years for his wives,
and Laban changed his wages ten times.
So Laban had no right
to say that it was all his,
and Jacob could have taken exception to it;
but he bit his tongue.
Why?
The goal was peace.
He wanted to make peace.
So Jacob took the high road.
Well, today, that name Gilead
is an appropriate name for our school.
And it reminds us of the blessed unity
that must pervade
through the organization today.
When you think of it,
Gilead has been a tremendous force
to unify God’s people.
As missionaries were sent
to the far corners of the earth,
they were supplicating people to come
into a peaceful relationship
with Jehovah God.
And as branches were formed,
the missionaries understood
how world headquarters worked,
and they helped to promote unity
between the branches
and world headquarters.
So the missionaries were agents of peace.
Now, of course, the focus of Gilead
is on strengthening the congregations,
strengthening the circuits,
strengthening the branches,
forging an unbreakable link
between the branches
and world headquarters.
And Gilead plays a part in all this.
We are “one flock,”
under “one shepherd.”
Don’t hurt any member of the flock.
Be a peacemaker.
If you want peace,
you have to work for it.
And sometimes to achieve it,
we have to bite our tongues.
Now, isn’t that a good lesson
that you members of the graduating class
and all of us can learn?
Because we all want to work
for the peace of Jerusalem;
we all want to work
for the peace of Jehovah’s organization.
Well, back to the first class of Gilead
—graduation day, June 23, 1943.
Wait a minute,
first day of class, February 1;
graduation day, June 23.
That wasn’t five months, was it?
But they had a lovely graduation day.
And the first to speak was a member
of what would later become
the Governing Body,
Brother W. E. Van Amburgh.
Well, today at the graduation
of the 144th class,
we have a member of the Governing Body
who will be first to speak,
not Brother Van Amburgh,
but Brother Anthony Morris.
And Tony is going to speak
to us on the subject
“Supplicate All the Time!”
You soon-to-be graduates
are very familiar with the fact
that in Scripture
there are different forms of prayer.
You have petition.
We petition Jehovah for various needs.
You have thanksgiving
—so much to thank him for.
And then, of course,
Jehovah always deserves praise,
so we have these prayers
we offer to praise him.
However,
I just want to implant in your minds,
as you get ready to graduate
and go to your assignments,
this matter of supplication.
It’s unique;
it’s just full of emotion
—earnest prayer.
And I think you understand that.
We want you to understand
why we’re suggesting
you should supplicate all the time
—all the time.
And take, for example, Christ Jesus.
He set the perfect example for us here.
And you’ll notice in Hebrews chapter 5
how priceless his perfect example was.
At least we try to reach for it.
But not just you soon-to-be graduates
but all of us
can benefit from this good counsel.
Now, notice Hebrews 5:7:
“During his life on earth,
Christ offered up supplications
“and also petitions,
with strong outcries and tears,
“to the One
who was able to save him out of death,
and he was favorably heard
for his godly fear.”
Now, did you notice, though,
that “supplications” is plural?
So, certainly he supplicated throughout
his three-and-a-half-year ministry.
But we can only imagine
the final weeks, days,
hours was with tears
—the supplication.
So this is the example for us,
and the closer we get to the end,
Jehovah wants us to imitate his Son.
In fact, Jesus made it very clear
how important this was.
And you’re aware of it,
but sometimes we get so busy
with the things
we’re dealing with that we can forget.
Notice what he commanded in Luke.
So find Luke,
and we’re going to look at the 21st chapter.
You’ll quickly remember it
—Luke chapter 21.
Now here, just to highlight a little bit
before we read verse 36,
you’ll notice in verse 34
that these are the things
we have to “pay attention to”
to avoid being “weighed down with overeating
and heavy drinking and anxieties of life,”
so that it doesn’t hit us like a snare.
Now notice verse 36:
“Keep awake, then,
“all the time making supplication
“that you may succeed
in escaping all these things
that must occur
and in standing before the Son of man.”
So this is what he said:
“All the time making supplication.”
Now, obviously,
it’s not going to be
something where if you’re driving a car,
you’re going to stop
and start supplicating on the road.
But the spirit of his counsel is,
‘Do you want to succeed like I succeeded?
You must supplicate all the time.’
It just has to be.
You can’t let a day go by
that you haven’t had supplication,
and the closer we get to the end,
the more important that is.
A lot of us need to focus on supplicating
—because it’s not what might occur,
it’s what will occur.
This is a reality.
So it’s very obvious,
and it’s understandable
that we will supplicate
when we or a loved one face a crisis,
something happens.
And then it’s just natural
to get that intense emotion in prayer,
and there could well be tears;
but it’s intense.
You’re just focused.
It’s just gripping you with the emotion
as you face different things.
So you may have
a life-threatening illness in the future;
you’ll start supplicating with that news.
If you have a loved one
and their life is threatened,
there’s going to be supplication.
But even though that’s appropriate
and Jehovah expects us to do that,
I just want to have you take back
with you on your assignments
something that you must supplicate about too.
And I have to take the same counsel.
It means a lot to Jehovah.
It’s very basic,
but look at Matthew chapter 6
—Matthew chapter 6.
And this is where Jesus
gave the example of prayer,
and it certainly extends to supplicating.
You’ll notice in verse 9 where he mentions:
“You must pray . . . this way:
“‘Our Father in the heavens,
let your name be sanctified.
“‘Let your Kingdom come.
Let your will take place,
as in heaven, also on earth.’”
So it’s Jehovah’s name.
You look at this wicked world,
and it’s getting worse.
The Bible foretold
it would go “from bad to worse,”
and it’s just so reproachful
to the holy name of God.
Everybody is in the face
of anything Scriptural.
And how terrible that is!
Supplicate about your concern
to Jehovah himself
—how that bothers you—
and that will touch him.
And it’s nice because it gets
your mind off yourself
(which is not always spiritually healthy)
and focused on Jehovah’s name,
because it’s his name and the Kingdom
that are going to rid the whole world
of all the problems anyway.
So it’s just something
we want you to take with you,
to supplicate about Jehovah’s name
and removing the reproach
and that his Kingdom come.
Do that often.
All the time, if you will.
Now just some final thoughts here
in a very familiar Psalm,
Psalm 83.
So if you’ll find Psalm 83 here.
And this connects with supplicating Jehovah
to have his will done
and his name vindicated
(as we say in English as well now),
cleared of the reproach.
I know you feel the same way I do.
I’m way over here.
I just—
It’s disgusting!
You’ve got to keep up
with some of the news,
but it’s almost like,
‘Let me stop!’
But you’ve got to know
a little something that’s going on.
And we have connections with our brothers
from all different parts of the earth;
things are coming up all the time.
There’s so much to supplicate about,
and the Kingdom
is going to finally put an end to all of it.
Now, what I thought you’d appreciate
if you look at the 83rd Psalm in context,
in the first five verses
(this is interesting),
it’s about those who hate Jehovah.
These arrogant enemies of Jehovah God
hate him and hate his people.
They’re cunning; they’re despicable.
Now, it’s quite fascinating that in verse 5,
see the “b” part of the verse:
“They have made an alliance against you.”
So this was an alliance of nations
coming against Jehovah’s name people
—an alliance.
What does that remind you of?
So by focusing on supplicating all the time,
you’re really getting yourself ready
for the great tribulation.
We call it a coalition of nations
—Gog’s attack.
It connects with what we see here
that happened in the past.
And these are beautiful thoughts here.
Notice verse 17 and verse 18
of the 83rd Psalm.
And this is from our heart.
We want to supplicate this to our Father:
“May they be put to shame
and be terrified forever;
“may they be disgraced and perish;
“may people know that you,
whose name is Jehovah,
you alone are the Most High
over all the earth.”
Ah! What a stirring supplication!
So with whatever you face,
you soon-to-be graduates,
in the future,
remember the Scriptural advice:
‘Supplicate all the time,’
and you are sure to succeed.
Beautifully done.
Thank you very much, Brother Morris.
Now, at the graduation
of the first class of Gilead,
the next to speak
was a responsible brother.
And we have a responsible brother
who is going to speak to us next,
Brother Hermanus van Selm.
He’s a helper to the Writing Committee,
and Brother van Selm is going to speak
to us on the interesting theme
“See and Be Jehovah’s Hand.”
Think for a moment
of your congregation back home.
Imagine that Jehovah observes
there a dear elderly sister
who has suffered
one painful setback after another.
As a result, she is heartbroken.
She even feels that Jehovah
doesn’t love her anymore.
But then through the working of his spirit,
Jehovah makes you aware of her situation.
You want to help your dear sister,
but you wonder:
‘How can I show her
that Jehovah is still reaching out to her?
‘How can I help her to see
Jehovah’s supporting hand
at work in her life?’
To answer,
let us consider a few verses
in the Bible book of Ruth,
which relates the touching story
of Naomi, Ruth, and Boaz.
As we remember,
Naomi’s husband had died.
Then her two sons got married,
but sadly,
both of them also died.
Those blows caused Naomi
to sink deeper and deeper into despair.
She even felt
that Jehovah had abandoned her.
Note at chapter 1, verse 13,
at the end of the verse,
note what Naomi said:
“The hand of Jehovah
has turned against me.”
Verse 20, at the end of the verse:
“The Almighty has made
my life very bitter for me.”
Verse 21,
at the end of the verse:
“Jehovah who opposed me
and the Almighty who caused me calamity.”
Now, these were strong statements,
but, of course,
none of them were true.
Jehovah had not turned against her.
Jehovah had not caused her calamity.
So how did Jehovah react
to Naomi’s bitter words?
Well, he did not send
fire from heaven to punish her.
He did not send
a prophet to reprove her.
Instead,
he used Ruth and Boaz
to reach out to Naomi
and pull her gently out of her despair.
In a sense,
Jehovah gave Ruth and Boaz
the privilege to serve as His hand
—that is, the means
through which He could provide
support to Naomi.
In this class,
we have 22 Ruth-like sisters
and 27 Boaz-like brothers.
Also, there are thousands
of Ruths and Boazes in this audience.
So how can we be Jehovah’s hand?
And how can we help
the Naomis in our congregation
to see Jehovah’s hand at work in their life?
To answer,
we will consider five steps
mentioned in the book of Ruth
that we could follow to help
our fellow worshippers who are in need.
Step number one:
Have the right motivation.
Since helping those in need
takes great effort,
we have to be motivated by love.
But it needs to be a special kind of love.
What do we mean?
Well, love is a bit like coffee.
Coffee?
In what way?
Well, coffee comes in different types,
such as cappuccino, caffe latte, caffe mocha
—mmm.
Similarly, love comes in different types,
such as love for family,
brotherly love, principled love.
But the love considered in the book of Ruth
is yet of a different type.
What is it?
It is mentioned at chapter 1, verse 8:
“Naomi said to both of her daughters-in-law:
“‘Go, return,
each of you to your mother’s home.
“‘May Jehovah show loyal love to you,
just as you have shown it to the men
who have died and to me.’”
“Loyal love.”
What kind of love is that?
It’s a very strong kind of love.
It’s a bit like a double espresso, undiluted.
It gives you a real boost that helps you
to attach yourself to a brother in need
and to cling to him until you
have pulled him out of his despair.
Now, that’s the type of love
we show to our brothers and sisters in need.
Step number two:
Be persistent.
When Ruth offered
her helping hand to Naomi,
Naomi first refused to accept it.
But Ruth, motivated by loyal love,
did not take no for an answer.
What was the result?
Chapter 1, verse 18:
“When Naomi saw
that Ruth insisted on going with her,
she stopped trying to convince her.”
Similarly today,
a sister in despair
may first refuse to accept our help.
Even so, loyal love
will move us to cling to that sister,
hoping that she will eventually accept
our hand of friendship.
Step number three:
Don’t take it personally.
When Naomi and Ruth
arrived in Bethlehem,
Naomi met her former neighbors.
What did she tell them?
Chapter 1, verse 21:
“I was full when I went,
but Jehovah made me return empty-handed.”
What did she tell them?
Now, put yourself in the place of Ruth.
She had gone out of her way to help Naomi.
She cried with her, she comforted her,
she walked with her for days on end.
And then,
with Ruth standing next to her,
Naomi said,
‘I returned empty-handed.’
She did not even acknowledge
the presence of Ruth.
How painful that must have been
for our dear Ruth.
Yet, Ruth stuck with Naomi.
Likewise today, a brother or sister,
because of their bitter feelings of despair,
may speak to us or treat us in a hurtful way
in spite of all of our efforts to help them.
But we try not to take it personally.
We stick with our sister in need
and pray to Jehovah:
“Please, open the sister’s eyes.
Let her see your outstretched hand.”
Step number four:
Give practical help.
Ruth realized that Naomi’s depression
prevented her from taking the initiative.
So, what did Ruth do?
Chapter 2, verse 2:
“Ruth . . . said to Naomi:
“‘Let me go out, please,
“‘to the fields
and glean among the ears of grain
behind whoever
looks on me with favor.’”
Now, today, we also realize
that the brother in despair
may lack the energy
to take any initiative to help himself.
So loyal love for our brother moves us
to take the first step
in giving him practical help
in and around his house.
Step number five:
Get encouragement.
Ruth badly needed encouragement,
and Jehovah moved Boaz to give it to her.
Look at chapter 2, verse 12.
Boaz said to Ruth:
“May Jehovah reward you
for what you have done,
“and may there be
a perfect wage for you
“from Jehovah the God of Israel,
under whose wings
you have come to seek refuge.”
Now, after Ruth had been hearing
negative talk for so long,
those heartwarming words of Boaz
deeply touched her.
In response, in the middle of verse 13
we read that Ruth said to Boaz:
“You have comforted me
and [you have] spoken reassuringly
to your servant.”
The kind and timely words of Boaz
gave Ruth the strength
she needed to carry on.
Today,
the kind words of a caring elder
will have the same uplifting effect
on those who give their all
in helping brothers and sisters in need.
If we follow these five steps,
Jehovah may give us
the privilege of being his hand.
With what result?
Consider what happened next to Naomi.
The Bible account continues
by telling that Boaz provided
a generous gift of food
for Ruth and Naomi.
What was Naomi’s reaction
to Boaz’s generosity?
Chapter 2, verse 20:
“At that Naomi said
to her daughter-in-law:
“‘May he be blessed by Jehovah,
“‘who has not failed in his loyal love
toward the living and the dead.’”
Now,
what a turning point this was for Naomi.
Earlier she had cried out in pain,
‘Jehovah caused me calamity.’
But then she exclaimed with joy,
‘Jehovah has not failed in his loyal love!’
Finally,
Naomi was able to connect the dots
and realize that when Ruth had said to her,
‘I will stick with you;
I will glean with you,’
Ruth was acting as Jehovah’s hand.
And then Boaz had gone
far beyond what was required
in caring for her and Ruth.
Boaz had acted as Jehovah’s hand.
‘Ahh, now I understand,’
Naomi must have thought.
‘Jehovah never left me.
‘He has been with me all the time.
‘I’m so grateful to Ruth and Boaz
that they helped me
to see Jehovah’s supporting hands.’
No doubt all three of them rejoiced
over the decisive turning point
they had reached.
In summary,
what gave Ruth and Boaz
the strength to pull Naomi
out of her despair?
Loyal love.
A strong kind of love that we give,
not to people in general,
but to our brothers and sisters,
especially those who are in need.
What was the result?
Boaz and Ruth had the joy
of seeing how Naomi
regained her spiritual balance.
Today,
we may experience the same deep joy
when we are able to help
our brothers and sisters in need,
to see Jehovah’s hand
and thus regain their spiritual strength.
Therefore,
our dear Ruth-like sisters
and Boaz-like brothers
of class 144,
it is our heartfelt prayer
that the precious education
that you received at Gilead
may help you more than ever
to see and to be Jehovah’s hand.
Well, that was better
than a double espresso, wasn’t it?
Now we’re going to have a helper
to the Teaching Committee to talk to us,
and he has the interesting theme
“Be the Keel”
—K-E-E-L.
So we’ll listen with interest.
Like a sailboat in the open sea,
you could be sailing along
—enjoying life, enjoying your view—
but then suddenly and unexpectedly
a turbulent storm, a trialsome situation,
could be confronting you.
That could really rock your boat.
How true are the words
found in The Watchtower
of the March 1, 1896, issue
where it stated:
“The Christian course of self-sacrifice
“cannot be one of ease
and continuous smooth-sailing and peace.
“There may be a calm now and then,
but storms and battles are the rule.”
Now, if that was the case 122 years ago,
way before all of us were alive,
how much more so is that the rule,
or the case, today.
Life in Satan’s system
is anything but smooth sailing.
How can you students
help others endure present storms
and prepare them for future tests
—future storms?
Be the keel.
What does that mean?
The keel is a heavily-weighted fin
attached to the bottom of a sailboat.
So when strong, gusting winds fill the sail
and the vessel leans on its side,
the keel serves as the ballast
—the counterweight.
It provides stability.
It prevents the sailboat
from blowing sideways
and from capsizing, or keeling over.
Our brothers and sisters,
now more than ever,
need to be strengthened.
They need to be stabilized
so that they can face
storms of anxiety, natural disasters,
and wave after wave
of ridicule and persecution.
That’s the focus of Gilead School
—to strengthen and stabilize
qualified men and women like you
so that you, in turn, can strengthen
and stabilize Jehovah’s organization.
Empowered with Jehovah’s spirit,
you can be like those strengthening aids
in the first century
who proved to be someone
who could stabilize
their brothers and sisters.
And there are many examples.
But let’s look at Acts 18:24,
and let’s see why the man Apollos
is someone who we want to follow.
There in Acts chapter 18,
let’s read together verse 24.
And there it reads:
“Now a Jew named Apollos,
a native of Alexandria,
“arrived in Ephesus;
“[and notice] he was an eloquent man
who was well-versed in the Scriptures.
This man had been instructed
in the way of Jehovah,”
and notice that he was
“aglow with the spirit,”
which caused him
to speak and teach accurately
about the things of Jesus.
“But he was acquainted
only with the baptism of John.
“He began to speak boldly in the synagogue,
“and when Priscilla and Aquila heard him,
“[What did they do?]
“they took him into their company
and explained the way of God
more accurately to him.”
Well, what outstanding qualities Apollos had
—qualities that you students have as well!
Now, Apollos had his strengths;
but like all of us,
he also had his weaknesses
and he knew
that he needed to humbly get more help,
more understanding.
So how thankful we are, and he was,
that Aquila and Priscilla filled in the gaps
—helped him to appreciate
the deeper things of Jehovah
so that he could speak more accurately.
Yes, this well-grounded,
spiritually mature couple
also helped Apollos learn life lessons.
Like what?
Like working as a team
—working in unity.
They also taught him life lessons
about going the extra mile
in helping those who needed help spiritually
as well as materially;
what it means to be generous,
to be hospitable;
and also the key that humility is needed
in order to support others,
so that we’re content in our assignment.
Like Apollos, you accepted
the invitation to come to Gilead
to receive extra schooling
to have a deeper understanding
of God’s Word, the Bible.
And along the way,
you learned vital life lessons
from this Bethel family,
who are supporting you.
You learned what it means
to go the extra mile
—to be hospitable,
generous, kind, and patient.
You also learned what it means
to be a giver and not simply a taker.
You will soon graduate.
You will have a diploma in your hand.
Is that it?
You walk away and that’s it?
That’s all for your instruction?
Of course not.
We know Jehovah promises
that he will continue
to give you instruction.
In fact, at 1 Peter chapter 5,
notice verse 10.
There at 1 Peter 5:10,
Jehovah promises
that he will “finish your training.”
Well, how will he finish your training?
It goes on to say
that his continued training
“will make you firm,”
it “will make you strong,”
and “he will firmly ground you.”
So just as a keel
is filled with heavy weight
to keep the boat stable and upright,
so too Jehovah promises
to give you his powerful holy spirit
so that you
can be strengthened and stabilized
and help others to do the same
—to be firmly grounded.
Now, because Apollos was humble
and he accepted the help,
he put himself in a position
to be used mightily by Jehovah
and by his organization.
Now, what did he do to greatly help
the congregations back then?
Notice Acts 18:27.
There at Acts 18:27,
Apollos not only helped
the congregation in Achaia
but it says
that “he greatly helped” them.
And it went on to say
in another translation of this verse
that “he powerfully reinforced” them.
So he was really someone
who took the training
and really made it happen.
In fact, if you look at verse 28,
he set an example of someone
who should be zealous in the ministry.
He used the Scriptures
that he had at the time,
and he used these as his authority.
And how did he speak?
Verse 28 says “with great intensity.”
So we could say
that basically Apollos
was a keel with zeal.
And we look forward to seeing
how you will use your Gilead training
to greatly help others in your assignments
and doing so with great intensity.
Now, when you look at a sailboat,
what’s the first thing that you normally see?
Isn’t it the sail?
Why?
Because it’s the most prominent,
outstanding thing on a sailboat.
Now, the keel,
on the other hand, is unseen.
It’s below the water,
below the boat, but there it is.
It’s doing its job.
It’s keeping that sailboat upright,
supported, and stabilized.
Now, you could hardly imagine
Apollos thinking to himself:
‘I know that my assignment as a keel
‘—as a support, as a stabilizer—
‘is important, but I don’t think
I’m being tapped into my true potential.
‘I don’t think the brothers
can really see me down here,
‘doing all that I’m supposed to do.
‘Yes, I know that I’m not an apostle.
‘I’m not being used
to write inspired letters,
‘although I would be a logical choice.
‘If only, if only, I could have
a more elevated, higher position,
‘maybe like the sail.
‘If I was the sail, everyone could see me
‘and I could get more airtime.
‘And then everyone could hear me
and my words that are so eloquent.’
Well, we know that that’s ridiculous.
He never thought that,
and he never acted that way toward others.
The Bible only reveals just a fraction
of all that Apollos said and that he did.
But what we do know
is that the most outstanding
and most prominent thing about Apollos
was his humility.
He was willing, humble,
to do anything
wherever he was sent to go.
He never allowed his strengths
to become weaknesses.
Likewise,
much of what you, Gilead students,
will do in the future
will be unseen by others.
But you know
that Jehovah sees everything you do
and all the work and the stabilizing you do
in behalf of his precious sheep.
You students have many gifts,
many strengths, many abilities.
But your humility must exceed
any gifts or strengths that you have;
never allow your strengths
to become your weakness.
Remember,
ability without humility is a liability,
but ability with humility is stability.
And that’s the key to a keel.
And no doubt
when you look back at your life,
there were many
that served as a keel for you.
They were the ones
who stabilized you, balanced you,
when you needed it most.
When you were going
through turbulent storms in your life,
they were there for you.
Who was your Apollos?
Who was your Aquila? your Pricilla?
Remember all that they said and did for you,
and remember that you can be
that person for someone else.
They can help you to be balanced,
stable, even-keeled.
Now it’s your turn.
Take your Gilead training
and greatly help your brothers and sisters.
Love them, support them,
strengthen them, stabilize them.
Be the keel.
By the way, I forgot to mention
that was Ron Curzan,
in case you didn’t know.
So we appreciate
that spiritual sailing lesson.
Now, at the first graduation in 1943,
there were four Gilead instructors
who gave parting words to the class.
Three of them
—three instructors,
not the original instructors—
three instructors are going
to be on the program today.
And so the first one is Brother Jim Cauthon,
and he’s going to speak on the subject
“Pause and Reset.”
There are two things that I know about you
and two things that you know about me.
The first is we want to serve Jehovah,
and we want to do so acceptably.
And the second is we want to be happy.
Wouldn’t you agree?
Now, to the first point,
there’s not much of a problem
because you’ve had five months of study now.
You’ve been through the Bible.
You know what Jehovah expects
—what he wants—
and you’re prepared to do it.
But, now, as to the second point,
that can be a little bit more challenging.
Why do I say that?
Well, happiness can be tricky.
We all know people who by all standards
should seem to be happy, but they’re not.
On the other hand, we know people who face
many, many difficult challenges every day,
but they just seem to radiate happiness.
We quickly realize that happiness
is not dependent
on things, on circumstances,
or even on people.
Why is that?
It’s because true happiness
is not an end goal;
it is a by-product.
But a by-product of what?
Well, the answer to that question
lies back in time.
Open your Bibles, if you would,
to Deuteronomy chapter 16.
And here, discussing one
of the three annual festivals
that Jehovah required
the Israelites to attend,
in verse 15 he gave these words.
He said: “Seven days you will celebrate
the festival to Jehovah your God
“in the place that Jehovah chooses,
“for Jehovah your God will bless
all your produce and all that you do,
and you will become nothing but joyful.”
Now, did you notice Jehovah’s words there?
“You will become nothing but joyful.”
You see, being joyful
as a worshipper of Jehovah
was not an option.
He actually made it an act of worship.
But why?
It’s because imperfect humans
can lose their appreciation
for things that become
a routine part of life,
even if these things are a reflection
of Jehovah’s loving concern.
So, what was it about these festivals
that would cause all who attended them
to “become nothing but joyful”?
Well, each festival was to be a time
when the Israelites
stopped what they were doing.
In other words, they would pause,
and they would go up to Jerusalem
to reflect on the blessings
that they had received from Jehovah
and that they were receiving.
In other words, they would reset.
What effect did this pause and reset
have on the Israelites?
One word
—gratitude.
You know what happens
when we feel gratitude?
Happiness always follows.
You remember Jehovah’s words:
“You will become nothing but joyful,”
and Jehovah knows that happiness
is a by-product of gratitude.
Now, how does this ancient example
help us today?
Well, life in this old system
is filled with hardships.
Ahead of you
will be challenges, uncertainties,
“time and unforeseen occurrence.”
And really, that’s true for all of us.
Jehovah knows this,
but he also knows
that it is precisely during times of crisis
that we have the most to gain
by having a grateful perspective.
Gratitude reminds us that our Creator
loves us and that he cares about us.
It reminds us that God’s goodness exists
even in the worst that life has to offer.
Gratitude doesn’t cure suffering,
but it has the power to heal.
Gratitude doesn’t erase despair,
but it has the power to radiate hope.
Gratitude nullifies negativity.
“The joy of Jehovah
[becomes our] stronghold.”
But it’s up to us.
Because gratitude
is more than just a feeling,
brothers and sisters;
it’s a mind-set, it’s a disposition,
and it’s a choice.
Why do we say a choice?
It’s because we can make a conscious decision
to see blessings instead of curses.
Jehovah is called “the happy God,”
and he gives us the recipe to be happy too.
That recipe is found, in part,
in Psalm 143.
Let’s turn there,
Psalm 143:5.
David, the psalmist, said this;
he said: “I remember the days of old;
“I meditate on all your activity;
I eagerly ponder
over the works of your hands.”
What’s the point?
The psalmist is basically telling us
that from time to time
we have to stop
and press the pause button.
We need to take time to look around.
Jehovah has bejeweled
our world with daily reminders
of his goodness, his power,
but most of all, his love for us.
All we have to do is take the time to look.
We are immersed in the goodness of God,
so pause from time to time.
Take a moment to appreciate
what God is giving you each day.
Contemplate the abundance
and the diversity of life.
Ponder, muse, meditate
on all the works of the true God.
Drink in the awesomeness of the universe
on a starry night.
No two sunrises and no two sunsets
are ever exactly alike.
Look up to the clouds.
What you see is ever changing.
There was nothing exactly like it before,
nor will there ever be again.
The feeling you will experience
is a refreshment of the soul;
it’s a reset.
Eyes see only light,
and ears hear only sound;
but a grateful heart perceives meaning.
We perceive
that Jehovah created all these things
as a gift for us.
That’s right; each day
was to be a very special gift,
unique unto itself.
Why?
To make endless life not just special
but amazing, wondrous, and always a joy.
Connecting with Jehovah’s creation
helps to discharge anxiety.
It shifts our attention
to something safe, something enduring,
something outside ourselves.
It helps us to accept life’s uncertainties
by reassuring us
that we are a part of something larger,
something everlasting,
something immensely important.
Yes, we are a part of God’s purpose.
Gratitude is important
not only because it helps us feel good
but because it inspires us to do good.
A grateful spirit will make you more loving,
more forgiving,
more feeling, more thoughtful.
Thankfulness is a soil in which joy thrives.
So open your hearts
to the blessings around you.
Let gratefulness flow
from the inside out to others.
You too “will become nothing but joyful,”
and that joy will show in your smile,
in your eyes, in your touch,
and in your words.
Why?
Because gratitude
is the ability to experience life,
not as a test, but as a gift.
It will impact every relationship
that you have
—your family,
your marriage, your work,
even your ministry.
You’ll be in a much better position to make
a real difference in the lives of others.
It will liberate you
from the prison of self-preoccupation,
and it will replace a critical spirit
with a sense of appreciation.
So pause regularly
to reflect on what Jehovah has given you.
Give the digital world a break.
Take a walk outside, and don’t just look
—pause and perceive.
Try to count all the blessings
that you receive each day,
and you will find it easier to cope
with the trials and the stresses of life.
We are never
more than one grateful thought away
from increased peace of mind
and greater peace of heart.
Just remember, pause and reflect.
I think we all agree that we needed that.
We appreciate that effective presentation.
Now, the second
of our instructors to speak today
is Brother Mark Noumair.
And he’s going to talk on the subject
“The Unsung Legacy.”
Legacy.
The word carries the thought
of passing on something of value
to those that come after you.
But what is an unsung legacy?
It’s a legacy that’s unknown.
So if no one knows about you,
how can you pass on
anything of value to them?
Can you influence others
if your work is behind the scenes?
Yes.
The Kenites did.
They’re not included
in the “cloud of witnesses”
in Hebrews chapter 11.
Yet the value of their faith,
what they’ve passed on to you,
is worth meditating on.
They never enjoyed the spotlight.
Yet, in Jehovah’s eyes,
they are so precious and unforgettable.
Let’s do some digging
and unearth the legacy of the Kenites.
And we want you to learn valuable lessons,
especially lessons that will help you
search your hearts and motives.
The first Kenite mentioned in the Bible
is Jethro, Moses’ father-in-law.
When hearing that Jehovah
freed the Israelites from Egypt,
notice what Jethro said here
—his response—
at Exodus 18:11.
Jethro says: “Now I know
“that Jehovah
is greater than all the other gods,
“because of what he did
to those who acted arrogantly
against his people.”
These are Jethro’s words.
And now in verse 12,
what he did was offer up sacrifices
to Jehovah God.
You see
—this Jethro, this Kenite—
he recognized that Jehovah God
was directing the nation of Israel,
and he recognized
that he was to help Moses.
Jehovah God was using Moses.
Moses had been given this exhausting job
of directing some three million people.
So Jethro said, ‘How can I assist?’
He wanted to support Moses
—support.
So he assisted Moses
to reach a God-approved solution.
‘Select capable, trustworthy men, Moses,
‘and appoint them as chiefs
over hundreds and fifties and tens’
and so forth.
Them, not me
—them.
You see, Jethro was not looking
for a position for himself.
He simply gave advice
to be of support to Moses.
Why?
So that Moses could continue
to do Jehovah God’s work.
He wanted to be involved in helping.
He saw Jehovah’s blessing on Moses.
He didn’t criticize.
Jethro didn’t sit back and say:
‘You’re not even a fluent speaker.
‘Who do you think you are,
trying to manage three million people?
I knew you as a shepherd boy,
back with me.’
He didn’t do that.
He said, ‘I want to assist.’
So the support of this Kenite
proved to be invaluable
not just to Moses
but ultimately for the entire nation
that was chosen by God.
So this is your first big lesson.
Like Jethro,
look for ways to support
and to be selfless.
Don’t look for position.
Positions come and go,
but your value to Jehovah God will not.
That’s what Jehovah is looking for.
He loves your faithful service, not position.
And rather than criticize others, help.
Help your brother succeed at their work.
Let them take the credit.
Drain the venom of position
and human recognition from your mind.
Jesus said,
“If I glorify myself, my glory is nothing.”
So prove to yourself
and prove to Jehovah God
that you are more
for the Kingdom than for the glory.
That’s Jethro.
But the legacy of the Kenites continues.
Jethro had a son, Hobab.
Hobab was Moses’ brother-in-law.
So when the time now came for the Israelites
to travel toward the Promised Land,
Moses requested something from Hobab.
And that’s found at Numbers chapter 10
—Numbers 10:31.
Now, at this Moses
says to Hobab, in verse 31:
“Please do not leave us,
“for you know where we
should camp in the wilderness,
and you can serve as our guide.”
As the footnote says, our “eyes.”
You see, Moses wanted Hobab to come.
Why?
He was familiar with the terrain;
he knew where to find water;
he knew where to find pasturage.
Hobab saw the big picture.
Hobab, come with us;
serve as our “eyes.”
Use your knowledge;
use your experience
as a scout for the nation.
We need your experience.
Hobab could have stayed home.
Why go?
‘I have a family; I have my friends;
I have a comfortable life.
‘Why should I throw my lot
in with some three million people?
I have no idea
what’s going to happen to you.’
But he went.
Hobab,
with no apparent reward for himself,
used his experience to guide the nation
as they traveled toward the Promised Land.
Now, what does this mean for you?
It means something big.
During the past five months,
you have become familiar
with this spiritual terrain
of the 66 books of the Bible.
You’ve been given the big picture.
You got it from Genesis to Revelation
—history lessons,
geography lessons, archaeology lessons,
lesson after lesson, day after day,
written review after written review.
You got it.
Use your experience now.
Use that knowledge
—to do what?
To serve as a guide for others.
For example,
when someone faces a crisis of faith,
they might find it difficult
to travel this unfamiliar terrain.
It could be challenging for them.
Show them from God’s Word
where they can find spiritual water.
Where can they get refreshment?
Where can they get the energy?
Help them travel that terrain.
You owe it to them.
You have been given a beautiful view,
while being here at school,
of the organization
—a unique vista of God’s organization
that many will never see.
You will go back to your assignments,
and many will never experience
what you’ve been able to experience.
Share with them
your memories, your experience.
Strengthen their confidence
in Jehovah God’s organization.
Don’t be stingy
by holding your knowledge hostage.
Train two to become better than you.
Then, they train two,
and then they train two,
and they train two.
Imagine, if you adopt and embrace
this healthy mind-set,
you will help forge a path
toward a strong and unified organization.
That’s your responsibility.
So now we have two
—two generations of Kenites
who loyally supported
Jehovah God and his people.
A legacy had begun.
Would it continue?
Well, let’s jump ahead
to the time of the kings.
We have 1 Chronicles 2:55
that identifies another Kenite named Rechab,
and his son was Jehonadab.
Jehonadab lived
during the time period of King Jehu,
when Jehovah God commissioned Jehu
to go wipe out Baal worship.
And then Jehonadab comes out.
He meets Jehu.
Imagine, he wants to meet him;
he wants to support Jehu.
At 2 Kings 10:15, what did Jehu say?
‘Jehonadab, is your heart with me?’
‘It is, my heart is with you.’
‘Then get up into this chariot.’
He pulled him up in.
Wonderful!
Jehonadab wanted to support [Jehu].
It was a privilege
for Jehonadab to come out publicly
and show his loyalty
for Jehu’s God-given commission
—a privilege.
I’m going to be with you.
When Jehonadab accepted Jehu’s hand,
imagine, he stepped into that chariot.
He didn’t get underneath.
He stood up.
He was proud to be a part of that process.
He in effect was saying:
“Jehu, I’m sticking with you.
“I’ll do whatever you need.
“It doesn’t matter what the job is.
I’m with you.”
Like Jehonadab,
be determined to accept the privilege
of loyally supporting the decisions
made by God’s visible organization.
Support those decisions today, tomorrow,
next week, next month, next year.
Who knows?
But you’re going to be
a part of this, and it’s big.
You know, from a human standpoint
the Kenites had no royal lineage,
no notable accomplishments, no home.
There’s no country of Kenite.
They’re easy to miss and overlook.
Unsung as a people
but not unseen by Jehovah.
Jehovah saw these faithful Kenites
and all they had done for his people,
and he never forgot them.
Jehovah didn’t forget them; he loved them.
How do we know?
Well, again, 1 Chronicles 2:55 says
that they are part of the genealogy of Judah.
They’re tacked on at the end.
Jehovah said, ‘Welcome to the family.’
Beautiful!
First Samuel 15:6 shows
that Jehovah protected them
when Saul was going
against the Amalekites.
And the Kenites,
get out of the way.
Because of your loyal love,
move out of the way
so that you don’t get hurt.
And he rewarded them.
In Jeremiah’s day,
he concluded a covenant
with Jehonadab’s descendants,
the Rechabites,
because of their enduring loyalty
for decades.
Jehovah declared at Jeremiah 35:19:
“There will never fail to be
a descendant of Jehonadab
the son of Rechab [ever]
to serve in my presence.”
Jehovah respected
the loyal endurance of these Rechabites.
He promised that they would survive
the destruction of Jerusalem in 607 B.C.E.
“There will never fail to be a descendant
. . . in my presence.”
Perhaps, just perhaps,
there were descendants
of the Kenites in Jesus’ time
that later became his disciples
and are in heaven right now.
Now, we can’t say for a certainty,
we don’t know.
But we would not be surprised.
This is a valuable lesson for you.
If you’re in a land
where our work is restricted
or an area where few know
the work you are doing,
you might feel alone
without an army of support.
Be assured that Jehovah’s eyes
are on your enduring loyalty,
and he so deeply appreciates
your faithfulness.
You see, like the Kenites,
your work
—it might not be in the spotlight.
At times, you might feel
overlooked, unacknowledged,
maybe unsung by humans.
But, again, never unseen by Jehovah.
And just as Jehovah did with the Kenites,
know that your heavenly Father
cherishes and treasures everything you do
and will never forget your faithful service.
The Kenites teach us what we need to do,
what you and I,
what we need to do
to be approved by Jehovah.
It’s so precious.
What do we need to do?
Nothing spectacular, just be faithful.
It’s not about fanfare.
It’s silent resilience.
The legacy of the Kenites is now yours.
What will you do with it?
Be a Jethro.
Prove that you love
the Kingdom and your brothers
more than your position.
Be a Hobab.
Use your experience
to help your brothers find refreshment,
bolstering their spiritual energy
to climb those difficult terrains.
And be a Jehonadab.
Show your loyal support
—your loyalty
for Jehovah and his organization
by saying,
“I’ll do whatever you need
for however long.”
The job doesn’t matter.
By imitating the Kenites,
their example will live on in you
and their unsung loyal support
will remain unforgettable.
Well, we appreciate
that wise counsel very much.
What a riveting
and faith-strengthening program!
Before we conclude,
we’d like to share
these greetings from Bulgaria.
Bulgaria is a beautiful mountainous country
in southeastern Europe.
Individual farms
are still an important part of life.
Many people still vint their own wine,
can their own fruits and vegetables,
and chop their own firewood
to prepare for the cold winters.
In late 1989, when the upheaval
of Communism shook Bulgaria,
there were less than 50 publishers
in the entire country.
In 1991,
the first Gilead-trained missionaries
were assigned there.
Today, Bulgaria has some 2,500 publishers.
Let’s visit the congregation in Vratsa,
a town where houses are built
right up to the steep mountain cliffs.
The dramatic rock formations,
waterfalls, and caves
attract many tourists.
The Vratsa Congregation has 43 publishers,
of which 5 serve as elders.
The publishers conduct on average
80 Bible studies each month.
Witnesses from other European countries
have moved there
to help in the ministry.
The congregation has 14 regular pioneers,
2 special pioneers, and 2 missionaries.
In the recent past,
the brothers and sisters in Vratsa
could be issued a fine
just for participating in the preaching work,
and some were harassed by the police.
But in October 2017,
the congregation rejoiced when a local court
ruled that limiting
our preaching work is unconstitutional.
We keep our brothers and sisters
in Bulgaria in our prayers.
We love them very much!
From the world headquarters
of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
this is JW Broadcasting.