I’d like to talk to you
on the theme “Do the Math.”
Yes, you heard right: “Do the Math.”
Now, math may not be your favorite subject,
but as we’re going to see,
someone has to do it.
Sometimes doing the math
is the only way we can make a time line
or get interesting background information
that makes our Bible reading more enjoyable.
And you do want to make
your Bible reading more enjoyable, don’t you?
Of course you do!
Well, let’s start with a number
we might quickly skip over
in our Bible reading.
Let’s turn to Matthew 19:28,
and let’s see how a number
can sometimes tell us
more than what’s written on the page.
Matthew 19:28:
“Jesus said to them: ‘Truly I say to you,
“‘in the re-creation,
“‘when the Son of man
sits down on his glorious throne,
“‘you who have followed me
will sit on 12 thrones,
judging the 12 tribes of Israel.’”
Did you see anything interesting there?
I’ll give you a hint:
These words were spoken near the end
of Jesus’ earthly ministry.
Does that give you a hint?
I’ll give you another hint: the number 12.
At this point, Jesus knew
that only 11 of his apostles
were going to be faithful.
Yet, he said there would be
12 thrones in the Kingdom, not 11.
What did it mean?
It meant that Judas
would have to be replaced as an apostle.
And sure enough, he was.
Well, that was easy, wasn’t it?
There was no math involved.
It was just a number.
But, let’s see how doing the math
can help us to answer a few questions.
During family worship, one of the kids asks
whether Noah and Abraham knew each other.
How are you going to handle that?
Do you know?
You might just say,
“The Bible doesn’t say” and leave it at that.
But you could figure it out
if you did the math.
Now, here’s what we know:
The Flood occurred in 2370 B.C.E.
Now, that date is absolutely solid.
And if you’d like
to figure it out for yourself,
you can look it up under “Chronology”
in the Insight book—2370 B.C.E.
That’s the Flood.
And Noah lived for 350 years after the Flood.
So by subtracting 350 from 2370,
we learn that Noah died in 2020 B.C.E.
But remember the question?
The question is,
Did Noah and Abram know each other?
Abram entered the land of Canaan
in 1943 B.C.E.
Now, once again,
if you want to prove that to yourself,
look in Insight under “Chronology.”
You’ll find everything
you need to prove it to yourself.
So in 1943 B.C.E., Abraham
(Abram in that case)
enters the land of Canaan
and he’s 75 years old at the time.
So Abram must have been born
75 years before 1943 B.C.E.
Add 75 to 1943,
and you find that Abram was born
in 2018 B.C.E.
So Noah died in 2020 B.C.E.,
and Abram was born
two years later, in 2018 B.C.E.
They never knew each other, but it was close.
Our publications have often said
that Jonathan was
at least 30 years older than David.
But the Bible doesn’t say that.
Your progressive Bible student
(you know, the one
who makes you prove everything)
asks you about that.
Can you prove it?
Can you?
You can if you do the math.
King Saul ruled Israel for 40 years.
Then David became king.
Now, how old was David
when he became king?
The Bible says that he “was 30 years old.”
That means that when David was born,
Saul had already been ruling
Israel for ten years.
But when Saul became king,
Jonathan was a grown man.
He was probably already in the army.
You had to be
at least 20 years old to be in the army.
So if Jonathan was at least 20
when Saul began to rule
and David was born 10 years after that,
what difference in age would there have been
between Jonathan and David?
About a 30-year difference
—20 plus 10 equals 30.
Now, the next one
is a bit more complicated;
it’s the last one.
And we can do this.
Insight on the Scriptures says
that Moses and Job lived at the same time.
But the Bible doesn’t say that.
How can we be so sure?
Once again, what do we do?
Do I hear it?
You’re right; we do the math.
Job’s test must have occurred
sometime after the death of Joseph.
We know that because in Job chapter 1,
Jehovah told Satan:
“There is no one like [Job] on the earth.”
“No one.”
Now, if Joseph had still been alive,
Jehovah would have said that there was
no one like Joseph and Job on the earth.
And if the test had occurred earlier,
Jehovah would have said
that there was no one like Jacob and Job,
Isaac and Job, Abraham and Job.
And remember, there were
only two years between Noah and Abraham,
so we can conclude that the test of Job
occurred after the death of Joseph.
When did Joseph die?
The date is solid.
It’s 1657 B.C.E.
How do we figure that?
If you don’t like math, trust me,
you don’t want to know!
But Insight and the Bible will give you
all the information you need
to figure it out for yourself.
But let’s keep it simple.
Let’s go with 1657 B.C.E.
That’s 144 years before Israel left Egypt
under the direction of Moses in 1513 B.C.E.
So Job’s test must have occurred
sometime within that 144-year period.
Now this is a big hint:
144 years before Israel left Egypt.
Are you beginning to put it together?
Here is the clincher:
Job lived for 140 years
after he passed the test,
so he was probably still alive
in the land of Uz
when Israel left Egypt.
Conclusion: Job and Moses
definitely lived at the same time.
So, what have we learned by doing the math?
Superficially, we might say:
“Well, we’ve learned that Abraham
was born two years after Noah.
“And we’ve proved that Jonathan
was at least 30 years older than David
and that Moses and Job
definitely lived at the same time.”
Superficially, we got the answers
to those questions, yes.
But the fact is
that probably none
of those questions ever kept you up at night.
There’s a broader picture here.
What we’d like you to take away
is the fact that sometimes a number
is more than just a number.
It can provide information
that we couldn’t get any other way,
and if we can understand that,
this discussion will have been
well worth having.
So when you see a number in the Bible,
don’t run the other way.
Embrace it; stop and think about it.
You may be glad you did.