The next part is a video
entitled The Inside Story,
hosted by Brother Ken Stovall,
who also serves
as a Theocratic Schools instructor.
I am so excited to be with you here again
on this segment of The Inside Story!
This time we’re
with class number 143 of the Gilead School,
and you are going to meet
some adorable brothers and sisters.
And let me tell you,
they have some moving experiences
to relate to you.
And we’re going to solve
two fascinating mysteries.
And we have music.
Students in this class are going
to thrill you with their musical talent.
There is a captivating song
that they’re going to sing for you.
So come with me as we, together,
get “the inside story.”
Let’s introduce our first guest.
And that would be Saša Komaromi
from the Serbia branch.
So, Brother Komaromi,
you serve at the Serbia branch.
But you told me that some years ago,
before you were in the truth,
you discovered that there were
two main interests you had in life.
One of them had to do with a career choice.
Could you explain that?
One was music.
Music.
Now, is this a picture of you?
That was the old me.
Evidently, you were in a band.
Yes, we were at a competition at the time.
That was one of your interests,
but there was another.
What was that?
Searching for the purpose of life.
And how did you
go about searching for life’s purpose?
I read a lot of books
—books about parapsychology, Buddhism,
spiritism, Tibetan Lamaism.
Amazing!
That’s a lot of books.
Now, at the time, though,
you were dating your wife, Vicki.
What did she think of all these books?
Did she share your interest
in all this reading?
I wished she did.
But no, she did not.
To be honest, it’s not really easy
to like to read those kinds of books
—for example, The Book of the Dead.
The Book of the Dead?
I can see that’s not going
to be a very enjoyable book.
Now, was it only books?
Was that the only way
you were searching for the purpose of life?
No, I was also experimenting
with different states of mind
under the influence of drugs.
During my hallucinations,
I had many things already “solved.”
You had everything “solved.”
This is what I thought.
But after I came to myself again,
I was again in the same room
and everything was the same.
So I was really, really disappointed.
And then I prayed to God.
I said:
“God, I’m asking just for one thing.
But whatever it is, just, please,
help me to be certain that I find the truth.”
Very interesting.
So you prayed for Jehovah
to help you find the truth.
Of course,
you didn’t know Jehovah at the time.
So how was your prayer answered?
Soon after that, I went to Germany.
I had the idea to form my music studio.
During my visit there,
I understood that my uncle
and my aunt were Jehovah’s Witnesses.
And you never knew that before?
No.
No, I didn’t know.
So, what did they have in their home
that would have been really exciting to you?
As all Jehovah’s Witnesses,
they had a lot of theocratic books.
Ahh.
So, did you read the books?
Yes, I read them a lot.
Actually, I read a book daily.
Wow!
So you get back home;
you open up the suitcases.
And Vicki is there,
and she sees books.
And you were supposed
to bring home musical equipment.
What did she think about that?
She thought,
‘Now definitely he’s totally crazy.’
So, what did you do?
I explained to her immediately
that from now on
I would like to live according to what I read
in these books and the Bible.
And I would also like it for her
—that she also live like that.
If this was OK with her,
we could stay together.
If it was not OK with her,
we were finished.
You like to be direct, don’t you?
I know, I was “very tactful.”
But I also offered her
the book Young People Ask.
Did she like that?
Yes.
Yes, she liked it
much more than my ultimatum.
I see.
We started studying the Bible.
At the beginning,
my wife started because of me,
but later
she did this because of herself.
And after six months,
we became unbaptized publishers.
Then we got married,
and we were baptized in 1994.
Immediately, we started full-time service,
and we served five years
as regular pioneers
and then almost five years
as special pioneers.
And now we’ve been
13 years at the Serbia branch.
Jehovah has answered your prayer.
You’re satisfied;
you found the truth;
you found the purpose in life.
But there’s still the music.
Did you have to give up
your desire to play music,
to be involved in music,
especially since you’ve come to Bethel now?
Actually, in 2013,
there was an idea
that we should start with a project
of recording vocal renditions
of our theocratic songs.
And my wife, Violeta, and I had the privilege
to participate in that project.
Now, was this just for the Serbia branch?
No, the plan was to record the songs
in four or five languages.
Four or five languages?
But would this mean, then,
that you would travel
around to different countries
surrounding Serbia?
No, the idea was that singers
would come from other countries to Serbia,
and they would be full-time singers
for a period of time
until we finished that project.
That must have been
a tremendous amount of work.
How did you get that accomplished?
Yeah, it’s easier if we see a video,
and it will be much more understandable.
All right, good.
Let’s watch the video.
One of the first things we needed
was a recording studio.
So with the help of many, we built our own.
A typical day began
with a little music theory,
a little stretching,
and a brief review
of the song’s Scriptural theme.
Once they received a new song,
they practiced in separate groups.
Then they would all come together.
Finally, it was time to record.
This resulted in 450 songs being recorded
in a period of 22 months.
Looking back,
these songs were sung not just with words
but with hearts full of love for Jehovah.
Look at them.
Those are nice greetings at the end there.
Yeah, nice surprise.
I loved the way the chorus sounded.
You did a good job with them.
That must have been
a tremendous amount of work,
getting that all done, though,
in five different languages.
Yes, the singers did a great job
and also all the crew.
And you really could see,
all the time,
their love for Jehovah
and love for the brotherhood.
And every day you could see
a lot of their self-sacrificing spirit.
Now, Saša,
let me ask you one more question.
We saw the picture there
of you as a musician,
and I know you have
some musical talent.
Possibly, you could have become famous.
Do you ever regret not pursuing
some sort of a career in the world
as opposed to giving your life
in full-time service to Jehovah?
As you said, I could be famous.
Or I could have become
a drug addict and now be dead.
That’s a good point.
So no, no regrets at all.
I received much,
much more than I ever imagined.
And in my case,
from my first prayer till now,
Jehovah assured me
that he’s really the “Hearer of prayer,”
as the psalmist
mentioned in Psalm 65:2.
Excellent!
Thank you so much, Saša,
for sharing
these very heartfelt comments.
You’re welcome.
Thank you.
Now, you know what we’re going to do?
We’re going to give you the opportunity
to get to know some of the students
in our audience.
We’re going to do an activity
I call What’s My Favorite Scripture?
So we’re going to ask
the students if they’ll volunteer
and give us their favorite scripture and,
in a minute or less,
tell us what it says
and why it’s their favorite scripture.
OK,
let’s see now.
Who would like to go first?
Shingirai Mapfumo from Zimbabwe.
Psalm 84:11.
And what does that say?
“For Jehovah God is a sun and a shield;
“he gives favor and glory.
“Jehovah will not hold back anything good
from those walking in integrity.”
OK, so tell us,
Why is that your favorite scripture?
During the economic crisis in Zimbabwe,
my pioneer partner and I ran out of food.
We were really starving,
and physically we were so weak
that we could not even function.
Still, we managed to go to town,
hoping that we could get
some money from the bank.
There was a long queue,
and the bank
was not giving any money either.
We were so distraught.
At that moment
when we didn’t know what to do,
a truck from the branch office
brought food supplies for us.
Then it became so clear to me
that Jehovah is “a shield,”
and he never “hold[s] back anything good”
from his loyal servants.
Amazing! Well, I can see why
that’s your favorite scripture.
All right, who else?
Let’s get Sister Tšèpang Mhlongo,
and she’s from South Africa.
My favorite scripture is Psalm 68:5,
and it says about Jehovah
that he is the “father of the fatherless
and a protector of widows.”
Why is that your favorite scripture?
Well, I became motherless
when I was only one year old.
But Jehovah has provided me
with hundreds of mothers around the globe,
both black and white.
And because our Bethel work
involves traveling
all around the African continent
working with the translators,
it makes it even more precious to me
that I adopt this family wherever we go.
Truly, Jehovah has proved to be my Father
and my Protector to this day.
Hmm, very touching.
And I’m sure that all
of those parents who have adopted you
are proud to have you as a daughter.
Who else could tell us
their favorite scripture?
All right,
let’s get Brother Sylvain Bois from Benin.
It is Psalm 94:18, 19.
And what does it say?
“Your loyal love, O Jehovah,
kept supporting me.
“When anxieties overwhelmed me,
you comforted and soothed me.”
So tell us,
Why is that scripture special to you?
Years ago, when I was attending
Ministerial Training School (MTS),
I had a serious stroke
and I was hospitalized.
When I awoke from the coma,
I felt very happy because I was alive.
But also very discouraged
because I thought
everything was over for me
—pioneer service, school,
and even my dream
to one day become a missionary.
But one of the instructors
and his wife came to the hospital,
and they read me that verse.
And my heart was full of anxieties,
but I really felt that day that Jehovah
was able to comfort me and soothe me.
And you know what?
One year later,
I was permitted to again attend MTS.
And a few months later,
Jehovah fulfilled another of my dreams,
as I was assigned as a missionary in Africa.
Brother Bois, that was very touching.
Thank you so much, and we’re so glad
to have you in this class of Gilead.
Well, that’s all
that we’re going to have time for.
So now it’s time to introduce our next guest,
and that would be Brother Paulo Maganha,
and he’s from Brazil.
Now, Brother Maganha,
you’re at the Brazil branch.
But you came into the truth
at nine years old,
at the same time as your mother.
And you went to the branch,
to Bethel, in your early 20’s,
and you’ve been there for 27 years.
What department
do you work in at the branch now?
I am now in LDC for one and a half years.
LDC.
OK, would you just tell us,
What does the LDC Department do?
LDC is
the Local Design/Construction Department.
It’s responsible for the work of planning,
construction, and maintenance
of Kingdom Halls and Assembly Halls.
You have the LDC Department there at Bethel,
but who outside of Bethel
works with building
Kingdom Halls and Assembly Halls?
Outside we have many brothers and sisters
serving as construction servants,
construction volunteers,
remote volunteers,
and field representatives.
Now, this is—
This is the mystery.
This is our first mystery.
What really, then,
does a field representative do?
OK, let’s just call them field rep. OK?
OK.
Field rep, I like that.
You could say that they are the eyes
and the ears of the LDC at the branch.
But what if I show you
some pictures regarding the work?
I would love that!
OK.
At the first step, the office asks him
to investigate some congregation needs.
He meets with the local elders
and the circuit overseer
to determine the needs.
And later, he sends
a recommendation to the office.
I see.
So if he has a large region,
he may have to have
many, many of these meetings
and do a lot of research to determine
what the needs are for Kingdom Halls.
Yeah.
Once the project is approved,
the next step is to search
for appropriate land, a property.
To do that,
he goes to the Internet,
consults real estate agents,
local brothers, neighbors.
To find the right property
at the right cost can be very time consuming
and requires of him
a lot of skills and abilities.
And the field rep
is also responsible for getting the permits,
the approvals, for construction.
And he visits
several different agencies every day
to get the permits to have
everything approved by the government.
In big cities, he may have to stand
in line after line after line.
This could take—
Yeah. And in bigger cities,
it can take even some weeks
or months
to get everything approved.
Finally, when everything is approved,
the construction group starts the work.
And you can see him again visiting the site
in order to give some technical support
to the construction overseer.
So, now, does he stay on the site
when a building is being built?
No, he returns to his office
but remains in contact with the group
to give some remote support.
Especially when some big issues
arise at the site,
the construction overseer
can always count on his good support.
OK, good.
I notice in this picture,
behind the field representative,
we see a sister pictured there.
Who might that be?
Well, if he’s married,
his wife can do
lots of work to help him.
But if he is not, he can count
on a local volunteer to help him.
Once the project is concluded,
he visits the site again,
now to do the commissioning
and to make sure that everything
was done according to the plans.
So, evidently, his job is done now.
No, not yet.
He’s also responsible
for giving training to local brothers
to properly maintain the building.
Wow!
So you have helped solve this mystery.
He does have a lot of work to do.
But really, does working
on one project keep him busy?
No, it is not just one, Brother Stovall.
They are very busy and productive workers.
On average, each field rep
can be working on 10 to 15 projects
in different phases but at the same time.
My goodness!
That’s amazing!
So they really do
an amazing amount of work then.
Paulo, I understand that at your branch,
you’ve come up with a very innovative idea
regarding Assembly Halls and Kingdom Halls.
Could you explain that to us?
Yes, we have done what is called
an expandable Kingdom Hall.
Expandable Kingdom Hall?
Saša, do you have
expandable Kingdom Halls in Serbia?
Not that I’m aware of.
I can’t even imagine.
How do you expand a Kingdom Hall?
OK, what if we see a brief video about this?
OK, I’d like that.
At first,
it looks like a normal Kingdom Hall.
But something wonderful happens
when the back walls are lifted.
It’s now large enough to hold
an entire assembly or convention.
But before we can meet there,
it has to be cleaned.
Chairs are rented and arranged.
And audio and video equipment must be set up
so that no matter where you sit,
you won’t miss anything.
All the hard work is worth it
when you see how much the friends benefit.
When the special weekend of activity is over
and the walls are lowered,
it goes right back
to being a Kingdom Hall again.
That’s our family there.
Uh-huh.
They sent you some spirited greetings.
Yeah.
And what a brilliant way
to get the most out of a building
and save money!
Now, Brother Maganha,
I just want to ask you,
What has impressed you the most
about working with the LDC Department?
What really touched my heart
is to see the spirit of willingness to help
shown by all those involved with the LDC.
You know, these brothers
and sisters have left their families,
their houses, their friends behind
to work with these projects.
All these sacrifices are done out of love
—love for our brotherhood
and especially love for Jehovah.
That’s the reason
that I really, really appreciate their work.
Thank you, Brother Maganha.
Obviously, those brothers
and sisters that work with LDC
set a good example for the rest of us.
Thank you very much.
My pleasure.
Now, Brother Komaromi,
it’s time for you to give us
a sample of your musical talent.
Would you go and join our band?
Recently, the Governing Body
has given us loving encouragement
through our regional convention program
to never give up.
Now, the Gilead students have written a song
that goes right along with that spirit
and that theme.
It’s entitled “We’ll Never Let Go.”
I thought that was a thrilling song.
You brothers and sisters
did a marvelous job on that.
And you know what I liked about the song too
is that it gets progressively more modern
as you go through the song.
So it really says to me that our organization
in its modern-day history,
even in early times, has never given up,
and we will never give up.
And it’s so joyful.
It says that we’re going to endure with joy.
No one can take that away from us.
It’s Jehovah’s gift through his holy spirit.
Now it’s time to introduce our final guest,
and that is Sister Angela Khang
from the United States.
Angela, you are one
of the single sisters in our class,
but where in the United States
do you serve?
I’m at the remote translation office (RTO)
in Sacramento, California,
and they translate
into the Hmong language there.
Now, I have to confess
—the Hmong language—
I never knew until very recently
that there was such a language
as the Hmong language.
And I didn’t realize
there was a Hmong people.
Why is that?
Well, for a long time, the Hmong story
was kept a secret from the American public.
Now this is another one of our mysteries
because why would it be
that someone would try to keep
the existence of a whole culture secret?
Well, during the Vietnam War,
which was a very unpopular conflict,
many U.S. citizens
didn’t want the war to expand.
So the U.S. government
actually went to Southeast Asia,
and they secretly recruited the Hmong men
who were living in the hill tribes of Laos
to fight Communism in that part of the world.
In the end, about 40,000 Hmong men
were killed in that war,
and so that’s about 1 in 4 Hmong men.
So every family lost someone.
Forty thousand men.
I don’t think that people
really are aware of that fact, are they?
No. Many historians
call that conflict the Secret War.
Looking at our monitor here,
what is it we are seeing here?
This was an exhibit
showcasing the Hmong experience
—how they came to the U.S.
And it’s a wall of unknown soldiers
who fought in the war,
and they were asking the Hmong community
to identify their loved ones.
So a few in our congregation
knew some of those men.
I see.
Now,
as I think back to the history of that war,
at some point in time,
the United States pulled out of Vietnam.
So, what happened then
to the Hmong that were left there
in Vietnam when the U.S. pulled out?
It was a desperate situation
because there was an aggressive campaign
to capture and kill
any of the remaining Hmong families,
and so many of them
had to find a way to escape.
And so we see that here in this photo.
This is Long Tieng Air Base in 1975.
About 30,000 Hmong people
converged on that airport,
hoping to find a way out.
But only about 2,500 were airlifted
—the more prominent officials.
I see.
You can see
that those thousands of people there
are not going
to fit on that airplane.
So all those thousands that were left behind,
what happened to them?
They were pretty much left on their own,
and they had to find their way out
along with thousands of other families.
And so that’s what happened to my family.
They found their way
across the Mekong River into Thailand,
and they were placed in refugee camps.
I see.
So who are we seeing
a picture of here now on the monitor?
This is my father
in a Thailand refugee camp
and my mother,
my grandmother, and my uncle.
So your family managed to survive
by fleeing into Thailand
and getting into the refugee camp.
But then how did they get
to the United States?
In 1979,
they were sponsored to the United States.
And the Hmong culture is patriarchal,
so you stick close with your clan.
And so my entire clan ended up in California,
and they settled in South Sacramento.
I can imagine that this experience
must have been a tremendous amount of loss
for the Hmong people, Hmong families.
My father lost his mother
when they were fleeing;
he lost his brother.
He saw many people lose their lives.
Many clans were separated.
Some of their relatives ended up in France,
and the rest of them
ended up in the United States.
And then when they settled here,
my mom lost her hearing.
So it was just an added stress
in their lives.
So how did all this suffering and loss,
how did it affect your mother?
Even though her background is animist,
she knew that the Bible was a holy book
that would teach her about the Creator.
So she found comfort in reading the Bible.
And she started to collect
different Bibles from different translations
and comparing them to try
to understand what she was reading.
And every night she would pray
with me and my sister.
And so from a young age,
we were taught that God is real,
even though we didn’t know Jehovah yet.
Wow, very, very interesting.
So she was
really, really looking for the truth.
So how did she eventually find the truth?
Well, in the meantime,
my uncle (the one who was pictured earlier)
and his wife started studying the Bible,
and they came into the truth.
And they asked a sister
to come and study with my mom,
and soon my entire family was studying.
In 1996, my mom was baptized.
In 1997, my sister and I were baptized.
Amazing! So, now,
you were baptized at the age of 12,
and then you
started pioneering at the age of 15.
Yes.
Now, first of all,
you were in an English congregation.
But what changed that?
Our circuit overseer came through,
and he was telling us about a Hmong group
that had formed in our sister congregation.
And he told us we had
no reason to be in English,
and he was right.
So as a family,
we moved over to the Hmong group,
and in 1999, that group
became the very first Hmong congregation.
So that made us very happy.
So you were associated
with the very first Hmong congregation
anywhere in the world.
Yes.
Amazing!
Now, later you toured Bethel,
and that had a profound effect on you.
Can you tell us about that?
Well, we came to Bethel,
and a brother in Translation Services
found out we were coming through,
so he wanted to meet with us.
And he sat us girls down,
and he told us,
“You have something you can give to Jehovah,
and that’s your language.”
So it really got me thinking
about what I could do
to really support the field.
So I went home,
and I really worked on my language
and worked on supporting the group.
And in 2007
when Bethel came looking for translators,
this same brother came out
and he interviewed a group of us.
And shortly after that,
my mom and another brother and I
were invited to serve
on the Hmong translation team
at the first RTO
here in the U.S. branch.
My goodness!
So the first Hmong congregation
anywhere in the world
and the first RTO for the U.S. branch.
Jehovah certainly has blessed you
with some wonderful privileges.
Could you just tell us,
What’s it like working
at the RTO from day to day?
Sure.
Would you like to see a video?
Yes, we would.
At the Hmong RTO,
many hands help in the translation work.
When questions come up,
we’re not left on our own.
The Translation Services Department
is always ready to provide support.
Once everything is approved,
it’s time to record.
Since Hmong wasn’t a written language
until the 1950’s,
audio publications are very important
to the Hmong field.
Some support the RTO
in other valuable ways too,
such as cooking and cleaning.
It’s the best feeling
to talk to the Hmong people
and to show them
something in their language.
You can see how it touches their heart.
As a result, we have many interested ones
attend our meetings.
As the Hmong field continues to grow,
many are learning our language
to help support the preaching work.
When we get together,
we have a great time
—with good food,
association,
watching the kids play.
It’s obvious to everyone in the community
that we’re not just a congregation
—we’re a family.
That is a wonderful video, really.
Angela, could you just tell us,
Why does the work done at the RTO
fill such a great need
among the Hmong people?
Well, the Hmong are a people
without a country, and throughout history,
they’ve been pushed
from one location to another.
They were pushed out of China
in the late 1800’s,
they were pushed out of Laos,
and from there
they were scattered across the world
—to the U.S.,
to France, to Australia.
And so for many of the Hmong brothers,
they feel like a forgotten people.
Excuse me,
I watched this video for the first time here.
It’s the first time she’s seen the video.
It’s the first time.
So it’s, it’s moving.
So many of the Hmong brothers
feel like a forgotten people.
But the work at the RTO is a reminder
that Jehovah hasn’t forgotten them.
In fact, he invites them
to become part of an international clan
—a brotherhood.
And when they respond to that invitation,
they find something
that they’ve been looking for all along.
They finally find a place
—a permanent home—
under God’s Kingdom.
Thank you for those heartfelt comments.
Really, those were very nice.
Now, Sister Khang,
we have a little surprise for you.
We really want the audience to know that,
well, the work done at the Hmong RTO
is not just for the United States,
but the effect
reaches clear around the world
In fact,
we have caught up
with a congregation in northern Thailand.
And I know this is a surprise;
we did not rehearse this.
No, we did not.
But we’re going to show you, if you’d like.
Yes.
Watch this.
Well, obviously,
they are grateful for the work
you brothers and sisters do in that RTO.
Wasn’t this a thrilling occasion?
It was wonderful, enjoyable,
to get to know these brothers and sisters.
We wish that Jehovah continues
to bless you in your faithful service to him
until the next time we get together
on The Inside Story.
Thank you very much, Brother Stovall,
for sharing with us The Inside Story.
We appreciate very much
your letting us in on it.
But I have to admit
that this is the first Gilead graduation
I’ve ever been to where
I couldn’t help but pat my foot back there.
I’m just so glad I was behind the curtain.