Welcome to the program!
This month,
we’ll take you to world headquarters
to visit one of the museums.
We’ll learn about the many activities
that are organized and directed
by the Governing Body today.
Next, how can we protect ourselves
from being lured into sin?
In this dramatization,
a young brother learns
how to make the right decision.
And how does the organization
ensure that our brothers
and sisters receive spiritual food?
In this example from Africa,
we’ll see how JW Broadcasting® is distributed
even when Internet connections are slow.
This is the July 2019 program
of JW Broadcasting!
We’ll begin by introducing you
to two sisters who live in the United States.
Early on in their lives,
they were exposed to two very different views
of what a family should be like.
Still, they came to realize that,
while life may change, Jehovah doesn’t.
This is my sister Lei Lei.
This is my sister Mimi.
My sister Lei Lei—
She is very caring.
I know that for sure.
One thing that I appreciate about Mimi
is that she has a self-sacrificing spirit.
We love our family.
Yeah.
What I love most about my mom
is that she has a big heart.
And I know that my dad
really, truly loves his family.
Our sister, Sophie, always takes care of you,
making sure you are OK.
Our family is something
that we never want to replace.
To us, it’s a forever family.
But it wasn’t always like that.
We haven’t always been sisters.
At a young age,
I was already in a foster home,
and then Mimi became my foster sister.
We were not treated as part of their family.
We never knew what love felt like.
There wasn’t a bedroom for us.
Me and Lei Lei would share a couch.
Our foster families would leave us
by ourselves at home,
and me and Lei Lei had to take care of ourselves.
And so we were very close together
because we would talk to each other
and just help each other out.
When we would go to school,
we didn’t have school supplies,
so I would steal stuff.
And we didn’t have school uniforms;
we had clothing that was dirty.
I felt like in some way
that with all these experiences
it kind of made me feel like I didn’t care.
I didn’t like authority figures
and didn’t really trust them.
I was lost.
I was confused.
I just did whatever I possibly could
to protect myself.
We have experienced things
that no child should go through.
We found out there was a family
who wanted to adopt us.
I was 12 years old.
And I was nine years old.
One thing that was tough for me was conversing.
I didn’t know any English,
and it was hard for my parents to know how I felt
because I had a hard time
expressing if I was sad or scared.
I had a difficult time trusting.
But they showed us love,
and they hugged us
and just made us feel at home.
As I got to know them better and I got to see
that they truly loved me
and that they truly treated me like their daughter,
it helped me to develop love and trust.
The first time I saw
my mom and dad praying at the dinner meal,
it was very new to me because I never knew
that there was a God.
I had some past experience with religion,
and I didn’t like it.
So when I first saw my mom and dad praying,
I was uncomfortable with it.
They had to figure out a way
to introduce their best Friend,
Jehovah, to us.
They took us to this place
called the Kingdom Hall.
The first thing we felt was warmth and love.
All these friends were coming up
and saying hi to us and giving us hugs
—just super loving toward us.
Dad would give us a notepad,
and he would tell us,
“Draw anything that you understand.”
And so those were our notes.
We would just draw pictures.
They would pray with us,
teaching us how to pray specifically
and to see how Jehovah
could answer our prayer.
We would eat breakfast
every day together and do the daily text;
we would reenact Bible stories.
And we prepared for meetings.
The simplified Watchtower came out,
and it really helped us so much.
I was able to really learn
more about Jehovah and understand it.
And that helped me to give
more comments and draw closer to Jehovah.
A big change for me
was during the 2014 international convention.
Just seeing the love and the unity
between brothers and sisters touched my heart.
That also helped me
to progress toward making
the decision of getting baptized.
Going out in service more—
I think it really helped me
to draw closer to Jehovah
and make the Kingdom feel real to me.
And so that’s why I wanted to get baptized.
After I graduated from high school,
I started to pioneer.
It’s one way to show my love for Jehovah.
I used to just take care of myself,
but I learned to take care of others
and to think of others first.
For us young ones, we should appreciate
every moment that we have with our parents.
Your parents are the best friends
that you could ever have.
Going out in service wasn’t easy for me at first
because I’m actually a very shy person,
but I decided to rely on Jehovah
and started pioneering.
And just recently,
I started commuting to Bethel one day a week.
The important quality
that Jehovah has taught me is love
I felt that love from my family,
from Jehovah, and from my friends.
I learned that it’s OK to love people,
and that’s what you are supposed to do.
You love people and take care of people.
And I feel like my life
is more satisfying and meaningful.
When I meditate and think
about what Jehovah has done for me and Lei Lei,
I don’t have to be afraid.
Jehovah is my “secure refuge,”
because life may change,
but Jehovah does not change.
The love and unity of the brothers
stood out to Lei Lei and Mimi
and helped them draw closer to Jehovah.
For a Bible student to progress to baptism,
he or she would need to develop
those very qualities,
which Lei Lei and Mimi did.
But there are
many additional aspects of our personality
that we as Christians need to maintain.
One of the most underrated qualities
in today’s world is modesty.
In fact, the world encourages
the exact opposite of modesty.
The world says that you are
the most important person;
you should promote yourself;
you have no limits;
you have the right to be anything you want to be.
As we’ll see, the world’s thinking
is completely backward
—and for several reasons.
Really, modesty is a quality
that stems from everything that is good.
Our theme scripture
for this discussion is Micah 6:8:
“He has told you . . . what is good.
“And what is Jehovah requiring of you?
“Only to exercise justice, to cherish loyalty,
and to walk in modesty with your God!”
Notice that modesty is one
of the key aspects of “what is good.”
To help us understand why,
let’s discuss three questions:
What is modesty?
Why do we want to have this quality?
How can we cultivate it?
First, what is modesty?
Basically, it’s an awareness of our limitations.
Of course, we often link modesty
with appropriate dress and grooming,
but much more is involved.
How do we know?
Consider what we read at Proverbs 11:2:
“When presumptuousness comes,
“dishonor will follow,
but wisdom is with the modest ones.”
Notice that modesty is contrasted
with a negative quality—presumptuousness.
A presumptuous person
runs ahead without the authority to do so.
He or she ignores
proper boundaries and limitations.
That kind of attitude
often leads to foolish mistakes
and a bad reputation with fellow humans.
And above all,
it can cause a person to lose God’s favor.
For example, we might think of King Saul.
Although he started out as a modest young man,
in time he became presumptuous.
He even went so far as to offer up
a burnt sacrifice
even though he was not authorized to do so.
As a result,
Saul lost Jehovah’s favor
and eventually the kingship.
In Saul’s case, presumptuousness definitely
led to dishonor.
On the other hand,
a wise and modest person
recognizes his limitations and works within them.
Why is modesty the course of wisdom?
This brings us to our second main point,
Why do we want to have this quality?
The foremost reason
is that modesty is essential
to pleasing our heavenly Father, Jehovah.
Although we don’t speak
of Jehovah as being modest,
even he works within certain limitations
that he’s imposed on himself.
He teaches us by example
how to demonstrate this quality,
even though it’s not one that he needs to display.
Why can we say that Jehovah
imposes limitations on himself?
Consider just one example:
He’ll never violate
the gift of free will that he’s granted us.
Jehovah will never force us to serve him
—even though, of course,
he has the power to do so.
Aren’t we grateful that he allows us to serve him
because we choose to out of love
and not because we are forced to?
Jehovah teaches us
to display modesty in other ways as well.
For example, we might think
of how he listened patiently
as Abraham voiced his concerns
about Jehovah’s purpose
to destroy Sodom and Gomorrah
or how Jehovah invited
the angels to suggest ways to fool Ahab
and then authorized
one of their suggestions to be carried out.
What’s the lesson for us?
If Jehovah, who doesn’t need
input or help from anyone,
patiently listens and delegates,
how much more should we do so
—especially since
we’re all so imperfect and limited!
Are you a family head
or an elder in the congregation,
or do you have
another responsible position in the organization?
If so, you can imitate Jehovah
by not micromanaging others.
Be willing to delegate tasks to them
and listen to their suggestions.
Imitate Jehovah’s example of dignifying others
and wanting to help them succeed.
Besides pleasing Jehovah,
we have other good reasons to be modest.
Modesty helps us to be joyful.
How so?
By going hand in hand
with a related quality—gratitude.
A faithful brother who worked
in the Writing Department
for some 50 years was fond of saying,
“Only a grateful person can be happy.”
If we’re modestly aware of our limitations,
we’ll be grateful and happy
for the help that we receive from others.
For example,
think of the leper who returned
to thank Jesus for healing him.
This man realized his limitations.
He was very thankful that Jesus
had done something for him
that he could never have done on his own.
Another reason to cultivate modesty
is that it promotes good relationships with others.
Let’s face it:
People aren’t usually drawn to those who think,
‘If I want something done right,
I have to do it myself.’
But they usually appreciate it when they’re shown
that we have confidence in them.
This, in turn, draws them to us.
Another way that modesty
promotes good relationships
is that it helps us
to avoid comparing ourselves to others.
Comparing ourselves to others
is always a dangerous road to navigate.
Just think, for example, of Jesus’ apostles
who argued many times
over who was the greatest
or of Joseph’s brothers
and the terrible things they did
because of being jealous of Joseph.
A modest person doesn’t obsess
over his perceived rank in comparison with others.
In this regard,
we can remember the good example of Moses.
How did he react when Jehovah
enabled some of his fellow Israelites
to begin acting as prophets alongside him?
Moses rejoiced,
saying that he wished all
of Jehovah’s people were prophets.
Moses didn’t feel that he was
the only one who should have such a privilege.
Finally, modesty promotes
good relationships with others
because it prevents us
from bragging about our accomplishments
or drawing undue attention to ourselves,
which could stir up resentment in others.
So now we know what modesty is
and why we want to have it.
This brings us to our third main point,
How can we cultivate this beautiful quality?
One thing we can do
is to read and meditate on Bible examples
—both good and bad—
such as those we just discussed.
Other Bible examples include Daniel,
who modestly didn’t take credit
for the interpretation
of King Nebuchadnezzar’s dream.
The lesson for us?
If we’re privileged to have a teaching assignment
or we enjoy a measure of success in the ministry,
we want to give all the glory to Jehovah.
We should modestly recognize
that we couldn’t do these things without his help.
We can also study the example of Jesus,
who didn’t even think of trying to grasp
for more authority than Jehovah had granted him.
Philippians 2:6 tells us:
“He . . . gave no consideration to a seizure,
namely, that he should be equal to God.”
Consider how Jesus responded
when his disciples James
and John approached him
with their mother
and asked for a privilege
that was beyond his authority to grant them.
Jesus modestly acknowledged
that only Jehovah could decide
who would sit at his right
and left hand in the Kingdom.
Jesus respected his limitations.
What are some other ways
we can cultivate modesty?
One is to apply the Bible’s counsel
found at 1 Corinthians 4:6:
“Do not go beyond the things that are written.”
This refers primarily
to ‘the things written’ in God’s Word.
By extension, the principle
also applies to the Scriptural direction
that we receive from our publications.
When asked for advice,
we would never want to impose our own opinion
or simply give an answer off the top of our head.
Rather, we want to direct attention
to the counsel found in the Bible
and Bible-based publications.
Another way we can cultivate modesty
is by asking for frank comments
from a trusted friend
as to whether or not
we have a reputation for being modest.
In this regard, we remember the Bible principle:
“As iron sharpens iron,
so one man sharpens his friend.”
If someone is willing to offer
kind observations about how we can improve,
we wouldn’t want to bristle at the comments.
Granted, it may sting our pride
to hear such honest feedback,
but don’t we all need
to hear these things from time to time?
As imperfect humans,
each one of us has blind spots, as it were.
It’s hard to see ourselves the way others see us.
Remember, we can work
to improve our Christian personality
—but only if we know
the areas that could use some improvement.
We can’t change what we don’t see.
A word of caution:
We want to beware of false modesty.
Remember that it’s not
about simply appearing modest
but actually being modest at heart.
To help us examine ourselves,
we might meditate on questions like these:
When I receive advice or counsel,
how do I really feel about it at heart?
Does my internal reaction
depend on whether the person giving it
has less or more experience
or authority than I do?
Am I willing to accept valid suggestions
regardless of who offers them?
A final way we can develop true modesty
is to ask Jehovah to help us.
We know what James 1:17 says:
“Every good gift and every perfect present is from above,
coming down from the Father of the celestial lights.”
Since modesty is one of Jehovah’s good gifts to us,
we can be sure that if we pray to Jehovah and ask him
to help us cultivate this quality,
he’ll answer our sincere prayers.
In review, what is modesty?
It’s a proper recognition of our limitations.
Why do we want to have this quality?
Because it pleases Jehovah,
it promotes good relationships with others,
and it adds to our joy.
How can we cultivate modesty?
There are many ways:
We can meditate on Bible examples,
both good and bad,
and then apply the lessons in our own life.
We should apply the counsel
to ‘not go beyond the things written.’
We can ask others for honest feedback
on how we’re doing in showing this quality.
And above all, we can pray to Jehovah
and ask him to help us develop it more fully.
When we think of all the positive ways
that modesty benefits ourselves and others,
wouldn’t you agree that it truly is a quality
that comes from “what is good”?
Modesty can also protect us
from Satan’s schemes.
In this dramatization,
a brother’s modesty
helped him to make the right decision.
Mom has been working hard lately,
but I wish she worked harder for Jehovah.
I try to help out where I can.
Oh, by the way, I’m Jin.
Every day starts the same.
I grab a drink of water;
I say hi to Jun (he’s in my congregation);
and then there’s Mee-Kyong.
OK.
Here we go.
I say hello,
she says something clever,
and I try to leave.
So this is different.
She’s having trouble
in math and needs my help.
I don’t want to be rude,
but
if I help her with her homework,
how far could the relationship develop?
How do you say no to a girl like her?
Why can’t I get her out of my head?
Things are always better
when Uncle and Auntie are around.
Even Mom makes sure
she’s home for “dinner and broadcast” night.
Uncle wants to work together
in service this weekend;
maybe that will help clear my head.
Jehovah must be disappointed in me.
I couldn’t take it anymore.
It was difficult,
but I told Uncle everything.
I felt guilty that I knew I shouldn’t,
but I liked the attention.
We read Genesis 39:7-12.
I knew the account about Potiphar’s wife,
but he mentioned something
I hadn’t thought of before.
He told Potiphar’s wife:
“How could I commit this great badness
and actually sin against God?”
But why did Joseph have to flee?
Joseph fought her every day,
but she wasn’t going to give up.
In her mind,
it wasn’t a question of if but when.
There came a point when he had to flee.
I explained why I was ending the relationship,
but she would not give up.
You know the last thing she said to me?
That I was a coward.
But she’s wrong.
You’re never a coward if you run to Jehovah.
Our young brother
saw that dating an unbeliever
would put him in harm’s way.
He was reminded that getting involved
with someone
who doesn’t share Jehovah’s values
could eventually lead to sin.
Having modesty protected him
from such dire consequences.
By his decision,
we could see our young brother’s faith in action.
Faith in Action
is also the name of one of the museums
at our world headquarters in Warwick, New York.
Have you had an opportunity to visit?
If not, we’d like to take you there right now.
And even if you have visited,
you’ll enjoy these reminders.
Welcome to the World Headquarters
of Jehovah’s Witnesses at Warwick, New York.
As Jehovah’s people,
we are multicultural and multilingual.
And as the artwork here emphasizes, our focus
is on our commission to ‘preach the good news
to people of all nations.’
So, what are we doing today as an organization?
How did we get here?
And what’s our main tool for this great work?
We invite you to come tour our museums
to find out.
We have three museums here at Warwick,
all funded by voluntary donations.
Each of them is alive with stories.
Upstairs on the second floor
is the museum Faith in Action.
There we’ll see the very latest
on what’s being done by Jehovah’s organization.
Also on the second floor is the museum
A People for Jehovah’s Name.
It takes us on an exciting journey back in time.
And downstairs
we have the Bible Museum.
There we’ll get to see up close
a spiritual treasure chest.
When you tour the museums,
you’ll notice that they
were designed to be, not passive, but interactive
so that you can put yourself in the experience.
So with that preview,
let’s take the tour.
This is the launching point
to the Faith in Action Museum.
Note that important, descriptive word: “action.”
What activities, or actions,
are being organized and directed
by the Governing Body today?
This display acquaints you right away
with the work of the Governing Body committees.
Each committee has specific responsibilities,
but as you take the tour,
notice how the committees work together
to accomplish their goals.
The Faith in Action Museum
is divided into four galleries:
“Show Love,”
“Meet Together,”
“Take In Spiritual Food,”
and “Make Disciples.”
As you walk through the galleries,
notice how each of them
is connected by a JW-blue ribbon.
So if you get lost,
just follow the blue ribbon.
This is the “Show Love” Gallery.
Here you’ll learn how the Governing Body
helps God’s people
to ‘have love among themselves,’
as Jesus commanded at John 13:35.
For example,
how do the brothers at headquarters respond
to needs that arise when a disaster strikes?
When things like natural disasters,
terrorist attacks, or civil unrest occur,
the Coordinators’ Committee directs relief efforts.
They, in turn, communicate
with the Branch Committee
that oversees the affected area.
Usually, within 48 hours,
a report of what’s occurred
and what’s being done to help our brothers
is compiled and sent to headquarters.
That report may be
the basis for informing the brotherhood
through an article on jw.org®.
There’s another way that love
is shown to Jehovah’s people
—schools.
Such schools as the School for Congregation Elders
and the School for Circuit Overseers and Their Wives.
These have been very effective in training brothers
to shepherd the congregations lovingly.
The Teaching Committee
is responsible for the curriculum,
while the Service Committee
arranges for the selection of the students.
This is the “Meet Together” Gallery.
Here you’ll learn how
the Governing Body is helping God’s people
to meet together “to incite
to love and fine works,” as directed
at Hebrews 10:24, 25.
How is the headquarters staff
at Warwick filling that need?
Because we keep growing,
there’s an ongoing need
to build new Kingdom Halls
and to renovate existing ones.
The Publishing Committee of the Governing Body
directs where Kingdom Halls will be built
and makes funds available to the branches.
The Publishing Committee
works closely with the branch office,
and its Local Design/Construction Department
carries out the work.
But where do these hardworking
brothers and sisters come from?
The Personnel Committee
appoints all construction servants
for assignments in their home country
or in a foreign land.
Have you worked on a theocratic building project?
Take our survey, and let us know.
Some Kingdom Halls are located in areas
where there is little or no electricity,
but that doesn’t stop us from meeting together.
The Publishing Committee
has arranged for a custom-built, portable sound system
to be used in these areas.
The unity player has a battery
that can be recharged by its solar panel
or with a built-in hand crank.
It’s a wonderful provision
that helps our brothers and sisters benefit more
from their congregation meetings.
This is the “Take In Spiritual Food” Gallery.
Can you guess what design we used?
That’s right, a dining table.
Here you’ll learn how the Governing Body
fulfills the Scriptural commission
at Luke 12:42
to feed God’s people spiritually.
To accomplish this,
millions of Bibles, books,
and other publications
need to be prepared, translated, and printed.
In addition,
a regular flow of material is released online.
Translators around the world
keep in close contact with Translation Services
—a headquarters department
that’s supervised by the Writing Committee.
Do you have a favorite publication?
Much more is involved than just the writing.
The section “From Start to Finish”
outlines 11 steps
that are taken to produce the final product.
What about our online spiritual food?
Each month, we look forward
to a new JW Broadcasting® program.
Once the Teaching Committee approves a video idea,
Audio/Video Services researches the subject
and prepares a script for final approval.
Approved scripts and storyboards
are assigned
to video production teams around the world.
This gives our videos an international flavor.
Well, we’ve come
to our final gallery, “Make Disciples.”
Here you’ll learn how
the Governing Body is helping us
to fulfill the Scriptural commission
at Matthew 28:19
to “make disciples of people
of all [the] nations, baptizing them.”
The command to preach can be daunting,
especially in certain lands.
So how are we meeting that challenge?
The Service Committee oversees
the preaching work worldwide.
They help all to have a share according to their ability
—some as congregation publishers,
others as full-time evangelizers.
Additionally, special preaching campaigns
and public witnessing
have resulted in many new Bible studies.
At times, though,
our religious freedom
is opposed by secular authorities.
So the Coordinators’ Committee supervises
the World Headquarters Legal Department.
Many courts have handed down favorable decisions.
Still, we must continue
to defend our right to preach the good news.
Our online tools are also
a huge help in making disciples.
This counter shows the average rate
at which people worldwide
are logging on to jw.org.®
Each day, some 250 Bible studies
are requested online.
Schools also help us to make disciples.
We have the Pioneer Service School,
the School for Kingdom Evangelizers,
and Gilead School.
Have you attended one of these schools?
Let us know.
Well, as we come to the end of our tour,
we hope you enjoyed some highlights
from this Faith in Action Museum.
What we’ve seen here reminds us
that now and always
Jehovah’s people are a people of faith
—faith in action!
As Brother Sanderson highlighted,
the organization’s actions speak volumes
of the faith of Jehovah’s people.
And we wanted to share
one more example of faith in action.
In Africa, a new provision has made it easier
for our brothers and sisters
to access spiritual food.
Some of the electronic information
that had been translated and provided
for the brothers in sub-Saharan Africa
was essentially unavailable to them.
There are many areas in Mozambique
that do not have Internet access,
and in some parts
there is no cell phone coverage.
So we started investigating
what it would take to have a 24-hour-a-day,
7-day-a-week satellite channel
dedicated to JW Broadcasting®.
When the announcement was made to our congregation
about the JW satellite channel,
our brothers and sisters
were very happy about the announcement.
Our organization has a lot of experience
distributing video via the Internet,
but to distribute it on the satellite was entirely new,
so we had to do a lot of research.
We don’t have our own satellite up in space.
We rent a channel on a satellite
that covers sub-Saharan Africa.
What is required from the brothers is
to have a satellite dish and a decoder.
This will allow them
to view the channel with no additional cost.
The brothers that are invited
to come here are trained.
First, how to set up the dish.
Second, how to set up the decoder
and learn how to adjust the dish properly
so that it works well.
Then, we teach them how to record the programs
with the goal that they can watch it
with the brothers and sisters in the congregation.
Our satellite channel is set up to transmit
one video track and 16 audio tracks.
This gives us the ability to broadcast our videos
in 16 languages.
We consulted
with the Translation Services Department,
and so these are the 16 languages
that give us the greatest audience
of our brothers in Africa.
We wrote new software that takes
any new video that comes to JW Broadcasting®
and mixes the 16 languages
of video together into a single video file
and delivers that to our satellite provider.
The Governing Body
lovingly approved
for the rental cost of the satellite channel
to be covered
from contributions to the worldwide work.
So there’s no expense to the brothers
in Africa to receive the program.
We broadcast over
a single satellite channel for most of our needs.
But occasionally, we use a second channel
when we broadcast live events, like conventions
or branch visits.
When the representative
from world headquarters gives his talk
from Bethel, it is transmitted to us
live through the satellite.
This makes us feel like we
are right there at Bethel.
We are very happy.
The most recent live event
that we broadcasted originated in France.
It was the release of the revised edition
of the New World Translation,
so this was very exciting.
And brothers and sisters
that attended conventions
in ten different branch territories in Africa
were able to tie in
to this broadcast that originated in France,
using the satellite.
In our branch territory,
we are arranging
for all new or remodeled Kingdom Halls
to have satellite equipment
as part of the standard audio/video package.
We were very happy
when we received the satellite dish
because we could see that now
we are really close
to the brothers on the Governing Body.
The satellite channel is excellent!
This provision touches our hearts.
The deaf all over the country
benefited from the special talk
as it was interpreted
into Malawian Sign Language,
showing that Jehovah truly loves deaf people.
And this helps us
to strengthen our relationship with Jehovah.
We hope and pray
that access to the JW satellite feed
becomes available
to as many of our brothers and sisters
as possible in sub-Saharan Africa.
As we could see,
the organization prioritizes
the needs of Jehovah’s people.
And as it does, it finds a modest solution
that can best serve the needs
of as many people as possible.
As we discussed earlier in the program,
modesty is equally important on an individual level.
But there are times when we have to ask ourselves
if we’re confusing modesty
with our own imperfect view of ourselves.
Meet Juan Cayul from Chile.
He’s of the Mapuche tribe
—a tribe which has faced
discrimination over the years.
Because of the discrimination,
some may be reluctant to use their language,
Mapudungún, in public.
This became a challenge for Juan,
since he wanted to give
his best in the ministry for Jehovah.
Mapudungún means ‘the speech of my land.’
It’s a beautiful and expressive language,
and it’s the language of my heart.
When I was 12 years old, I went to live
with my grandfather and my uncle’s family
so that I could study at a nearby school.
My cousins spoke Mapudungún a lot,
which made me really happy.
When I saw that some of my classmates
didn’t understand their schoolwork,
especially in math class,
I would try to help them out.
That’s when I started to think about becoming
a math teacher so that I could really help others.
But the head teacher told me
that because I was speaking
Mapudungún and because
I was helping my classmates,
she was going to lower my grades.
When my father saw my grades, he was furious.
He accused me of being lazy and not studying.
He withdrew me from school,
and I went back home to Tromén.
My dream of becoming a teacher
was shattered.
Because my dad had suffered so much
as a victim of discrimination,
he told us that we
were not to speak Mapudungún.
When I think about everything that happened,
it makes me very sad.
Years later, I met Sylvia
who was Mapuche like me.
She proved to be a sensitive and loving person.
We spoke Mapudungún together,
and that helped to relieve the bitterness
I felt in my heart.
Some time later, I learned about someone else
who made me feel loved and valued—Jehovah.
That changed my life.
All my pain disappeared
once I got to know Jehovah.
My wife and I studied the Bible
with the Witnesses in Spanish.
And so when I started to preach and teach,
I used Spanish too.
One day, I was out in service,
and as we approached a house
an elderly Mapuche woman came to the door.
She was scared.
So straight away I greeted her in Mapudungún.
She invited us inside and spoke with us.
That was the first time
I had spoken about Jehovah in my mother tongue.
On our way back, I was deep in thought,
praying to Jehovah
about how to help the Mapuche people.
Many years passed
before I saw an answer to my prayers.
Then one day after the meeting, I received
an invitation to be a speaker at the first assembly
to include talks in Mapudungún.
But I didn’t want to accept the assignment.
I felt worthless because
of all the discrimination I had endured.
So
I prayed again and again to Jehovah
and began to meditate a lot.
Jehovah was now giving me
an answer to my prayers.
He sees our true value.
I was so happy, so very happy.
I understood that Jehovah loved me
and cared for me
and that he would continue to help me.
In just a few years, not one,
but several Mapudungún congregations were formed.
And now my wife and I,
as well as our two children,
serve in Mapudungún-language congregations.
I’ve been assisting with Mapudungún translation
for more than seven years now.
When I tell the brothers and sisters
who work with me at the translation office
about my childhood dream of becoming a teacher,
they tell me, “You’re our teacher now.”
I want to say to my brothers
and sisters around the world:
“Don’t put yourselves down.
“You are precious; you are precious to Jehovah.
He will always help you.”
It took courage for Juan
to overcome his fear of discrimination.
In our lives as Christians,
we can imitate Juan’s example
of courage in many different ways.
When we do,
let’s remember the words of Joshua 1:9:
“Have I not commanded you?
“Be courageous and strong.
“Do not be struck with terror or fear,
for Jehovah your God
is with you wherever you go.”
With that scripture in mind,
please enjoy the music video
for this month entitled
Be Courageous and Strong.
It’s dark outside.
To start the day,
She humbly starts to pray
For her kids at school
And the brotherhood:
“Father, help us be faithful.”
When things make it hard to cope,
She never thinks of losing hope,
Never stops being kind.
And that song—it’s always on her mind:
‘I will make you strong.
Do not be afraid.
I will be with you.
I will be your aid.’
Be courageous and strong.
It’s her favorite song.
And “he will make you firm,
And he will make you strong.”
Time to get on her feet—
Try to make ends meet—
Never sure what to expect.
Her true friends out there
Really show her they care,
So she never needs to fret.
She’ll soar on wings
To rise up high,
Like eagles in the sky.
All the roles she plays—
So little time each day—
And in her heart, she starts to pray.
Aching feet and tired hands—
She tries the very best she can.
But there’s strength she can find
In that song that’s always on her mind:
‘I will make you strong.
Do not be afraid.
I will be with you.
I will be your aid.’
Be courageous and strong.
It’s her favorite song.
And “he will make you firm,
And he will make you strong.”
We’ve seen many examples of modesty
on the program this month.
First, the McConnell sisters helped us appreciate
that true family happiness
is only possible when we
follow Jehovah’s principles.
Modest parents know their limitations
and will rely on Jehovah’s guidance.
After the talk,
we saw how a young brother’s modesty
protected him from sinning against Jehovah.
Next, we saw examples
of organizational achievements,
all of which require modesty.
We saw this not only
in the Faith in Action Museum at Warwick
but also with the satellite provision
for JW Broadcasting®
in sub-Saharan Africa.
And we need to be careful not to confuse
our imperfect view of ourselves with modesty.
Instead, we should do all we can
to support Jehovah’s work.
And as we do,
Jehovah will support us,
as this month’s music video highlighted.
And later this month,
you’ll find an exciting report
on Video on Demand.
It’s about the work of the Publishing Committee
of the Governing Body.
So tune in again for that.
To conclude,
let’s visit our brothers
and sisters in Tasmania, Australia.
Tasmania is Australia’s smallest state
and is an island located about 240 kilometers,
or 150 miles, south of the mainland.
Despite its small land mass,
it’s known for its very diverse landscape
featuring beautiful yet rugged mountain,
lake, and coastal landscapes.
The central plateau
is a prominent feature of Tasmania,
thanks to its more than 4,000 lakes
of glacial origin.
This island is home to close to 1,800 publishers
in 22 congregations.
And this is the Huonville Congregation.
They care for Australia’s southernmost territory.
Although their territory is vast
and many of the publishers
are advanced in years,
the congregation is known
to assist neighboring congregations
with their territories.
In 2016,
the Huonville Congregation
was happy to see
their Kingdom Hall get renovated.
And when visiting brothers
come to give a public talk in Huonville,
it’s not unusual that they get
a box of local produce as a gift.
Our brothers and sisters
in the Huonville Congregation
send us their warm Christian love,
and we love them very much.
Until next month,
this is JW Broadcasting
from the World Headquarters
of Jehovah’s Witnesses.