You know,
there are many people today
who say that we’re not living
in the time of the end.
They say: “The world is just
the same as it’s always been.
There are no real changes
that have taken place.”
But, of course,
we know they’re deceiving themselves.
Never before have
so many people around the globe
openly practiced and flaunted
sexual immorality,
not just among themselves
but they’re seeing
that it’s brought into the homes
by means of Internet,
television, and other means.
Never before has man had the power
to decimate entire populations
by dropping just one bomb
or by means of chemical warfare.
Never before has there been
such widespread lack of love
and of natural affection
that results in the death of children.
It’s interesting that some calculate
that over one billion abortions
have taken place since 1980.
That’s really something.
That’s just about the population of China
—if you can imagine.
And that is something that’s accepted;
it’s commonplace in our day.
So some people think,
‘Well, things haven’t changed.’
But is that true?
No, quite to the contrary.
And something else
that we’re fully aware of
is that people around the earth
are making a garbage dump
out of the planet that we live on
—polluting the air, the seas,
the land.
And yet, some still insist
that things haven’t changed.
Now, why is it?
Why do people have that attitude?
Well, part of it lies in
what the Scriptures tell us,
what Paul wrote
at 2 Corinthians 4:3, 4.
And there it says that Satan
‘blinds the minds of the unbelievers.’
And the “unbelievers”
are not just atheists.
The “unbelievers” are found
throughout the churches of Christendom.
They don’t believe
—really believe—
what the Bible has to say
about prophecy,
about morality,
or that God is really going
to clean up this planet
and that it’s going to be
a wonderful new world
of peace and happiness.
And so to help people
understand these things,
we go out and we preach.
We tell them
about what Matthew 24 says
and Mark 13
and Luke 21 and 2 Timothy 3
—that we’re living in the time of the end.
But there is something
we have to remember
if we get a little bit discouraged
when people don’t respond
as we feel they should
to all of the evidence
that we see and we appreciate.
The Bible indicates very clearly
that many people would not see the sign;
they would not accept
what the Bible has to say.
And what’s most interesting about that
is that the people who ignore
and who deny the sign
that we’re living in the time of the end
are part of the sign themselves
—what they do and the way they think.
Turn to Second Peter
—2 Peter chapter 3.
And we’ll read verses 3 and 4
and the first line in verse 5
—2 Peter 3:3, 4
and the first line in verse 5.
Peter wrote: “First of all know this,
that in the last days,”
so this is something Peter is saying
would happen during our time,
“ridiculers will come with their ridicule,
“proceeding according to their own desires
“and saying:
‘Where is this promised presence of his?
“‘Why, from the day
our forefathers fell asleep in death,
“‘all things are continuing exactly
as they were from creation’s beginning.’”
And then the reason for it
is given in the next line:
“For they deliberately ignore this fact.”
Well, here the fact was that they
ignored the Flood of Noah’s day.
The fact for us today is that they
ignore what the Bible clearly says
or what Jesus said would be
the sign of the last days.
So they don’t realize it,
but they’re part of the fulfillment.
What contributes to an unbelieving attitude?
Well, one of the things
is what we could call gradualism.
The Watchtower
of January 15, 2014, paragraph 30,
or page 30,
paragraph 11 stated the following:
“It seems
that the more familiar a situation is,
“the less people
are inclined to pay attention to it.
“A steady decline in the morality
“of society in general
may seem less shocking
“than a sudden, unexpected change
in the behavior of a close acquaintance.”
And then it says:
“Nevertheless,
this gradual decay
of morality is dangerous.”
And isn’t it true
that most of us were raised
in an environment
that was not so good?
There were immoral things
taking place around us, wars, crime.
And so people get to the point
where they accept it as normal.
And as it escalates,
it really doesn’t impress
on them that ‘No!
‘Times have changed.
They’re becoming
far worse than ever before.’
Gradual decay of morality is dangerous.
It makes me think of an illustration
about how to boil a frog.
If you heat up a pot
and you have the water boiling
and drop a frog into it,
what’s going to happen?
He’s out of there;
he’s not going to stay.
That frog isn’t stupid.
He hits the water,
and it’s terribly hot, and out he jumps.
But if you fill the pot with cool water,
drop the frog in,
and then
gradually (little by little) you heat it up
until it gets to the boiling point,
he’s cooked!
And that’s what’s happening
in the world today.
The gradualism is not perceived
by people in the world,
but they’re being cooked.
It’s getting hot.
And so we know that wicked men
are going to continue to increase
—impostors,
scoffing at the truth.
World conditions are escalating;
they’re getting worse constantly.
But they’re going to have to deal
with the Creator and his judgment.
And there are three Psalms
I’d like to just mention briefly
that I find very interesting
that tie in nicely
with the wickedness of the world
and what Jehovah will do.
Psalm 10:4:
“In his haughtiness,
the wicked man makes no investigation;
“all his thoughts are:
‘There is no God.’”
Psalm 12:8:
“The wicked walk around unrestrained
because the sons of men
promote depravity.”
That could’ve been
this morning’s headlines
in The New York Times.
And the last,
Psalm 92:7:
“When the wicked sprout like weeds
“and all the wrongdoers flourish,
it is that they
may be annihilated forever.”
And to that we say:
“Amen.
So be it!”