Welcome to another edition
of JW Broadcasting!
Have you ever felt discouraged
due to circumstances beyond your control?
We’ll discuss how we can still have joy
despite our limitations.
And we’ll see examples,
both Biblical and modern day,
that will encourage us
to keep giving Jehovah our best.
Jonah had faced several reasons
to become discouraged and give up.
How did Jehovah help him carry on
with courage and faith?
And what lessons from his experience
can we apply to problems we face today?
Can we change
our personality for the better?
We can with Jehovah’s spirit
and diligent effort.
This brother describes
how far his personality and lifestyle
took him away from Jehovah.
He explains how he regained
a clean conscience
and freeness of speech.
Jehovah can turn tragic events
caused by man
into open doors of activity
for His loyal Witnesses.
In this report from Greece,
we’ll learn how our brothers
are bringing spiritual comfort
to refugees.
You’re watching the June 2017 edition
of JW Broadcasting!
There are many exciting things happening
in Jehovah’s organization.
Why, month after month, we read articles,
watch videos, and hear personal experiences
about our brothers and sisters
who are doing more for Jehovah.
They are serving where
the need is greater or reaching out
for the School for Kingdom Evangelizers.
They are working
on construction, renovation,
maintenance of Kingdom Halls,
or other theocratic projects.
No doubt,
many of you watching this program
are excitedly looking forward
to expanding your ministry
in one of these areas.
We encourage you to do so.
You can be assured
that you will receive much fulfillment
and many blessings from Jehovah.
On the other hand,
there are others
who are watching this program
who may feel discouraged
because their circumstances
may seem to limit
their being as involved as they would like.
What are some of these circumstances?
These may include our age, our health,
our economic situation,
or our physical limitations.
For some of us,
perhaps our upbringing
or past errors
we have made in our life
may cause us to feel
that we are limited
as to what we can do
for Jehovah.
As we know well,
focusing on our limitations
can affect our joy,
causing discouragement.
What can we do?
There are many examples
in the Scriptures of men and women
who had circumstances
beyond their control
that seemed to limit how much
they could do for Jehovah.
Others had to deal with the effects
of their upbringing and family life
or with serious errors they made.
Did they allow themselves to be limited
by their circumstances or their past?
How did Jehovah feel about them?
How does Jehovah feel about us?
That is what we are going to discuss
in this month’s broadcast,
which has the theme
“Are You Defined by Your Circumstances?”
Let’s start by looking at some
who could have let
their circumstances limit them.
Consider first the example
of Joseph in the book of Genesis.
Now, Joseph faced injustice at its worst.
His situation was especially hurtful
since it was initially brought on by those
who should have been closest to him
—his family!
As a slave in Egypt
and later as a prisoner,
Joseph was indeed limited
in what he could do.
How might Joseph have reacted?
Well,
Joseph could have become so preoccupied
with what he could not do
that he lost sight of what he could do.
Did Joseph let his circumstances
paralyze his life?
No!
He chose to make
the best of his situation.
In fact,
note what Joseph did
while serving as a slave
in Potiphar’s house
if we turn together
to Genesis 39:4:
“Joseph kept finding favor in his eyes,
“and he became his personal attendant.
“So he appointed him over his house,
and he put him
in charge of all that was his.”
Joseph worked diligently
within the limitations
of his circumstances.
He took a similar approach while in prison.
Joseph focused on what he could do
despite suffering the effects of injustice.
As a second example,
consider Hezekiah.
Hezekiah is one
who might easily have felt
that he was defined by his upbringing.
Look at the terrible example
that was set by his father, Ahaz,
as recorded in 2 Kings chapter 16.
Second Kings chapter 16,
and notice what verse 3 says about Ahaz:
“Instead, he walked in the way
of the kings of Israel,
“and he even made his own son
pass through the fire,
“following the detestable practices
of the nations
that Jehovah had driven out
from before the Israelites.”
Hezekiah’s father did detestable things
in opposition to Jehovah.
But Hezekiah showed
that he was not the helpless victim
of a poor parental example.
What did he do?
Well, turn in your Bibles
to 2 Kings chapter 18
and notice verse 3,
what it says about Hezekiah:
“He kept doing what was right
in Jehovah’s eyes,
just as David his forefather
had done.”
Verse 5 says of Hezekiah:
“There was no one like him
among all the kings of Judah.”
He became fully involved in true worship.
Verses 6 and 7 say that Hezekiah
‘held fast to Jehovah,
and Jehovah proved to be with him.’
How encouraging
Hezekiah’s example is for us!
We can choose to be loyal to Jehovah
and do much in our worship of Jehovah,
even if we did not grow up in a family
that served Jehovah fully.
We are not helpless victims
of our environment.
Hezekiah’s example
reassures us that our past
does not have to control our future.
As a third example,
consider the apostle Paul.
He did not let his own past mistakes
involving religious prejudice and violence
stop him from giving his all to Jehovah.
How did Paul feel about his past?
Well, let’s read together
at 1 Corinthians 15:9:
“For I am the least of the apostles,
“and I am not worthy
of being called an apostle,
because I persecuted
the congregation of God.”
“I am the least of the apostles.”
Later, when writing to the Ephesians
as recorded at Ephesians 3:8,
he calls himself
“less than the least of all holy ones.”
Finally, at 1 Timothy 1:15,
he now calls himself
the “foremost” of all sinners.
Yes,
Paul’s prior treatment of the congregation
weighed heavily upon him.
Could Paul have reasoned
that he was damaged?
Could he have reasoned that his past
limited what he could do for Jehovah?
He could have,
but Paul did not do that.
He poured himself out
for the congregation.
Why, Paul was privileged to write
more books and letters
in the Christian Greek Scriptures
than anyone else.
He demonstrated
an outstanding zeal for the ministry.
Paul did not let his conduct in the past
dictate what he could do for Jehovah.
And there are many other examples as well.
For example,
are we in a difficult economic situation?
The account in 2 Corinthians chapter 8
tells us about the Macedonians.
Paul says that they were in deep poverty.
Yet they begged to have a financial share
in the relief work.
Are we older in years?
We may think of Anna.
The account at Luke 2:36-38
tells us that she was 84 years old
and that her husband had died
after just seven years of marriage.
Yet,
“she was never missing from the temple.”
She rendered
‘sacred service day and night.’
What lessons do we learn
from these accounts?
Our dear brothers and sisters
in Bible times were just like us.
Many were in circumstances
that they would not have chosen.
Yet,
they did not let their circumstances
or their past define them.
They joyfully did what they could
within the limits of their situation.
And these are just a few examples.
There are many others in the Bible.
Why not make it a personal study project
to research faithful ones
who were in circumstances
similar to yours?
How did they stay involved
in Jehovah’s work?
We are sure
that you will be greatly encouraged.
In fact,
let’s look at an example
of how you might do this
with a familiar Bible character.
In this dramatization,
a brother and two sisters
use their personal study time
to learn about Jonah.
Sometimes, as we know,
Jonah was discouraged
by events beyond his control;
at other times it was
because of his own failings.
Does Jonah’s experience relate
to what they are feeling?
And how do the lessons
Jonah learned help them
to not remain trapped
in their circumstances?
But John, there’s still plenty
you can do
in the congregation.
Sure, that sounds good.
But I’m no longer
a ministerial servant.
Why did I let my zeal
for the ministry cool off?
I know what the brothers
must think of me now.
Hello?
Oh, good morning.
My name is Jane.
How are you?
Not bad, thanks.
I know you may not be interested,
but I have this tract
I’d like to leave with you . . .
“You may not be interested?”
Where did that come from?
Not my best presentation,
but it didn’t seem like she wanted
to talk more anyway.
Well, what does that mean?
It may be manageable,
but long term,
given your other conditions,
you’re looking at possibly
some further tests . . .
Manageable?
Long term?
Oh, Jehovah,
how can I do this by myself?
Of course Jehovah values you.
Try to think of someone in the Bible
who may have felt like you do,
like Jonah.
Jonah?
Felt like I do?
“What comes to your mind
when you think of Jonah?
Do you think of him
as a disobedient prophet?”
“Reluctant to obey Jehovah’s command,
“Jonah boarded a ship that carried him
farther and farther away
from his assignment.”
“Did Jonah’s recent actions
“disqualify him
from ever again serving God
in an official capacity?”
He sure could have thought so.
I know I do.
“No,
“Jehovah mercifully and lovingly
renewed the prophet’s commission.”
So if Jehovah didn’t see Jonah
as a total failure,
then what must he think of me?
First Samuel 16:7:
“For the way man sees
is not the way God sees.”
“Jonah did not see Nineveh
as Jehovah did.”
Well,
with all that they were doing,
how could he view them any differently?
But the account says:
‘When God saw they had turned back
from their evil ways,
‘he reconsidered the calamity,
and he did not bring it.’
“Despite the people’s badness,
“Jehovah cared about them.
“He values human life
“and the potential
that each individual has
for repenting and learning
to do what is right.”
Well, of course that’s true.
Why didn’t Jonah see that?
But am I seeing people
the way Jehovah does?
Am I assuming they won’t listen
and then not giving my best?
How can I know
how a person will respond?
‘Jonah learned to be merciful.
Will we?’
Matthew 5:7 says:
“Happy are the merciful,
since they will be shown mercy.”
“Then Jonah prayed to Jehovah his God
“from the belly of the fish, and he said:
“‘Out of my distress
“‘I called out to Jehovah,
“‘and he answered me.
“‘Out of the depths of the Grave
I cried for help.
You heard my voice.’”
God heard Jonah and delivered him.
But I can’t expect a miracle.
“Then my prayer came in to you,
into your holy temple.”
“My prayer.”
“My prayer came in to you.”
Jonah didn’t know
if Jehovah would rescue him,
but he prayed in faith
that Jehovah cared.
“But as for me,
“with the voice of thanksgiving
“I will sacrifice to you.
“What I have vowed, I will pay.
Salvation is from Jehovah.”
As long as I still can,
I’ll keep sacrificing to God.
Salvation is from Jehovah!
Like those in our video,
do you sometimes feel as Jonah did?
Can you apply the lessons
from Jonah’s account
to better see God’s mercy
in your life?
A personal failing
discouraged our brother.
But like Jonah,
he realized Jehovah still valued him.
Our young sister
reinvigorated her ministry
after meditating on the way Jehovah
mercifully viewed the Ninevites.
And our sister was determined
to imitate Jonah’s faith
that God hears our prayers
about circumstances beyond our control.
Sometimes, however,
our circumstances
are only perceived barriers
to doing more for Jehovah.
For example, some may feel limited
by economic concerns
if they reach out for special privileges.
In the Netherlands,
many brothers and sisters
assisted with the construction
of the Swifterbant Assembly Hall.
Some had to make adjustments
to be able to work on this project.
Listen, however, to their comments
on the blessings they received
and what their goals are
now that the project is completed.
In the Netherlands,
there was a need for a new,
suitable Assembly Hall,
which could accommodate almost all
of the 300 congregations
of Jehovah’s Witnesses.
Additional building ground
was acquired next to the existing hall,
so that a second,
completely new hall could be constructed.
More than 200 volunteers
worked on this project.
What challenges did they face?
And what blessings did they receive?
We had to sell our house
and close our business.
It’s a step into the unknown.
I had to quit my job.
It was exciting to step
out of my comfort zone
and rely completely on Jehovah.
Everything is structured, organized.
That is why things run smoothly.
That doesn’t come naturally to me.
We were invited to come
and work in the kitchen.
I love to cook at home.
I’m really fond of it.
What was my assignment?
Doing the dishes.
Working on yourself,
your Christian personality,
and cooperating
with your brothers and sisters
—that has everlasting value.
It was wonderful training for the future
when we will be building together
in Paradise.
You realize that everyone
sacrifices something and becomes happier.
No one regrets their decision.
That Jehovah takes into account
your personal makeup,
that he is patient with us.
I’ve really learned how to work together
in a theocratic arrangement
and still have fun.
You can work on yourself all day long
and therefore be able to improve.
I really learned to study more
and to read the Bible more often.
Because we worked together so closely,
you got to know each other very well
and I really started
to love and appreciate people.
We really came to appreciate
that every brother and sister
has this beautiful inner person.
Visitors and contractors
were always very surprised
that there were so many women
working at the construction site.
It’s great working with sisters.
I have a construction background,
and communication with men
can be really up front.
That doesn’t work with sisters.
You just have to be calm,
talk, and listen.
I had to work on a lift platform,
but that was kind of a problem
because I’m afraid of heights.
The brothers were so kind
to seal the sides up completely
so that I could not look down.
It was fun working together
on that lift platform.
We called it our little flat.
The atmosphere was amazing,
and we all had a great time.
Now we work in the kitchen
at the Swifterbant School Facility
—a real privilege.
We’ve been trained
to cook during construction,
but if needed,
I’ll even do the dishes as well.
I’ll never work five days again.
Now I work three days,
and since July 1st,
I started pioneering.
That’s just great.
He was offered a job.
He could even choose between two jobs.
Now he works three days a week,
which always seemed impossible.
Eventually, we were
in Swifterbant for one month only.
Then we went to Mozambique
for three months.
Then for five months
to Swifterbant again.
Then three months in South Africa.
Bethel called and assigned us
to Congo (Kinshasa).
All the volunteers who helped
to make a success of this project—
Well, they had to give up a lot.
As a result,
we can enjoy this beautiful hall.
It’s amazing to be here.
It’s great to be encouraged
and to be strengthened for the ministry.
If you think about it,
every day we have
around 700 new brothers and sisters.
That means every three days
we could fill a hall like this
with new brothers and sisters.
These kinds of halls
are really needed worldwide
in order to provide education
to all those additional brothers and sisters.
It’s so faith-strengthening to be here.
Words cannot express it.
I feel so united, so warm, peaceful.
It’s so wonderful to be able
to serve Jehovah together.
Did you notice a common thread
in the volunteers’ comments?
Any economic concerns they may have had
just faded into the background,
didn’t they?
They reached out to help,
and in turn Jehovah helped them.
In fact, the Assembly Hall project
was finished at a lower cost
and a year earlier than originally planned.
And did you note that after the project,
some who previously felt
they couldn’t pioneer
reduced their secular workdays
and are now doing
what they thought was out of reach?
It brings us joy to see
so many making adjustments
and reaching out to do more
for the organization,
and in turn they experience
something they’ll never forget.
Now,
we’ve considered examples of those
who did not let
their circumstances hinder them
from giving their all to Jehovah.
But another question is:
How does Jehovah
view his faithful servants
despite their limitations?
Now, I’ve often thought
about the example of John the Baptizer.
As we know, he was arrested
shortly after Jesus started his ministry.
John could have felt
that he was no longer of use
to Jehovah or the work.
Yet, as recorded at Matthew 11:11,
Jesus said about John:
“Among those born of women,
there has not been raised up
anyone greater than John the Baptist.”
Jehovah’s and Jesus’ view of John
was not based
on the man’s circumstances
of being in prison.
Their view of John was based on
who he was on the inside
and on his relationship with Jehovah.
Jehovah did not focus on the limitations.
In Jehovah’s eyes,
John was great.
He was still a faithful servant
doing the best that he could,
and that was all that really mattered.
Another example
that may come to your mind
is that of King David.
As we know,
King David committed serious sins.
Yet,
David repented for his sins,
and there is no record
that he repeated them.
How did Jehovah view him?
Did Jehovah see David as damaged,
as a man who would always be
limited in serving him?
Notice Jehovah’s words
directed to King Jeroboam
at 1 Kings 14:8:
“But you have not become
like my servant David,
“who kept my commandments
“and who walked after me
with all his heart,
doing only what was right in my eyes.”
Jehovah viewed David
as a special servant.
He says that he
“kept my commandments.”
He did
“what was right in my eyes.”
That’s what Jehovah remembered.
How encouraging that is for us!
If we have repented
of our past mistakes
and set matters straight
to the best of our circumstances,
we too can be assured
that Jehovah loves us dearly.
He appreciates whatever we can do
in our worship of him.
So, what’s the point?
Well, our past
or our present circumstances
do not define our value before Jehovah.
Our Father loves us for who we are,
and he values our efforts
as we do the best
that we can to serve him.
Why do you think it is important
that we strive to see ourselves
as Jehovah does?
Because we can weaken,
discourage, or limit ourselves
if we see ourselves only
in the framework of our circumstances.
May we work hard not to do that.
What does Jehovah see
when he looks
at his faithful servants today?
Well, turn, please,
to 1 Samuel 16:7.
And the setting is
that Samuel was about to go
to anoint the next king of Israel;
and he goes to the house of Jesse;
and Jesse lines up all of his sons,
except for David,
who is still out in the field;
and Samuel walks in
and he sees Eliab.
And based on what he sees,
Samuel concludes that this surely must be
the next king of Israel.
Yet, note what Jehovah saw.
Please read with me 1 Samuel 16:7:
“But Jehovah said to Samuel:
“‘Do not pay attention
to his appearance and how tall he is,
“‘for I have rejected him.
“‘For the way man sees
is not the way God sees,
“‘because mere man sees
what appears to the eyes,
but Jehovah sees into the heart.’”
That’s the way Jehovah sees.
He does not look
at our outward appearance and our abilities;
he sees into our hearts.
He sees what we would be doing
if all of the limitations
were lifted off of us.
Why, just the fact
that we keep going,
that we keep putting
one foot in front of the other,
endears us to Jehovah.
We understand the truth
of that statement,
and we all may agree
that this is how
Jehovah views his people.
However, we may have
a hard time convincing ourselves
if this really applies to me.
Have you ever wondered:
‘Does Jehovah really see me?
‘Does he see what’s in my heart
and value my desire to do more for him?’
The answer is yes.
In fact, Jehovah has already seen
what is in your heart.
Think about this:
Why are you watching this program?
Why do you care about spiritual things?
Why are you, perhaps,
the only one in your family
who is a dedicated,
baptized servant of Jehovah?
Or why are you, perhaps,
the only one at your place of employment
or the only one near where you live
who’s serving Jehovah?
Is it because you are
so much more studious
or smarter than everyone else?
No!
Haggai 2:7 tells us
that Jehovah
“will shake all the nations,
and the precious things
of all the nations will come in.”
John 6:44 says
that ‘no man can come to Jesus
unless the Father draws him.’
Jeremiah 31:3, Jehovah says:
“I have loved you with an everlasting love.
That is why I have drawn you.”
So again, why are you serving Jehovah?
Because Jehovah loves you.
Jehovah drew you.
As he was shaking the nations,
he looked down into your heart
and he saw something very precious
and he drew you to him.
He said,
“I want to draw this person to my Son.
“I want to draw this person to me.
I love this person.”
Jehovah drew you,
not because you have
perfect circumstances,
but because of your heart
and because he loves you.
He greatly appreciates
that his servants give their best to him.
But how do we know
that Jehovah really sees each one of us,
no matter where we are?
Consider an example:
Thousands of refugees who faced
severe hardships in their home countries
have sought shelter in parts of Europe.
Watch how Jehovah
has lovingly assured them
that they’re not alone
by satisfying their spiritual thirst.
Welcome to Greece!
We really feel that Jehovah is blessing us
by opening a large door
of opportunities to preach the good news
to the many refugees
who are streaming into the country.
For this reason, the brothers
immediately informed us of the situation
and we directed the bodies of elders
to concentrate on the harbors,
especially in Chios.
The brothers were willing to work in shifts
—24 hours a day.
The refugee shelters in our area
only have families with children
and are located near a military airport.
Whenever military planes flew overhead
and the children would see and hear them,
they would immediately run
and try to hide because they were afraid.
They sought protection
from the tragic conditions
they had experienced during warfare.
This impressed upon us
how greatly they needed
the comforting message of the good news,
so we felt the urge to approach them.
Therefore,
the Service Department arranged
for four language classes
to be held for the brothers.
We try to speak to people
in a language quite different from our own.
At times, we might think:
‘Will these people understand us?
Will we be able to reach
their heart with these basic truths?’
Something that helped me not to hesitate
to approach these people
despite the language barrier
is what our teachers told us
in the language class:
“Go and talk to them.
“Show them things from the Bible.
“Even if you don’t say things perfectly,
they will understand you.”
After we received permission
from the branch office,
we also printed thousands of tracts,
since we did not have enough.
This whole effort created
an atmosphere of enthusiasm.
I’m deeply moved when I see how lovingly
Jehovah cares for these people
who have never had the opportunity
to hear the Kingdom message
that gives them a future and a hope.
It was exciting
for them to hear that we have
a Bible-based video in their language.
We told them that the problems, calamities,
and the terrible war they had experienced
were not punishment from God,
but the result of the influence
Satan the Devil exercises
over this system of things.
And this provided
a good answer to their question.
On a return visit,
after two days,
a refugee girl said something very touching:
“Now I understand why
we have to go through all this.
It’s very difficult,
but it’s not God’s fault.”
On another occasion,
Gardinia, a refugee woman
who showed interest, told us:
“Since meeting you,
I have a purpose in life.
“I have a reason to live.
Until now, I was just waiting to die.”
A refugee approached
the Arabic witnessing cart,
and we read Revelation 21:4 to him.
He said, “Please,
could you read that to me once again?”
So we read it a second time.
He replied,
“May I have a Bible of my own?”
So we gave him a Bible.
Then he said,
“Would you please show me
the sentence you read in my Bible?”
So we marked the verse for him.
And on the way back
to our home at about 11 o’clock at night,
on the same road, at a well-lit point,
we saw that same refugee
sitting on the sidewalk reading the Bible.
About two and a half years ago,
I met Moustafa.
He attended the meetings
and made speedy progress.
Moustafa was baptized a few months
before the refugees started pouring in.
We do not believe
that this was a coincidence.
He would say,
“I want to speak about Jehovah,
but I can’t do that
in the Greek language.”
When I can speak to people who are refugees
—just as I am a refugee—
in my own language,
this is a great opportunity for me.
And when I see that they listen
to the truth and are loving it,
it makes my heart beat faster.
It touches my heart.
By expanding my ministry,
I’m sharing in a form of service
that could even be described
as missionary work,
since I’m helping
people hear about Jehovah
for the very first time.
I’m living what I have only read
about in experiences.
Many were
—perhaps for the first time—
discovering new skills in themselves,
indicating how Jehovah
through his spirit can enable certain ones
to cultivate qualities they didn’t realize
they had to such an extent.
We are so grateful to Jehovah
for opening a door
leading to such wonderful activity.
It gives us great joy,
and we praise him daily for this.
At the time this report was prepared,
over 100 Bible studies had been started.
One refugee told the brothers:
“You are the best thing
that has happened to us here in Greece.
We thank Jehovah for meeting you.”
Another said:
“We do not need material things.
“We need hope,
and you are giving this
to us through the Bible.”
In our program, we have been discussing
how Jehovah values each one of us,
no matter what our circumstances are.
In some parts of the world,
our brothers and sisters
are in deep poverty
and lack even the basic needs for life.
But this does not diminish
Jehovah’s feelings for them.
He loves them dearly.
In this next report,
see what’s been done
to care for faithful brothers and sisters
in the Democratic Republic of Congo.
My name is Maska Mahamba.
I love the preaching work.
However, my various illnesses
prevent me from giving
my all in the ministry.
My first wife died,
and we had six children.
I was alone with the six children,
and then I married Beatrice,
who has five children.
Since we are living in the last days
of this system, it is not easy.
I like the example of Jesus,
who was passionate about preaching
the message that he shared.
At the same time,
he took into account
the suffering of the people of his time.
He would take time to show kindness,
to encourage, and to heal.
The branch sees where there is a need
and then organizes a humanitarian mission.
I believe I can use my medical skills
to help our brothers.
It is love,
not just in writing,
but in action.
It’s a real joy
to help these brothers who need us
in remote locations far from towns.
It is always a pleasure.
Well, the two are the same;
both eardrums are completely perforated.
Well, we are here
in the village of Walikale in the middle
of the forest on the main road
—well, the only road in the village.
It serves as our runway.
I can’t bear to see anyone suffer,
so I use all my skills to try
to find a solution.
What moves me to help the brothers
is what Jesus said,
that “there is more happiness in giving than
. . . in receiving.”
A long day
—really very tiring—
but at the same time,
there was an encouraging case:
Brother Munyakaragwe, 68 years old,
10 years in the regular pioneer service,
and he has 15 Bible studies.
This brother came
from the territory on a motorcycle.
It took him two and a half hours
on a very rough road
instead of an hour and a half
because he has a paralyzed leg.
And he was able to go
back to his field service,
well, with some medication.
So it was really encouraging to see him
getting on the motorcycle
with a smile on his face.
These are mosquito nets for those in need,
and there’s a big need here.
So we give them to each family.
You know, to protect your baby,
one of the best things is for him
to sleep under a mosquito net.
Jehovah has done well because he has gone
through you to provide us with care.
We are very grateful.
We thank the many brothers
who have volunteered to serve us.
I thank Jehovah because without him
our identifying mark of unity wouldn’t exist.
You have helped me.
I had this problem for two years.
Now I’m so happy.
I will be able to hear at the meetings again.
Thank you.
The brothers are aware
that they must thank Jehovah,
and we ourselves are aware
that all of this is possible
thanks to Jehovah’s holy spirit
and his organization.
How heartwarming!
Those dear ones are not defined
by their circumstances.
They have been serving Jehovah
whole-souled despite their challenges,
and they’re determined
to use the relief assistance
to continue worshipping him.
Earlier, we discussed
the examples of King David
and the apostle Paul
and the mistakes they made.
Perhaps for us,
our past mistakes are keeping us
from moving forward.
That was the challenge for Jim Loyd.
He was raised in the truth
but did not progress to baptism.
By his teen years,
he was getting into trouble.
As he describes it,
in his heart he had left Jehovah.
His later involvement
with gangs and violence
put him in a place
he never expected to be.
But you will be greatly encouraged
to see where he is now.
Things that have happened to you,
you can’t change
—but your personality you can.
We can change our personality
with Jehovah’s help.
By the time I was 25,
I was associating with notorious criminals.
I guess I was a criminal too
—just took a wrong turn and kept going.
I found myself a fugitive on the run.
I was sentenced to many years in prison.
At 25, I felt like it might as well
have been a life sentence.
Isolation and lockdown
was a very lonely place,
and I thought,
‘How did I get here?’
I remember a happier time in my life.
My mom would take us to meetings.
I was in the Theocratic Ministry School.
All the friends were so loving.
My mom sent me subscriptions
to The Watchtower and Awake!
I had a box under my bunk,
and I’d toss them in there
—never opened them.
And I must have had a years’ worth.
You know, I never told her:
“Stop sending them, Mom.
I’m not reading them.”
I found out through my mom
that my dad had died.
I felt that I broke his heart.
I pulled out the box from under my bunk.
Right on top was a book,
The Truth That Leads to Eternal Life.
And at that moment, I knew
Jehovah hadn’t forgotten me.
I remembered that book.
I remembered that book when I was a boy.
I placed that book out in service.
I opened it up.
And, of course, the theme scripture
for that publication
was Revelation 21:3, 4:
“The tent of God is with mankind.”
I read it that night the whole night.
I read the whole book.
Of course, that little bell went off.
I couldn’t deny that this was the truth.
So what was I going to do about it?
Shortly after that, I got transferred,
so I called my mom and told her.
It was funny; she asked,
“Do you think there are
any Jehovah’s Witnesses
that go up there?”
I told her: “I don’t think so.
“It’s way up in the mountains.
I don’t think they go up there;
it’s a little fire camp.”
I wasn’t a spiritual person yet.
All the magazines and books
went back into the box
and back under my bunk.
I’d only been there five minutes,
and a guard came in and said,
“Are you a Jehovah’s Witness?”
I couldn’t believe it.
And I told him, “I studied with,
been studying with Jehovah’s Witnesses.”
And he said:
“Oh, good. Follow me.”
And I followed him,
and he took me
and introduced me to a brother
who had been coming up
there regularly
to study the Bible
with inmates there.
And I realized
at that moment that once again
Jehovah had not forgotten me.
That brother faithfully came up there
for the next two years
every Friday night.
He thought that it’d be
a good idea to have
a Theocratic Ministry School,
so he got it approved.
He would do the number one talk,
and the other brother
that would come with him
would do the highlights,
and then the three of us inmates
would do the other parts.
I was giving a talk every week.
And he started making
tape recordings of the meetings.
I’d listen to them over and over,
until the next week.
I knew that if I was going
to return to Jehovah,
I had to make some adjustments.
With Jehovah’s help
—I leaned on him more,
relied on his strength more—
it was then that I really felt
that I could do this.
The beard became a goatee,
and then it just became a mustache.
No drugs, no alcohol, no smoking,
and I cleaned up my language.
Then I finally got released,
got a job as an electrician,
and was able to get my own place
and started going to meetings.
I was listening to the Watchtower,
and different ones were commenting.
‘Oh, that’s his wife’
—one of the brothers
who came up to visit me.
I kept looking to see,
so I could finally put a face
to the voices
that I’d been listening to.
I let Jehovah mold me
into something good.
There are many blessings
since dedicating my life to Jehovah.
I’ve been an elder for ten years now.
One of my sons came into the truth.
I met my wonderful wife.
She’s helped me
to grow spiritually
and to love Jehovah even more.
One thing I kept praying for and he’s blessed
me with is to forgive myself
—to have a clean conscience
and freeness of speech.
And he’s done that.
Jim shares the same joy as so many others
who return to Jehovah.
The feelings common
in such real-life experiences
are what we’ll see depicted
in our music video.
It’s called I Can Get Back Up.
It is especially touching
for those of us who have stumbled
but need encouragement
to move ahead with Jehovah’s help.
This loneliness I feel inside
is hard to bear.
Jehovah, I can see where I went wrong.
Feeling so downhearted,
I need strength to carry on.
I’m yearning to be back where I belong.
I remember things you taught me
—things I still recall—
The precious truths found
in your Holy Word.
That even if I stumble, even if I fall,
I can get back up.
I know the ones who care for me,
Who showed their love before,
Those who love Jehovah from the heart.
Your word is like a lamp
that lights the way that leads me back.
The road to life is where I want to be.
Ev’rywhere I go, ev’rything I see,
reminds me of the truth:
The end is drawing near.
So Jehovah, Father,
please hear my prayer tonight
And help me now,
I’m in my time of need.
You know that when I stumble
so many times,
I can get back up.
I know Jehovah understands;
sometimes I need a helping hand.
He knows that I am weak
and sees what others cannot see.
He’s looking for the best in me.
So I’m going to the hall tonight
to feel the love I lost,
Back to where I know I belong.
And even if I stumble,
even if I fall, I will get back up.
I can get back up.
What a beautiful reminder
that if we stumble,
we can get back up!
Having seen the examples
throughout the program,
can you confidently answer
the question of our theme,
“Are You Defined by Your Circumstances?”
What do you think?
Remember,
not the way man sees is the way God sees
—Jehovah sees what the heart is.
May we work hard
to see ourselves as Jehovah does
and be determined to never give up.
May we never forget that it is
the privilege of bearing Jehovah’s name,
having a relationship with him,
and our love for Jehovah that defines us.
Jehovah is happy
if we give the best that we can.
So may we do our part
by not limiting ourselves
due to our circumstances,
but always look for ways
to give our best to Jehovah.
You beautiful older ones,
even those with severe health problems,
can do much to help
in the great work that’s taking place today.
Now, you may wonder
what can you do.
You can pray for your brothers and sisters.
We need your prayers.
Pray for the Governing Body.
Pray for those who are taking the lead.
Pray for the elders in your congregations.
Pray for those who
are going through difficult times.
Do such prayers help
the work of the organization?
Absolutely!
James 5:16 tells us
that ‘a righteous person’s supplication
has a powerful effect.’
No matter who we are
and whatever our situation in life,
may we find joy
in giving what we can for Jehovah.
And may each one of us
rejoice at the privilege we have
of being part of what Jehovah
is accomplishing
in these last days.
Of course, we share that privilege
with our worldwide brotherhood
—a part of which we enjoy
seeing each month.
To conclude this program,
we visit with our brothers
and sisters in Togo.
Located in western Africa,
Togo enjoys
a very pleasant climate year-round.
The southern coast contains
extensive lagoons with sandy beaches,
while farther north are
rolling forested hills
and yellow tinges of savanna land.
Togo may be one
of the smaller countries in Africa.
Yet, it is sending up a great shout
of praise to Jehovah.
In the town of Kpalimé,
there are 577 of our brothers and sisters,
56 of whom are pioneers.
Kpalimé is located
on a scenic woodland plateau.
Steep hillsides can sometimes
make service a challenge
but not a deterrent.
Our faithful brothers and sisters
not only meet this challenge
but are very zealous
in carrying out their ministry.
They diligently search out all persons,
no matter where they are.
And many honesthearted ones are listening
to the good news from God’s Word.
The first congregation in Kpalimé
was formed in 1961.
Now there are seven
in this small town alone!
The Kingdom Halls
are very well cared for by the brothers.
This is the newest Kingdom Hall,
Kpalimé-Nogo.
It was just dedicated
in December 2016.
And here is their Assembly Hall,
constructed in 2008.
All 577 send you
their love and greetings.
And we, in turn,
send them our love
and pray for Jehovah’s strength and blessing
to be upon each and every one of them.
From the world headquarters
of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
this is JW Broadcasting!