James 4:6:
“God opposes the haughty ones,
“but he gives undeserved kindness
to the humble ones.”
Well,
haughtiness is really disdainful pride,
superciliousness, arrogance.
One who is haughty
is in his own estimation
superior to his fellow man.
On the other hand,
humility is freedom
from pride or arrogance.
It’s the state of lowliness of mind.
Humility and haughtiness
are the exact opposites of each other.
Humility is here;
haughtiness is at the other end
of the spectrum.
Which one are you?
Likely neither,
but somewhere in between.
Now, if Jehovah
had a “humble/haughty meter,”
where would the needle be
if he was monitoring you?
Would it be in the middle?
Well, hopefully not.
Hopefully it would be closer to humility.
We’re imperfect, but we want to be
as far away from haughtiness as possible.
The verse said:
“[Jehovah] opposes the haughty,”
but he favors those who are humble.
Haughtiness is not totally
a mental condition per se.
Please find Mark chapter 7 with me,
Mark 7:21, 22.
Jesus put haughtiness in a lineup
with many unsavory qualities and actions.
Well, if it’s not totally a mental condition,
what is haughtiness?
Notice how Jesus describes
where it comes from
at Mark 7:21, 22.
It says:
“For from inside,
out of the heart of men,
[so it’s a heart condition]
“come injurious reasonings,
sexual immorality, thefts,
“murders, acts of adultery, greed,
acts of wickedness, deceit,
“brazen conduct,
an envious eye, blasphemy,
“haughtiness, and unreasonableness.
All these . . . things come from within
and defile a man.”
So haughtiness is really
a condition of the heart,
the inner person.
And it says it’s a ‘wicked thing.’
Well, what about humility?
In some ancient cultures,
a humble person
was always thought to be a slave,
miserable, a pitiful person.
But humility is not the same as humiliation.
Instead,
in the Bible it stresses that humility
—this lowliness of mind—
can actually lead to honor,
to status with God.
And so Proverbs 22:4 says:
“The result of humility . . .
is riches and glory and life”
—not miserable,
not pitiful by any means.
Well, we said earlier that if Jehovah
had a “humble/haughty meter,”
the needle likely would not be pegged
on humility in our case
nor on haughtiness.
Well, why is that?
Well, because as dedicated Christians,
none of us are absolutely haughty at heart.
But as imperfect dedicated Christians,
none of us have the market
on true humility.
Only Jehovah and Jesus
are absolutely humble.
Well, can we be basically
a humble person
and yet act haughtily,
or arrogantly, at times?
Well, let’s consider Moses.
Jehovah gave him tremendous authority.
And it’s known that power,
authority, a responsible position
can erode humility.
But Moses proved
his humility time after time.
For example,
in Numbers chapter 11
he gathered together 70 elders,
and verse 25 says that Jehovah
took some of the spirit of Moses away
and put it on the 70 elders,
and they began to behave as prophets.
Well,
there’s nothing that indicates Moses
jealously tried to guard
his authority and privileges.
He was humble.
And we all remember the account
where Moses’ father-in-law
suggested that he delegate
some of his workload to others.
Moses did not arrogantly resist that.
He humbly accepted the suggestion.
And then later,
at the end of his life
when Jehovah chose his replacement
—Joshua—
Moses humbly accepted that decision.
He urged the people to follow Joshua’s lead.
Well,
we could say nothing else
than Moses was
an excellent example of humility,
but he was not perfect.
Please find with me Numbers chapter 20,
Numbers 20.
Humble Moses allowed himself
to be provoked
and perform an act of haughtiness,
or arrogance.
The situation was that there was no water
for the assembly of Israel,
and the people began to show
an arrogant, rebellious spirit.
Please pick up the dialogue with me
in verse 4 of Numbers chapter 20.
They said:
“Why have you brought
Jehovah’s congregation
“into this wilderness for us
and our livestock to die here?
“And why have you led us up out of Egypt
to bring us into this evil place?
“It is no place for seed and figs
and vines and pomegranates,
and there is no water to drink.”
Well, they got under Moses’ skin.
They caused him
to lose his humility momentarily.
Look at verse 9:
“So Moses took the rod
from before Jehovah,
“just as He had commanded him.
“Then Moses and Aaron
called the congregation together
“before the crag,
and he said to them:
“‘Hear, now, you rebels!
“‘Must we [meaning Aaron and I]
bring out water for you from this crag?’”
Well,
that was a haughty, arrogant act.
Admittedly,
the people were out of line
with their speech and attitude.
But Jehovah took note
of “the spike in the needle”
of the “haughty meter.”
Look at verse 12:
“Jehovah later said to Moses and Aaron:
“‘Because you did not show faith in me
“‘and sanctify me before the eyes
of the people of Israel,
“‘you will not bring this congregation
into the land that I will give them.’”
So although generally Moses’ “needle”
was always very close to humility,
Jehovah was displeased
with this “spike on the needle”
toward haughtiness,
even though momentary.
Well, it’s good for us to consider this
because it’s easy
for us to lose our humility,
particularly if we are invested
with some authority.
Maybe we have a new responsibility
in the congregation,
in the circuit, at the branch.
Or maybe we have a skill
and talent that we excel in,
and we get compliments galore.
Or we’re at odds with a fellow believer.
Will we maintain our humility?
There was a great line
in the February 2013 Watchtower.
It said: “Remember:
In order to be useful to Jehovah,
our humility
should always exceed our ability.”
Well, King Saul allowed his ability
to exceed his humility.
And at 1 Samuel 15:17
—he was not to take
any spoils from the land,
but he allowed that to happen—
in verse 17,
Samuel confronted him, and he said:
“Were you not insignificant
[or humble] in your own eyes?”
And then he said:
‘Why did you disobey Jehovah?’
Well,
Saul stammered and stuttered.
But bottom line,
Jehovah was not pleased
because in verse 23,
Jehovah said through Samuel:
‘Rebelliousness is the same
as the sin of divination,
‘and pushing ahead presumptuously
the same as magical power and idolatry.
You rejected the word of God,
I reject you as king.’
Well, it’s just as our text said:
“[Jehovah] opposes the haughty ones.”
May we all strive to keep
our “needle” close to humility.