Well, now we’re looking forward
to something that has become
a very special part
of our Gilead graduation program.
It’s the video The Inside Story,
and this is going to be chaired for us
by Brother Kenneth Stovall.
Welcome to this edition of The Inside Story.
Why is there a body of water
in the South Pacific
called Ironbottom Sound?
If you were asked to go to Transcarpathia,
would you know how to get there?
If you had a friend who spoke Guarani,
where likely would he be from?
We’re going to discuss all of those topics
this time on The Inside Story.
Let’s introduce our first guests,
Brad and Hilda Fraser,
serving at the branch in the Solomon Islands.
Thank you so much for coming.
Have a seat.
So now, Hilda,
you and your family
are native Solomon Islanders.
Mhm.
But, Brad, your family moved
to the Solomon Islands
when you were just a small boy.
Wasn’t that even before there was
a branch in the Solomon Islands?
Yes, that is correct—yes.
And actually, my father was a member
of the first Branch Committee
in the Solomon Islands.
Now, I’ve never been to the Solomon Islands,
and I imagine most of our viewers have not.
Tell us, what are the Solomon Islands like?
The Solomon Islands
are made up of less than 1,000 islands,
and mainly it’s two chains of islands.
And in the middle there’s a body of water
that’s called the Ironbottom Sound.
Now, why is it called that?
It was given that name by the Allied soldiers
during the second world war
because of the vast number of iron vessels
that sunk during the war.
When I think of islands in the South Pacific,
I think of a tropical paradise.
Is that what it’s like?
Yes, beauty is everywhere.
You have dense jungles,
blue waters, coral reefs,
and many humble people
waiting to hear the good news.
In fact,
about 40 percent of the population
has not yet been exposed
to the Kingdom message.
My, interesting.
Well, what is it like to preach there?
You need a spirit of adventure
and oftentimes a lot of determination.
Now, why is that?
The Solomon Islands’ territory
is a vast territory,
and most places are very remote.
So there’s no running water,
electricity, or telephones.
So when you go preaching,
how do you usually travel?
Transportation can be very difficult.
Since most of the populated areas
are near the coast,
it’s actually safer
and easier to get a boat
to go to these areas
than to try to drive there.
Interesting.
Now, you told me a story one time
about your 25th wedding anniversary.
We took a vacation day from Bethel,
and we planned to do some preaching
in the Florida Islands.
So that’s about 20 miles (30 km)
across the Ironbottom Sound.
We have a small boat
that we use around the place,
and it’s about 14 feet (4.2 m) long.
It’s big enough for our needs.
OK.
Now, this sounds a little frightening to me.
You’re going to venture out
in a 14 foot (4.2 m) boat,
20 miles (30 km) across open ocean.
Aren’t there some dangers
associated with doing that?
If a storm blows up suddenly,
it can be a rather frightening experience.
Or if fog comes in,
you can easily get lost.
But I’ve learned a local way
of dead reckoning navigation.
Well, that’s a nice skill to have, I’m sure.
So, then, you made it OK
to the Florida Islands?
The weather was good that morning.
And we visited some families,
and we showed them some of the latest videos
that we had previously downloaded.
And then at 4:00 p.m.,
that’s when we returned back.
That’s when the seas became rough.
The swells got up to just under three meters,
or about eight feet high.
So this meant that water was crashing
over the bow of the boat
and filling the boat with water.
My goodness!
Hilda, weren’t you frightened?
No.
We have been in rough seas before,
and I just perform my usual duties
when things like that happen.
You perform your usual duties.
So, what are your usual duties?
I move to the back of the boat
so that the bow will pitch up,
and we can just go over the waves.
And then I use a bucket
that we keep in the boat to bail water,
and that helps the boat stay afloat.
This sounds like a lot of hard work,
bailing water constantly out of the boat.
Didn’t you get exhausted?
Yes, it was hard work.
But Brad bought me
a box of chocolates for our anniversary.
That’s romantic.
Mhm.
So I started eating the chocolates
to keep up my energy,
and then I began to sing
one of the original songs
to keep up my spirits.
So how long did you
have to keep up this bailing?
After four hours, we got home safely.
So that’s how you spent
your 25th wedding anniversary.
I’m going to have to tell you,
Hilda is an amazing woman.
I mean,
with just a box of chocolates
and a bucket, she saved two lives.
How many women
could do so much with so little?
Yes, you’re certainly right.
That’s true.
Brother Ken, would you like to see
how the preaching work
is done in the Solomon Islands?
I think I would!
Great!
Let’s follow along by means of this video.
The Solomon Islands:
This group of over 900 islands
spans a land area
of nearly 29,000 square kilometers
(11,197 sq mi)
in the isolated South Pacific Ocean.
The brothers and sisters
make the most of their opportunities
to spread the good news
through public witnessing
in the capital city, Honiara.
Reaching the many inhabited islands
is a challenge.
Traveling long distances across the open sea
is only one of the many obstacles.
Our brothers encounter
many different languages,
cultures, and customs.
When the branch office
received a request for literature
from the island of Ulawa,
it was decided to send two special pioneers
to follow up on the interest.
The brothers would need
to be mostly self-sufficient
during their extended time on the island.
They would not even be able to arrange
living accommodations in advance.
I was worried about going by ship to Ulawa.
What are the people like in Ulawa,
and where would I stay?
I just took some boxes
of books and magazines,
also a video screen, two bicycles,
and three bags of rice,
with my mat to sleep on.
Seeking out deserving ones
in these isolated places
often involves long journeys
by foot, by road,
or even by dugout canoe.
The effort is great,
but the rewards are even greater.
When we arrived in Ulawa,
we met a family
that had been looking
for Jehovah’s people from 2009
up until 2019.
They had been using one copy
of Examining the Scriptures Daily
for that whole time.
When they met us, they were so happy,
and they wanted to study the Bible with us.
Theocratic videos are very effective.
This group is eager
as they watch the monthly broadcast
in their local Pidgin language.
Here in a makeshift Kingdom Hall,
more than 20 interested ones attend.
I always think about them.
Even though I am now back
in the Guadalcanal Province,
I still want to go back
to the people of Ulawa.
If my next assignment is to go to Ulawa,
that would be really good.
These intrepid brothers and sisters
continue to heed the call
to search out deserving ones
in this vast oceanic territory.
What a beautiful place!
Could you use more help there?
Yes, it is a beautiful place,
and it’s full of beautiful, humble people
waiting to listen to the good news.
So as you can see, there is a need
for many more adventurous
and determined preachers of the good news.
But we have faith
that Jehovah will listen to our prayers,
and he will give us
what we need to finish the work.
Thank you, Brad, thank you, Hilda,
so much for sharing
this interesting experience with us.
Now we’re going to travel to a place
on earth that has
a totally different situation
than the situation faced
in the Solomon Islands.
Let’s welcome our next guest,
Brother Vasyl Kobel.
He is going to tell us about Transcarpathia.
Vasyl, thank you for joining us.
Thank you.
Have a seat.
So, Vasyl, where is Transcarpathia,
and what is it like?
It’s a beautiful area that lies south
of the Carpathian Mountains
in western Ukraine.
On a short drive you see mountains,
dense forests, alpine meadows,
and rolling lowlands
covered with small farms.
Beautiful!
But now, you serve at the branch in Ukraine.
Can you just tell us
what your assignment involves?
I work with the Service Department,
specifically helping to organize
the Romanian-
and Hungarian-speaking circuits in Ukraine.
These are located near the border
of Romania and Hungary in Transcarpathia.
So now,
is the preaching work bearing fruit there?
Oh, yes.
So much so that it presents
some unique and unexpected challenges.
What do you mean
by unique, unexpected challenges?
After the fall of the USSR,
Ukraine enjoyed
an explosive publisher growth
in the mid-90’s.
Because of that,
we now have a high concentration
of Witnesses in some areas,
especially in Transcarpathia.
In one city, Nyzhnya Apsha,
approximately 25 percent
of the local population are Witnesses
—it’s one out of four.
In another, Hlybokyy Potik,
nearly 30 percent
of the population are Witnesses
—it’s one out of three.
So you’re saying
that if you’re walking down the street,
every third or every fourth person you meet
might be one of our brothers and sisters.
Yes.
One circuit overseer in Transcarpathia
has a circuit that consists
of 19 congregations,
and they are all in one small village.
He doesn’t have to travel very far, does he?
Absolutely!
Well, it must be a blessing to be surrounded
by so many brothers and sisters.
Indeed.
As Deuteronomy 28:2 says:
‘The blessing has truly overtaken us.’
In some regions, there are so many Witnesses
that it is hard to find someone to preach to.
So it must be difficult,
then, to get territory to work.
Yes.
One circuit overseer
once wanted to work a territory,
and the brothers placed a note
on the territory: Died.
The circuit overseer
asked what the note meant
and was told that the territory
was just one house.
It was learned that only one person
lived in that house and,
unfortunately, he had died.
My goodness.
So, then,
does that mean that a territory
could actually be just one house?
Yes, it could
—or even a few persons
or only one person in the house.
That’s what I call thorough coverage.
We do our best.
Well, so do the brothers feel
that the preaching work
is done in Transcarpathia?
No.
They are working harder
than ever with renewed zeal.
“Renewed zeal,”
that’s an interesting expression.
So, what do you mean?
It’s because of their love for Jehovah
and love for their neighbors
that many find unexpected ways
to cultivate the fields right around them.
Can you give me an example
of what you’re talking about?
OK.
For example,
the Nyzhnia Apsha Levada Congregation
has 132 publishers,
but there are only 70 people
in all of their congregation’s territory
that are not Witnesses.
So does that dampen their zeal?
No.
In March of 2018,
25 publishers signed up to auxiliary pioneer.
Where did they preach?
Some Romanian-speaking publishers
are working to improve
their Russian and Ukrainian
and then travel to preach
to other villages some distance away.
When someone finds an area
with receptive people,
then they invite others to come,
as many as are able,
to join them on their next trip
to this territory.
So, then, a few take the lead
and find the receptive territories
and in the true sense of the word
—“pioneer.”
Yes.
We have a short video that shows
the preaching work in Transcarpathia,
and I know you
will enjoy watching this video.
Sure.
Yes, let’s watch.
There is a unique territory
located in the west of Ukraine.
In six small Romanian-speaking villages,
the number of Jehovah’s Witnesses
is unusually high.
For example, the relatively small village
of Hlybokyy Potik
has eight Kingdom Halls and 17 congregations.
Nearly one third of the population
are Jehovah’s Witnesses.
We are 21 in our class,
and 15 are children of Jehovah’s Witnesses.
We need to be inventive
in order to preach in our territory.
It’s important to find
a personal approach to each person.
I noticed that our website
and various videos
help to sustain the interest of people.
I’m so happy that now
I conduct 15 Bible studies in my village.
When all in the village know you,
they take note of how you behave
and what your actions are.
Also, it’s important to listen to others.
Everyone likes to see
that we care for their views.
Each morning, we pray to Jehovah
with my Daddy and Mommy
to give me opportunities
to preach and to overcome my fears.
I practice with my dolls
what I can say to people in the ministry.
And to make the Bible
more interesting for my classmates,
I prepare cards for them
with fascinating Bible questions.
People watch us when we preach.
If they see a big smile on your face,
they see that this makes you happy,
and they also want to be happy.
It must be attractive to them.
To expand their ministry,
these brothers and sisters preach
in neighboring villages, remote areas
located hundreds of kilometers away,
and at times, they even travel
to the nearby country of Romania.
The efforts of our brothers and sisters
have been richly rewarded.
Last year, in the village of Hlybokyy Potik,
nearly 60 percent of the population
attended the Memorial.
Approximately 160 people
from these villages get baptized each year.
As these zealous preachers
expand their ministry
using every method possible,
they continue to see
Jehovah’s blessings overtake them.
That is just remarkable!
It’s so good to see that even young ones
are seeing results
from their hard work and their zeal.
Yes.
Usually,
families in Transcarpathia are very close.
Parents are realizing that one way
they can give back to Jehovah
is by helping their children
reach theocratic goals
like pioneering or attending the School
for Kingdom Evangelizers,
even though it may mean
that they may move away
to a territory where the need is greater.
Well, the brothers and sisters
in Transcarpathia,
whether they’re young or old,
are certainly to be commended
for the spirit they show
and their hard work and zeal.
Thank you, Vasyl,
for giving us this wonderful report.
Thank you.
Now let’s introduce our final guests.
This is Brother Marcos
and Sister Nanci Morel,
and they are serving
at the branch in Paraguay.
Hi, Nanci.
Hi, Marcos.
Hello, how are you?
Very good.
We brought you a treat.
What is it, tea?
More than tea, this is tereré.
It is a traditional Paraguayan beverage
that is shared
among the closest of friends . . .
. . . and family.
It’s delicious!
I feel so privileged.
Thank you.
Let’s start out by talking
about the language of Guarani.
Now, as I understand it,
you both spoke Guarani at home
when you were growing up, not Spanish.
Yes, we spoke Guarani at home,
but we were not taught to read and write it.
We learned to read
and write Spanish in school.
In Paraguay,
at least 70 percent of the people
speak Guarani as their first language.
So even though we have
two official languages,
Spanish and Guarani,
most of the people speak Guarani.
And a third cannot speak Spanish at all.
That’s very interesting.
So if most of the people speak Guarani,
why do you have two official languages?
Because of the mandate
of a previous government,
Guarani was looked down on
and Spanish was designated
as the official language of Paraguay.
For many years it was forbidden
to teach it in public schools.
In fact, if you were caught
speaking Guarani at school,
you could be punished.
Oh, my.
So when did that change?
It was not until 1992
that it began to be taught
in the local schools.
And in the same year, it was made
an official language along with Spanish.
How did this language situation
affect our meetings and the preaching?
Since Spanish was
the only official language for many years,
the preaching and meetings
were done only in Spanish.
But the truth presented in Spanish
didn’t reach the hearts of humble ones
as well as Guarani did.
So can you give me
an example of what you mean?
Yes.
For example, in the ministry
when we read a Bible verse in Spanish,
frequently, afterward,
we would have to translate it into Guarani
so the householder
could understand the meaning.
What about personal study?
How did this situation affect that?
Truthfully,
it was difficult for many of the friends
to even do personal study
using Spanish publications.
They just didn’t get
the sense of the material,
and for a while there were
no Guarani publications.
So how did this begin to change?
Can you tell us about that, Nanci?
Yes.
Back in 2002,
I was invited
—I was asked to come to Bethel
for what I thought
was a temporary assignment.
But they fooled me.
Hmm, they fooled you.
After I came to Bethel,
I was asked to become a regular Bethelite
and to work with a small team
of three persons
to translate a few tracts into Guarani.
I felt so privileged to be part
of the very first Guarani translation team
in Paraguay.
OK, interesting.
But now at that point,
you only had permission
to translate just a few tracts.
How did things progress?
Our small team really had the desire
to translate more publications in Guarani
because we could see the need for it.
Also, we knew that Brother Lösch
was coming as a headquarters representative.
So what did you do?
Wisely, our overseer,
Brother Gordon Hansen
—a Gilead missionary—
told us that we
should not all attack Brother Lösch
in the hallway
to express our feelings
but that we should pray
and leave matters in Jehovah’s hands.
Sounds like wise advice,
but what was the result?
We prayed and, to our surprise,
one of the very first things
that Brother Lösch did
when he arrived at the branch
was to come to our little department
to see what progress we were making.
Has anyone ever told Brother Lösch
that you prayed him into your department?
Yes.
So, what happened after that?
So in 2003, we got approval
to translate more publications in Guarani.
The very next year,
the branch organized
the first Guarani congregation.
My.
And now there are seven Guarani circuits
with over 119 congregations
and several groups.
We saw Jehovah’s hand every step of the way.
And when Jehovah wants something to happen,
nothing can stop it.
Well, that’s certainly a fact.
Now, when the brothers started using
what was really their first language,
the language of their heart, Guarani,
how were they affected?
Oh, we were hoping that you would ask.
Let’s watch a video that explains it.
OK.
For many in Paraguay,
Guarani is the language
they have spoken since childhood.
In the past, many learned
to read and write Spanish in school.
But for Bible truth to touch their heart,
they would need to hear it in Guarani,
the language of their heart.
It was very difficult for us to understand
the publications in Spanish.
I felt bad because I
would read The Watchtower
over and over again
and I could not understand it.
Sometimes after reading it many times,
I just stopped trying.
I told Jehovah that I had the strong desire
to have the publications in Guarani.
Jehovah answered their prayers
when his organization began translating
the literature into Guarani.
I had to practice every day
so that I could read
and write well in Guarani.
Many adults will now need to develop
the skill of reading this language
that they grew up speaking.
For some it was a struggle.
But this would not be their only challenge.
Some said that I
should stop speaking in Guarani
because it is the language
of the uneducated people.
But I want to imitate Jehovah
because all languages are equal to him.
So I always pray to Jehovah
and ask for his help.
This effort would pay off,
for many were understanding
deep Bible truths for the first time.
I was overjoyed when we
received publications in Guarani.
I received them with all my heart.
This has helped me
to be more kind to my wife,
my family, and all the brothers.
Being able to read Jehovah’s thoughts
in the language of our heart
is a precious gift.
It can draw us closer to him
in ways that exceed even our imagination.
What a touching video!
But I’d like to ask you,
In your lives,
have you personally seen any benefit
from the translation work into Guarani?
Yes.
When my mother and I
first came into the truth,
my father was slightly opposed.
But when we finally got
a circuit overseer that could speak Guarani,
he did something that shocked us all.
He did?
What was that?
My mother had invited
the circuit overseer for a meal,
and when my father
heard him speaking Guarani,
he came to the table
and joined us for the meal.
He never did that before
with the circuit overseers
that spoke Spanish.
But he didn’t just sit at the table,
he offered the brother tereré.
Really?
—as though they were close friends.
And when we got
more publications in Guarani,
I witnessed how the truth
really touched my father’s heart.
Twenty years after my mom
and I were baptized,
we were very happy to see
my father dedicate his life to Jehovah.
What a joyful outcome!
Marcos, Nanci,
thank you so much for being with us
and sharing
these very interesting experiences.
Hasn’t it been faith-strengthening
to see how Jehovah cares
for each and every one of us
no matter what language we speak?
And hasn’t our faith been strengthened
as we’ve seen that around the globe
our brothers and sisters face many obstacles
and do so with zeal and success?
No matter what obstacle you may be facing,
may Jehovah bless you
until we’re together again
on The Inside Story.