It’s a pleasure to relate to you two aspects
of the Teaching Committee’s work.
First, what does it take
to put a regional convention
together these days?
And second, what can we expect
with regard to our midweek meetings?
The Teaching Committee is very grateful
to every Bethel department.
Each of you has contributed in some way
to the spiritually festive events
that we enjoy at our conventions
and our midweek meetings.
Our conventions
have come a long way since 1889.
But as you’ll see, the improvements
must be attributed to Jehovah.
This convention is so beautiful.
It moves you to the core.
It’s a very spiritually enriching
experience for all of us.
We really see
the Governing Body is caring for us.
It’s amazing!
This sentiment
has been echoed for over a century.
How is it that year after year people
who have been in the truth for decades
can say that the most recent convention
has surpassed all preceding ones?
And how do the brothers
who prepare convention programs feel
when they hear comments like that?
If this were merely the work of humans,
they might feel like Caleb as depicted
in the 2017 regional conventions.
Thankfully, this is not the work of one man.
All praise goes to Jehovah
for the timely conventions we enjoy.
His spirit is working through
many willing volunteers.
Let’s take a brief look
at how our conventions are made.
It all begins with the theme.
As Brother Morris pointed out
at the 2017 regional convention,
one-word themes
are determined years in advance.
That one word will guide
those preparing the program.
Dramas
—the most labor-intensive part of a program—
are developed five years in advance.
To prepare scripts,
the Teaching Committee cooperates closely
with the Writing Department
in working with a team
known as the Drama Review Group.
These experienced writers
develop Scriptural plots
that teach lessons in harmony
with the convention theme.
Scripts are extensively researched
and then sent to Audio/Video Services,
or AVS, for production.
All of this work has to begin early.
But how is the rest
of a convention program developed?
Each year, the Teaching Committee
carefully considers reports
from around the world
from Branch Committees
and world headquarters representatives.
Often, such reports indicate topics
that could be addressed on a convention.
The Teaching Committee
then selects a more specific theme
that will serve as the basis
for addressing the needs
of our worldwide brotherhood.
The theme is submitted
to the entire Governing Body for approval.
Then, work begins on Scripture themes
for each day of the convention.
The Friday program lays the foundation:
What is the central truth under discussion?
Why should we give attention to it now?
Saturday brings admonition
on personal conduct,
field ministry, and family life.
Sunday often highlights what the Bible says
about our future
and encourages us to maintain our hope.
Once this general framework is established,
talks are conceived
and additional lines of reasoning are chosen.
Attention is given to how to present ideas
in a variety of ways:
Could a Scriptural discussion
reach the heart more effectively
by means of an interview or a video?
This detailed sketch is all worked out
before the Teaching Committee
assigns teams of writers.
AVS collaborates with the writers
in the development of brief videos.
The Art Department brainstorms ideas
for convention branding.
The compiler follows
the written content through 70 steps
of research, fact-checking, and proofreading.
Then, all of these outlines and scripts
have to be translated
into the 343 languages
in which we hold regional conventions.
Translation Services
helps teams around the world
to overcome challenges with the text.
Composers and arrangers
make music tracks for the 18 songs
that have been selected
and the 6 music-video preludes.
Music services also produces and records
musical scores
for the feature film, the audio drama,
and some 40 other brief videos
that are used on the program.
But the Teaching Committee’s involvement
doesn’t end here.
It provides direction
regarding the assigning of speakers,
the design of sound systems,
the securing of contracts
for hotels and venues,
the operation of convention departments,
and the training of volunteers.
Thousands of willing workers are involved,
each submitting to the inspired direction
in God’s Word and the influence
of his holy spirit.
The benefits of such collaboration are felt
not only at our annual conventions
but also at our weekly meetings.
It’s been two years since the inception
of the Our Christian Life and Ministry
midweek meeting.
How have things been going on that front?
Everything got better:
how the brothers and sisters feel
about the meeting and how they participate.
There are more videos at the meetings,
so I feel closer
to the worldwide brotherhood.
I really enjoy what it does for young ones,
especially the two-minute parts.
You see young ones, even very young children,
do a demonstration.
Instead of just underlining to prepare,
now I get excited looking for gems.
We really dig into a Bible account.
I learn a whole lot more.
After the meeting,
we enjoy discussing the gems we discovered.
Every meeting gives
you something practical
that you can apply
the next weekend right away.
Now we don’t just read
the Bible as a family,
but we pay more attention
to Jehovah’s qualities.
Young ones and new publishers
are now less hesitant
about sharing their beliefs at the door
because they simply do
what they learned at the meetings.
Regarding production of the meeting,
methods of the Gilead School are employed
in the approach to study.
The Gilead approach to study
considers context, explanation,
and application.
Analyzing the context
considers the time period,
the historical setting,
and the writer’s intent.
These are built
into the Treasures From God’s Word
and the Bible Book Introduction Videos
we see at the midweek meetings.
The explanations for the verses
are all based on the publications
of “the faithful and discreet slave”
to ensure accuracy and correct understanding.
After all, at Gilead School,
students aren’t allowed to guess.
Once a scripture is explained accurately,
then it can be applied properly.
This method of context and explanation
followed by application
leads to meaningful Bible study.
The Service Committee Office
provides input on field service presentations
and Living as Christians.
The Writing Department gives insight
on how to feature our publications.
What will change after January?
As announced at the 2017 annual meeting,
the public edition
of The Watchtower will be published
three times a year instead of six.
The same will be true for Awake!
Also, specific monthly literature offers
have been discontinued.
Thus, we will enjoy some adjustments
in our field service presentations.
As you will see, the new focus will be
not so much on publications
but on conversations.
Clearly, the production
of our midweek meetings
and regional conventions
takes a lot of planning
and the cooperation of many willing workers
in a variety of Bethel departments.
But the positive effects
are felt around the world.
All I can say to Jehovah is,
“Thank you, Jehovah, for letting me be here.”
I feel very grateful
to Jehovah for the meetings.
Thank you, Jehovah.
Sometimes Bethel receives letters
that go something like this:
“Thank you for your tireless efforts.”
Actually, the brothers and sisters
working on all these projects are tired.
But they never tire
of trusting in and cooperating with the One
who truly is tireless:
the Source of all divine instruction,
Jehovah.
He alone can replace copper with gold,
so that each segment of divine education
truly is the best ever.