Welcome to our program!
Here are just a few of the things
we can look forward to:
Can the lure of fame
draw us away from Jehovah?
How does this brother
feel about the decisions
he made as a young person?
What does his story teach us
about how to use our
God-given abilities and talents?
Throughout the organization, young brothers
and sisters are reaching out
to do more in Jehovah’s service.
Their spirituality and youthful energy
are helping to advance
the Kingdom work.
But how is showing respect
for experienced brothers
an important part
of any theocratic assignment?
We’ll also hear
from young brothers and sisters
from around the world.
Why is their relationship with Jehovah
so important to them?
What do they do to build
and maintain their spirituality?
And we’ll consider
even more ways Christian youths
are setting a beautiful example
for our worldwide brotherhood.
This is JW Broadcasting
for December 2016!
During the past five years,
over 1.3 million faithful ones
have symbolized their dedication
to Jehovah by water baptism.
That’s an average
of over 700 each day.
And among those
courageously taking their stand
for true worship
are thousands of children,
teenagers, and young adults.
Young brothers and sisters,
we know it is not always easy
to serve Jehovah
and live up to your dedication.
Like older ones,
you need to be encouraged
and strengthened spiritually.
With that in mind,
our theme this month is
“Young Ones, ‘Become an Example
to the Faithful Ones.’”
It is based on the inspiring true-life story
of a young Christian named Timothy.
Before we discuss Timothy’s example,
did you know that the Bible
specifically foretold
that many young people would take
sides with Jehovah in our time?
Let’s look at this at Psalm 110:3.
And as we read it together,
note how young ones are having a share
in fulfilling this prophecy.
Notice the first part of verse 3,
David sang:
“Your people will offer themselves willingly
on the day of your military force.”
According to this prophecy, Jesus,
the Messianic King,
would have a large army
of willing supporters.
Since 1914, millions have carefully
investigated the facts
and chosen to side
with Jehovah God and Jesus Christ.
But where do young ones
come into this picture?
The rest of the verse continues:
“In splendid holiness,
from the womb of the dawn,
“you have your company of young men
just like dewdrops.”
Here, the prophecy refers to a “company,”
or group, of young ones.
They also would study the evidence
and support God’s Kingdom.
How many young people
did Jehovah foresee
supporting true worship?
We get an idea by the comparison
made to dewdrops.
Have you have ever gone outside
early in the morning
and noticed a light, sparkling coating
of water on the ground?
That may have been dew.
Jehovah designed our atmosphere so that,
under certain conditions,
when the temperature
cools during the night,
a blanket of moisture
forms on the ground.
That coating is made up
of a multitude of little drops.
Young ones,
what does dew have to do with you?
In the Bible, dew is connected
with blessing and abundance.
Dewdrops are also refreshing,
life-sustaining, and numerous.
Now, remember in Psalm 110:3,
Jehovah was looking ahead to our time.
And what did he see?
The September 15, 2002,
Watchtower on page 8
explained it this way:
“Just like refreshing dewdrops,
“many young men and women
cheerfully serve God
and assist their fellow worshipers.”
Today, there are so many mature,
bright, happy young ones
in the Christian congregation
that they are like countless dewdrops
that sparkle in the morning sun.
You faithful children, teenagers,
and young adults who have dedicated
your life to Jehovah
or who are working toward that goal
are living proof that Jehovah’s confidence
in young people was never misplaced.
He cherishes you very much and so do we.
Of course, knowing
that Jehovah has confidence in us
can be very encouraging.
But what if doubts or negative thoughts
tend to bring us down?
On occasion,
a young Witness might wonder,
‘Does anyone other
than Jehovah notice me?
Does my example really matter to others?’
To address these questions,
let’s now consider Timothy’s example.
Open your Bible, please,
to our theme text at 1 Timothy 4:12.
When you find it,
you might want to bookmark the verse
because we want to first
understand the setting.
How old was Timothy at this time?
Often, when thinking of Timothy,
I picture a teenager or a young man
in his early twenties.
And when he
first started traveling with Paul,
he was about that age.
But several years passed
before Paul wrote letters to Timothy.
So by the time
First Timothy was written,
Timothy was likely in his early thirties.
Now, what do you think?
Was Timothy young or old?
Some of you younger ones
may be thinking to yourselves,
‘If he was over 30,
then he was old!’
But remember,
a much older man like Paul
would say that Timothy was quite young.
In fact, notice the expression
he uses when writing to Timothy.
First Timothy 4:12, Paul says:
“Never let anyone
look down on your youth.
“Instead, become an example
to the faithful ones
“in speaking, in conduct, in love,
in faith, in chasteness.”
Paul called Timothy a youth
and urged him to be a good example.
While Timothy may have been
in his early thirties at this time,
remember that he
was taught about Jehovah
from the time he was a baby,
and he did well in the truth
as a young person.
In fact, when he was still a teenager
or in his early twenties,
the elders recommended him
to serve as a missionary with Paul.
So, in effect,
Paul here is urging Timothy
to continue to be
a good example for others.
What else do we know about Timothy?
He was not proud, or haughty.
He likely did not view himself
as some amazing example.
I’m sure he never dreamed
that one day Christians all over the world
would study his life in detail
so as to imitate his faith.
Timothy was modest
—and this despite his privileges.
Paul’s words may indicate
that Timothy was somewhat shy.
Like many of us,
he may have battled with feelings
of self-doubt on occasion.
Based on this information,
let’s do something interesting now.
Let’s use our imagination
to visualize Timothy,
an elder in his early thirties,
coming to give a Scriptural talk
in the congregation.
Got the picture?
In your mind,
please look at Timothy
and then look at the audience.
Who do we see?
Many in attendance are old enough
to be Timothy’s parents
or grandparents.
How do you think Timothy felt?
Super confident?
Are you visualizing him proudly walking
into the meeting place, saying:
“I sure wish my friends back
in Lystra could see me now.
Look at the crowds
that come to hear me speak!”
No, that’s not the Timothy we know.
It’s much more likely that Timothy,
like most of us,
rehearsed his presentation
over and over again.
He probably prayed constantly,
and he probably still got nervous,
like all of us.
And remember,
Timothy did not have the benefit
of theocratic schools like we do today.
In summary,
what can we say about Timothy?
Like so many of you,
he was an example
of faith and obedience.
He was exceptional
in displaying Christian qualities,
such as modesty and humility.
But Timothy was a person
with normal human feelings,
like all of us.
Though he had a rich,
happy life in Jehovah’s service,
life in the old world
brought real tests and challenges.
Timothy also dealt
with frequent cases of sickness,
and he was imprisoned for a time.
Some of you in various countries
can relate to those bitter experiences.
But Timothy endured.
Was he some “super Christian”
with superpowers?
No, but he did
prove to be a super example!
How does all of this
help you Christian youths
who have taken the commendable step
to dedicate your lives to Jehovah?
We just read how Paul told Timothy
to let no one look down on his youth.
A few of you may be thinking,
‘I wish someone would tell my parents
‘or my elders not to look down on me.
They still treat me like a little kid.’
If that’s the case,
we feel for you.
No progressive young one
wants to be treated as if he were a child.
But let’s look again at 1 Timothy 4:12.
Is the apostle Paul speaking
to the congregation,
to parents, or to the elders?
“Never let anyone look down
“on your youth.
“Instead, become an example
to the faithful ones in speaking,
in conduct, in love,
in faith, in chasteness.”
It’s clear, isn’t it?
Paul said your youth.
He was speaking only to Timothy.
Young ones, by extension,
what is Jehovah saying to each of you?
It’s this: To gain and maintain
the respect of faithful ones,
you have to work
at proving yourself as a Christian.
The key is not wanting or hoping
that others will respect you.
Rather, it’s earning such respect
by setting a good example
in all areas of life.
If you do that,
then no one will have any legitimate reason
to look down on your youth.
Doesn’t it make sense
that we gain respect by earning it?
We are confident
that you young ones are trying hard
to live by Christian principles at school
and in the neighborhood.
But in verse 12, did you notice
who Timothy was to be an example to?
To “the faithful ones.”
Are you an example to Christians,
both younger and older,
in your congregation
and in your circuit?
If you work on Kingdom Hall
construction projects or at Bethel,
are you an example
to your fellow workers?
Well, what are some specific ways
you can become an example
to all of these “faithful ones”?
In our theme text,
Timothy was first directed
to become an example in speaking.
On this topic,
I’ll never forget an illustration
used in the “Young People Ask” article
from the January 2012 Awake!
It quoted a young man,
James, who said:
“Once you squeeze toothpaste out,
you can’t put it back in the tube.
“The same is true with our words.
Once we say something hurtful,
we can’t take it back.”
God’s Word agrees with James.
Note what it says at Ephesians 4:29.
It tells us:
“Let a rotten word
not come out of your mouth,
“but only what is good
for building up as the need may be,
to impart what is beneficial
to the hearers.”
For some years now,
those getting baptized
have been encouraged
to complete a study of the book,
“Keep Yourselves in God’s Love.”
Chapter 12 is entitled
“Speak What ‘Is Good for Building Up.’”
On page 140,
there is a box with five questions
that can help us evaluate our speech.
For example:
“When was the last time I offered
someone specific commendation?
“Do I express my respect for others
by saying please and thank you?
“In conversation,
do I speak mainly about myself,
or am I also interested
in the thoughts and feelings of others?”
Young ones,
over the next few days,
why not review that box on page 140,
look up the scriptures,
and think about what Jehovah is saying?
Then apply what you learn to your speech.
Doing this will draw you closer to Jehovah
and help you to become
an even better example
to the faithful ones.
The second area
mentioned in our theme text
is becoming an example in conduct.
Of course,
upbuilding speech would be empty
or hypocritical
if our conduct was questionable.
Think again about Timothy.
It wasn’t enough for him to give comments
and talks at the meetings
or preach from door to door.
Later in the same letter,
Paul reminded Timothy
that he needed to treat older men
and women as fathers and mothers;
younger men and women
were to be treated as brothers and sisters.
Second Peter 3:11
provides a similar urgent reminder
about our conduct.
Let’s read that together.
Again, that’s 2 Peter 3:11.
There it tells us:
“Since all these things
are to be dissolved in this way,
“consider what sort of people
you ought to be
in holy acts of conduct.”
Let’s think about that.
For a person’s conduct to be holy
from Jehovah’s perspective,
he or she must be morally clean.
While physical cleanness
is on the outside,
moral cleanness is on the inside
—in our thoughts and desires.
Is being morally clean really important?
Think about it this way.
When eating a meal,
would you be content to eat from a bowl
that had been washed
only on the outside?
Of course not!
We want to eat from clean dishes
—dishes that are
thoroughly clean inside and out.
So when we wash dishes,
we wash the outside and the inside.
Similarly,
Jehovah expects his servants
to be clean through and through.
And because Jehovah
—the perfect reader of hearts—
will soon dissolve, yes,
eliminate this dirty system of things,
it’s urgent that we do so.
This means
that we have to work very hard
so that nothing unclean
enters our mind.
That means firmly rejecting
so-called fun
and exciting entertainment,
which features sex,
violence, or spiritism.
At 1 Corinthians 14:20,
the Bible tells us
that we should become
like “young children as to badness.”
No matter our age,
we don’t need and we don’t want
any experience
with the wickedness of this world.
Rather,
we keep the inside of the dish,
our mind and heart,
clean at all times.
And when we do so,
our exemplary conduct
pleases Jehovah and it strengthens
our faithful brothers and sisters.
Really, it’s the only way
to respect ourselves
and to gain the respect of others.
Our theme text at 1 Timothy 4:12
goes on to mention other areas
where we can make steady progress
in becoming an example,
such as in love, in faith,
and in chasteness.
During your personal study,
that is, your personal time
with your best Friend, Jehovah,
why not examine these areas
in more detail?
The treasures you gain
from such a study project
can last a lifetime
—an everlasting lifetime.
So, what have we learned?
In fulfillment of Bible prophecy,
a large company of young people
from around the world
are taking a stand
with Jehovah and Jesus.
That includes all of you.
Like dewdrops,
you’re not only abundant in number
but you sparkle in our congregations.
Your presence is very refreshing.
So please,
don’t look down on your youth.
Rather, rejoice in your youth!
Yes, “become an example
to the faithful ones”!
In the following dramatization,
a young brother is doing
just what we’ve discussed.
He’s becoming an example
to faithful ones
and working hard
at the assignments he is given.
But there’s something he lacks
—a quality that would make him
even more valuable to Jehovah
and to the congregation.
Before the meeting starts,
I need to get things ready.
I’m Ben.
And as a ministerial servant,
I can do a lot
to help the congregation.
And that night
I was given another assignment.
Brother Richards asked if I could help him
update the territory maps
and organize our schedules
for public witnessing.
I think the brothers know
I can modernize all of this.
Brother Richards said to talk
to Brother Bello, first.
He was the service overseer for years.
Great idea!
But I can already imagine
the possibilities.
By that weekend,
I had almost finished.
I couldn’t believe the outdated ways
our records were kept.
This is going to be way better
for the congregation.
And who knows
what else could be improved?
I thought I had everything ready
to show Brother Richards.
He liked the new ideas,
but then he asked me,
“What did Brother Bello think?”
Oh, Brother Bello!
I forgot.
I should have asked him,
but at this point,
did it really matter?
Brother Richards suggested
we read about Elisha.
When the older Elijah’s work was ending,
Elisha stuck close to his teacher.
Urged to stay behind,
Elisha repeatedly said:
“As surely as Jehovah is living
and as you are living,
I will not leave you.”
Until the moment Elijah left,
Elisha wanted to learn from him.
Like a son asking his father,
he wanted a double portion
of Elijah’s spirit
to continue the work he started.
And Elisha’s first miracle
was the same as Elijah’s last:
dividing the Jordan
with Elijah’s official garment.
Everything Elisha did
revealed his respect
for the experienced man Elijah.
I wasn’t finished
with my new assignment after all.
There was a lot I needed to learn
from Brother Bello.
He really understood
our preaching territory
and the people who live here.
He liked my ideas,
but everything he showed me
made them even better.
I can do a lot
to help the congregation.
And I pray that Jehovah
lets me do even more
with the gifts he gave me
and with the wisdom
of experienced men.
Ben had good ideas to improve
the work he’d been assigned,
but he also learned to respect
the experience of older brothers.
You too may have ideas
to benefit your assignment,
whether in the congregation,
at Bethel, or on a construction project.
Like Ben, seek the wisdom
of experienced brothers and sisters
who did the assignment before you.
Find out why they did things
a certain way.
What were the challenges
they faced?
What direction and resources
influenced their efforts?
How can their experience
help you succeed?
You’ll see the wisdom
in what may at first
look like outdated methods.
Speak respectfully
of their past work,
and you’ll reflect how Jehovah
treasures what they did for Him.
Jehovah will, in turn,
bless the work of your hands.
What else will bring
Jehovah’s blessing?
He draws close
to spiritually-minded people.
Young Christians all over the world
are experiencing
the benefits of maintaining
a close relationship with God.
Each of you faces
a unique set of circumstances
that make it difficult
to be a spiritually-minded youth.
So we interviewed young Witnesses
from different lands
to find out what they do
to keep growing spiritually.
Our relationship with Jehovah
can start when we’re young.
For me, it was the example
that others set
of putting Jehovah first
and the happiness
that came as a result,
as well as being
in that sort of environment
that really helped me
to want to reach out
as well as be available
for those opportunities.
And once we do
give our life to Jehovah,
it’s amazing to see the blessings
that he has in store for us.
But in order to build that relationship,
we need to read God’s Word;
we also need to pray to him.
The more you
get to know him,
the more appealing things
you learn about him.
That makes you not want to lose him
as your friend.
I always knew it was the truth
and that I wanted
to serve Jehovah forever.
But I needed to reassure myself
of certain aspects,
so I did some research projects
with my parents,
using the Creator book and some items
from the Bible Teach book.
After that,
it only became more obvious.
And I was certain that I wanted it
and that I was ready to get baptized.
To strengthen
my relationship with Jehovah,
I read the Bible daily
and I pray.
Especially when
there is no one around or it’s quiet,
I talk to Jehovah
with all my heart at that time.
Making myself available
for spiritual opportunities
was a little bit difficult for me at first,
but I didn’t give up.
After my baptism,
I became a ministerial servant,
and I also served
almost two years in Bethel.
And now I’m a regular pioneer
in Hpado
in a Karen-speaking congregation.
I didn’t know or speak
the Karen S’gaw language,
so the local brothers helped me
to learn not only how to speak
but also how to read.
Prayers
are important to strengthen
my relationship with Jehovah.
For me, it’s like talking
to a friend,
and that’s always helpful.
He’s someone real to me,
and I fully trust
that he listens to me.
I support the elders by helping
with the cleaning of the hall,
serving as an attendant,
handling microphones,
as well as helping
the congregation spiritually.
When I share Jehovah’s promises
of eternal life with others,
I too am encouraged.
I’m constantly remembering
what Jehovah promises,
and that motivates me
to keep preaching.
There’s a family
in our congregation
who took me into their home
and served
as my spiritual parents.
Through our family worship,
they helped me
to progress spiritually.
The elderly ones in our congregation
have been helping me a lot.
First, they’re good examples.
They also remind me
to keep my eye simple.
Despite their limited circumstances
because of age,
they are determined
to serve Jehovah God.
And that made me
reflect on my situation.
I’m very young.
What prevents me from doing
the things that they do?
Before I
began pioneering,
I used to sell fish
seven days a week,
but now I sell fish four days a week,
so three days are available for pioneering.
To be able to be available
for spiritual opportunities,
I closely associate
with my congregation.
I offer some older ones
a ride to the meetings
or in the preaching work.
The reason I’m doing this
is because I want to give
my youth and energy
to Jehovah God.
When I was at school,
I would conduct Bible studies
with some of my classmates.
In time, they joined me
in serving Jehovah.
When I think about being with them
in the future Paradise,
it gives me deep joy.
I have the privilege
of studying with a deaf girl
who lives two hours
from where I live.
We have to walk all the way.
She is very happy
with what she’s learning,
and her family is very supportive.
So knowing that Jehovah
is helping her
and I have a part in it,
it’s just priceless.
Auxiliary pioneering
definitely helped me
because it was like a stepping stone
to regular pioneering.
The ministry definitely gives you
the opportunity
to be able
to work closely with Jehovah.
And then it—
By doing that, you’re reaffirming
your faith in what
you already believe in,
and then you’re drawing closer
to Jehovah in friendship.
Having jw.org and the broadcast
has definitely drawn me
closer to our brothers
and sisters but also to Jehovah as well.
Just by nature,
I feel like I’m more of a timid person,
so going door to door
can be a little scary.
But seeing other young ones
in different parts of the world
that are enduring
very difficult circumstances
and living conditions
and yet are still giving
their best to Jehovah
is so encouraging for me.
And it helps me to keep going on
and give Jehovah my best as well.
When I think personally
about all the avenues of service
that we can have a hand in today,
there are so many that are exciting
—whether it be pioneering
in a foreign country,
serving where the need is great,
even serving at Bethel.
Unless we “taste and see
that Jehovah is good,”
unless we put ourself out there
and are available
to try that at least once,
we’ll never know
what it would be like
to really serve Jehovah.
And in doing that,
you will see how Jehovah
does want the best life for us.
Those young ones
and others like them
are developing the same
spiritual qualities
that Paul saw in Timothy.
Read along with me and see
how Paul described Timothy
at Philippians chapter 2
starting at verse 20:
“For I have no one else
of a disposition like his
“who will genuinely care
for your concerns.
“For all the others are seeking
their own interests,
“not those of Jesus Christ.
“But you know the proof
he gave of himself,
“that like a child with a father
he slaved with me
to advance the good news.”
What is it that Paul
saw in Timothy?
He saw his spiritual disposition,
or attitude.
He observed his genuine interest
in his brothers and sisters.
Timothy really desired
to do God’s will
even though others were seeking
their personal interests.
And Timothy earned
his fellow worshippers’ respect
by working with older
and more experienced Christians,
like Paul, in the ministry.
When you
spiritually-minded young ones
cultivate that beautiful
Timothy-like disposition,
you make Jehovah’s heart rejoice.
Of course,
putting Kingdom interests first
and the needs of others
ahead of our own is not always easy.
We know there are real temptations
that can lead a young person
away from Jehovah.
When others
outside the congregation
recognize our abilities
and talents,
we could begin to seek
“great things” for ourselves,
perhaps fame and recognition.
In this interview,
Brother Edgardo Franco
relates how this desire
caused him
to turn his back on Jehovah.
So, if the Devil tempted Jesus,
don’t you think
he will try to tempt us
in order to jeopardize
our relationship with God?
This is the best contract
we’ve ever offered you.
Listen, I’ll get you a plan
so you can attend
your religious meetings during the week.
Just do the concert
for us on the weekend!
People always ask me,
“Why did you leave
the music world?”
When I was still a boy,
I had dreams
about becoming a famous singer.
Then I learned the truth,
but I never fully removed
those dreams from my heart.
And then I started listening
to some bad influences from my past,
and they got me hooked.
Then they reeled me
into the recording studio.
The lyrics in the songs
—they really bothered
my conscience.
So they offered me
some liquor to loosen me up,
and then I started
to feel more comfortable.
I started singing,
and they liked what they were hearing.
And those songs ended up
all over the radio stations.
It was as if Satan
gave me a trophy
for abandoning Jehovah.
I became addicted to the applause.
Everything looks so beautiful,
but when you’re on top
—when you’re really at the top
of Satan’s world—
there’s nothing beautiful there.
I was an actor,
and when the cameras
turned on,
my face and my smile
turned on too.
But when I would get back
to the hotel,
it was a huge letdown.
There was no applause
—just that silence
that tormented my conscience.
So basically, you had to find
other distractions,
and one of those for me
was the slot machine.
And, of course, casinos
don’t just come with slot machines.
They also expose you
to prostitution and alcohol.
My conscience would ask,
‘What are you doing here?’
I remember those times on tour,
from my limousine,
I’d see the brothers preaching,
and that would always touch my heart.
I would say to myself, ‘Wow!
‘Jehovah trained you
to be doing that,
and look at what you’re doing!’
That really cut deep into my heart.
The road back to the truth was,
really, very hard.
Every time I was going to retire,
I’d say, “This is it!”
But then there would always be
a bigger contract.
I had to make drastic decisions.
But finally I said:
“I don’t care what they offer me.
“I have to return to Jehovah.
“I have to fulfill the vow
“I made to him
when I was a young man,
when I dedicated my life to him.”
So I prayed to Jehovah
very earnestly and said:
“Jehovah,
I need to return to you.
“I need to return
to your loving arms.
“Satan has ripped me
away from you.
Please help me.”
I remember that before I went
in to that first meeting,
I told Jehovah, “Please give me a sign
that you will take me back.”
And there was
an elderly sister there.
She gave me a great big hug
and said, “Welcome back, son!”
And she took my hand
and sat by me
during the entire meeting.
I had betrayed Jehovah,
but I thank—
I thank the brothers
because Jehovah
put brothers at every turn.
They showed me with the Bible
how far I had strayed
from the paths of the true God,
and everything you do
has consequences.
I have asked Jehovah many times
to forgive me for all the things
I have done
—and the brothers too—
all the people
I offended by my actions.
All those trophies I won
—every last one of them—
are there collecting dust.
But Jehovah has given me
a different kind of trophy
in his organization
—helping others to dedicate
their lives to him.
That’s something no one
can take away from you.
We don’t all
have to learn the hard way.
We have to keep enduring
and never turn
our backs on Jehovah.
That’s the worst mistake
anyone could make.
We know that it’s Jehovah
who gives us our talents,
so we should use them
all in his service.
I have found happiness,
and that gives me
a glow that’s not just
for the cameras.
Everyone who knows me
can see it.
Brother Franco enjoys serving
as both a regular pioneer
and congregation elder.
He feels privileged
to shepherd young people
facing some of the same temptations
he experienced.
He often relates a favorite scripture
from Proverbs 8:35.
Referring to wisdom,
that scripture says:
“For the one finding me
will find life,
and he receives approval
from Jehovah.”
Brothers and sisters,
Jehovah does want us to find life,
and he wants us to be successful
in our spiritual pursuits.
In this Bethel morning worship,
Brother Robert Luccioni
discusses how we can reach
the potential that Jehovah knows
we have.
Our text today is very encouraging
as it reminds us,
through this example of Amos,
that Jehovah notices the potential
of each one of his servants.
In fact, one of the comments
from today’s text states:
“Even though we may
lack self-confidence,
“Jehovah can help us
go beyond our perceived limits
and reach goals that we
would not have imagined.”
See, Jehovah knows our potential.
But you note from that statement,
this is also a reminder
that we have to put forth effort
to reach our potential.
You see, if we’re not careful,
we can sabotage our own efforts
to reach the potential
that Jehovah sees in us.
How’s that possible?
Well, let’s look at three examples.
Number one:
We can limit potential
by not throwing ourselves
into what we are asked to do.
Now, we may remember
the account of Jehoash
the king of Israel
there in 2 Kings chapter 13,
when he visited
the prophet Elisha who was dying.
And you notice there
at 2 Kings 13:17
that Elisha
notes Jehoash’s potential.
You notice he says there
that: “You will
strike down Syria . . .
until you finish it off.”
See, he noted the potential
that he had to finish off Syria.
But then what happens?
Well, you remember that’s where
Elisha tells the king
to beat the arrows
on the ground three times or—
beat it on the ground,
and he only does it three times.
Notice what happens in verse 19:
“At that the man of the true God
“grew indignant at him and said:
“‘You should have struck the ground
five or six times!
“‘Then you
would have struck down Syria
“‘until you finished it off,
“‘but now
you will strike down Syria
only three times.’”
What happened?
Well, you see, by not throwing himself
into what he was asked to do
—showing zeal for his assignment—
he would only
have limited success.
Jehoash limited his own potential.
Number two:
We can limit our potential
by focusing on our inadequacies
or our insecurities.
The account that drives that home
for me is that of Moses.
If you look in Exodus chapter 3,
and in this account we know
it’s not due to lack of zeal,
but, rather,
Moses’ own insecurities
that nearly caused him to limit
how he was used by Jehovah.
So we know in Exodus chapter 3,
he received a very weighty assignment
—going to Pharaoh.
And notice what happens
in verse 11,
Exodus 3:11.
It says: “However,
Moses said to the true God:
“‘Who am I that I
should go to Pharaoh
and bring the Israelites
out of Egypt?’”
Now, that’s a normal reaction.
We probably would have felt
the same way.
‘Jehovah, are you sure
you have the right person here?’
And Jehovah says, ‘No.
I do.
I will be with you.’
You look on in verse 13, it says:
“But Moses said to the true God:
‘Suppose I
“‘go to [Israel] and say to them,
“‘“The God of your forefathers
has sent me to you,”
“‘and they say to me,
“What is his name?”
What should I say to them?’”
Jehovah says, ‘No problem,’
and He explains His name
—even tells him
what His name means
and how that power
will be behind him.
Chapter 4, verse 1:
“However, Moses answered:
‘But suppose they do not believe me
“‘and do not listen to my voice,
for they will say,
“Jehovah did not appear to you.”’”
‘No problem, Moses.
What’s in your hand?’
It’s where he has the staff.
He shows him miracles
that he can perform to show
that Jehovah is behind him.
Look at verse 10:
“Moses now said to Jehovah:
‘Pardon me, Jehovah,
“‘but I have never been a fluent speaker,
neither in the past
“‘nor since you have spoken
to your servant,
for I am slow of speech
and slow of tongue.’”
‘OK, Moses,
who created the mouth?
I’ll speak for you.
Don’t worry about it.’
Look at verse 13:
“But he said: ‘Pardon me,
Jehovah, please send
anyone whom you
want to send.’”
And notice what it says
in verse 14:
“Then Jehovah’s anger
blazed against Moses.”
‘Fine, you know, I’m going
to just send somebody else.’
But, you see, thankfully,
Moses got the point
and he jumped into the assignment
and was used further by Jehovah.
But what happened here?
You notice, Moses got caught up
worrying about his inadequacies,
worrying about all the things
that could go wrong.
Jehovah was saying,
‘Just get moving,
and I will take care
of the rest.’
Jehovah saw that
Moses had the potential
to carry out this assignment;
however,
Moses was limiting himself.
Number three:
We can limit our own potential
by becoming paralyzed by fear
—fear of failure.
If you turn to the account
in Numbers chapter 13,
we notice that this
is what happened to the ten spies.
And it’s very interesting,
a phrase they used when they
came back from spying out the land.
Numbers chapter 13,
and look at verse 33.
It says:
“And there we saw the Nephilim,
“the sons of Anak,
who [were] from the Nephilim,
and in comparison
we seemed like grasshoppers,”
and notice, “both to us
and to them.”
You see, they ran into these
sons of Anak who were giants,
men of extraordinary size
who inhabited
the mountainous region of Canaan,
and it was understandable
that these enemies of Jehovah
viewed the Israelites
as puny grasshoppers.
‘You can just squash them
—no competition.’
But, you know, the ten spies
saw themselves the same way.
And, see, their view
of themselves in this situation
paralyzed them with fear
and caused them
to demoralize the entire nation.
But now, in contrast,
we think of the account of David,
who as a young man
also encountered a giant, Goliath.
And remember, Goliath also saw David
as a defenseless little boy
and as a grasshopper,
if you will.
But did David see himself
the same way?
No, he said: ‘You are coming to me
with sword and spear.
I am coming to you
with the name of Jehovah.’
You see, David did not allow himself
to be paralyzed by fear.
He trusted in Jehovah,
and David lived up to the potential
that Jehovah saw in him.
So, what’s the lesson for us?
Well, the lesson is that this illustrates
—these accounts illustrate—
that sometimes we can be
our own worst enemy at times.
See, lack of zeal
—not throwing ourself into the work,
as in the case of Jehoash;
or our own insecurities,
as in the case of Moses;
or fear of failure,
as in the case of the ten spies
—can cause us to limit
the potential that Jehovah sees in us.
So, what do we do?
Well, Jehovah’s words to Gideon
remind us of what we could do,
and we invite you
to turn to Judges chapter 6.
And you remember
that for seven years
the Midianites
oppressed the nation of Israel,
and Jehovah’s angel appears
to Gideon and says that He is going
to deliver Israel
out of this wicked nation.
How could he possibly succeed?
We read the account,
and Gideon saw himself
as the least significant
one of his father’s house.
And he said his father’s house
was the least significant family
of the tribe of Manasseh.
But yet Jehovah saw
the potential that Gideon had.
And what did Jehovah
tell him to do?
Look at Judges 6:14.
It says:
“Jehovah faced him and said:
“‘Go with the strength you have,
“‘and you will save Israel
out of Midian’s hand.
Is it not I who [sent] you?’”
Interesting.
‘Go with the strength
you have.
‘I know you cannot do it
on your own strength.
‘Just get moving;
throw everything you can into it;
and I, Jehovah,
will make up the difference.’
You see,
that’s what Jehovah is saying,
and that’s exactly what happened.
So may we be determined
to do the same.
We know that none of us
accomplish Jehovah’s work
on our own strength,
on our own wisdom,
on our own abilities.
But when we receive an assignment,
we need to just start moving.
Do not let our inadequacies
paralyze us.
Do not let fear of failure
Throw ourselves into the work.
Have a zeal for the work.
Go with the strength
that you have.
Trust in Jehovah
to make up the difference,
and you will live up to the potential
that Jehovah sees in you.
What excellent counsel for all of us,
and especially for young ones
with a life of service to God
ahead of them.
That life with Jehovah
can be everlasting!
That is our firm hope.
Until then, will you remain loyal,
resist what the world offers you,
and reach your potential?
Imagine your life
100 years from now.
Will you regret the decades
you gave to Jehovah?
Will anything you endured
in Satan’s system
slow you down
from gaining life’s prize?
Some of our brothers and sisters
can already look back
that far and answer
those questions.
Sister Alma Miller’s family
learned the truth
when she was ten years old.
She was baptized in 1937
and is now 107 years old.
To her, just about everyone
is a young person.
See the encouraging effect
her loving and faithful example
has on young ones
in her congregation.
People often tell me,
“Why, I never talked to a person
that was 107 years old.”
And I tell them,
“You know what?
I never did either.”
I would describe Alma
as probably the most energetic
100-plus-year-old lady
that I’ve ever met.
She has, pretty much,
the whole theocratic history
in her mind that she carries with her.
So you can ask her anything
about the organization,
and she can be able to tell you about it
because she’s even met
a lot of those people.
We read about it, but she lived it.
She’s amazing.
Even though she’s 107,
she has an incredible memory.
I go back quite a ways.
When I was very young,
ten years old,
we saw the “Photo-Drama of Creation.”
And it was just packed with people.
They were even standing in the back.
We were so thrilled.
We never forgot it.
And we realized
that we found the truth.
My father left the church
and he became
one of Jehovah’s Witnesses
and they were called Bible Students
at that time.
In the early days,
we went to special conventions,
and some places,
they had a big field
where they put the cars
and they set up their tents.
They even named different streets.
It was just like a little city.
I was really thrilled
to see Brother Rutherford speak
at the conventions I attended.
I got married to Harold Miller in 1931.
That was when the depression
was going on,
and times were very difficult.
Everything was scarce.
There were no jobs to be had.
Food was rationed.
People were really hungry.
And they moved in any little shack
that they could just to get by.
We didn’t have anything.
And we couldn’t drive the car,
so we used to have a little white horse
—the name was Lou.
And we went out witnessing
with the horse and buggy.
She took us all over the place,
far distances.
They would take this buggy,
and they would go
20-30 miles in one direction;
20-30 miles the other direction.
All the hard work that they put forth
has resulted
in several congregations in the area.
We used to carry that magazine bag
when we were witnessing
for awhile there.
And so we put it
around the horse’s neck,
so the horse was taking part
in our witnessing.
People knew
who was coming when they saw
the little white horse
come into their yard.
Sometimes it was cold,
and I remember wearing two coats.
Yeah, it was tiresome,
but we were young.
They would just go out
regardless of rain or shine
or whatever was going on at the time,
and they didn’t have a car.
And to me, that’s amazing
because we get so used to
the conveniences
—I guess you could call it—
the coffee breaks,
the cars, and everything.
It’s like, well,
if Alma can do it, surely I can do it.
One time,
Harold went out witnessing,
and 50 years later,
he talked to the same man.
He said, “50 years ago,
“there was a young guy
that came through here
“riding on horseback
and telling people that,”
he said,
“I think it’s ‘Armaggigon,’
he said was coming soon.”
And he remembered
Harold riding horseback
50 years ago in that territory,
and he got there again.
And that happened
a couple times more.
So it was a long life of witnessing.
Alma is so zealous for the ministry.
She does not like not-at-homes.
She wants to talk to people.
Yeah, I enjoy the ministry.
I go out as much as I can
in my old age.
We want to help the people
to see the truth.
There’s no greater joy.
I try to read the publications,
so I have a reading machine.
The letters come right out of the screen,
and I can study all my lessons.
I would be lost without it.
It helps me to keep up
in present truth.
What does dedication mean?
Sister Miller, please.
Dedication means that. . .
Some young ones might be concerned
about what they should do
with their life,
what choices they should make.
Well, here we see an example
of somebody who has served Jehovah
for over 100 years.
And we see that she’s happy
and has no regrets with her life.
And that’s an example
that we want to imitate.
Well, giving my life to Jehovah,
that’s the best thing
I could do for myself.
If I have any advice
for young ones today,
I would say
to keep on in the truth.
They have a whole world before them
to serve Jehovah
—something that endures forever.
Wasn’t that encouraging?
With all the videos we use
in our worship today,
it’s also interesting that
Sister Miller’s introduction to the truth
was the “Photo-Drama of Creation.”
That was a photographic slide
and motion picture production,
complete with color and sound,
which first showed in 1914.
You might enjoy learning more
about that historic presentation
as a personal study project.
Sister Miller has experienced
much in her 107 years.
She’s endured economic depression,
health problems,
and the loss of family and friends,
including her dear husband.
But as we saw,
Jehovah has blessed her
with a spiritual family
in the congregation.
At the same time,
those interviewed with Sister Miller
are enjoying a close friendship
with someone older.
Even very young ones
are finding friends
among older brothers and sisters.
David, age nine, wrote this
in his letter to the Governing Body:
“I like to listen to older ones.
“I just used to have
a circle of friends,
but now I feel more comfortable
going and talking to older ones.”
It’s no surprise, then,
that in the latest
Become Jehovah’s Friend video,
Sophia learns that you’re never
too young
or too old
to be someone’s friend.
Sister Elsa,
did you paint these?
I did.
They’re amazing!
How long
have you been drawing?
As long as I can remember.
It’s my way
of being able to share
all the stories of my life.
Could you show me?
Yes, of course!
I remember a time when I was young
and in East Germany.
We weren’t allowed to do our work
as Jehovah’s Witnesses;
we were under ban.
I helped in copying
our Watchtower magazines by hand
and then hiding them in food.
You did?
Yes!
We’d then send the food
to our brothers who were in prison.
I was also asked to help
in distributing Bible literature
to our congregations
as an underground messenger.
Wow!
Time passed and then things
started getting better in Berlin.
Shortly after,
I immigrated to New York.
And I met my darling husband.
Wow, that was a great story!
Thank you.
But I’m sure you have stories.
What do you like to draw?
Well, actually, here!
This was the time
when Caleb and I went to the park,
and we met a little girl there.
I’m glad I reached out that day.
Lasting friends can be of any age
when they love Jehovah.
Elsa and Sophia already share
much in common
and are likely
to become good friends.
We’re pleased to announce that
this new Become Jehovah’s Friend lesson
is available
on Video on Demand
under the “Children” category.
You parents and family heads
are doing all you can
to teach your children from infancy
to love Jehovah
and to become his friend.
As they grow,
you also teach them
how to study and pray
on their own.
You know they need
these spiritual skills.
Young ones, remember that
your personal study time
is when you
can ask Jehovah for help
with what you
are personally experiencing,
and that study time
has other good effects.
As this music video tells us,
“Study Makes You Strong”!
Since we could crawl,
our family studied it all.
Even though small,
we understood what we were learning.
Father would read to me
before I would sleep.
Now I am taller;
I still keep up with that routine.
And when I’m by myself,
I take that book down off the shelf.
I remember what the scripture said
that I would need so I could stand firm.
Study makes you strong,
Just like a tree that’s planted
by a river stream.
Study makes you strong.
Your leaves just won’t dry out
and everything succeeds.
Study makes you strong,
Just like a tree that’s planted
its roots down deep.
Study makes you strong.
You’ll grow so big and tall
there’s nothing you won’t see.
What will I say when a big chance
comes my way?
What will my classmates say
if I don’t follow with them?
All of the information’s
here on display.
I’m not afraid,
because I learned this as an infant.
ʹCause when I’m by myself,
I take that book down off the shelf.
I remember what the scripture said
that I would need so I could stand firm.
Study makes you strong,
Just like a tree that’s planted
by a river stream.
Study makes you strong.
Your leaves just won’t dry out
and everything succeeds.
Study makes you strong,
Just like a tree that’s planted
its roots down deep.
Study makes you strong.
You’ll grow so big and tall
there’s nothing you won’t see.
Every word that’s helping me
Could contain the very key
To offer just the help
and encouragement somebody needs.
Study makes you strong.
Study makes you strong,
Just like a tree that’s planted
by a river stream.
Study makes you strong.
Your leaves just won’t dry out
and everything succeeds.
Study makes you strong,
Just like a tree that’s planted
its roots down deep.
Study makes you strong.
You’ll grow so big and tall
there’s nothing you won’t see.
Study does make us strong!
As depicted in the music video,
the Bible reading and study habits
that the young sister
started with her family
became her own personal habits.
When a challenging situation or opportunity
to give a witness came along,
she already knew how to research
what she needed from the Scriptures.
Our prayer is that all of you
young brothers and sisters
grow spiritually strong
in the same way
and become examples
to faithful ones everywhere.
That brings us
to our video postcard
from faithful brothers and sisters.
This month we visit beautiful Austria,
in Central Europe.
Brother C.T. Russell
first visited Austria in 1891.
He returned in 1911 to plant
further seeds of Kingdom truth
in the capital city, Vienna.
Today, there are more than 21,000
active publishers
among the eight million
who live in Austria.
One of the 301 congregations
is the German-language congregation
in Uderns.
They preach in a territory
of alpine mountains and valleys.
Some farms are as high in elevation
as 1,700 meters,
or more than 5,500 feet.
But difficult terrain does not slow
the Kingdom message.
The 48 publishers there
recently reported conducting
51 Bible studies.
We thank them for showing us
another encouraging example
of the brotherly love that unites
God’s people worldwide.
They send us their Christian love
and greetings,
and we send our love in return,
along with prayers for Jehovah’s favor.
We thank you for joining us,
and we look forward
to an encouraging program next month.
From Brooklyn, New York,
this is JW Broadcasting!