Today’s scripture text and Watchtower comments
encourage us to exert ourselves
to show love to others,
especially our brothers.
So let’s discuss the theme
“Pursue the Way of Love.”
And interestingly, that expression,
“pursue love,” is found three times in the Bible.
The verb “pursue” is very appropriate.
Why?
Well, it means to chase,
to persistently follow in an effort
to overtake or capture.
Now, we could illustrate with
a small child chasing a butterfly
—pursuing it, chasing,
pursuing in an effort to overtake or capture.
Now, what is the butterfly trying to do?
Get away, escape, evade.
If we think about it, that’s what love tries to do to us.
But, now, why?
The question is,
Why does love try to get away from us,
thus requiring that we pursue it?
Well, the main reason
is because of the imperfection that we’ve inherited.
Genesis 1:27 tells us
that originally Adam was made
in Jehovah’s image,
perfectly reflecting Jehovah and his qualities.
He did that just perfectly.
But then when he sinned,
imperfection entered.
And we could say that Adam became
a distorted reflection of Jehovah and his qualities.
Now, we can illustrate this
with a distorted mirror,
perhaps at the fair or circus.
It can make you look a lot taller,
a lot shorter, a lot fatter,
a lot thinner than you really are
and distort you in other ways.
Well, in effect, Adam became a distorted reflection
of Jehovah and his qualities,
and we’ve inherited that condition.
We are distorted reflections
of Jehovah and his qualities,
so we have to pursue love.
But now let me ask this,
Would you say
that Jehovah is pursuing the way of love?
Well, that could be a trick question.
But is Jehovah chasing, trying to catch love?
No.
First John 4:8: “God is love.”
He just naturally displays it, see.
He doesn’t have to work at it.
He, you can say, radiates it.
It emanates from Jehovah God.
But with us it’s different, see.
In our imperfection,
love is not our natural inclination;
we have to pursue it.
But now the question is, How do we do it?
Well, the entire Bible tells us how to pursue love,
but specifically the five verses
at 1 Corinthians 13:4-8
tell us how to pursue love.
Now, there we have 16 expressions of love:
nine ways that love does not behave
and seven ways that it does behave.
And if we closely examine
those 16 expressions of love,
we’ll have direction in our pursuit of love.
We won’t wander aimlessly;
we won’t travel erroneously.
Now, as time permits,
let’s discuss some of the ways that love
does not act and ways it doesn’t behave.
One: “Love is not jealous.”
Now, in the Bible, jealousy can have
a good connotation or a bad connotation.
In the good connotation,
it’s closely related to zealous.
But, of course,
here Jehovah is using it in the bad sense,
and by far the majority of times
in the Bible that’s the way the word is  used.
Now, what does it mean?
Well, it means envious
of good things coming to others.
It can be worse than anger.
Anger can come and pass quickly,
but jealousy can be harbored deep.
In fact, Proverbs 14:30
talks about it being deep down in the bones.
Well, how can we avoid jealousy
and pursue love even though it’s not easy?
We have to prayerfully, with Jehovah’s help,
do what is mentioned in Romans chapter 12.
Please turn there.
In Romans chapter 12,
here’s what Jehovah tells us to do,
verse number 15:
“Rejoice with those who rejoice;
weep with those who weep.”
Now think about it.
Which of the two is the hardest?
Well, generally, it’s not so hard
to weep with someone who is weeping.
They found out they have cancer;
they lose a loved one in death.
We can be very sorry with them.
But, now, often it’s harder
to rejoice with someone who rejoices.
They may receive some good thing
or something good has happened to them,
and it didn’t happen to us.
Now, here’s just one little illustration:
Let’s say an elder is so happy that he received
an assignment for the regional convention.
Now, we’ve always wanted to get an assignment,
but we didn’t get an assignment.
Are we going to rejoice
with our brother who is rejoicing
—not just on the outside,
outwardly appearing that we’re happy for him—
but inside we have jealousy?
Truly in our heart being happy,
rejoicing with our brother who is rejoicing
—with Jehovah’s help—
we can do that.
We can work on our attitude.
And if you think about it, about the only emotion
that is stronger than jealousy is love.
With love we can smash jealousy.
Now, another expression of love:
Love “does not brag.”
If we’re pursuing the way of love,
we will prayerfully work hard
not to elevate ourselves in our speech.
We’ll strive not to so often use the pronouns
“I” and “me,”
thus directing attention to ourselves.
Rather, we’ll play our role down.
We’ll direct attention to others
and especially to our God, Jehovah.
Another expression of love:
Love “does not get puffed up.”
Now, puffed up is closely related to bragging
because normally a person
who is puffed up brags, doesn’t he?
But do you think it would be possible
to be puffed up and not brag?
Yes.
We could actually have this attitude,
thinking too much of ourselves
even though we didn’t make
an outward expression of that attitude.
Well, why would that be unloving
if we were puffed up but we didn’t brag?
Well, others would sense it
—see, that attitude would come across.
It would project and, in effect,
it would put others down rather than build them up.
And most important,
Jehovah would read that attitude in our heart,
and he wouldn’t bless us.
So here’s what he
tells us to do regarding our thinking.
Romans 12 again,
and this time take a look at verse 3,
and right in the middle there Jehovah says:
“I tell everyone there among you
“not to think more of himself
than it is necessary to think.”
So you notice, Jehovah is saying that we
shouldn’t even think that way about ourselves.
We should have a humble attitude.
Another expression of love:
Love “does not behave indecently.”
Now, there are varying degrees of indecency
—shocking indecency, immorality.
But on the other end of the spectrum,
perhaps a lack of good manners.
Well, we don’t even
want to be slightly indecent, do we?
Especially as Bethelites,
we want to have good manners
by generously using the expressions
“thank you” and “please,”
by holding the door for others,
by allowing them
to have their preferences
—the first place, and so forth.
When we pass them in the hall,
warmly greeting our brothers
and not being
more interested in our electronic device
than we are that brother that we’re passing.
See, show good manners
as we interact with our brothers.
Another expression of love:
Love “does not become provoked.”
Now, here’s one example, just quickly.
Let’s say we’re driving our car;
we’re parked at a red light;
the light turns green,
and immediately
the person behind us blows the horn,
indicating we should move on quicker.
Now, does that get to us?
Do we start off very slow?
We’re going to make them pay for that.
Well, we’re getting provoked.
Remember, love does not get provoked.
One more example:
Love “does not keep account of the injury.”
Does that mean
we have to totally blot out of our mind
any recollection of the injury?
No.
As the scripture says,
we don’t “keep account of the injury,”
which would indicate maintaining a ledger
—a debt being owed.
Now, we may remember the injury,
but we have forgiven in our heart.
We have cancelled the debt.
Well, there we have six expressions of love.
And I’m going to assign you the other ten
to do the research
there in those verses that we were talking about.
But from our discussion,
it’s obvious that we have to pursue love.
It doesn’t come easy;
it doesn’t come effortlessly
—none of these expressions.
Like that butterfly we talked about  in the beginning
trying to get away from the child,
love tries to get away from us.
But with Jehovah’s help, we can pursue it.
And we’re going to have to keep doing this.
How long?
Well, until the marvelous time
when we’re perfect,
and then we’ll no longer have to pursue love.
Like Jehovah and Jesus,
we will simply be able to display love.
But until that marvelous time,
may 1 Corinthians 13:4-8
give direction to our pursuit of love.