It’s true, isn’t it?
When we look at this prophecy
in the book of Micah,
it’s very exciting
because it portrays to us
what’s actually happening
among God’s people today.
We know that although
in the new world
there will be a tremendous unity
displayed by God’s people,
chapter 4 of Micah
is actually portraying  what’s happening now,
and we’re involved with this.
We know that because
in verse 5 it says
that at the same time
that this unity would be evident:
“All the peoples will walk,
each in the name of its god.”
Well, that’s not talking
about the new world, is it?
It’s talking about the time
we are living in now.
Well, what is it that helps all
of Jehovah’s Witnesses worldwide
to be so united and not to be involved
with the wars of this world?
Well, one of the things that helps us
is our Christian neutrality.
What do we mean by neutrality?
We mean not taking sides
in political issues.
Of course, we take sides
with Jehovah and the Kingdom,
but with regard to worldly political debates
and issues that arise,
we don’t take sides.
Why is this so important?
Well, let’s turn our Bibles
to Revelation chapter 13.
Revelation 13:16, 17,
and here it tells us:
“It puts under compulsion all people
—the small and the great,
“the rich and the poor,
the free and the slaves
“—that these should be marked
on their right hand or on their forehead,
“and that nobody can buy or sell
except a person having the mark,
the name of the wild beast
or the number of its name.”
What’s the point of this verse?
Well, of course,
we will look forward to seeing
how this may
turn out in the future
and what pressure is put
on God’s people at that time.
But even now,
we see the principle here
that the political system is wanting
to put its mark on us,
mentally as well as physically.
So we see the forehead
as well as the hand being involved.
So we need to be absolutely certain
that we remain neutral
with regard to political issues
in the world,
not only by
not being involved actively
in the political issues
but also mentally not allowing
ourselves to take sides.
What are some of the things
that perhaps could erode our neutrality?
Well, maybe we could mention
three things this morning.
One is the propaganda
that the world puts forward.
Now, we have seen what the media says
about Jehovah’s Witnesses, haven’t we?
How distorted some of their reports are
and how they can paint
a negative picture with regard to us.
Well, should we expect
that they are neutral
with regard to other events
that they report on,
particularly when there are conflicts
between two nations?
The media
in one particular nation may promote
certain ideas about the other nation.
We may be affected by that.
We may be surprised perhaps
to visit some other countries
that have a different political ideology
and be surprised to see
how things perhaps are a little different
in that country to how it’s portrayed
by the media in our country.
So we need to be careful
not to be influenced
by the propaganda of this world,
particularly media reports and so on.
What’s another thing perhaps
that could cause us
to lose a measure of neutrality?
Sporting events.
Sometimes sporting events
are able to achieve
certain goals
with regard to nationalism.
We see the national anthem
being played at many of these events.
It reminds me many years ago
when I was in a different country,
a friend of mine asked me
to record a certain sporting event.
I wasn’t particularly
interested in the event,
but because he made this request,
I recorded it.
And, of course, I wanted to make sure
that I got the last ten minutes of it.
I thought our friendship
may be strained
if I didn’t get
the actual last part of the game.
When I watched it,
it was absolutely exciting
—nail-biting finish.
Well, after the brother
gave me back the videotape,
I thought maybe
some of the other brothers
who would be interested
in this sporting event
may want to have it
rather than just wipe the tape.
So I offered it to several,
and each one of them said to me:
“No thanks.
If we had won,
perhaps it would be different.”
Now, what was the problem?
As I said to them,
“Were you watching the game
or were you taking sides?”
An interesting concept,
because here
two different nations were involved.
So we have to be careful
that even sporting events
don’t stir up within us
certain nationalistic feelings,
and perhaps we could take sides
with regard to certain events.
The third area that perhaps
could erode our neutrality:
the political promises being made,
particularly at election time.
Perhaps one of the candidates
is from our ethnic background
or perhaps
is the same gender as we are.
When we look at the political situation
these days with many elections,
it seems to be more in the form
of entertainment than anything else,
with music
and very colorful characters.
But if we were
to say in our heart,
‘I hope that idiot
doesn’t get into power,’
are we neutral?
Or worse still, if we say,
‘I hope the other person
gets into power,’
well, we need
to be careful, don’t we?
I remember many years ago
as a young pioneer in Australia,
I was facing
the conscription issue
—the national call-up
for the military.
At that time,
the Vietnam War was being fought.
And then there was
an election in Australia.
And at that time, the party
that was trying to get into power
said that if they got into power,
they would abolish conscription.
So now that affected me personally.
I remember how hard it was sitting there
watching the election results,
not to say in my heart,
‘I hope they get in.’
And then, when they got in,
not to say, ‘Yes!’
You see, if we personally are affected
by some of these political promises,
we may violate our neutrality.
So brothers and sisters,
let’s work hard at remembering
that we’re no part of this world.
We support the best government
that could ever rule this earth.
And by doing so,
we will keep our neutrality,
and we will keep our unity.