Welcome to our program.
This month’s theme is
“You Are Precious to Jehovah.”
Here are some highlights.
When we’re going through difficult times,
does Jehovah notice?
As we’ll learn in Malu’s experience,
Jehovah does care
and he helps us overcome
even the most challenging circumstances.
Prayer is a powerful way
that we can ask for and receive
loving comfort from Jehovah.
We’ll see that in our new music video.
Soon, all over the earth,
Jehovah’s Witnesses will be inviting people
to this year’s conventions.
Can attending a convention
change a person’s life?
We’ll find out in this report.
Welcome to the April 2020 edition
of JW Broadcasting®!
We begin with the experience
of Juan Pablo Zermeño.
Notice how he found a life
of real meaning and purpose.
When you’re little,
you just want to be happy.
But sadly, my father
had a problem with alcohol,
and no child wants to live through that.
One day, my family
from the United States came to visit us.
They looked so happy!
The way they talked,
it was as though they only had fun
—a good life
with no economic problems.
I was shocked.
I asked myself, ‘How can we live
in such poverty
while their life is so great?’
That was the life I wanted for my family.
So when I was nine years old,
I left my mother and the rest of my family
to cross the border into the United States.
I lived in a pretty rough neighborhood.
So I joined a local gym
to learn how to defend myself.
The trainer, Leo, was like a father to me.
He always tried to give us good advice.
Raymond was part of the boxing team.
He was a good friend.
We got along really well.
He respected me, and he looked after me.
After several years of being around Raymond
and the other members of the team,
I felt really comfortable.
To some extent, I admired him
because I could see
that he was really doing well,
because Raymond was selling drugs.
I knew that it wasn’t right.
But in time,
I began to sell drugs as well.
Raymond was in a drug deal gone wrong,
and he was murdered.
I said to myself,
‘This could happen to me too.’
It had been six years
since I had seen my mom and my siblings.
My mother was studying the Bible
with Jehovah’s Witnesses.
It helped her to cope
with a lot of suffering.
It brought her peace.
She was so happy.
I began to realize
that this was what I really needed.
I also thought about my friends at the gym.
I wanted them to understand why life
was so hard for all of us,
so I returned to the United States.
But they weren’t interested.
My trainer, Leo, told me
that I didn’t need to sell drugs anymore;
he could make me a professional boxer,
and I could help out my family in that way.
He even gave me the nickname The Bible Boy.
But I realized that
that was just a temporary solution.
What I was learning
was going to help me forever.
I was determined to serve Jehovah.
I returned to Mexico.
I started to study the Bible
and take it seriously.
I began to view Jehovah as my Father
because he helped me
to find real relief from my pain,
to have peace
—a tranquility that makes you
feel accepted, loved, and wanted.
I have enjoyed
an incredible life serving Jehovah.
Decades later, my father was baptized
as one of Jehovah’s Witnesses.
Jehovah has been so kind to me,
my family, and my siblings.
Truly, I have no way to repay Jehovah
for the life he’s given me.
I’ve had so many blessings in my life:
a wonderful wife
and great friends,
including those that I serve
alongside of in Bethel.
I’m not on my own anymore.
Jehovah has given me
a life full of real meaning, purpose,
and so much happiness.
Can you imagine
leaving your home at the age of nine?
Juan Pablo sought a better life,
but that only led
to danger and disappointment.
Juan Pablo said that it was
Jehovah who gave him
“a life full of real meaning,
purpose, and . . . happiness.”
Juan Pablo is precious to Jehovah.
As we mentioned—
Our theme for this month’s program is
“You Are Precious to Jehovah.”
How vital it is
that we remind ourselves of that!
Why?
Well, let’s consider three reasons.
First, Satan wants us to believe
that Jehovah doesn’t love us
or value our service.
He wanted Job to believe that.
But that was a lie in Job’s day,
and it’s still a lie today.
A second reason that we need
to be reminded that we’re precious to Jehovah
is because of negative circumstances
or events that have taken place in our life.
Severe illness,
advancing years, injustices,
mistreatment,
a difficult family life, or other situations
may cause some brothers and sisters
to feel that they’re just not worth loving.
Some may question why Jehovah
allows those things to happen.
Finally, we need reminders
of how Jehovah feels about us
because our imperfection
can cause us to have negative thoughts.
Some may still punish
themselves for past mistakes,
doubting that Jehovah has forgiven them
or that he could ever love them.
Others wage a constant battle
against feelings of worthlessness.
One Witness wrote:
“Satan has done an excellent job of making
“even those who love Jehovah
feel worthless and unlovable.
“. . . I never felt worthy of Jehovah’s love,
“so I tried to do
more and more in his service
“as a way of earning that love.
“. . . So no matter
how many hours I spent in the ministry,
“or how many people I helped,
I felt it was not enough.
I saw only the lack in me.”
One brother stated:
“I came from a family
that showed little love.
“I was belittled, teased, and laughed at.
“So, early in life I felt worthless.
“I still carry
entrenched feelings from my past
“that beat me down
when I experience calamity.
“When I stopped serving
as a congregation elder,
“I felt like a failure as usual
—to God, my family,
and my brothers in the congregation.”
If you’ve experienced such feelings,
you’re not alone.
So how can you
be assured of Jehovah’s interest?
Let’s examine three lines of evidence
that prove you’re precious to Jehovah.
First, we’ll examine
Jehovah’s feelings for the nation of Israel.
Second, we’ll reflect
on an event recorded in the Gospels.
And third,
we’ll consider a modern-day example
of one who was very precious to God.
By the end of the 16th century B.C.E.,
millions of Israelites
were enslaved in Egypt,
where they were severely oppressed.
In their distress,
the Israelites cried out to Jehovah.
How did he feel?
Turn with me to Isaiah 63:9.
The A portion reads:
“During all their distress
it was distressing to him.”
Did you notice?
Not only did Jehovah see their troubles
but he felt for his people,
and he was moved to act in their behalf.
Isaiah 63:9 goes on to say:
“In his love and compassion
he repurchased them.”
Jehovah couldn’t see
their suffering or hear their outcries
without feeling for them
and doing something about it.
That may remind us of the loving concern
that a mother has for her newborn child.
When that baby cries,
the mother takes notice
and she feels for her child.
In fact, notice how
this is expressed at Isaiah 49:15.
It reads:
“Can a woman forget her nursing child
“or have no compassion
for the son of her womb?
“Even if these women forget,
I would never forget you.”
It’s hard to imagine a mother forgetting
to nourish and care for her nursing child.
That baby is helpless
—day and night
it needs its mother’s attention.
Sad to say, however,
that we hear at times
of such maternal neglect.
But what did Jehovah say
to reassure the Israelites?
“I would never forget you.”
Yes, the tender compassion
that Jehovah felt for his servants
was immeasurably stronger
than one of the most tender
and natural feelings we can imagine
—the compassion
a mother normally feels for her baby.
Jehovah’s feelings for the Israelites
are summed up
in another expression in the book of Isaiah.
Please read with me Isaiah 43:4:
“For you became precious in my eyes,
you were honored, and I have loved you.”
Jehovah clearly expressed
his feelings for his people.
As one of Jehovah’s servants,
you can be sure
that he also loves you most tenderly.
No matter what trials you’re facing now
or have endured in the past,
Jehovah sees you and he feels for you.
When you hurt, he hurts.
You’re far too precious to Jehovah
for him to forget you.
He remembers your past efforts,
and he sees
your continuing efforts to please him.
Notice how Jehovah promises
to sustain and comfort his people
according to Isaiah 66:12, 13:
“You will nurse and be carried on the hip,
“and you will be bounced on the knees.
“As a mother comforts her son,
so I will keep comforting you.”
What a heartwarming scene!
Imagine a loving mother
carrying a baby on her hip
or bouncing him on her knees.
In this way,
Jehovah touchingly illustrates the intensity
and tenderness of his love for you.
Just as Jehovah loved his people, Israel,
he likewise feels that you
are very precious and dear
—never doubt that!
A second example
of how Jehovah feels
about his faithful servants
can be found in the Gospels.
Let’s read what happened on one occasion
when Jesus was at the temple in Jerusalem
at Luke 21:1-4:
“Now as he looked up,
“he saw the rich dropping their gifts
“into the treasury chests.
“Then he saw a needy widow drop in
“two small coins of very little value,
“and he said:
“‘Truly I say to you that this poor widow
“‘put in more than they all did.
“‘For all of these put in gifts
“‘out of their surplus,
“‘but she, out of her want
“‘[or as the footnote says, “poverty”],
put in all the means of living she had.’”
The study note for verse 2
in the New World Translation
of the Holy Scriptures
tells us that the Greek word
for “needy” may describe
“a person who lacks
the basic necessities of life
“or someone for whom
life is a great struggle.
In the Christian Greek Scriptures,
it is used only here.”
Just think about the widow’s circumstances.
Not only had she experienced the grief
of losing her husband, her provider,
but she also lived in a religious climate
dominated by leaders who,
according to Luke 20:47,
would “devour the houses of the widows”
rather than help such vulnerable ones.
That widow was so poor
that her contribution to the temple
was what a laborer
might earn in just a few minutes.
Life wasn’t easy for her.
In fact, Jesus said that she
“put in all the means of living she had.”
Our publications have stated
that the coins the widow contributed
were likely two lepta.
With eight lepta,
a person could buy two sparrows,
which were among the cheapest birds
used for food.
So the widow had
only half the amount needed
to buy one sparrow,
hardly enough for a single meal.
Yet, both the widow and her contribution
were valuable to Jehovah.
Jesus said that her contribution was greater
than the contributions of the rich.
When she put those two small coins
in the treasury chest,
they would be mixed
with what the rich had put in.
To imperfect human eyes,
they might seem lost, buried.
Yet, this precious widow
was the one Jesus singled out for praise.
When the treasury workers
came across the coins,
they wouldn’t have known
how precious the coins and their donor
were to Jehovah.
But God’s view
was the one that really mattered,
not what other people thought
or even how that dear widow viewed herself.
Like that widow,
you may find that circumstances limit
what you can contribute to Jehovah.
Age, infirmities,
or other circumstances beyond your control
may limit the amount of time
you’re able to spend in the ministry.
You might feel
that your efforts are like those
“two small coins of very little value.”
Still, we learn from this account
of the needy widow
that Jehovah notices
and he treasures each act done for him,
especially when we do it
despite difficult circumstances.
For a moment, think back on your worship
of Jehovah during the past year.
Some of you may feel
that you accomplished little.
Your imperfect heart
might cause you to wonder
whether Jehovah
was pleased with your efforts.
However, did one of the hours you spent
require a special sacrifice on your part?
If Jehovah took notice of the widow
dropping in those two coins
and valued her contribution,
don’t you think he also noticed
and valued what you did
for him during that hour?
Jehovah values every gift,
no matter how small,
that springs from a heart motivated by love.
He remembers, and he’ll reward
even the smallest contribution
given in support of his Kingdom.
That’s proof of how Jehovah feels about you.
Finally, let’s consider a modern-day example
of one who was very precious to Jehovah.
It’s the experience of Sister Areti Pina.
Sister Pina lived
on the southern coast of Albania
in the town of Vlorë.
She was baptized in 1928 at the age of 18.
There was a strong congregation
in Vlorë in the 1930’s,
and Sister Pina was a zealous evangelizer
who climbed up and down rugged mountains,
preaching with her Bible in hand.
In time, a congregation
no longer existed in Vlorë,
and Sister Pina lost contact
with the brothers.
Yet, she kept preaching faithfully
on her own.
Do you think her efforts
went unnoticed by Jehovah?
Well, years later, word reached the brothers
that there was an old, senile woman
who was reportedly preaching in Vlorë.
People thought she was crazy
for keeping faith in God
during years of totalitarian rule.
Yet, Sister Pina, now in her 80’s,
was anything but senile.
When the brothers arrived at her home,
Sister Pina invited them in,
but she seemed somewhat reserved.
When they explained
that they were her spiritual brothers,
she had no reaction.
After a few minutes,
Sister Pina started firing
questions at the brothers:
“Do you believe in the Trinity?
What is God’s name?
“Do you believe in hellfire?
What happens when we die?
What about the earth?
How many go to heaven?”
The brothers answered each question.
“Do you preach?” she then asked.
“Yes,” said one brother, “we preach.”
“But,” she responded,
“how do you preach?”
“We preach from house to house,”
replied the brother.
“Now I know that you are my brothers!”
she exclaimed.
“Only Jehovah’s people
preach from house to house!”
Through her tears, Sister Pina stated:
“Jehovah is wonderful.
He never forgot me!”
Sometime later, the brothers
were notified that Sister Pina was ill
and that she wanted to meet
with one of the responsible brothers.
When he arrived, she asked in part,
as she gasped for air,
“Has the book of Revelation been fulfilled?”
The brother responded,
“Yes, Areti, most of it has.”
Sister Pina said:
“Now I can die in peace.
I needed to know how close we are.”
Shortly after that conversation,
Sister Pina
faithfully finished her earthly course.
What do you think?
During all those years of isolation
from the earthly part
of Jehovah’s organization,
did Sister Pina’s efforts
go unnoticed by Jehovah?
Absolutely not!
Just imagine Jehovah’s joy
as he watched her faithfully doing
what she could in his service.
Do you think that Sister Pina
was precious to Jehovah?
Without a doubt she was.
Well, your efforts in Jehovah’s service
do not go unnoticed by him either.
Like Sister Pina, you are precious to him.
So, what has this consideration
helped us to realize?
We may have to contend with Satan’s lies,
negative circumstances
and events in our lives,
and our own imperfections.
But we should never forget
that Jehovah highly values his servants.
We saw that in his words to the Israelites
through the prophet Isaiah.
You can be sure that Jehovah
loves you most tenderly.
No matter what trials you’re facing now
or have endured in the past,
Jehovah sees you and he feels for you.
When you hurt, he hurts.
You’re far too precious to Jehovah
for him to forget you.
The account of the widow in Luke chapter 21
can assure you that although circumstances
may affect what you
can contribute to Jehovah,
he notices and treasures
each act you do for him,
especially when you do it
in the face of difficult circumstances.
He remembers,
and he will reward
even the smallest contribution
given in support of his Kingdom.
And what beautiful modern-day examples
we have in the organization
of brothers and sisters
who have proven their loyalty to Jehovah
and are precious to him,
like the example of Sister Pina!
Dear brothers and sisters, please,
never forget that you
are precious to Jehovah!
Here’s another modern-day example
—Sister Malu Mørch.
As we’ll see, she faced a number
of serious hardships early in life.
Notice all the ways
she received comfort from Jehovah.
My name is Malu Mørch.
No one can imagine
how much Jehovah has helped me.
I was raised in Sisimiut in Greenland.
My childhood was wonderful.
We were very often out in nature.
In the summer, we sailed.
And in the winter, we rode dog sledge
and we went hunting and fishing.
When I was a child,
I was very close to my parents.
I was a “daddy’s girl.”
He called me “My Beloved,”
so “Beloved” became my nickname.
It has been so wonderful
to be raised in the truth.
The greatest gift that I could get
is to know Jehovah through them.
When I was nine years old,
my parents got divorced.
It was terrible.
I saw how my siblings were hurt.
It cannot be explained how—
I mean, we were very wounded in our hearts.
When my parents divorced,
my father was disfellowshipped.
It was very hard to be separated like that.
I missed my dad a lot.
When my mom started to drink,
I also felt abandoned.
Because I knew what she had been doing,
I was not surprised when,
after some time, she was disfellowshipped.
But, of course, I felt very hurt and sad.
I supplicated Jehovah
to help me stay in the truth.
The pioneer sister who studied
with me helped me a lot.
She studied with me and sometimes took me
in the ministry and invited me to dinner.
When I was about 12 years old,
my father came back into the truth.
I was very happy that it finally happened.
I began to have
a good relationship with him again.
We sailed a lot,
drove snowmobiles, and rode dog sledge,
and my father and I
watched movies in the evening.
I remember that when my dad
heard that I was going to be baptized,
he shed a tear,
and I could see that he was proud.
When I was 15 years old,
my world fell to pieces.
My father committed suicide.
It’s difficult to describe
that my father was suddenly gone.
I can’t understand
why he would do such a selfish thing.
I missed him a lot.
It was like my heart was stabbed.
I was also very angry at him.
I wrote a lot.
And I wrote many letters to my father
about things that I wanted to tell him.
I also cried out to Jehovah in long prayers.
I love Psalm 34:18
about Jehovah being close
to “those who are crushed in spirit.”
That was how I felt.
And the thought that Jehovah is close to them
comforts me a lot.
I also did all I could
to go to all the meetings,
even when I didn’t want to see anyone.
Even if I had cried before the meeting,
I went anyway.
One month after my father’s death,
I got baptized.
I got baptized because I loved Jehovah.
When I was nine years old,
I had promised Jehovah
to serve him for the rest of my life.
My relationship with my mother
is much better now.
It is great to serve Jehovah
together with her now.
We preach together every Sunday,
and I always look forward to going
in the ministry together with her.
When I was 18 years old,
I began to help
in the remote translation office.
Later, I started pioneering.
I have always learned a lot from King David.
No matter what circumstances he faced,
whether bad or good,
he used them to draw close to Jehovah.
Jehovah has helped me to overcome
challenges through the congregation,
giving me “power beyond what is normal”
and taking me in as his daughter.
As a child,
Malu’s nickname was Beloved.
Yet, for a while,
she felt anything but loved.
She said that her “world fell to pieces.”
Have you ever felt that way?
Remember what helped
Malu stay close to Jehovah:
A pioneer sister encouraged her;
personal study reminded Malu
that Jehovah helped his servants in the past;
she pursued spiritual goals,
such as auxiliary pioneering;
and she went
to as many Christian meetings as she could,
even when she wanted to be alone.
In all these ways,
Malu was reminded
that she is precious to Jehovah.
As she said,
‘Jehovah has taken me in as his daughter.’
For some people, staying busy
may seem like the right thing to do
when they’ve suffered a serious setback.
Does staying busy really help?
Let’s find out in this dramatization.
I, Steven, take you, Emily,
to be my wedded wife.
I, Emily, take you, Steven,
to be my wedded husband.
I had no doubt our vows were forever.
Nothing could have prepared me
for the heartbreak.
I never expected her to be unfaithful
and unwilling to work things out.
I felt humiliated.
How could she do such a thing?
I was embarrassed,
and I didn’t want to talk to anyone.
I read somewhere that time
would help me heal
and just to stay busy.
It seemed to work.
But I was constantly reminded of what I lost:
our spiritual goals,
the hopes and dreams we had
—all destroyed.
I didn’t want to dwell on the hurt,
but I just couldn’t ignore it.
Was I really coping?
Or was I leaving myself open
to even more pain?
Brothers and sisters,
we’re going to talk about marriage today.
If we turn to Ephesians chapter 5, . . .
I was angry, but not just with Emily.
I was angry with everything.
Steven!
Hey, let me stop by tomorrow.
What I had to say,
I wouldn’t have blamed Tom for judging me,
but he didn’t.
You’re right, Steven.
I can’t understand how you feel.
But you know who can.
Do you remember Psalm 34?
I think verse 18 says it best.
Can you read it for us?
“Jehovah is close to the brokenhearted;
he saves those who are crushed in spirit.”
Isn’t that a beautiful scripture?
Take advantage of Jehovah
being that close to you,
and include him in everything.
Jehovah is  a loving Shepherd.
When we hurt, he cares.
I knew this, but in a way, I’d forgotten.
I realized I hadn’t included Jehovah
in the ways I tried to cope.
Staying busy was important,
but I needed to draw closer to God,
not push away.
And when I did,
the real healing began.
Even though the pain is still there,
Jehovah sees the tears;
Jehovah feels what I feel.
It is getting better, slowly,
because “Jehovah is close
to the brokenhearted.”
The vast majority of marriages
among Jehovah’s people prosper
because Christian husbands and wives
apply Bible principles,
but a few fail to live up
to their marriage commitment.
Are you among the brokenhearted?
If so, never forget
that you are precious to Jehovah
and remember what will help you heal.
In our dramatization,
Steven kept himself busy
with recreation and other activities.
But he experienced
true comfort and healing
when he drew close to Jehovah.
Always remember
how Jehovah is described
at Psalm 34:18:
“Jehovah is close to the brokenhearted;
he saves those who are crushed in spirit.”
Prayer is one of the most powerful ways
Jehovah helps us.
We’ll see that in our new music video.
When I called yesterday,
I could tell you’d lost your way.
Be assured you are loved
By our God up above.
So do not fear.
When you’re broken, he is near.
Trust in Jehovah; don’t give in.
Just let it go; roll it on him.
You’re not alone; you can pray.
He hears your words; he feels your pain.
Don’t keep that burden in.
Roll it on him.
Raise your eyes up and see;
The new world is in our reach—
No more tears, only love
Through the gift of God’s dear Son.
But until then,
We can endure down to the end
If we trust in Jehovah; don’t give in.
Just let it go; roll it on him.
We’re not alone; we can pray.
He hears our words; he feels our pain.
Don’t keep that burden in.
Roll it on him.
Trust in Jehovah; don’t give in.
Just let it go; roll it on him.
We’re not alone; we can pray.
He hears our words; he feels our pain.
Don’t keep that burden in.
Roll it on him.
What a beautiful reminder
that we can go to Jehovah
in prayer at any time
and express our deepest feelings to him!
As the song says:
“Don’t keep that burden in.
Roll it on him.”
When we’re experiencing
pain and difficulty in life,
it may not be easy to see
all that Jehovah is doing in our behalf.
In the following Morning Worship program,
Brother John Ekrann helps us
to see Jehovah’s hand in action.
Sometimes, I think all of us would agree
that it’s easy to see Jehovah’s hand
when things are going well
—when we get a court victory,
when someone’s health improves,
or maybe when someone really asked to come
to study the Bible with us
and they’re at our meetings.
But it’s harder to see Jehovah’s hand
when we see bad things happen
either to us or to our brothers and sisters.
So we may wonder,
‘How can we see Jehovah’s hand
when bad things are happening?’
Well, you can see my hand right now, right?
But if I put it away, you can’t see it.
Now, do you assume
that because you can’t see my hand
that I don’t have a hand anymore?
Well, no.
You reason on the fact
that since you see the rest of me,
and there’s probably still my hand attached.
So likewise, there are times
when it’s easy to see Jehovah’s hand,
and there are other times
when we have to reason
on what we know about Jehovah
in order to see his hand in action.
So let’s consider one thing.
What do we know about Jehovah
so that we could reason
that his hand is in action?
Well, let’s reason on the point
that he is a “happy God.”
Now, how does Jehovah stay happy,
seeing all the bad things that are happening?
Maybe you’ve wondered that.
I know it’s crossed my mind.
How does Jehovah stay happy
when he sees
all the suffering that’s going on?
And frankly, he sees all  the suffering;
he sees everything going on.
I know how I feel,
and you probably know how you feel
just when you read about what’s happening
to our brothers in Venezuela or in Russia
or with all of the hurricanes
and earthquakes
that we’ve had in recent times.
And we see the suffering
not only of our brothers and sisters
but also of other people,
and we consider,
‘How can Jehovah stay happy
when he knows all of what is happening?’
Well, let’s consider three
(I’m sure) of many reasons
why Jehovah can stay happy
even though he knows all the suffering.
And then we can see
how that could benefit us as well.
First of all,
his hand is hard at work
preparing the new world for us.
And I think Jeremiah 29:11
really covers how Jehovah feels
about the future for us.
At Jeremiah 29:11, he says:
“‘For I well know the thoughts
that I am thinking toward you,’
“declares Jehovah,
‘thoughts of peace, and not of calamity,
to give you a future and a hope.’”
So Jehovah
is not simply just watching events occur.
He’s actively working on the solution.
He, along with Jesus and the heavenly angels,
is working hard on the Kingdom.
Now, we can’t see into heaven right now,
but I want you to just imagine
all the activity of the angels,
the resurrected anointed brothers,
and Jesus working hard on making preparations
for Armageddon and the new world.
Just think of all the work
we’re doing just to prepare
for the annual meeting and dedication.
Can you imagine all the work
going on in heaven that is there?
I mean, how far along are the new scrolls?
How are our basic needs
as far as clean water,
food, and homes
going to be provided for the survivors?
So while we can’t see into heaven,
we know that his hand is there.
So Jehovah is happy
because he’s actively working right now
to make things better for us.
What is the lesson for us?
We can be happy
when we see the suffering around us
because we know what Jehovah
and our brothers are doing up there
to prepare for the new world.
A second point about how Jehovah can be happy
is that he can comfort us right now.
He is happy when he can do that.
In verse 12 of Jeremiah chapter 29,
Jehovah continued after saying
that he was working on the future (he says):
“And you will call me
and come and pray to me,
and I will listen to you.”
So I love this point
because Jehovah is saying,
‘Don’t worry; I’m taking care
of building a better future for you.’
And we appreciate it.
If we’re going through some trial
—some difficulty—
and a good friend of ours reminds us,
“Remember things are going
to get better in the future;
Jehovah is going to change this;
it’s going to get better,”
it is comforting.
But it is also comforting
(like Jehovah says here in verse 12)
when the person says,
“What can I do for you right now?”
And Jehovah is saying right now,
‘Come, pray to me.’
Jehovah is there to comfort and help us.
We could kind of illustrate
the way Jehovah feels
by thinking about parents
and how they deal with a small child.
Have you ever seen a small child,
maybe two or three years of age,
and they fall really badly
and scrape their knees badly,
and they are screaming in pain?
There’s this red liquid leaking out of them.
They are distraught.
In fact, in that child’s mind,
he may think: ‘This is the end of it.
This is the end of my life as I know it.
‘I’m never going to recover from this.
I’m going to die.’
But for the parents, of course,
their perspective is different, isn’t it?
But they comfort the child;
they help to take care of the skinned knee.
They comfort them, and they tell them:
“You’re going to live.
It’s going to be OK.
It’s going to be all right.”
And why can the parent have that view?
Because they know that in a few hours maybe
(at least in a week or so),
the child is not even going to remember
that skinned knee.
It’s going to be just a very distant memory.
Well, Jehovah also knows
that whatever we’re going through right now
—whatever suffering
we may be going through now—
that soon in that new world,
we aren’t going to recall that suffering.
And he knows that he can solve
any problem we’re facing
as easily as we heal from a scraped knee.
He knows our whole eternal lives
are ahead of us.
So he comforts us;
he listens to our heartfelt prayers.
And like a kind parent, he’s telling us
(through our brothers,
the Bible, and holy spirit),
‘You will live.’
Jehovah is happy
because right now, what can he do?
He can comfort us and help us.
Well, what is the lesson for us?
We can comfort and help others.
We’re, really, kind of all
in this “lifeboat” together,
trying to make it to the “new-world shore,”
and we can help one another.
Third,
his hand is patiently waiting
for the right time to act.
Jehovah is waiting patiently
for the complete vindication
of his sovereignty.
I really love
what the June 2017 Watchtower  article
“Keep Your Eyes on the Big Issue” said:
“Let us not become
so absorbed in our own lives
“that we lose sight of this big issue
“—the vindication of Jehovah’s sovereignty.
“And let us appreciate
that our role in this vital issue
“entails remaining faithful
even under difficult circumstances.”
Isn’t that a beautiful quote to think about?
Jehovah knows that by his being patient now,
he and all his faithful servants
will never have to go through this again.
The issue of sovereignty
will be completely settled.
Don’t you admire Jehovah’s patience?
I mean, to watch all that is happening
and to have the self-control
to wait for the appointed time
is truly an example of patience in action.
When we think about the different situations
our brothers and sisters and others face
—when a mother, for example,
watches a handicapped son
struggle to walk or to talk
or a husband watches his wife
struggle to breathe—
we want so much at that moment
to press that big, red,
“start-the-new-world” button now.
But when you have that feeling,
remember our text for today:
“The hand of Jehovah
will become known to his servants.”
What is the lesson for us?
We need to be patient
and keep our eyes
on the big issue of Jehovah’s sovereignty.
So let’s just review those three points.
How can we see Jehovah’s hand
and be happy when we see
all of this suffering around us?
Well, we can be happy knowing
what Jehovah and Jesus
and the resurrected anointed
are doing right now
to prepare for the new world.
And we can be happy
because we have a role
in comforting and helping others.
And we can be happy being patient,
knowing why we’re being patient.
We have our eyes
on that big issue of Jehovah’s sovereignty.
We may not always
be able to see Jehovah’s hand,
but we can be sure,
as our text for today says,
that Jehovah’s hand is there,
and it will become known.
Every year, millions of people
come together at our conventions
to learn about Jehovah
and encourage each other.
Starting next month,
“Always Rejoice”! Conventions
will be held all over the earth.
Jehovah’s Witnesses
will be actively inviting their neighbors,
workmates, schoolmates,
and all interested ones to join us.
What effect can receiving an invitation
have on a person’s life?
Let’s watch the following report.
I came to Greece as an immigrant
when I was just 16 years old.
Because of that, I never felt safe
with people around me.
At that time, I was renting
an apartment from a man
who was studying the Bible
with one of Jehovah’s Witnesses.
One day I joined the study,
and the brother invited me to the convention.
I was very cautious at the beginning,
but the brother seemed trustworthy.
I always had questions about the true God,
and I wanted to learn more about Him,
so I decided to go.
In 2016,
I received an invitation
from my son to attend
the convention of Jehovah’s Witnesses.
He was getting baptized at that convention,
and it was important to him
for me to be there,
and so he asked me to go.
Even though I was very active
in another religion for 30 years,
I went in order to please him.
I learned the truth after I supplicated God
with all my strength
because I was really lost.
I asked for answers to questions
that were yet unanswered.
And God answered me.
Jehovah gave me the answer
to my prayers when I found this.
This invitation, “Deliverance at Hand!,”
was the answer to my prayers.
Arriving there, at that convention,
I observed the crowd—many people.
Starting right at the parking lot,
everything was organized;
people were entering in an orderly manner.
Inside the Assembly Hall,
everyone was very organized,
well-dressed, very loving.
And when the convention began,
I saw such spiritual food
that I had never seen in my religion.
Thirty years in a religion
—I thought I knew a lot,
but I didn’t know anything.
So I decided to study.
When I arrived at the convention,
I started watching the people.
Their faces were smiling.
They seemed to be happy.
There were men, women, and children
from different races and nationalities.
When they sang,
I could sense their true joy and unity.
For the first time in my life,
I felt very safe.
I was not in fear
of being taken advantage of.
Also, what I learned at that convention
drew me to the true God.
I thought, ‘If all these people
‘are truly happy and feel really safe
being part of this organization
‘—Jehovah’s organization—
then, indeed,
this is what I was looking for.’
I went to the convention on Sunday.
I was really warmly welcomed
by all the brothers and sisters there.
I listened to all of the morning program,
and at noon,
I recognized the sound of the truth.
I was sure it was the truth.
I decided to become
one of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
and I became one of Jehovah’s Witnesses.
I got baptized in 2017,
and now I serve as a pioneer.
My first study was the following Wednesday.
I was happy to get to know Jehovah.
Now I am one of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
and as much as I can,
I participate in the invitation campaigns.
I really hope that it helps
many people to be delivered.
I started attending meetings
right after the convention.
I started a Bible study,
and eventually I got baptized
as one of Jehovah’s Witnesses.
My mother, one of my brothers,
and my two sisters
are now serving Jehovah as well.
Later on, I got married to a faithful sister,
a very good wife,
and we serve Jehovah together.
People need to feel safe,
and I know for sure that Jehovah’s
organization is the safest place you can be.
Did you notice how
the convention invitations were obtained?
They were given by a relative
or an associate
or simply left at the door.
We never know how even a single invitation
can help a person come to know Jehovah.
Our diligence in the invitation campaign
can make a powerful difference.
This month’s program
has helped us remember
that we are precious to Jehovah.
We learned that even if we
had a hard start in life,
we don’t have to be a victim of our past.
We saw how Jehovah sees us,
cares for us,
and provides loving help in many ways.
We were reminded
that “Jehovah is close to the brokenhearted”
and that through prayer,
we can unburden ourselves
and receive comfort,
knowing that whatever suffering
we’re enduring now will soon be forgotten.
Let’s conclude our program by visiting
our brothers and sisters in Cuba.
The Republic of Cuba
is a chain of 1,600 islands and islets
at the intersection of the Atlantic Ocean,
the Caribbean Sea,
and the Gulf of Mexico.
Cuba itself is by far
the largest island in the chain,
with one major city: Havana.
Many are embracing the truth.
Cuba is home to almost 95,000 publishers
in 1,400 congregations.
They’re conducting
more than 135,000 Bible studies.
Lush mountains and hills
cover a quarter of Cuba.
At the western end
of the island is Viñales,
famous for its towerlike hills
called mogotes.
Caves and rivers run through many of them.
The Este de Viñales Congregation
is located in this part of Cuba.
Here, 128 publishers conduct
275 Bible studies.
Because of its vast territory,
the congregation has three groups.
One group that has only seven publishers
had 75 people attend last year’s Memorial.
To cover their territory,
the brothers travel long distances,
sometimes by bicycle or motorcycle.
They witness to people wherever they are
—on farms and in their homes.
The brothers enjoy Christian fellowship,
good coffee,
and singing songs of praise to Jehovah.
Our brothers and sisters
in the Este de Viñales Congregation
send their love to the worldwide brotherhood.
From the World Headquarters
of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
this is JW Broadcasting!