We’re very happy for Daniel.
He’s going to be a blessing
in his new assignment.
But we are going to miss him
and everything he was doing
for the congregation.
This will change things for us.
We really want to be there
for our brothers and sisters.
And it’s true:
Having plenty to do
in the Lord’s work is good.
But where will we get more help?
We do have good ministerial servants
like Richie.
But after Daniel left,
our elder body is one fewer now.
That prompted a good question:
Are we doing all we can
to train our brothers?
Richie, do you have some time for me?
I have some calls you can help me with.
Sure, I’d like that.
I realized it had been
a while since we talked
about him qualifying to do more.
He explained that he wanted to help
but didn’t want to appear presumptuous.
He’d been praying about it,
and he wanted to know what else
he could do to keep reaching out.
Talking to Richie
made me think of Jesus’ example.
His disciples offered themselves willingly,
and he trained them.
They were eager but needed his direction.
Jesus’ training gave them confidence
to do the assignments he gave them.
They were happy,
not just to follow Jesus,
but to work alongside him.
And Jesus was happy to share his work.
Up to his final evening with them,
he prepared them for the work ahead.
“Most truly I say to you,
“whoever exercises faith in me
will also do the works that I do;
“and he will do works greater than these,
because I am going my way to the Father.”
I now remember how much training
I had received from the brothers.
It was easy to forget
that I didn’t always get
things right at first.
Soon,
Richie was taking on more responsibility.
And he told me something
that I too once felt.
He just didn’t realize how much work
went into caring for Jehovah’s sheep.
But once he knew,
he was glad he offered himself willingly.