Welcome to our program!
This month’s theme is
“Are You Paying Attention?”
Strained relationships,
illnesses,
careers,
entertainment
—we’ll learn how to stay focused on Jehovah
despite these potential distractions.
We’ll see how our ministry
is more effective
when we focus
on reaching the hearts of people.
And our new song was written
especially for you young adults
to help you keep your eyes
on the prize of life.
This is JW Broadcasting®
for November 2020.
Are you paying attention?
Perhaps you’ve been asked that question
by your parents, a teacher,
or someone else in authority.
It’s a good question
for each of us to ask ourselves.
Can you think
of occasions associated with our worship
that require us to pay special attention?
For example, when reading the Bible,
attending meetings,
elders when shepherding,
you children
when being instructed by your parents.
We want to pay attention,
and yet there are so many distractions
—electronic gadgets,
the conversations and activities
of those around us.
Truly, it can be a challenge
to pay attention.
Did you know that the phrase “pay attention”
occurs dozens of times
in the New World Translation?
In many of those occurrences,
Jehovah is instructing his people
to pay attention.
What does it mean to “pay attention”?
And how important is it
that you and I pay attention to Jehovah?
The account in 1 Samuel chapter 15
will help us to answer those questions.
In verse 3, Jehovah instructs King Saul
to strike down the Amalekites
and to devote them
and everything they have to destruction.
However, verses 8 and 9 tell us
that Saul did not obey.
He spared the king of Amalek
and the best of the animals.
How did Saul respond
when Samuel confronted him?
As we read verses 13-15,
note how Saul tried to justify
his disobedience:
“When Samuel finally came to him,
“Saul said to him:
“‘May Jehovah bless you.
“I have carried out the word of Jehovah.’
“But Samuel said:
“‘Then what is this sound
of the flock in my ears
“and the sound of the cattle that I hear?’
“To this Saul said:
“‘They were brought from the Amalekites,
“‘because the people spared
the best of the flock and the herd
“‘for sacrificing them to Jehovah your God;
but what was left
we devoted to destruction.’”
Did you notice?
Saul attempted to justify his disobedience,
claiming that the animals
would be sacrificed to Jehovah.
Was Jehovah pleased with Saul?
As we read verse 22,
please note the connection
between paying attention
and obedience:
“Samuel then said:
“‘Does Jehovah take as much pleasure
in burnt offerings and sacrifices
“‘as in obeying the voice of Jehovah?
“‘Look!
“‘To obey is better than a sacrifice,
and to pay attention than the fat of rams.’”
What was one of the causes
of Saul’s disobedience?
He didn’t pay attention
to Jehovah’s instructions.
His failure to pay attention
resulted in disobedience
and brought Jehovah’s disapproval.
What a powerful lesson for us!
As happened with Saul,
our worship
could become unacceptable to Jehovah
if we fail to pay attention!
Now that we understand
why it is important to pay attention,
let’s consider
three aspects of paying attention
that are discussed in the Bible.
The first scripture we’ll consider
is 2 Chronicles 19:6:
“And he [Jehoshaphat] said to the judges:
“‘Pay attention to what you are doing,
“‘for you do not judge for man
but for Jehovah,
and he is with you when you pass judgment.’”
This admonition to “pay attention”
was given by King Jehoshaphat
to appointed judges
throughout the land of Judah.
What a sobering reminder!
Those judges had good reason
to pay attention to what they were doing.
Why?
They were responsible to Jehovah.
They represented him,
and their decisions
affected the lives of fellow worshippers.
Thus, they needed to be familiar
with Jehovah’s thinking on matters
and to hold to his unprejudiced viewpoint
when handling matters.
This is an excellent reminder
for those who serve as elders.
Good elders are good students of the Bible
and Bible-based publications.
Why?
Their attentiveness to Jehovah
enables them to pay attention
to what they are doing.
If they are going to represent Jehovah
and reflect his thinking accurately
as they handle matters
—whether they’re shepherding
the congregation,
delivering a part at a meeting,
caring for a challenging assignment,
or addressing wrongdoing
—they must pay attention
to what they are doing.
That is why they must be familiar
with Jehovah’s thinking
and then take care to follow his direction.
If they do, they show
that they are paying attention
to what they are doing.
Jehovah’s interest in assisting the elders
is demonstrated
in the ongoing education he provides.
Each time the circuit overseer
visits the congregation,
he presents material
prepared especially for the elders.
The Kingdom Ministry School
and the School for Congregation Elders
provide more intensive instruction.
How important
that elders pay close attention to
and apply such instruction!
Their doing so protects,
not just themselves
but also fellow worshippers.
By paying attention, elders will be able
to convey direction
to the congregations accurately.
This can be especially important
if our worship is banned
or restricted
in the event of a natural disaster
or other catastrophic event.
This brings us
to the second aspect of paying attention
that we’ll consider.
Let’s read Luke 8:18:
“Therefore,
“pay attention to how you listen,
“for whoever has will be given more,
“but whoever does not have,
even what he imagines he has
will be taken away from him.”
What did Jesus mean when he said:
“Pay attention to how you listen”?
Those in Jesus’ audience in the first century
had the wonderful privilege
of hearing Jesus’ literal voice
as he instructed them.
Of course, we can’t hear
the voice of Jesus today,
but we can read his words
and learn of his actions
as revealed in the Gospel accounts.
In fact, we have many opportunities to listen
to Jehovah, Jesus,
“the faithful and discreet slave,”
the elders in our congregation,
our marriage mate,
and our children.
No wonder the Bible writer James stated
that “everyone must be quick to listen.”
Think about it:
If Saul had truly listened receptively
to Jehovah’s direction
regarding the Amalekites,
he would likely have grasped
the importance of the direction he received
and would have been motivated to obey.
However, his lack of attentiveness
led to disobedience
and Jehovah’s disapproval.
If we don’t pay attention to how we listen,
we could find ourselves becoming critical
or unappreciative
or even disobedient.
So as Jehovah instructs and directs us,
we need to think
about what we are being told,
ponder over its meaning,
mull it over in our mind
and, most important,
apply the instruction in our own lives.
If you’re a young person,
how can you show that you’re paying attention
to how you listen?
Consider the admonition
at Ephesians 6:1-3:
“Children, be obedient to your parents
“in union with the Lord,
“for this is righteous.
“‘Honor your father and your mother’
“is the first command with a promise:
“‘That it may go well with you
and you may remain a long time
on the earth.’”
You children, who do you think
is the source of this direction?
We know that these words come from Jehovah.
Did you notice that the verses state not only
that children
should “be obedient” to their parents
but also that they should
“honor” their parents?
How can you show that you’re paying attention
to how you listen to this direction?
When I was a boy, I can remember occasions
when my parents would ask me
to do something,
perhaps to take out the trash.
I would always obey.
But at times, I’d make it very clear
that I didn’t really want to do
what was asked.
I think you young ones know what I mean.
However, if we’re truly paying attention
to how we listen to Jehovah’s words,
we’ll be careful to honor our parents,
which is an essential element of obedience.
In this way, we contribute
to the peace of the family,
and we make Jehovah’s heart glad.
Additionally,
as the promise in verse 3 indicates,
paying attention to how you listen
will protect you
and contribute to your success in other ways
throughout your adult life.
Of course, all of us should remember
that our everlasting welfare will depend
on our willingness to listen and obey.
How important, then, that all of us
pay attention to how we listen.
The third aspect of paying attention is found
at Luke 21:34, 35:
“But pay attention to yourselves
“that your hearts never become weighed down
“with overeating and heavy drinking
“and anxieties of life,
and suddenly that day
be instantly upon you as a snare.”
When Jesus admonished his followers
to pay attention to themselves,
he didn’t have in mind the selfish thinking
that characterized King Saul
and that’s so common, even encouraged,
in today’s world.
Rather, Jesus’ words reveal
that the key to paying attention to ourselves
is knowing ourselves
—knowing what’s in our figurative heart.
This is a challenge for all of us.
Why?
The Bible explains at Jeremiah 17:9:
“The heart is more treacherous
than anything else
“and is desperate.
Who can know it?”
Verse 10 answers:
“I, Jehovah, am searching the heart,
examining the innermost thoughts.”
So Jehovah knows what is in our heart,
and he can help us to know.
He can help us to examine
our motives and goals
and to discern why we do certain things.
Carefully and honestly looking at ourselves
in the mirror of God’s Word
can reveal areas in our thinking, words,
and actions
that need attention.
For example, some of Jehovah’s people
—including those of retirement age
who have enjoyed
very comfortable circumstances—
have concluded that they needed to make
adjustments in their lifestyle,
simplifying their lives
so that they can serve Jehovah more fully.
Some who have done so have had the privilege
of attending
the School for Kingdom Evangelizers.
Although it meant
stepping out of their comfort zone,
perhaps moving to a new congregation,
they’ve experienced Jehovah’s blessing
in ways that they couldn’t have anticipated
as they share
the benefits of their experience
and theocratic education
in their new assignments.
How grateful we are
that Jehovah is providing ongoing,
life-saving instruction
by means of his Word and organization.
May each of us be determined
to “pay attention”
to what we are doing,
to how we listen,
and to ourselves.
By doing so, we’ll avoid falling
into the trap of disobedience
as King Saul did.
Instead, as attentive and obedient servants,
we’ll enjoy Jehovah’s friendship forever.
Elders play an important role
in helping us stay focused on Jehovah,
particularly when we’re facing
difficult problems.
In our first video,
notice how elders provide loving assistance.
Everything was going fine in my marriage
—or so I thought.
My ex-husband was disfellowshipped,
left home
and, in less than a month,
we divorced.
Right after the divorce,
I had to figure out
how I would provide for the girls,
so I began working as a cleaner.
I also had to provide for them spiritually.
But many times,
because of discouragement and tiredness,
I couldn’t be there for them
as much as they needed me to be.
Besides all of this,
I also had to deal
with very negative feelings.
It was a very difficult time in my life.
I had never been so sick.
I couldn’t even get up to go to the hospital.
To cope with this problem,
I just kept praying.
I was not able to walk,
and I was not able to get to the meetings.
The elders realized
that I was missing from the meetings.
The elders quickly came to my aid.
I remember that one of the things
that touched me the most
was when the elders read a scripture.
Psalm 139:3:
“You observe me when I travel
and when I lie down;
you are familiar with all my ways.”
I realized that I am precious to Jehovah.
It was as if Jehovah was healing me.
I now knew that Jehovah
was interested in me
and that he was looking after me.
He was making sure that I knew it.
Something else that I remember fondly
was after a meeting at the Kingdom Hall.
One of the elders gave me
some scriptures to read at home
and said that if we needed any help,
the elders were there for us.
Two elders lovingly came to see me,
because Jehovah uses them as shepherds.
I live very far from the Kingdom Hall.
But the brothers made the sacrifice
to get public transport,
get off at the main road,
and from there they walked 40 minutes
to reach my house.
I don’t know what I would have done.
When the elders arrived,
they listened to me,
they cried with me,
and they read the Bible with me.
Jehovah loves me.
When I started to feel better,
I went back to the group.
I was really happy
to be back with my brothers.
Now, after all the help we have received,
we are doing well.
The congregation is our second home,
and we feel very good there.
Everything I have today,
I owe to the brothers and sisters,
especially the elders.
I see shepherding calls
as a very evident way
in which Jehovah demonstrates
his full love for us.
I understand that at times
these visits might be
a challenge for the elders,
but the results are really good.
Without a doubt,
they can see that all the work
and all the effort is worthwhile.
I will never forget the help
that I received from the elders.
This situation taught me that Jehovah
will not let his sheep get lost,
not even one.
Jeremiah 23:4 says:
“‘And I will raise up over them shepherds
“‘who will really shepherd them.
“‘They will no longer be afraid or be terrified,
and none will be missing,’ declares Jehovah.”
How did the elders help Mariana and Elias?
As good shepherds,
they were attentive to Jehovah’s flock,
so they were quick to notice
that help was needed.
They visited Mariana and Elias
in their homes,
shared encouraging scriptures, and listened.
They showed that Jehovah
cares for every one of his sheep.
Those brothers,
like the elders in your congregation,
paid attention
to the loving training and instruction
they’d received from Jehovah.
To expand their ministry,
many Witnesses
have learned another language.
Have you?
If so, Jehovah knows
your selfless effort and hard work
to preach and teach in that language.
But is preaching to people
in their native language
sufficient to reach their heart?
Let’s see in this dramatization.
Our family had been learning Chinese
for over a year.
It wasn’t easy.
God has many titles.
Did you know he has only one name?
[Speaking Chinese]
I was ready, or at least I thought so.
Matthew!
Yeah, I’ll be right there.
We were making progress,
and we weren’t giving up.
It seemed like most people
just weren’t interested.
We were not having a good morning.
What happened?
Mom and Liz weren’t having
a good morning either.
Brother and Sister Lin joined us.
They’ve been a big help to us.
We told them about our morning.
We were finally able to converse a little
and give presentations,
but everything seemed to fall flat.
You ask good questions at the door
—but not always the right one.
You see, when you learn the language,
do not forget to learn about people.
He was right.
Our questions started conversations
in our old territory, but not here.
Your pronunciation is very good, see.
Thanks, Brother Lin.
We needed a different approach
where we didn’t just learn the language
but also how to reach the heart
of someone who speaks it.
In the July 2019 Watchtower,
we read about “Reaching the Hearts
of Nonreligious People.”
Did you notice in paragraph 7,
how do you think that we could be more
like the apostle Paul?
Well, Paul was a Jew,
but when he was talking to other people,
he had to adapt his presentation.
I like what 1 Corinthians 9:20-23 says:
“To the Jews I became as a Jew
in order to gain Jews;
to those under law I became . . .”
Liz was right.
When Paul spoke to fellow Jews in Athens,
he reasoned from the Scriptures.
But when he spoke to the Greeks
at the Areopagus, he adapted,
reasoning with them first without the Bible.
He later wrote:
“I have become all things
to people of all sorts,
so that I might by all possible means
save some.”
That’s what we needed to do.
We learned more about the people.
We started to listen more
and talk about things
that interested them.
We found different ways
to start conversations.
And we kept learning more about the culture.
Part of a Chinese proverb I found says:
“He who comes near ink is stained black.”
It’s been a great way to introduce
Proverbs 13:20:
“The one walking with the wise
will become wise.”
It all comes down to showing love.
The more we paid attention
to how we were teaching,
the more we were able to show people
the God who loves them.
What a beautiful reminder
that in the ministry,
we want to pay attention to people
—to what interests them
and to what helps them!
And as we saw,
we may need to analyze
and adapt our teaching methods,
just as Paul did.
Even as we endeavor to reach the hearts
of people in the ministry,
we must safeguard our own heart.
A recent Watchtower article
offered practical suggestions
to help us do that.
In our next video,
notice how our brothers
benefited from applying what they learned.
Well, very good friends of ours
decided they wanted
to go their own way and leave Jehovah.
And in the interim,
they became bad association for us.
We had many good times together.
We drove to isolated territory together;
we even visited a brother who was sick
in the hospital to encourage him.
I feel heartbroken
that they’re no longer serving Jehovah.
It’s really hard to lose a friend spiritually
—very hard.
I was about to enter into full-time service,
but I still needed reassurance.
I was raised by my mother as a Witness.
Even though I had
very little contact with my father,
he still tried to oppose
my spiritual progress.
I kept fighting for the truth,
and I got baptized when I was 11.
I guess I felt like I was doing OK.
And after high school, I went to university.
I had to make some changes
in my choice of entertainment.
We really never stop learning.
I do enjoy relaxing and watching television.
But I must admit
that it is more and more difficult
to find something decent to watch these days.
Well, I’m not saying
that I watch bad programs.
I would never do that,
but still I wonder
if what I watch
is spiritually healthy for me.
The way of thinking
I was exposed to in university
was pressuring me to find security in my life
through material things
—like having my own place to live
and economic stability.
But at what cost?
I remember that paragraph.
It said that Satan promotes making money
as the only way
you can find security in this world.
But one could sacrifice
so much to achieve it.
You could even lose
your friendship with Jehovah.
That article—it was just what we needed.
It described a watchman
who would protect the city
by sounding out an alarm on impending danger.
And at sounding that alarm,
he would shut the gates
to the city to protect the city.
And I needed to do that.
We both needed to do that.
It’s true.
And it’s not even a question.
Our loyalty to Jehovah comes first
—before we’re loyal
to any friends we have in this world.
The Watchtower  said
that storytelling
does more than entertain us.
In Bana, the city of Cameroon
where I was born,
mothers spend their evenings
with their children, telling them stories.
And even though I was young,
the stories my mother told me
continue to influence me even today.
So I said to myself: ‘Oh, no.
Wait a minute, Happy!
‘It means that the stories
that I watch on television
‘will also affect me sooner or later,
and the Devil knows that too.’
So I decided to completely cut out a number
of programs that I used to watch.
Now I’m serving in full-time service,
and I love it!
Jehovah is really taking care of me,
but I don’t want to forget
the beautiful principles
I’ve learned from that article.
I still have to safeguard my heart.
I want to give my best to my Father, Jehovah.
Not a day goes by where we don’t think
about these friends of ours.
And it’s certainly our hope
that they come back to Jehovah
and that we can serve Jehovah
together shoulder to shoulder.
But we’ve also learned
to keep our “little watchman” in check.
We need to make sure he does his job
to “sound the alarm” and “shut those gates.”
Hmm, we never stop learning.
Well, true, it’s easier said than done,
but it is up to us.
It’s so important to safeguard your heart!
We all enjoy reading The Watchtower
and commenting at the Watchtower  Study.
But truly paying attention
means putting what we learn into action.
What else goes
into being a discerning student?
That was the topic
of a recent Morning Worship program
presented by Brother Joel Dellinger.
Our focus in the Watchtower study article
is on how we can unleash
the power of God’s Word
when teaching from the platform.
But, you know, whether we’re teaching
in a congregation setting,
on a Bible study, or in the family,
isn’t it true that all of us,
brothers and sisters,
need to ‘pay constant attention
to ourselves and to our teaching’?
And we know why that’s so important
—because lives are at stake.
And all of us, younger or older,
touch the lives of other people.
So when we teach effectively,
we are giving opportunity to others
to attain the wisdom and the discernment
that God’s Word can give them.
That’s why we need to approach
any teaching opportunity
seriously and prayerfully.
Over 20 years ago, a kind elder gave me
some constructive counsel
after a public talk.
And then, with a warm smile, he said this,
“Remember, none of us teach like Jesus did.”
Well, I’ll never forget that counsel.
Why were those observations so helpful?
Well, it reminded me that when teaching,
our model needs to be Jesus,
the Great Teacher.
There’s more to learn from him.
And Jesus’ example reminds us of the need
to remain humble and diligent
students of Jehovah
—the Grand Instructor.
Though all of us are teachers on occasion,
isn’t it true that most often
the role we play during spiritual programs
is that of students?
Just for a moment, think about the many hours
we spend as students
—not teachers—
when we’re in the audience
at congregation meetings,
at assemblies, and at conventions.
Add to that the time we are students
when we buy out time to watch
the monthly broadcast,
to prepare for meetings,
to engage in family and personal study.
And then think of the added privilege
that many of us here have
—to enjoy morning worship five days a week.
You know, a typical program
of morning worship
lasts between 20 to 25 minutes.
If you multiply that by 5 days a week
and then by 52 weeks,
at a minimum, we are exposed
to at least 86 hours
of divine instruction each year.
But if we’re not careful,
some or much of that valuable instruction,
encouragement, and counsel
could just wash over us.
So for the remaining time
for our program this morning,
let’s consider some things all of us can do
to listen more effectively
at spiritual programs.
Please, for our first point, open your Bible
to Ezra 7:10,
and let’s consider Ezra’s example.
That’s Ezra 7:10,
and notice the reading carefully:
“Ezra had prepared his heart
“to consult the Law of Jehovah
“and to practice it,
“and to teach its regulations
and judgments in Israel.”
Now, if you have the Bible with the asterisk
next to “prepared his heart,”
if you tap on that, you’ll notice
that that could be rendered as
“had determined in his heart.”
Well, what do we learn from Ezra?
He had the right attitude
going into a period of study.
He had the right approach
to study and learning.
He recognized that it was Jehovah
who would be teaching him through His Law.
And as the verse goes on to say,
he first recognized
that he needed to personally practice
what he was learning.
Only then would he be in a rightful position
to effectively teach others.
Well, this scripture emphasizes the point
we’ve already made, doesn’t it?
Though we are teachers on occasion,
we are always first and foremost
students of God’s Word.
How can we imitate Ezra’s example
and prepare our hearts before study,
before attending a spiritual program
(whether here at Bethel
or in the congregation),
before watching a monthly broadcast?
Well, we need to prepare our hearts
by specifically praying to Jehovah,
recognizing him
as the Source of the teaching.
What should we pray specifically about?
Well, for one, we want to pray
that we remain humble
while listening to theocratic instruction.
We need to listen
—no matter how long
we’ve been in Jehovah’s classroom—
because none of us know it all,
nor will we ever know it all.
Proverbs 1:5 reminds us
that “a wise person listens
and takes in more instruction.”
Well, this leads to another question:
What if we find we have
a somewhat negative attitude
toward a certain presentation
—perhaps the material doesn’t interest us,
or we have a negative attitude
toward a certain brother
and his teaching ability?
What should we do?
Prepare our heart.
Pray to Jehovah
to recognize and appreciate
that the instruction is from him.
Pray to have a thankful spirit.
You know, back in 2002,
The Watchtower  made this helpful point
in an article that was entitled
“Pay More Than the Usual Attention.”
I quote: “Some may tend to gauge
the quality of a meeting
“by the teaching abilities
of the participants. . . .
“Though the teaching ability
of participants is important,
“it is not the sole factor contributing
to a meeting’s success.
“Do you not agree
that our prime concern should be,
“not how well the speaker delivers his talk,
“but how well we incline our ear?
When we attend meetings,”
the article continues,
“and pay attention
to what is being presented,
“we are worshiping God
in harmony with his will.
“That is what makes the meeting a success.
“If we are eager
to take in the knowledge of God,
“we will benefit from meetings,
regardless of a speaker’s abilities.”
What a beautiful reminder for all of us!
So our first point: Like Ezra,
let’s prepare our hearts with prayer,
as students who are determined to always
accept and apply
what Jehovah has to teach us.
Let’s consider a second point:
the need to focus our attention.
Have you faced the challenge
of staying focused
during spiritual programs?
Our minds may be distracted
with anxieties and many other things.
Noise and movements around us
could distract us.
If we’re watching morning worship
at a location other than
the Bethel dining room,
likely we well know the numerous distractions
that fight for our attention.
Some of us have ailments
and physical discomforts
that may make it difficult to concentrate.
Recently, a sister in our congregation
told us about her long-term battle
with migraine headaches.
I tried to put myself in her shoes,
having a migraine headache
while attending a spiritual program
—difficult to concentrate.
Well, whatever the case may be, we know
—we admit—
that there are many challenges
and distractions.
What can we do about it?
Well, since the eyes strongly influence
where we focus our attention,
the Benefit  book provides this suggestion:
“Use your eyes to help you concentrate
by keeping them on the speaker.
“When he cites a Bible text
—even a familiar one—
look it up, and follow along as he reads it.”
And then it said this:
“Resist the temptation to turn your head
“in the direction of every noise or movement.
“If the eyes are flooding your mind
with distracting information,
you will miss much
of what is presented from the platform.”
And think about, too,
the use of electronic devices.
Have you ever been alerted,
messaged, or e-mailed
while looking at the Bible on your device?
How wise it is when we turn
those devices to a mode
that eliminates unnecessary distractions!
Well, what about anxieties
or disquieting thoughts?
What could we do about that?
Well, here, again, is where we can remember
who the Grand Instructor is
and how close he can be to us
when we’re in a teaching environment.
Open, please, your Bible to Psalm 94:19
to recall what the psalmist said to Jehovah.
At Psalm 94:19,
we read:
“When anxieties overwhelmed me,
you [Jehovah] comforted and soothed me.”
What a beautiful reminder!
Jehovah can soothe and comfort us
when attending spiritual programs
so that we can focus
on what he’s teaching us.
Yes, spiritual programs
are a provision from him
—a spiritual lifeline.
So as needed during a spiritual program,
we should pray to Jehovah
to help us stay focused.
Pray repeatedly as needed.
Well, in summary, what have we learned?
All of us are teachers from time to time,
but first and foremost, we are students
in the classroom of the Great Teacher
and the Grand Instructor.
Like Ezra, humility and appreciation
should move us to ‘prepare our hearts’
before every spiritual program.
We don’t want to miss anything
that Jehovah has for us.
We’re determined ‘to consult that Law
so that we can practice it
and then teach it.’
And in view
of all the potential distractions,
let’s make it our aim to use
our eyes, our mind, and our heart
to focus attention on the goodness
of Jehovah’s spiritual provisions.
If you are a young Christian
who recently graduated from school
or will soon graduate,
you’ll make many decisions
that will affect your future.
How, though, can you make decisions
that let you
successfully run the race for life?
That’s the subject of our new music video.
Don’t look back
To the things behind.
Keep your eyes straight ahead
On that finish line.
Now’s the time to be strong.
Keep building your faith.
Don’t let the world
slow you down.
Put off ev’ry weight.
So let’s
Run the race; run the race.
Run the race
for life.
Let’s run the race;
yes, run the race.
Keep your eye
on the prize.
Let’s run the race;
run the race.
You’ve got to keep on going—
Got to keep on moving.
Let’s run the race.
The prize we gain—
It’ll never fade away.
All the blessings in store—
Soon we’ll see the day.
So let’s
Run the race; run the race.
Run the race
for life.
Let’s run the race;
yes, run the race.
Keep your eye
on the prize.
Let’s run the race;
run the race.
You’ve got to keep on going—
Got to keep on moving.
Let’s run the race.
Run the race
for life.
This world would like
to have you turn around
And lose yourself in this life.
But don’t let your hands drop down.
So let’s
Run the race; run the race.
Run the race;
run the race.
So let’s
Run the race; run the race.
Run the race
for life.
Let’s run the race;
yes, run the race.
Keep your eye
on the prize.
Let’s run the race;
run the race.
You’ve got to keep on going—
Got to keep on moving.
Let’s run the race.
Run the race for life.
You’ve got to run the race, yes.
Come on, and run the race.
Run the race.
Let’s run the race.
Run the race for life!
Volunteering
for theocratic construction projects
is a goal for many.
Recently, thousands of brothers and sisters
sacrificed their time and energy
to build a beautiful new
branch facility in Britain.
Would you like to see
the results of their hard work
and the blessings they received?
Please enjoy this report.
How will you feel
when all we came here to do
is finally completed?
No doubt, we will find a moment to reflect
on the words of Philippians 2:13.
Yes, Jehovah energized us
and gave each and every one of us
“both the desire
and the power to act.”
How has sharing on this project
affected your life?
It all started over seven years ago.
Can you imagine how excited
you’re going to be
when we hear
that the new branch facility at Chelmsford
has been approved by the City Council?
Well, guess what?
Yesterday afternoon we received the approval.
Whilst the buildings are beautiful,
at the end of the day,
they are just buildings.
The really special part of this project
has been the people;
even non-Witnesses saw that something special
was taking place on our site.
It’s a very friendly site to work on.
It’s just how friendly everyone is.
You walk in, and it just—
I find it mind-blowing.
In a negative (sometimes) society,
when you come here,
it just puts a smile on your face.
A truly unexpected success
was the visitors’ center.
How we underestimated the appreciation
Jehovah’s people have
for theocratic activities.
Visitors from all around the globe witnessed
the activities of Jehovah for themselves.
This is partly why
I’m actually studying the Bible
to get baptized,
because when I came here,
it just hit me somewhere, you know?
Me and Alicia can’t see,
so everyone has been
so encouraging and thoughtful.
We really feel like Jehovah is with us
and he’s supported us.
I really liked the ladies driving tractors.
Everyone wanted to have
a part in the project.
Every single contribution warmed our hearts
and sometimes our heads too.
Another beautiful project highlight
was the day-volunteer program.
The effort and expense brothers and sisters
sacrificed reminded all of us
of what a privilege it is
to work for Jehovah.
And how about the commuters
who helped on the project?
Would the BRD family have had
the same spirit without our commuters?
Don’t you just love being a part
of this amazing family?
We were regularly reminded that spirituality
is of the utmost importance.
Did you ever say that a monthly meeting
was the best one yet?
What lies outside the comfort zone
is the faith zone.
Don’t cry because it’s over;
smile because it happened.
What is your story?
The center of all of our stories is Jehovah.
He is the one who energized us;
he is the one who gave us
both the desire
and the power to act.
He is the one we can thank
for the lifelong friendships we have formed,
the training we have received,
and the challenges
we have been able to overcome.
Remember your story.
Really, it’s only just beginning.
In this month’s program,
we learned what it means
to pay attention to Jehovah.
We saw how we can stay focused on Jehovah
despite potential distractions.
Elders are good shepherds
because they are attentive
to Jehovah’s instruction.
Our ministry is more effective
when we focus
on reaching the hearts of people.
And our new song
reminds our young adults
to keep their eyes
on the prize of life.
Before we say goodbye,
let’s go to the southwest tip of Japan
and visit our brothers and sisters
in the Ishigaki Congregation.
Their territory includes the Yaeyama Islands,
an archipelago
of 12 islands
and more than 360 coral reefs.
Emerald-green waters
surround these lush,
jungle-covered islands.
With almost no light pollution,
this is an ideal place to observe
Jehovah’s beautiful heavenly creation.
Vast distances between the islands
make the ministry a challenge.
To reach remote communities,
publishers take ferries and small airplanes.
This is costly,
and economic conditions here aren’t easy.
Transportation includes bicycles
as well as carts and wagons
pulled by water buffalo.
Public witnessing is an effective way
to share the good news
with the many tourists who travel here.
More than one million
visited during one recent year.
Contact cards also produce good results.
The Ishigaki Congregation has 112 publishers,
including 35 regular pioneers.
They’re conducting
more than 100 Bible studies every month.
The Kingdom Hall
is in Ishigaki City on the main island.
Talks from this Kingdom Hall
are streamed to this small meeting place
for the seven brothers and sisters
who live on remote Iriomote Island.
The publishers work together
to maintain the Kingdom Hall,
and they enjoy upbuilding association
in this beautiful land.
Our brothers and sisters
in the Ishigaki Congregation
send their warm love and greetings.
From the World Headquarters
of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
this is JW Broadcasting.