I invite you to turn, please,
to Proverbs chapter 17.
And as you locate this in your Bible,
I invite you also to imagine
two runners.
One is rich;
the other is poor.
The rich runner has a gymnasium,
an olympic-size pool,
all the weight machines,
a nutritionist, a physical therapist,
a doctor, and a personal trainer.
And he has access
to the finest foods there are.
But somewhere along the way,
he’s grown just a little bored
with the whole concept of footraces,
and so he hasn’t put his heart into training.
Also, lined up next
to him is the poor runner.
The poor runner also has a few advantages.
He has a good pair of shoes;
he has real food;
he eats—not much—mostly plants.
But he loves the race;
he has a heart for it;
he trains in all kinds of weather.
Now, which of the two will win the race?
The man with the most advantages
or the man with the heart?
Now, with that illustration in mind,
notice what it says
at Proverbs 17:16:
“What good is it
“that the stupid one has the means
“to acquire wisdom when he has no heart
for acquiring it?”
Like winning a race, acquiring wisdom
does not happen without effort,
without cost, without sacrifice.
Hence, a person has to have the means.
And yet, doesn’t Jehovah really supply
the necessary ingredients
for each of us to acquire wisdom?
All of us have access to thinking ability,
information, opportunities,
evidence in some degree or another
—if we really want it.
But as Proverbs 17:16 asks,
‘What good is that if a person has no heart,
no drive, no sense?’
It’s not about the multiplicity
of our advantages
or the quality of our advantages;
it’s about the heart
—the total inner person.
Now, when it comes to acquiring true wisdom
and making sound decisions
despite not having much data
at one’s disposal,
our publications have often pointed
to the example of Joseph.
Long before Moses
recorded Jehovah’s law against adultery,
Joseph understood
that this was a sin against God.
Recall his words at Genesis 39:9:
“There is no one greater
in this house than I am,
“and he has not withheld
from me anything at all except you,
“because you are his wife.
“So how could I commit this great badness
and actually sin against God?”
—conscience fully engaged.
But the question is,
How did Joseph know that?
Follow along in Genesis,
and consider what may have
influenced his thinking.
Joseph had one Bible principle
and no less than four real-life applications
of that principle to meditate on.
The principle, of course,
is stated at Genesis 2:24:
“That is why a man
“will leave his father and his mother
and he will stick to his wife,
and they will become one flesh.”
The words of Jehovah God himself
(earth’s first wedding talk),
‘one man, one wife, one flesh’
—that’s the standard.
Joseph meditated on that.
Likely, he meditated on what happened
to his great-grandfather Abram,
in chapter 12, as Abram and Sarai
traveled to Egypt—Genesis 12:17.
This account tells us that Abram failed
to tell Pharaoh that he was married to Sarai,
so when Pharaoh
showed special interest in Sarai,
Genesis 12:17 says
that “Jehovah struck Pharaoh
and [all] his household
“with severe plagues because of Sarai,
Abram’s wife.”
Later in chapter 20, Abraham and Sarah
went to the land of Gerar
and employed a similar strategy;
they didn’t reveal that they were married.
And the king of Gerar, Abimelech,
had this experience at Genesis 20:3:
“Afterward, God came by night
“to Abimelech in a dream and said to him:
“‘Here you are as good as dead
“‘because of the woman whom you have taken,
“‘since she is married
and belongs to another man.’”
And Abimelech said to Jehovah,
‘Listen, I didn’t know.’
And Jehovah said,
‘I know you didn’t know.’
And so he says in verse 6 at the end:
“I held you back
from sinning against me.”
“Sinning against me”
—Joseph undoubtedly meditated on that.
Then, at Genesis 26:10,
his grandfather Isaac
and his grandmother Rebecca
also went to Gerar.
They also met a man named Abimelech,
likely a successor
of the Abimelech mentioned in chapter 20,
and they too didn’t tell Abimelech
that they were married,
but the king found out.
And so at Genesis 26:10:
“Abimelech continued:
‘What have you done to us?
“‘One of the people
could easily have lain down with your wife,
“‘and you would have brought guilt
[guilt] upon us!’”
Undoubtedly, Joseph meditated on that.
Or consider what happened
in Genesis chapter 34.
The principle recorded at Genesis 2:24
again came into play
—a man, his wife, one flesh.
Shechem was not yet married to Dinah,
but he violated her.
And Genesis 34:7 says:
‘Something like that ought not to be done.’
That was how it was viewed.
So while it’s true
that Joseph didn’t have the Mosaic Law,
Young People Ask,
Learn From the Great Teacher,
JW Library®, or jw.org,
he had a principle.
He had enough.
He had seen no fewer
than four applications of that principle.
If only Reuben and Judah
had also had such appreciation
for that principle.
But the point is,
Joseph fed his heart with that knowledge.
And there’s also another important factor
that we can’t lose sight of at Genesis 39:21.
It wasn’t just
an intellectual exercise for Joseph.
Look at chapter 39
and what it says in verse 21:
“Jehovah continued
with Joseph
and kept showing loyal love to him.”
Yes, even before
the situation where he was tested
with Potiphar’s wife,
Jehovah had been showing loyal love to him.
That’s born out in Genesis 39:3.
And afterward, he kept showing loyal love.
And to whom does Jehovah show loyal love?
Jehovah shows loyal love
to those acting in loyalty toward him.
Doesn’t that bespeak a relationship?
Joseph wasn’t just interested;
he didn’t just love
Jehovah’s righteous standards;
he loved Jehovah as a person.
And that was the key.
Turn with me, please, to Psalm 119:9.
Joseph had what Proverbs calls
“the means to acquire wisdom.”
He didn’t have the libraries, the websites,
and the Broadcast, but he had enough.
Now, notice the similarities
between Joseph’s situation
and that described here at Psalm 119:9:
“How can a young man keep his path clean?
“By keeping on guard according to your word.
“With my whole heart I seek you.
“Do not let me stray from your commandments.
“In my heart I treasure up your saying
so that I may not sin against you.”
Joseph had what
these verses are talking about.
He searched for Jehovah with his whole heart;
he treasured up
Jehovah’s sayings in his heart.
And that’s how he
was able to stay true to Jehovah
—the Person that he loved.
Well, we can do the same.
We have so much more data than Joseph had.
We have such excellent tools,
and Jehovah hasn’t changed.
So the essential questions
always boil down to this:
How is my heart?
Am I still seeking Jehovah
with my whole heart?
Or are fear, greed, immoral desires,
and other negative emotions
depriving me
from the completeness of my heart?
If our heart is complete, then we can indeed
avoid being swept away
by the flood of immoral propaganda
spewed out by Satan’s system of things.