Welcome to our program!
What are the benefits
of making the effort
to serve
in an unassigned territory?
Join this family as they travel
to a distant area to support
the Kingdom preaching work.
We will see how such a decision
builds their faith.
And our young ones,
have you started noticing the opposite sex?
And yet, you know
you’re not old enough to get married.
What can help you to take control
of such natural feelings?
We will find out
later in the program.
We’ll also hear the fascinating story
of Erich Frost—a brother
who was sent to a Nazi concentration camp
during World War II because of his faith.
How did he and his fellow brothers
help each other to remain faithful?
You will find this story
very encouraging.
That, and much more,
is coming your way
on this May program
of JW Broadcasting!
I would first like to read to you
some passages from the Bible
found at Ephesians chapter 3,
verses 14 through 19.
This will also establish the theme
for my comments this month.
Ephesians 3,
starting with verse 14, Paul said:
“For this reason
I bend my knees to the Father,
“to whom every family in heaven
and on earth owes its name.
“I pray that he may grant you
through the abundance of his glory
“to be made mighty
in the man you are inside,
“with power through his spirit,
“and that through your faith you may have
the Christ dwell in your hearts with love.
“May you be rooted
and established on the foundation,
“in order that with all the holy ones
you may be thoroughly able
“to comprehend fully
what is the breadth
“and length
and height and depth,
“and to know the love of the Christ,
which surpasses knowledge,
“so that you may be filled
with all the fullness
that God gives.”
Now, verse 15
is the inspiration
for my theme, namely,
“Glorify Jehovah—The One
to Whom Every Family Owes Its Name.”
The family unit is under a vicious attack
in these last days.
The Insight book
lived up to its name
under the heading “Family.”
The very insightful comment
reads this way:
“The inspired Scriptures
have foretold a vicious attack
“on the family institution
with a consequent breaking down of morality
and of human society
outside the . . . congregation.”
The article pointed out
that in “‘the last days’
“a condition in which
disobedience to parents,
“disloyalty, and absence
of ‘natural affection’ would be rife,
even among those
‘having a form of godly devotion.’”
How can married couples,
parents, and children
counteract
such a diabolical attack?
Do you remember those verses
we read in Ephesians chapter 3?
Verse 16 said that the One
to whom every family owes its name,
Jehovah, would ‘grant us
to be made mighty
in the person we are inside.’
Yes, Jehovah can give us
the internal
spiritual strength to fight back
against Satan’s efforts
to destroy the family.
How?
By being immersed in God’s Word.
In particular,
by imitating the loving way
that Jesus treated his disciples.
Did you note
that Ephesians 3:17 said
we are to “have the Christ
dwell in [our] hearts with love”?
Yes, if each of us cherishes
the Christ in our hearts
to the point that he dwells,
or resides, there constantly,
our family
will not only survive
but it will truly thrive.
This will be so evident
that verse 17 further states
that we will “be rooted
and established on the foundation.”
We will be solid!
And keep in mind
that 1 Corinthians 3:11 says
that the “foundation”
on which we build
“is Jesus Christ.”
Then verse 18
of Ephesians chapter 3 indicates that
our spiritual peripheral vision
will be enhanced.
We will not
have spiritual blind spots
that could allow the spirit of the world
to creep into the family.
That verse says
that we will “be thoroughly able
“to comprehend fully
what is the breadth
and length
and height and depth.”
All aspects of Jesus’ personality
will come into play
as we interact
with family members.
Finally, verse 19
sums up the result when it says
that we would then
have come “to know the love of the Christ,
which surpasses knowledge.”
Granted,
knowledge is important,
but it is the application
of Christlike love
that will preserve our family,
keeping it vibrantly intact.
Family life
in these critical last days
could be likened to those
who suffer from diabetes.
It is believed
that diabetes is caused
by both genetic
and environmental factors.
Similarly, all in the family
have inherited sin
and imperfection
from our first human parents,
Adam and Eve,
as if genetically.
However, we are also exposed
to the ever more toxic
environmental factors
of Satan’s evil world.
Most who suffer
from a serious case of diabetes
need to use two methods
to successfully relieve the symptoms
and lead a normal life.
They have to watch their diet
and, in many cases,
take an injection
of insulin daily.
Spiritually,
we need to avoid the sickly,
sweet junk food
that the world promotes in movies,
talk shows,
the Internet, and in print.
Just as with the person
who has diabetes,
this requires
a permanent lifestyle change
from what we might have
exposed ourselves to in the past.
In addition to avoiding
unwholesome junk food
from Satan’s system,
we also need
to take daily “injections”
of God’s Word
and other wholesome provisions.
This has become more
and more important
the deeper we get
into these last days.
How has our organization provided this
when it comes to family life?
Well, in the early 1900’s,
the focus was on preaching
the good news.
Little attention was given
to building strong
Christian marriages and families.
For a time,
marriage was even discouraged
well beyond
the intent of the Scriptures.
I did some checking,
and commendably
between 1919 and 1921
there was a feature
in the Golden Age magazine
once or twice a month
called the “Juvenile Bible Study.”
In 1920,
a brochure was released
called The Golden Age ABC.
Then it wasn’t until 1941
that the now famous book
entitled Children was handed out
to all young ones
at the convention that year.
But as the last days progressed,
more and more information
for families was produced.
For example, in the 1970’s,
the book Making Your Family Life Happy
was released.
About the same time,
the books Listening to the Great Teacher
and Your Youth—Getting the Best out of It
were published.
In 1982, Awake!
began a regular series
that has run for decades
entitled “Young People Ask.”
We now have two up-to-date books
with the same title,
and the series of articles
continues on the jw.org website.
We have the book
Learn From the Great Teacher
and so many features
and activities for young ones
on the website that I would be out of time
if I tried to enumerate them all.
There are also regular articles
in our magazines
about marriage
and family life.
And I will certainly never forget
the privilege I had in 2012
to introduce the animated series
Become Jehovah’s Friend.
That has proved
to be a blessing
for both young ones
and their parents.
What a teaching tool for both!
In 2014, I attended
the international convention
in Atlanta, Georgia,
here in the United States.
After a little two-year-old girl
saw my face
on the big jumbo screen
giving a talk,
she eagerly started searching
all around her for someone.
When her parents asked her
who she was looking for, she said, “Caleb.
He must be here because I saw
his grandfather giving a talk.”
Many children ask
to meet Caleb in person
when they visit Bethel.
Two postings
of an item every month
is making quite an impression
on little hearts.
With Bible principles
being impressed on the minds and hearts
of children so early,
we prayerfully anticipate
many spiritually-minded teenagers
in the years to come.
We have so much
healthy spiritual food
for counteracting
family “diabetes.”
For this,
we give all glory to Jehovah,
the one “to whom
every family . . . owes its name.”
One of the favorite passages
of Scripture that anyone
professing to be Christian
loves is the 23rd Psalm.
Family heads, can we benefit
from imitating not only
the Fine Shepherd, Jesus,
but also the Great Shepherd,
Jehovah God?
I am going to borrow
the text of the 23rd Psalm
and adjust the words so that we
can sense a family’s tranquillity
when headship
is exercised properly.
In fact, you husbands,
as the script is read,
imagine it is your wife’s voice
describing the effect
your headship has on your family.
‘[My husband]
is [our] shepherd.
‘[We] will lack nothing.
‘In grassy pastures
[refreshing recreation]
‘he makes [us] lie down;
he leads [us]
‘to well-watered resting-places
[meetings and conventions].
‘He refreshes [us].
‘He leads [us in the ministry]
‘in the paths of righteousness
for the sake of [Jehovah’s] name.
‘Though [we] walk in the valley
of deep [economic] shadow,
‘[we] fear no harm,
for [Dad is] with [us];
‘your rod and your staff
[loving discipline] reassure [us].
‘You prepare a table [of family worship,
helping the children]
‘for [us] before [our] enemies.
‘You refresh
[our] head[s] with oil;
‘[Our] cup
[of family well-being] is well-filled.
‘Surely goodness and loyal love
will pursue [our family]
‘all the days of [our] life,
and [our family]
will dwell in the house
of Jehovah for all [our] days.’
No further application called for.
We feel the sense of security
that envelops
the interior rooms
of such a home, don’t we?
Do you remember
the point made
in Ephesians chapter 3,
which we read earlier?
We are to treasure
Jesus’ personality
and let it “dwell”
in our hearts.
If all in the family
make a determined effort
to treat each other
like Jesus would,
we can conquer the world!
Yes, we—His spiritual family
in heaven
and all humans on earth
who dedicate their lives to Him
—give glory to Jehovah!
Indeed, we thank Jehovah
for all the spiritual provisions
he has made through his Word
and organization to protect every family
who takes up his name.
May Jehovah bless
all of you families
as you strive to win
the war that Satan wages
against you
in these last days.
An important aspect
of keeping
the family’s spiritual health intact
is by making full use
of the Family Worship arrangement.
In this dramatization,
pay attention
to how the family head
is aware of the needs of the family
and how he plans accordingly.
Hi, my name is Joe.
A few weeks ago,
we all sat together for supper.
I was so tired, and my wife,
Jenny, felt the same way.
She always does it all,
taking care of the children so well,
but it was not easy
for her in recent weeks.
Sarah felt that we are too restrictive
on how she dresses.
She just does not understand.
It was hard to convince her.
And to motivate her
to share in the field service
is becoming a challenge.
It was not always like this.
She used to enjoy
going out in field service.
And Tom,
he is such a good boy,
but all of a sudden,
he was raving about the games
his classmates
have on their phones.
It’s always
about having supernatural powers,
and it fascinated him,
even though he is small.
But when I asked him
to take out the garbage,
suddenly
his superpowers left him.
And Mike,
our smallest,
it was hard
to get him to go to bed
or clean up his room.
I realized there are a few things
we need to speak about.
Joe came to me, and we talked
a lot about our children that same evening.
We wondered,
‘What would be the best for them?’
We prayed together.
Then we had an idea!
The following day
we asked our children
if we could consider Noah
as the theme for our next family worship.
All of us liked the idea.
Each one of us
should prepare something.
Mike, Tom, and I
wanted to build the ark.
And, of course,
we need the animals.
And Sarah
should collect pictures
for the story
from our publications.
I also had to take time
to think again about the story of Noah
and how it
can help our family.
Jenny and Sarah were responsible
for the wardrobe and food.
While preparing,
I got the chance
to speak with Sarah about her dress
in a more relaxed setting.
She understood that,
like Noah,
when it comes to Jehovah’s commands,
we need to do “just so.”
Then the evening arrived.
We talked about
how it was before the Flood
and what kind of world
Noah and his family lived in.
Noah’s family needed
real courage to preach.
They had to explain about the rain
and how the ark would be needed
to survive the Flood
—something that had never happened before.
All the people
thought they were crazy!
And while we were talking
about this, it came out
that Sarah felt embarrassed when she met
a schoolmate in the field service recently.
I realized Noah must have felt
the same as me,
and yet,
he was so courageous.
Dad read Genesis 6:9:
“Noah walked with the true God.”
So he could have every confidence
in his Friend, Jehovah.
I want to be just like that!
For Tom,
I found a great picture.
Dad told us that the world
at this time was very bad.
People were fighting
and many were afraid,
and that is why
Jehovah brought the Flood.
It made me think
about the games from my schoolmates.
I like to play those games,
but I know that Jehovah does not like that.
So why do I?
And the best part
was when we got inside the ark!
Then I read Genesis 6:19:
“And bring into the ark
two of every sort
of living creature.”
Dad showed us
how the animals went into the ark.
Each one had its own place,
and they went inside
two at a time without any chaos.
I explained that we also need
to keep our rooms clean like the ark.
I saw that Mike got the point.
We wanted
to keep in mind Genesis 6:22:
“And Noah did according to all
that God had commanded him.
He did just so.”
And then the rain came,
but we survived!
That was great!
We all realized
Noah also must have been
tired sometimes,
but he never gave up.
This was a good lesson for us.
We must take care
of our family as Noah did,
also by having
a regular family worship
like this.
That example really showed
many of the great benefits
of family worship.
In addition to the obvious
—coming together to learn
more about our heavenly Father
—we saw how family worship
gave the daughter
an opportunity
to open up about matters
that had been bothering her.
And thanks to the good work
of the parents,
all of the children
learned something
they could apply
in their daily lives.
We’ve now invited
Brother and Sister Ortiz
from New Britain, Connecticut,
to visit our studio.
Brother Ortiz serves as an elder
and as a regular pioneer.
He’s had many additional privileges
of service over the years.
And Linnette has been regular pioneering
for over six years.
However, the reason we wanted
to talk with them is that thus far
they have successfully countered
Satan’s attacks on their family.
We’d like to hear
how they accomplished this.
First of all, Freddie,
tell us a little bit
about your family.
Neither Linnette nor I
were raised in the truth.
However, we met,
and we fell in love.
At that time,
marriage was not for me.
So we started
a romantic relationship for two years
before we started attending
the first meeting at the Kingdom Hall.
Soon thereafter,
we started studying the Bible;
and we took two studies per week;
we knew this was the truth.
But also we learned
how Jehovah sees immorality,
so we needed to do some changes.
Linnette’s parents
wanted her to continue
with her education,
so we needed to change our behavior.
So two years after,
we did the changes.
Number one
because we did love Jehovah.
Number two because we loved
what we were learning.
It was worth it
to follow Bible principles.
So two years later,
we got married
and we got baptized
—and we got married.
Very good.
So, Linnette, you were raised
without a knowledge of Jehovah God.
What changes did you both
have to make to ensure
your own family
would have a fine foundation
and be successful?
Well, prior to our baptism,
Freddie had a serious drinking problem.
And based on the way we were raised,
there was a lot of jealousy going on
and, I would say, a lack of confidence
and trust in each other.
My Bible teacher,
thankfully, suggested to us
to study the book
Making Your Family Life Happy.
And we ended up studying
that book twice.
That publication and the Bible principles
in it became the foundation
of our wonderful marriage
and the happy family we enjoy today.
Very nice.
So, Freddie, maybe you
can tell us about your children
and what they are doing
with their lives now.
We have two sons.
Gabriel, he’s the oldest one.
He started regular pioneering
when he was 14 years old.
At 18, he was appointed
as a ministerial servant.
At 22 years old, he has been working
in the Plumbing Department
at the Warwick construction
for more than two years.
Adrian is now 18 years old.
And he also started
regular pioneering when he was 14.
Currently, he handles
the accounts for the congregation
and other privileges as well.
Well, they both have had
an early start in their theocratic careers.
That’s commendable.
I’m sure you’re both
proud of them.
And we’re confident
that Jehovah,
the One “to whom
every family . . . owes its name,”
is pleased that they are giving
an answer to his taunter.
In addition
to the Family Life book,
what else contributed
to the success your family
has experienced, Linnette?
The Governing Body has provided us
with so many publications
with direction for families,
of course, all based on Jehovah’s Word.
So we decided early on that whenever
a question or an issue came up,
we would not make
any decision based on impulse.
Instead, we would research it
in the publications.
We pray to Jehovah
for him to give us wisdom.
And we even pray
for him to guide us
to find the right time to talk
to each other or to counsel the boys.
I have always heard
that there are stages
in the child’s life
and personality development.
So I researched in advance
as to what to expect.
In that way,
we were not surprised
when we saw changes
in attitudes or ideas.
And that helped us
realize what needed
to be addressed or corrected
as opposed to what was normal
for that stage
in the boys’ lives.
Very practical.
Freddie,
what can you add?
Over the years, I have learned
how essential it is to become a good listener
—also understanding.
I tell my family
how much I love them every day
because we never know
when circumstances might change.
Family worship
is very important for us.
I know it is easy to put off,
but the benefits are hard to beat.
Well,
before this arrangement started,
we as a family, we valued
the Bible study with the family.
I learned that a fetus
that is six months,
he can recognize
the family’s voice.
So I started a Bible study with my sons
when they were still in the womb . . .
Isn’t that nice.
. . . and continued
to do so after that.
I know that secular work
and other activities
can block
a regular program,
but we need to fight that tendency
if we want to succeed in family worship.
Very good.
Well, it seems your efforts
paid off when we consider
how well your family
has done spiritually
and the close relationship
you have with each other.
Now Linnette,
it sounds as if the family is perfect
—no challenges.
Is that the case?
No, not at all.
First Corinthians 10:13 says
that Christians will face
challenges
that are “common to [all] men.”
And we have faced the normal challenges
that come with raising a family.
The same verse indicates
that if we do things
Jehovah’s way,
we may increase the opportunity
for him to “make the way out” for us.
One unexpected challenge
that has changed
our family dynamics
over the years now,
was when Freddie
was diagnosed
with cancer in 2012.
The treatment was aggressive
and took its toll on his health.
Our whole lifestyle changed.
We had to move out
from our house . . .
Oh, boy.
. . . to an apartment,
we gave away our dog, Spike,
and we have to watch our expenses
really closely to keep going.
This could have put a lot
of strain in our family,
in our marriage,
and in our spirituality.
But, again, by praying to Jehovah constantly
and applying Bible principles,
I can say my marriage
and my family
have never been better.
Wow.
Spiritually, we kept our routine,
and we all stayed
in full-time service
throughout the ordeal.
The boys
have cooperated very well.
They have offered
to work to give us money.
But we prefer for them
to keep focused on the Kingdom
because we are confident
that Jehovah
will add on
to the things we need.
Freddie has been
a great example for all of us
because he pushes himself
to keep his spiritual routine.
You never see him
complaining or in a bad mood.
And that has been very inspiring
for the rest of the family.
Boy, that is quite a story.
You folks will certainly relate
to the convention drama video
that was advertised
on our April program.
Freddie, we’re very sorry to hear
about your physical condition.
Are there any
favorite scriptures that you use
to help keep you going spiritually
and to stay strong?
There are many of them.
Just to mention a few,
Philippians 4:6,7
has been my life since 2012,
where I have to pray
to Jehovah constantly
so that he can give me
the strength that I need
to overcome my health.
And also,
Philippians says
that he will give us
peace of mind.
In addition,
he will safeguard our heart.
And that’s something
I’ve been seeing from Jehovah.
Also, Isaiah 41:10 states:
“Do not be anxious,
for I am your God.”
Those words give me comfort
that he will keep on helping us
in these different circumstances
in our life.
I do understand that my wife has a lot
of responsibilities in the household,
so I had to reread
Proverbs 31
verses 10 to 31,
where it describes
all of the responsibility a good wife
might have to shoulder
for the family.
So Brother Morris,
she is my Proverbs 31 wife!
A good wife for sure.
You’ve obviously shown how much
you love and respect each other.
That’s commendable.
And your focus on being the best parents
you could be is a good example
for parents viewing
the program at this time.
This will come
as a surprise to you,
but we would like to invite your two sons
out to see what they remember
from growing up
in the family.
We have Gabriel
and Adrian with us.
Mom’s getting a little teary-eyed.
That’s understandable.
It was a surprise, see.
So Gabriel,
since you’re the oldest,
we will start with you.
What do you remember
about your family life,
first in Puerto Rico
and later here in the United States?
I remember faithfully going
to all the meetings and going out in service
every Saturday
—that was just the routine.
In Puerto Rico,
my dad had to work a lot though,
and like he said before,
that’s easy to get in the way
of a good family worship routine.
But I can honestly say that once we made
that transition of moving over here,
that helped us to have
a good family worship routine,
and it has helped us
to get closer and closer each day.
Now, isn’t that nice?
Now, Adrian, anything you can add
about the homelife?
Yeah, my mom
and dad have always
shown a great love for Jehovah
but also for each other.
So as kids,
you could just sense that.
So love and respect
is what we’ve always known.
Even now that my brother and I are older,
we have a great bond with each other.
We love each other and we can tell
each other everything about our lives.
And it’s due to that love
and respect that they have shown.
And even if there are disagreements,
which there are always going
to be disagreements
because it’s an imperfect family,
but that love is always there
to bridge those differences.
I also would like to add,
something that helped me a lot
was a routine
that my dad and I had
right before going to school;
we would always read the daily text.
And he would always say, “Behave,
and remember that Jehovah loves you.”
I don’t think he knows
how much that really helped me
go through
everyday challenges at school.
That’s priceless.
Now, very nice observations.
Gabriel, I’m interested
in understanding what prompted you
to regular pioneer
when you were only 14 years old?
It was at a point
where my dad lost his job.
Rather than stressing about it
—worrying about it
—he looked at things
with a spiritual perspective.
So he started to pioneer.
And since our schedules
matched perfectly,
I was his little pioneer buddy.
I would go out in service
with him whenever he needed it.
And I feel like if spiritual families,
you know, focus on spiritual matters,
it helps them
to become closer.
And I can’t imagine
how our relationship
and respect for one another
can be any better than what it is now.
Very nice.
Now, Adrian,
you began pioneering
when you were 14 as well.
How do you think
that affected you as a person?
Well, first of all,
the reason why I started pioneering
was because I was going out in service
with the rest of my family,
and since they were already pioneering,
I was getting the time in.
But I do think
that taking on the responsibility
of getting
at least 70 hours a month
in the service
does make you think differently
at 14 than it would have otherwise.
I think it has helped me
mature spiritually,
and it has contributed to me being used
to my full potential in the congregation.
And honestly, I wouldn’t trade it
for anything, well, maybe going to Bethel.
Gabriel, back to you.
Tell us what was it like
when you learned
that your dad
had a serious health problem
and would not be able to provide
for the family like he used to?
That was probably one
of the biggest challenges I have ever faced.
When my dad got diagnosed with cancer,
it was about the same time
that I got my call to Bethel.
And I was torn; I was divided.
I felt like if I was to go
to Bethel now,
it would be selfish of me
to leave my family at a time like that.
But my family
always had a spiritual view
on things and cited scriptures
like Matthew 6:33 constantly.
It helped me to see as a whole—as a family
—we put Kingdom interests first;
that Jehovah
was going to provide
because he’s a loving father
and friend.
And then my dad lost his job,
and again all these feelings came up.
But my family was adamant.
They let me know that the congregation
had been taking care of them
for months now,
and then doing some simplifying
on their own
helped them as well.
And I didn’t have to worry
about anything.
I do know that there’s a scripture that says
that we’ve got to take care of our own.
So I do anything I can
to help my family back home.
The only thing I hope
is that I can have a good faith
like they’ve shown
through these difficult times.
Well, thank all of you
for joining us.
I think all of us
are feeling that emotion
and feel very close
to you for sharing that.
Now, as a father, I can appreciate
all that Freddie is trying to do
as head of the family.
And, Linnette, your support
beyond normal
is very much
to be commended.
We can tell your family
is thriving spiritually,
and we pray Jehovah
will continue to bless your efforts,
come what may.
And we thank you,
Gabriel and Adrian,
for your surprise
to the studio.
Thank you very much
for taking the time to be interviewed.
Thank you for the privilege.
Thank you.
As we just learned,
an excellent way of maintaining
the spirituality of the family
is by spending quality time
together in the ministry.
We would now like to introduce you
to a family from Russia.
They traveled far away
to work together
in unassigned territory
in Siberia.
Their experience confirms
how spiritual activities
not only build up our faith
but can also bring our family
closer to each other.
We are traveling
to a very interesting territory.
It is on the shores
of Lake Baikal.
From where we live,
it is 600 kilometers.
We have so many memories
to take home.
The scenery is always stunning
in all types of weather.
Here there are beautiful cliffs
and valleys.
We cross
several mountain passes.
Then we go by ferry.
It felt very strange
being in the car while crossing the river.
When we have the opportunity,
we witness
to people
we meet on the way.
Why do sincere people
trust the Holy Scriptures?
Please have a look
at what it says here:
“All scripture is inspired of God.”
We usually serve
in isolated territory for a week or more.
We have come to the same place
where we were last year,
so we already know
a lot about it.
Living in a tent
is very different
from living in the city.
Here we don’t have
any conveniences,
like a toilet or a shower.
The only place to wash
is in Lake Baikal, which is freezing.
This simple life
is like an adventure.
As we have quite a big group
—there are 12 of us
—we have also organized
our spiritual routine.
We consider
the daily text together and take part
in discussing our publications
using the questions.
We have a friendly,
relaxed atmosphere.
Everybody enjoys it.
Our isolated territory,
where we are preaching,
is a rural area.
Here we don’t have
any prepared maps.
So when we have our meetings
for field service,
we divide up,
all taking different streets.
We also think
about what clothes to wear.
Experience has shown
that our clothes
can help us
to win over these people.
So we try to dress simply.
We don’t wear ties.
The people there are kind.
Sometimes they even invite us in.
We can have discussions
with some of them—sometimes long ones.
There you meet
more receptive people
than unresponsive ones,
and that really is encouraging.
It makes you just want
to keep on preaching
without stopping.
The trips have helped
our son make spiritual progress.
For us as his parents,
that is the greatest blessing.
For example,
after one of these trips,
he became an unbaptized publisher.
This territory is different
from what I am used to,
so I was worried.
I didn’t know
what sort of people lived there
or what their attitude
was toward Witnesses.
But after praying when knocking
on the first door, my fear disappeared.
I was able to place 270 tracts.
While we were witnessing,
we showed the people
the addresses in our publications
so that they could write
if they found
what they had read interesting.
We usually start witnessing
about 12 noon, and we finish
around 5:00 p.m.
Then the relaxation part
of our day begins.
We have a campfire,
some games,
some music, and fun.
Early in the day,
we used our energy in the ministry,
and afterward we were able
to relax and enjoy each other’s company.
So we combine
both our ministry and relaxation.
One of the delights
of these trips is the fish
—the famous Baikal omul.
These trips really strengthen
the unity in our family.
We really have
drawn closer together.
It is invigorating
and enriches us spiritually.
We experience
pure joy from knowing
that Jehovah
has blessed our efforts.
We feel like we have our batteries
charged for the entire year.
It is very encouraging to see
such a spiritually focused family.
And did you notice
that it was after one such trip
that their son
became an unbaptized publisher?
I’m sure that brought
much joy to his parents.
Are you interested
in a preaching assignment
in territory seldom worked?
If so, form a group
of no more than 20 publishers
and ask the elders
in your congregation for further instructions
and an Application
for Territory Seldom Worked.
Once you have filled out the form,
the Congregation Service Committee
will review it and submit it
to your local branch.
Theocratic activities,
such as family worship,
spending time in the ministry together,
along with balanced amounts of recreation,
can truly fortify our family.
As we saw in the interview
with the Ortiz family,
such spiritual preparation
helps us when we face challenges.
In this dramatization,
a family followed Scriptural counsel
when they faced the challenge
of having to relocate
to another city.
For 23 years,
we’ve called this place home.
We’ve raised a family here
—two beautiful girls.
Six months ago,
my boss called me into his office.
The company was restructuring.
They valued my work,
but if I wanted to keep my job,
I would need to move.
It was a difficult decision.
My job allowed me to support my family well,
and it had never interfered
with our spiritual routine.
We said many prayers about it.
We discussed it as a family,
and we decided to move.
But we were anxious.
My family has only ever known
one home, one congregation.
My girls have many friends
in the congregation,
good examples who are helping them
to serve Jehovah.
This is going
to be hard on all of us.
A brother in our hall had moved
into the congregation a few years ago.
I asked him how his family
coped with the challenge.
He said that the key to staying grounded
is maintaining the one thing
that should never change
—our spiritual routine.
But that requires
work and planning
to make sure our move doesn’t stop us
from getting to the meetings,
sharing in the ministry,
spending time
with our brothers and sisters,
and looking after our family.
His advice was spot-on.
After some research, I found a scripture
that illustrated our situation.
“And the rain poured down
and the floods came
“and the winds blew and lashed
against that house, but it did not cave in,
for it had been founded on the rock.”
The discreet man
built his house on good foundations.
It took a plan,
and he worked hard.
When the storm came,
his house survived.
As a family,
we needed a plan that would help us
stay spiritually grounded through our move.
So we wrote our own plan.
Just like the discreet man,
we wanted to build our move
on a strong spiritual foundation.
So we made a visit
to our new congregation ahead of our move.
Over the years,
it becomes a comfort
to walk into a Kingdom Hall
and see familiar faces.
Walking into our new congregation
reminded me
how much we are going
to miss everyone.
But the Bible tells us
that ‘with the measure we measure out,
others will measure
to us in return.’
So we resolved
to show love first.
Hello, I’m Jessica.
Hi, I’m Samantha.
Nice to meet you.
The best way to get to know
our new congregation is to work
with the brothers
and sisters in the ministry.
No matter where we go,
we’ll find people
that love Jehovah
and each other.
Moving day finally arrived.
The last boxes were packed.
We locked the door one final time
and began our journey to our new home.
It took effort,
but visiting the congregation
ahead of time
was well worth it.
Look!
We already have friends here.
Unpacking seemed to never end,
but the one thing
that we all promised ourselves
at family worship
was that we would not let
our move affect
our spiritual routine.
Has anyone seen my ties?
Found them!
We planned that we
wouldn’t let anything stop us
from going to the meetings.
The ministry is very different.
We’ve had to adapt
and learn new techniques.
The brothers and sisters
are different too.
It’s important not to focus
on negative comparisons.
Instead, be positive.
During this transition,
it is especially important to be sensitive
to our spiritual needs.
Family worship is vital.
Keeping spiritually grounded
through such a big transition isn’t easy,
especially with a family.
It took a lot of time
and energy to care for our needs,
not just spiritually,
but emotionally too.
Planning ahead,
like the discreet man,
helped our family
to stay spiritually grounded.
Having a spiritually strong family
prepares us also
for other changes in life.
Perhaps you are in your teens
and you’re starting to notice
those of the opposite sex.
Such emotions are natural
and are part of growing up.
But if you’re not old enough
to get married,
what do you need
to keep in mind?
This young sister
made wise decisions
with the loving help
of her parents.
Uhh, yours?
Yeah.
Thanks.
You’re Lily, right?
Yeah.
And you’re Sean.
I’ve seen you around.
You play good basketball.
Thanks.
So do you.
So you want
to hang out sometime?
Sure.
My name is Lily,
and I sorta had this problem.
There’s a boy named Sean
that recently moved to our school.
I know I’m not supposed
to like anyone who is not a Witness.
The trouble was,
he is a Witness.
Sean and his family
moved into our congregation.
And the more I saw of him,
the more I liked him.
“My strength is exhausted
because of my sighing.
“If only I knew
where to find God!
“I would go
to his place of dwelling.
I would present my . . .”
Like I said,
“I had a problem.”
Every day I see
couples my age at school.
To me, they look happy.
Honestly, I wanted
that happiness too.
My parents noticed my problem too
and talked about it that night.
And pretty soon
I didn’t feel alone anymore.
The next day, my mom invited me
to go with her to run an errand.
Afterward,
we went to a little café.
She asked me
how things were going.
At first,
I didn’t want to tell her,
but she made me
feel really comfortable.
So I told her
my feelings for Sean,
expecting her
to think bad of me.
But she didn’t.
Everything you’re feeling
is natural, Lily.
I remember having these same feelings
when I was your age too.
Really?
It’s true.
That’s just how Jehovah
created us, Honey.
And because he created us,
he knows
the best way
for us to be happy.
And that’s all he wants for us.
And that’s all Daddy
and I want for you too.
She didn’t scold me;
she didn’t make me
feel embarrassed.
And most importantly,
she didn’t seem to be in a rush.
My mom wasn’t the only one
helping me.
My dad was preparing
to help me with my problem too.
That evening,
we had family worship.
And once again,
they just let me talk.
They told me I didn’t have
to hold back, so I didn’t.
I just don’t know what to do.
Lily, thank you
for telling us how you feel.
Let me ask you something:
Why do you think Jehovah created us
with these natural feelings
toward the opposite sex?
So that one day a man
and woman could marry.
That’s right!
In fact, a good marriage
is like two skaters on the ice.
A beautiful performance
can seem effortless,
but is it really?
No.
No one would even
attempt that without practice,
a capable partner,
or the right kind of guidance, right?
Yeah.
Well, it’s the same
with a good marriage, Sweetie.
It doesn’t just happen.
It too depends
on a good partner,
coordinated effort,
but most importantly,
wise counsel from Jehovah.
In fact,
could you please turn with me
to Psalm 32:8
and read that for us.
Sure.
It says:
“I will give you insight
“and instruct you
in the way you should go.
I will give you advice
with my eye upon you.”
Lily, Jehovah loves us very much.
And if we listen to him,
we’ll make good decisions in our life
with absolutely no regrets.
We talked some more,
and then I got some homework.
My dad gave me some articles
he printed out for me to read,
so I did.
And as I read the words
and started meditating on them,
I realized something.
By holding off dating a little longer,
I wasn’t missing out.
Rather, I was preparing myself.
I could use the time now
to focus on something
much more important
—my relationship with Jehovah.
I could also gain Christian qualities
and experience that will help me later
if I ever do get married.
A strong spiritual upbringing
can truly be a protection for us
when young
but also strengthens us as adults.
Brother Erich Frost
was a young man in Germany
who set a good example
in making wise decisions early in life.
He was born in 1900,
baptized 23 years later,
and entered
the full-time ministry in 1928.
Not long after, he was put in charge
of the underground work
of the persecuted
Witnesses of Jehovah in Germany,
caring well for that assignment
for eight months
until he was incarcerated.
In this archived audio recording,
you will hear the fascinating experience
of how Brother Frost
composed a Kingdom melody
in the middle of Sachsenhausen
—a Nazi concentration camp.
I always had the desire
to compose music.
As everybody knows,
we had the hardest work
and suffered the hardest
in the concentration camps.
We were starved,
the labor
exceeded our strength,
and the harassment was often unbearable.
So, as usual, I wanted to find
a way to build up the brothers.
We had such a fine unity
there in the Sachsenhausen camp.
I felt moved
to compose a song
that we could sing together
for our mutual encouragement.
Every morning we marched
to the construction site
of a sewage plant
in Oranienburg.
Our labor group
consisted of about 40 brothers
under the strict watch of the SS.
While marching,
my mind went back and forth
and “Bum Bam Badam
Bam Tarambambamba.”
And gradually,
a melody formed.
That’s how the music
was developed.
But how could the verses
enter the camp
without being able
to write them down?
I found a few brothers
who helped me.
I repeated the first verse
to one of them until he knew it by heart,
either while marching or while driving
the wheelbarrow at work.
I told the second verse
to another brother,
still to others the third
and the fourth.
In the evening, I asked
each of the brothers to recite his verse.
That’s how the song came to life.
In the mornings,
when the 40 of us were marching
through the streets of Oranienburg,
we already felt worn out.
When one started humming
that melody,
the entire labor group
trembled with excitement.
We had to control ourselves
to not break out in loud singing.
That would have been dangerous,
of course.
They would have brought us
back to the camp
and severely punished us.
As we sat together in the evenings
and someone started humming that melody,
quite a number of us
sang along, and we rejoiced.
Our eyes were shining.
This gave us
new courage and hope.
We also had evenings of worship.
Talks were given, and we had copies
of The Watchtower that we studied together.
So we were able to have
some real times of peace
and special encouragement
and felt uplifted by that song.
Brother Frost,
who was one of the anointed,
finished
his earthly course in 1987.
After World War II
and nine years of imprisonment,
he served as the overseer
of our branch office
in Germany for ten years.
This was before
the arrangement was instituted
of having a Branch Committee
oversee the work.
The very descriptive paintings
that you saw in this segment
were painted by a brother
who was imprisoned
in a concentration camp
similar to the one Brother Frost was in.
And I’m sure
you recognized the song.
You can find it in our songbook,
though the tune is a little different.
When Brother Frost found out
that his song had been included in it,
he was overjoyed
and said, “My clumsy lyrics
were transformed
into three wonderful verses.”
If you turn to song 17
in your songbook,
you’ll find the song
originally composed by Brother Frost
—“Forward, You Witnesses!”
Like Brother Frost,
we want to do our best
to expand our ministry
for Jehovah.
One way of doing that
is by learning a language.
In this music video,
pay close attention
to the blessings that resulted
from this couple’s heartfelt desire
to serve
in the foreign-language field.
You may be contemplating,
‘Should I make the move?’
Prayerfully meditating,
‘Jehovah, what should I do?’
So let’s just take a moment
And try to help you decide.
‘Cause if you step on over,
You’ll be so happy you tried!
You gotta step on over
And leave your worries behind.
‘Cause when you step on over,
You will be blessed if you try, oh.
Step on over.
Step on over that Macedonia line!
The preaching work is amazing,
With overwhelming success.
You’ll be appreciating
How strangers give you their best.
And you will draw even closer
To Jehovah each day.
‘Cause he will always be there
To help you learn every step of the way.
You gotta step on over
And leave your worries behind.
‘Cause when you step on over,
Oh, the treasures you’ll find.
Maybe you’re thinking it over
And wondering if it’s right, oh.
You gotta step on over.
You will be blessed if you try, oh.
Step on over.
You gotta step on over that Macedonia line!
Did you notice
some of the blessings
this couple enjoyed as the result
of learning a new language?
Not only were they able
to expand their ministry
and show their love for neighbor
but they also spent a lot of time together
as a couple, reaching the goal
of learning a language as a family.
By working hard to build up
and protect our family spiritually,
we can all take part
in glorifying Jehovah
—the One “to whom every family
. . . owes its name.”
You’ll also enjoy a Bethel morning worship
that is now available
on Video on Demand.
It ties very well into the theme
of this month’s program.
The video is entitled
‘Practice Godly Devotion
in Our Own Household’
and is presented
by Brother David Schafer,
a helper
to the Teaching Committee.
But we have more
in store for you.
We’re also pleased to announce
the release of a new brochure
entitled
Answers to 10 Questions Young People Ask.
The content of this 32-page,
full-color brochure
is based on articles
in Awake! and the two volumes
of Questions Young People Ask
—Answers That Work, as well as
the “Young People Ask” articles
on the jw.org website.
This new brochure
will be particularly helpful
to those who speak a language
in which that material is not available.
However, all young people
can benefit from this new brochure
because the original articles
have been updated and rewritten.
Each section of the brochure
addresses one question.
After stating the question,
the section begins with a pointed statement
under the feature
“Why It Matters,”
letting the reader know
why that question is relevant.
Then, a “What Would You Do?”
scenario is presented,
putting the reader
in a hypothetical situation
related to the topic.
After discussing various principles,
Scriptural advice
directs the reader to the best answers
for that particular question.
The 10 Questions brochure
is interactive,
allowing the reader
to write responses
to the various questions presented.
The final topic,
“How Can the Bible Help Me?,”
is designed to invite readers
who are not Jehovah’s Witnesses
to accept a Bible study.
The brochure
makes numerous references
to the jw.org website
and directs readers to more information
that can be found there.
Also, the brochure
is designed in such a way
that young people can be comfortable
sharing it with their peers
and with others in the ministry.
This brochure
is already approved for translation
into 324 languages.
Of these languages,
223 do not produce Awake!
and 262 have not produced
the Young People Ask books.
So we expect that Answers
to 10 Questions Young People Ask
will help
many more youths benefit
from the Bible’s practical wisdom.
Following this program,
digital formats of the brochure
will become available
on the jw.org website,
the JW Library app,
and on Watchtower ONLINE LIBRARY
as they are produced
in each language.
Additionally, printed copies
of the brochure can be requested
through your congregation
at the conclusion of this program.
Before we finish,
we’d like to share
this postcard from the city
of L’viv, in Ukraine.
The city has approximately
800,000 inhabitants and is surrounded
by beautiful forests.
But L’viv is also the home of 5,000
of our dear brothers and sisters.
One of the 49 congregations
in L’viv
is the Topolna Tsentralnyi Congregation.
This congregation
has 107 publishers,
including 42 regular pioneers.
Last year, during the month of August,
70 percent of them took part
in some form of pioneer service,
despite the fact that this congregation
has [one of] the smallest
territories in the city.
Public witnessing using carts
has proven very effective,
and the publishers also cover
remote territories
in small villages outside the city.
The publishers
of the Topolna Tsentralnyi Congregation
send their warm Christian love
to all of us worldwide.
This is JW Broadcasting
from Brooklyn, New York.