How many times have you read
in our publications
experiences whereby someone is praying
to be guided by God
while at the same time
one of our Kingdom proclaimers
is praying to be directed
to someone with whom they can share
Jehovah’s inspired wisdom?
What happens?
South Africa:
A sister begins
her auxiliary pioneer service
praying for Jehovah
to help her find someone
with whom
she can study the Bible.
The territory
includes the home of a person
who had been very rude
to her in the past.
Courageously,
she knocks on the door anyway
and discovers
that new tenants live there
—a mother and daughter
who had been praying
for someone to help them
understand the Bible.
Soon, all three were out
in service together.
The angels certainly know
how to work these things out.
Is it reasonable, then,
to believe that the angels
could also play a role in ensuring
that baptized Christians
get the information
that they need
either to receive or to give?
As our text indicates,
Jehovah ‘guides us with his advice.’
How does that work?
Well, often we find ourselves
in need of wisdom.
We pray to Jehovah for direction;
we search the Bible;
we search our Christian publications;
and at times, we ask people
who are already wise for their advice.
After all, Insight, Volume 2,
under “wisdom” refers to this as
“a superior and
timesaving way to wisdom.”
Superior, that is,
to experiencing punishment
or watching other people
go through it.
The Insight book
then cites Proverbs 22:17.
Let’s read that together.
Proverbs 22:17,
which says:
“Incline your ear and listen
to the words of the wise,
“in order to apply your heart
to my knowledge.”
Who is the “my”
in the expression “my knowledge”?
Well, Jehovah is speaking to us
through the pages of his Word,
indicating that if we listen
to counsel from wise people,
we can, in fact,
detect the wisdom of Jehovah.
Moreover,
Psalm 32:8 gives us this promise:
“I will give you insight
“and instruct you
in the way you should go.
I will give you advice
with my eye upon you.”
Now, does that mean
that if we pray intensely,
Jehovah will give us
tailor-made counsel
designed to fit
our individual circumstances
—that somehow through either
an encouraging visit
by a mature Christian,
a talk at one of the meetings,
or some information
in one of our publications,
we will find exactly what we need?
Yes,
prayers are often answered
in that exact way.
Now, with regard to elders’ meetings,
our brothers are trained to recognize
that Christ by means of his holy spirit
can influence any elder
(even the youngest,
most reticent elder on the body)
to make an expression
that results
in wise decisions
—decisions that may not have been reached
if each elder
had been consulted individually.
But, now, does that mean
that every expression
made by an elder automatically
reflects the knowledge of God?
We have to remember
that just as one who desires wisdom
has a responsibility to seek it,
so likewise one who gives advice
has a responsibility to base his comments
on Jehovah’s inspired Word.
Sometimes emotion
may get the better of an adviser.
How can we tell whether
that is taking place?
Turn with me, please,
to 1 Samuel chapter 23
—1 Samuel 23.
Now, how many times
did King David receive advice
from the likes of Gad, Nathan,
Abigail, Abishai, others?
How did David respond to it?
Well, first, please note
that David had the admirable habit
of inquiring of Jehovah
before making decisions.
Look at what it says here
in chapter 23,
1 Samuel 23:2:
“So David inquired of Jehovah:
“‘Should I go and strike down
these Philistines?’
“Jehovah said to David:
“‘Go, strike down the Philistines
and rescue Keilah.’
“But the men of David
said to him: ‘Look!
“‘We are afraid while here in Judah;
“‘how much more so if we go to Keilah
“‘against the battle line
of the Philistines!’
“So David inquired
once again of Jehovah.”
And many other texts show
that this was David’s practice.
Of course, there were also
notable occasions
when David
did not first inquire of Jehovah,
such as when he determined
to destroy Nabal
and every male in his household,
as reported in chapter 25.
But David recognized
in the words of Abigail
the knowledge of Jehovah.
Notice what he said
at 1 Samuel 25:32, 33:
“At this David said to Abigail:
“‘Praise Jehovah the God of Israel,
who sent you this day to meet me!
“‘And blessed be your good sense!
“‘May you be blessed
for restraining me
“‘this day from incurring bloodguilt
and from taking revenge
with my own hands.’”
Abigail brought Bible principles
back to David’s mind,
and he could see
that this was from Jehovah.
And yet, there were other times
when David’s advisers
were pointing to what
they considered to be proof
of Jehovah’s divine intervention,
but David did not buy into it.
Notice what it says
at 1 Samuel 24:4:
“David’s men said to him:
“‘This is the day
“‘on which Jehovah is saying to you,
“‘“Look! I am giving
your enemy into your hand,
and you can do to him
whatever seems good to you.”’”
Now, how would David
respond to that?
Would he say: “You’re right.
“Saul tried to kill me three times.
He’s been hunting me for years.
“He’s obviously lost
Jehovah’s holy spirit.
“Isn’t that why
Samuel anointed me?
“And now, look,
here he is by himself,
“vulnerable, in our very cave.
“When does that ever happen?
“Clearly, Jehovah has given me
this opportunity to seize the kingship.”
David did not draw that conclusion.
Why not?
We get a clue
in 1 Samuel chapter 26.
Notice, once again,
the counsel he receives in verse 8.
Was it a coincidence
that David and his men
now find Saul
and his army of 3,000 men
totally incapacitated
by deep sleep?
When does that ever happen?
Clearly, that was a gift from God.
That was what Abishai thought,
and so he said in verse 8:
“Today God has surrendered
your enemy into your hand.
“And now, please,
let me pin him to the ground
“with the spear just once,
and I will not need
to do it twice.”
Now, was that really
counsel from God
or just well-intentioned advice
driven by emotion?
David rejected it.
Why?
Was he thinking
about Bible principles?
about Leviticus 19:18?
‘You must not take revenge.’
Likely, as we read what it says
in verses 10 and 11,
notice what it says:
“As surely
as Jehovah is living,
“Jehovah himself
will strike him down,
“or his day will come
and he will die,
“or he will go down
into battle and perish.
“It is unthinkable
from Jehovah’s standpoint for me
to lift my hand
against the anointed of Jehovah!”
David loved Jehovah’s Word.
He tried to consider each situation
from Jehovah’s standpoint.
He sought to discern the difference
between God’s knowledge
and human reasoning.
Today, we too may face
a difficult situation, a decision.
Someone might even encourage us
to take action
without fully considering God’s will.
We need to pray for Jehovah
to direct our hearts to his knowledge
not only that we may receive it
but even that we might convey it
when appropriate.
Sometimes you may be the one
who needs to give
the word of guidance.
Inquire of Jehovah.
Make sure your counsel
is in harmony with his Word.
If it is and if the recipient
also has a prayerful attitude,
then he too may feel
as in the words
of today’s inspired text writer
—that Jehovah is guiding us
with his advice.