My theme for this month’s broadcast is
“Young Ones
—Build Your Future With Jehovah!”
If you do,
1 Timothy 6:19 assures
that you will
‘safely treasure up for yourself
a fine foundation for the future,’
and you will
“get a firm hold on the real life.”
Obviously, we will be directing
many of our comments
directly to you dear young ones
in Jehovah’s organization.
Yet, if we think about it,
all of us figuratively
are very young ones
compared to eternity
—how long we hope to live.
So, in a sense,
our comments during this broadcast
have application to all of us.
Personally, I am so thankful to Jehovah
that positive peer pressure
was put on me
to enter the pioneer ministry
right out of high school.
What a blessing and a protection
it was to enter
the regular pioneer work
at age 17
and to be able to go to Bethel at 18.
Even though there was considerable
worldly pressure put on me
to pursue university education,
I am so happy that with Jehovah’s help,
I decided to build my future
with Jehovah.
Truly, I have no regrets.
And this is always true of young ones
who serve Jehovah from their hearts
—they have no regrets.
In fact, you will enjoy
these expressions from young ones
who are building
their future with Jehovah.
Before I started pioneering,
I was really nervous that I wouldn’t be able
to get my time in every month.
It was a bit hard when I started pioneering
because I didn’t have a car.
My boss,
he didn’t give me part-time work.
I found it really hard
to balance schoolwork
and pioneering
at the same time.
My biggest struggle was fear of man,
so that really hindered me
because I wasn’t very good
at talking to people.
Having a good routine was a struggle.
My brother and I are
the only ones in the truth.
My family didn’t understand
why we wanted to go preaching.
I didn’t think
that I’d make a good pioneer.
I’ve had Type 1 diabetes
since I was five.
So I was always worried
about whether or not
I could balance that health condition
with pioneering.
The challenges
don’t seem that big now,
but back at that time
they were a really big deal.
But the coolest thing
was how Jehovah helped me.
Prayer to Jehovah
helped me overcome my fears.
My family was
a massive help from Jehovah.
Because my dad was the one
who first encouraged me to pioneer,
when I did start pioneering,
he promised that I would have
the full support of my family.
When I spoke to brothers and sisters
who spent their youth
in the full-time service
that really helped me
because it was really encouraging,
and it really motivated me
to want to make my own memories
and my own experiences
in the full-time service.
So there were
practical things I could do.
I didn’t have a car;
I just walked or I caught the bus.
I had to work out
what my priorities were first.
So I had to find out how many hours
would I have to go witnessing every week.
So then I just sat down
and I looked at every day
and planned out which days
I could go witnessing,
which days I had to go to school,
and also allocated time
so that I could do my homework and study.
Having a schedule
was really good
because I could see it
all out in front of me,
and I could see
that the hour requirement
was actually attainable,
so that made it a lot less daunting.
I first set short-term goals of pioneering
in the special months of activity.
Then I was able
to begin continuous auxiliary,
and then eventually
I started regular pioneering.
One of the best things I did
to prepare myself for pioneering
was to auxiliary pioneer beforehand.
It really set me up
to be able to overcome
any challenges
that I faced while I was pioneering.
I thought about Malachi 3:10.
I knew I trusted in Jehovah,
but this was my chance
to test him out.
I prayed,
put my trust in Jehovah,
and put my application in.
After my form
was in for pioneering,
a brother, with time,
a brother called me and offered me work.
I had unemployment
for three months,
which wasn’t a good time.
But during that time,
I had Jehovah as my main focus.
And so he supported me,
and he didn’t let me down.
Asking brothers and sisters to come
and work with me,
maybe on days that I knew
that I wouldn’t get as much support,
really helped.
That helped me to organize
my hours a little bit more,
and also I’d get to know
my brothers and sisters more as well.
One of the greatest joys of pioneering
has been to pioneer with Mum.
And we had the privilege of going
to the pioneer school together,
which was really special.
Psalm 16:8 reminds me
that Jehovah is right beside me.
When I’m preaching,
it’s like Jehovah is holding my hand.
So with full-time service,
I love making Jehovah happy.
With everything that he has given me,
I’m finally able to give something back.
Looking back
—pioneering—
it was the best decision
I’ve ever made.
It’s opened up
so many different avenues
of service to Jehovah,
and it helped me also
to have that real desire
to want to stay
in full-time service.
Helping someone
on the road to everlasting life,
it’s the best feeling ever;
and it’s really irreplaceable.
The only thing I can say,
“As a young person, start pioneering!”
What a fine attitude
those young ones have!
They are clearly following
in Jesus’ footsteps.
Jesus was the wisest man
who ever walked the earth.
He could’ve pursued any career
and truly excelled at it.
He could’ve been
the greatest carpenter who ever lived.
Think about it,
he helped his Father
build the physical universe.
Can you imagine
what kind of houses he could’ve built?
Or what if he had pursued
being an inventor?
With his perfect brain,
he probably could’ve invented
the telephone,
automobile, or computer
in the first century.
Or what about becoming
a businessman?
With perfect intelligence,
he likely could’ve come out on top
of every business transaction
that he entered,
becoming the richest businessman
who ever lived.
Or have you ever thought about
if he had pursued becoming
an athlete?
And excelling in athletic contests
was a huge endeavor in Jesus’ day.
With a little training,
it is likely that his perfect body
would have outperformed all people
with imperfect bodies,
enabling him to become
the most famous athlete who ever lived.
Or one more example,
what if he had decided to become a doctor?
He could cure sick people
—even raise the dead.
Can you imagine how much
he could’ve charged rich people
to raise their dead loved ones?
But Jesus pursued none of these careers.
Why?
Because he knew
that any of such endeavors
would have only very limited
and temporary benefits.
Instead, he pursued something
he knew would bring far-reaching
and everlasting benefits:
the full-time ministry.
If this is how the wisest man
who ever walked the earth—
If this is how he reasoned,
we are wise if we strive to think
the same way.
That makes me think of the comments
of a well-adjusted teenage brother
whom we served
while in the circuit work many years ago.
This young brother went straight into
the regular pioneer work
out of high school,
and I asked him why he did so.
He explained that he knew
he could’ve gotten a full-time secular job
and bought a new car for himself,
but he reasoned that in a few years
that car would rust out and break down,
and he would have nothing.
But he knew that he could go
into the pioneer work
and build a close relationship with Jehovah
and perhaps even find
an honest-hearted person
and be able to teach that one the truth.
And he knew that would last forever.
Now, that is some wise thinking
on the part of that young brother.
And today, that brother
has a beautiful Christian wife
and several spiritual children,
and he is serving as a fine elder.
But if you young ones
are going to think this way
and continue to pursue spiritual goals,
it is vital that you wisely choose
your associates.
In a sense, our associates
can be likened to an elevator.
What do we mean?
Well, they can take you up
or they can take you down.
If you choose wisely,
they will take you up
—elevate your good qualities
and make you a better person.
But if you choose poorly,
they will take you down.
Depending on how badly you choose,
they can take you way down
—to the basement,
even the subbasement.
At Proverbs 13:20,
our loving heavenly Father,
who made us,
explains how it works.
Jehovah tells us there:
“The one walking with the wise
“will become wise,
“but the one
who has dealings with the stupid
will fare badly.”
“Walking with”
and “having dealings with”
mean “associating with.”
And who are the “stupid” ones?
Well, this scripture contrasts
such a person
with those who are wise.
It is not talking about someone
who lacks mental intellect.
It is talking about someone
who does not make
wise decisions spiritually
from Jehovah’s standpoint.
And if we think about it,
anyone who is not really serving Jehovah
—at least right now—
that one is unwise indeed.
And if we associate closely with such ones,
Jehovah says that we “will fare badly.”
We could use another illustration.
Think about someone who is physically sick
and is running a high fever.
If we spend a lot of time with that person,
we will probably catch the same sickness.
Or worse,
if we spend a lot of time
near a dead body—a corpse—
we will probably pick up a disease.
Well, it is similar
with spending time with a person
who is spiritually sick,
or worse, spiritually dead.
On the other hand,
if we choose as our associates
those who love Jehovah
and who are building
their everlasting future with Jehovah,
we will benefit greatly.
Please observe carefully
this variety of young ones
who are busy storing up
treasures in heaven
with Jehovah.
How heartwarming it is to us
—and we know it is to Jehovah—
to see these beautiful young people
doing what Jesus encourages
at Matthew 6:20, 21.
There, Jesus encourages:
“Store up for yourselves
treasures in heaven,
“where neither moth nor rust consumes,
“and where thieves do not break in and steal.
“For where your treasure is,
there your heart will be also.”
And if we think about it,
in the final analysis,
after all is said and done,
whether we are younger or older,
our net worth will be
what we have stored up
in heaven with Jehovah.
We will not be able to take
material treasures with us
through the great tribulation.
And if we die,
we certainly will not be able to take
material treasures with us,
but we can take spiritual treasures
with us through the great tribulation
and even through death and resurrection.
It is true with all of Jehovah’s people,
as it is with the anointed,
what is stated at Revelation 14:13.
It says there:
“The things they did go right with them.”
And how encouraging it is
to see young ones getting baptized
—publicly demonstrating
that they are giving their lives to Jehovah.
And we sincerely hope
that you young ones
who are not yet baptized
will not hold back from getting baptized
as soon as you qualify.
The sooner you can get baptized,
the sooner you will receive
greater protection
and blessings from Jehovah.
Not long ago,
it made me very happy
to observe a little ten-year-old brother
get baptized!
And young ones,
never be afraid to identify yourselves
as one of Jehovah’s Witnesses.
Never allow the fear
of what others may think
to cause you to hesitate to do so.
Jehovah tells us
at Proverbs 29:25:
“Trembling at men is a snare,
“but the one trusting in Jehovah
will be protected.”
Many years ago when I was in school,
I can remember being
at times somewhat worried
about how my fellow classmates
would view me.
But then a little while later,
I got out of school
and never ever again even saw
most of those former classmates.
Then it dawned on me
that it doesn’t really matter
what people think about us.
It is Jehovah’s rating of us
that truly counts.
Humans cannot add
even five seconds to our lifespan,
but Jehovah can add
or subtract eternity.
And he alone
can also give us true happiness.
And as Proverbs 29:25 indicates,
what a protection
it is to courageously identify ourselves
as one of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
fully trusting Jehovah
and taking our stand solidly with him.
Never be ashamed of who you are.
You are one of Jehovah’s Witnesses.
And please, dear young ones,
we warmly encourage you
to listen to those who love you.
Jehovah loves you very much;
the Governing Body loves you very much;
the elders love you very much;
your Christian parents love you very much.
And these ones will tell you the truth,
even though at times
it may not be what you want to hear.
They will not ‘tickle your ears,’
perhaps like ones at school
or in the neighborhood
who don’t really love you
or have your best interests at heart.
But please believe those
who will tell you the truth
because they love you.
And never view
Jehovah’s laws and principles
as depriving you of something good.
View them as protecting you
from what will hurt you.
If you recall,
Satan convinced Eve
that she was being deprived by Jehovah
and was missing out on something good.
Now, it is true that Eve
was missing out on something.
But what was she really missing out on?
A tormented conscience,
her beautiful hair turning gray,
her teeth falling out,
her perfect skin wrinkling up like a prune,
being bent over from old age,
hobbling around on a cane,
and finally dying!
But Satan convinced her
that Jehovah was depriving her,
so foolishly she reached out to get
what she thought she was missing out on.
Well, Satan will try to use
the same kind of strategy on you,
but please don’t let him do it!
This also makes me think
of an experience a brother once related.
He said that he was visiting
an animal observatory,
and a large lion lunged toward him
but was prevented from reaching him
by a thick glass pane
separating the animals from the observers.
As the lion stood on his hind legs,
clawing the glass
and baring his massive teeth,
the brother came to realize in a special way
the protective value of that barrier.
Previously, he said
that he somewhat viewed the glass pane
as a restriction
because the smudges on it
partially blurred his view,
but now he viewed it
as a real protection.
Well, in a similar way,
Jehovah doesn’t want Satan,
who is described
as ‘a roaring, devouring lion’
at 1 Peter 5:8—
He doesn’t want him
to gobble down you young ones.
And His laws and principles
are designed to keep that
from happening to you.
So please listen to Jehovah.
He loves you!