Our text is focusing
on the powerful effect
that prayer can have on us
when it is true prayer,
genuine prayer.
Mere communication with God
is not necessarily prayer.
In Genesis
chapters 3 and 4,
after Adam had sinned,
he had dialogue with Jehovah,
but it could hardly
be viewed as prayer.
Why?
Because prayer involves trust,
respect, humility, devotion,
and a sense of dependence
on the one to whom
the prayer is directed.
Now, just to highlight
the importance of trust
and prayer’s effectiveness,
let’s open our Bibles
to Psalm 91,
and we’ll see the important quality
of trust highlighted.
Psalm 91,
we’ll read verses 1 and 2.
“Anyone dwelling in the secret place
of the Most High
will lodge under the shadow
of the Almighty.”
Well, we notice “the secret place,”
a place of spiritual security
where no one or no thing
can rob us of our faith in Jehovah
or our love for Jehovah.
And it’s secret because unbelievers
can’t understand it.
But now,
how do we get there?
Verse 2:
“I will say to Jehovah:
‘You are my refuge
and my stronghold,
my God in whom I trust.’”
So the key of getting
into the secret place,
the key to getting
the peace of God,
is this humility
and trust in Jehovah.
And we notice
the expression here:
“You are my refuge
and my stronghold.”
In this context, not ours
—while it’s true—
but it has to be personal.
And that’s the trust
that we have on an individual basis.
And how grateful we are
that we have Jehovah’s listening ear,
and he hears us
because of something
that David said.
We go to Psalm 69 this time,
and as we turn here,
we’d like to ask you to think,
“Have you ever felt,
to a reasonable degree,
the same way that David
expresses himself here?”
He’s going through
a very stressful time, overwhelmed,
and in verse 20 of Psalm 69,
he says:
“Reproach has broken my heart,
“and the wound is incurable.
“I was hoping for sympathy,
but there was none,
and for comforters,
but I found none.”
So at times,
our fellow believers
—our family members even,
close friends—
they may not be able to help us
the way we need to be helped.
And why is that?
Well, for one thing, they may be
very busy dealing with their own problems,
and they don’t have
the time to really notice.
Or the other factor is
that we all have things that differ
when it comes to causing us stress.
What is a real stress for one person
is not so hard for another.
And if they look on
and see someone
going through something
that they find easy,
perhaps the sympathy will be lacking.
But, nonetheless,
verse 33 of this same Psalm says:
“For Jehovah
is listening to the poor,
and he will not despise
his captive people.”
Now, in principle,
sometimes we may feel captive
to our circumstances
or to the feelings
that we’re experiencing,
to our emotions,
to what we are going through
—we feel trapped.
Other people may not understand
or may not be able to help us.
But notice the reassurance
in 2 Chronicles 6:29, 30.
This is the prayer of Solomon
at the time
of the dedication of the temple.
And in 2 Chronicles 6:29
he says:
“Whatever request for favor
“may be made by any man
“or by all your people Israel
“(for each one knows
“his own plague and his own pain)
when they spread out
their hands toward this house,”
so we’re unique.
Other people may not be able to do it.
Why?
Verse 30:
“Then may you hear
from the heavens,
“your dwelling place,
and may you forgive;
“and reward each one
according to all his ways,
“for you know his heart
“(you alone truly know
the human heart).”
So even if our friends care,
even if they want to be helpful,
they cannot possibly see
the depth of what we’re feeling
or what we’re thinking
or how it’s affecting us,
but Jehovah does.
He sees right
to the heart of the matter,
and how reassuring that is.
So we trust him
because he really knows us.
But there’s something else
involved in this trust.
Matthew 6:33 says:
“Keep on, then, seeking first
the Kingdom and his righteousness,
and all these other things
will be added to you.”
Now, there’s personal trust
—trust that Jehovah
knows what I need
and that he’s going to,
as he always has, provide it.
But there can be a pitfall.
If a person
is naturally calm, confident,
perhaps has a natural ability,
family history that’s rich
—both emotionally,
maybe even financially—
all of these things
can make a person begin to feel,
‘Yes, I trust in Jehovah,
but I can do this myself.’
You know, sometimes
we may hear this expression
when we hear of someone
that’s being transitioned
from one form of special service,
perhaps into
the regular pioneer work
or they have to leave Bethel
for good reasons,
and they have to go back
and get some secular work.
Have you ever heard this?
“They’re going to do fine
because they have marketable skills.”
Now,
that’s a good thing.
Perhaps those marketable skills
have been developed
in pursuing Kingdom interests,
and that’s fine.
But we have to be careful.
Will they be fine
because of their skills
or because of their continuing
to seek first the Kingdom
and they let Jehovah
be the one that provides for them?
And we’ll have to be careful too
when we use that expression
“They’ll have no problem;
they have marketable skills.”
What if someone doesn’t?
Well, Jehovah
takes care of them too.
Amos 7:14, 15,
Amos said:
‘I wasn’t a prophet
or the son of a prophet.
I was a nipper of figs,
a very lowly herdsman, shepherd.’
But Jehovah took him,
used him, and provided for him.
So marketable skills
were not the key factor.
And so we keep that
in its proper perspective.
And finally,
in imitation of Jehovah,
when we try to help people,
we want to use the most powerful tool
we have to encourage them
and to help them deal
with their anxiety.
There was an experience
in the February 15, 1988, Watchtower
about Brother Arthur Winkler.
Now,
the Gestapo found him,
and they beat him
without mercy,
knocked out his teeth,
dislocated his jaw.
His whole body
was raw from the beating,
and they threw him in a dark cell.
At that moment,
Brother Winkler said,
“I was in desperate need
of spiritual food,
and I prayed to Jehovah.”
And then he talked to the guard
and asked him to help him.
The cell door opened
and a Bible was thrown in,
and he said:
“That daily enjoyment
of those pleasant words of truth
“were precious.
I felt myself
getting stronger spiritually.”
So, then,
when we go to help people,
the best thing we can do
in helping them cope is,
not with some
often-used phrase
or something that is
repeatable all the time,
but make sure it is the Bible.
They may feel captive,
imprisoned by their situation.
But an account from the Bible
—an account of a Bible character
that had gone through tough times
and came through—
those are the most meaningful things
to deal with it.
Perhaps
2 Corinthians 11:23-31,
where Paul reviewed
all of those things that he went through,
and yet years later,
he wrote our day’s text for today,
saying Jehovah helped him
stay calm and assisted him.
So may these reminders
from the Scriptures
help us to cope and help others
to cope with anxieties.