We welcome all of you
to the December program
of JW Broadcasting!
This month
we have something different
to share with you.
The Governing Body has decided
that Gilead graduations
and the spiritual portion
of the annual meeting programs
will be featured as monthly
JW Broadcasting programs each year.
At this time, you will be able
to watch the first part
of the graduation
of the 143rd class of Gilead.
You will enjoy listening
to the five Scriptural talks
that will each be introduced to you
by Brother Herd of the Governing Body.
Most languages
that our monthly program is produced in
did not have
the resources to also translate
and produce
the Gilead graduation.
Now, by using the graduation
as the monthly program,
many more of our brothers and sisters
around the world
will be able to enjoy
this rich spiritual banquet.
We now invite you to enjoy
Part One of the graduation
of the 143rd class of Gilead!
It’s graduation day
for this 143rd class of Gilead.
And it’s been a long time coming
with a lot of work, worry, sweat,
and nerve-racking parts given
in front of your instructors
and fellow classmates.
Wow! Ooh.
But none of you received
a failing grade
—not one.
You’re going to graduate today.
This is your day.
And it’s a joyful day, isn’t it?
A very joyful day for you,
and a joyful day
for each and every one of us.
We’re glad you came to Gilead school,
and it saddens us a bit
to know you are leaving us.
You’re not going to be here much longer.
Your fine spiritual instructors
—Brothers Cauthon, Lippold,
Noumair, Samuelson, and Stovall
—they would like to cry,
but they’re good manly men,
and it’s hard for good manly men
to cry in public.
Of course, there is a host of others
—too many to name—
such as Sam Herd.
Oops, it just slipped out
beyond my control.
Your instructors have done
a fine job of helping you
to open your eyes
to see your “Grand Instructor”
mentioned at Isaiah 30:20.
After all, he is the one
who has been teaching
by giving his holy spirit
to all these brothers that I’ve mentioned.
Look at what is stated at Isaiah 66:1
—66:1—it says:
“This is what Jehovah says:
‘The heavens are my throne,
and the earth is my footstool.’”
For the last five months,
you’ve been sitting at Jehovah’s feet
and you have been taught
by your Grand Instructor.
What you have learned
is much more than you knew
when you first sat down five months ago.
Without a doubt,
the knowledge you have taken in
has brought you closer to Jehovah.
You have really drawn close to Jehovah,
and he has drawn close to you.
However, you’ve only scratched the surface.
Job said: . . .
[Indiscernible whispering]
Did you hear what I said?
Of course you didn’t.
Now let’s read the scripture,
Job 26:14:
“Look!
These are just the fringes of his ways;
only a faint whisper has been heard of him!”
This is just about as much as we have learned
compared to what Jehovah knows.
Who knows all that Jehovah knows?
No one
—not even Jesus,
and he knows quite a bit more than we do.
He’s been around longer, hasn’t he?
Much longer.
In fact, Jesus was present
when the earth was created.
When was that?
Well, if you’ve been listening
to morning worship,
you’ll know that one member
of the Governing Body
told us that in Proverbs chapter 8
—he says take a look at that—
verses 29 and 30, and he read it to us,
he said: “This is what it says.”
“When he established
the foundations of the earth,
then I was beside him
as a master worker.”
Do you remember that?
You don’t if you didn’t hear
today’s text or read it.
But we are convinced
that you heard it and you read it.
Well, that’s a long time, isn’t it?
The earth
—foundations of the earth—
how long?
Well, based on the very old zircon rock
from Australia,
some scientists say we know that the earth
is at least four
and one-half billion years old,
give or take a hundred million years.
Well, no one really knows down here on earth,
but we have to listen
to some of these so-called wise men.
Jesus, in his prehuman existence, was there.
There’s no doubt about that.
Colossians chapter 1 shows that,
that he was there.
He was at Jehovah’s side way before then
—listening and learning.
And he’s at Jehovah’s side today, isn’t he?
You know that.
He’s right there seated beside Jehovah,
doing the work that Jehovah
has outlined that should be done.
When measured by Jesus,
we’re newborn infants.
We barely have our eyes open, barely.
What we see is not what we’re going to see
in the years to come.
We’re just looking; we’re just learning;
we’re touching things
—and for the first time.
Just think, in the past ten years
how many things
we’ve touched for the first time.
Even though we’ve read the Bible
over and over again,
and we’ve listened to it
being read to us over and over again,
but we’ve just touched a few things
—like the generation,
20 years ago, the generation.
And now we know
all about that generation, right?
And so many other things
—dragnet—
many other things,
like the sanctification of God’s name,
vindication of his sovereignty
—touch, touch, touch.
You Gilead students,
you’ve touched a few things,
but not everything,
not everything.
But what you have learned,
put to good use in your assignments.
Keep in mind that you don’t know it all.
And here’s something else: You never will.
No matter how long we live,
we’ll never know it all.
Jehovah will still be revealing things to us,
and they’re always good things.
We benefit from what Jehovah gives us.
He knows exactly what we need,
and he gives it to us.
So always keep that in mind.
We’re students under Jehovah,
and that’s where we’ll always be.
But we’re happy.
We’re glad to be here.
We’re glad to be here with you students,
every one of you,
and you’re good students too.
Now it’s true, not all of you
are A-plus students.
I’m not either.
I was happy to get a good C-plus in school.
Well, we’re going to get started now
with a major part of our meeting.
“Being Happy Despite Challenges”
is the theme of Brother Gerrit Lösch’s talk.
Brother Lösch is a member
of the Governing Body.
He is the senior member
Now, I mean by that,
he’s been a member of the Governing Body
longer than the rest of us.
I’m the oldest one on the Governing Body.
We all face challenges of some sort.
So let’s listen carefully
to what he has to say, Brother Lösch.
“Oh happy day.”
These are the first words of the gospel song.
And it goes on to say,
“Oh happy day,
when Jesus washed my sins away.”
And we can agree
with these music lyrics
from the 18th century.
We agree that forgiveness of sins
makes us happy, doesn’t it?
But for many others,
the happy day is the payday
at the end of the month.
Now, what is a happy day for you students?
Graduation day.
But you are not happy because it’s over,
but because you had
the privilege to attend Gilead.
Many in the world believe
that if they had more money,
they would be happier.
However, many who made gaining of wealth
the chief goal in life
now suffer disappointment.
Some have lost their house,
being unable to pay the mortgage
when they were laid off from work.
Wealth does not bring happiness.
Rather, lasting happiness
comes from doing Jehovah’s will.
What is happiness?
Happiness is a state of well-being,
contentment, even deep and intense joy.
But in the world, many are unhappy.
In 2015, there were more than
twice as many suicides
in the United States
—namely 44,193—
more than homicides,
where there were only 17,000 of those.
Up to 120 people take their life
in the United States each day.
How sad.
Though very rare, due to depression
even some true Christians
have taken their life,
but generally we are a happy people,
aren’t we?
And here are 12 reasons for our happiness.
For one, we can be happy
because we worship a happy God.
Psalm 33:12:
“Happy is the nation whose God is Jehovah.”
Secondly, because we have our sins forgiven,
as mentioned in the introduction.
Romans 4:7 says:
“Happy are those whose lawless deeds
have been pardoned
and whose sins have been covered.”
Number three, we can be happy
because we’re being loved
by Jehovah and Jesus.
Four, we’re happy because of being united
with our worldwide brotherhood.
Five, we can be happy
because of living in a spiritual paradise,
having peace with Jehovah,
with our brothers,
and also having plenty of spiritual food.
Six, in the Sermon on the Mount,
Jesus emphasized spirituality when he said:
“Happy are those conscious
of their spiritual need.”
In this sermon, he mentioned nine things
that make us happy.
What things?
Well, you’ll find out
by rereading this sermon.
Number seven, we are happy
because our life has meaning,
namely, according to Ephesians 1:12,
to “serve for the praise of his glory.”
Number eight, at Revelation 1:3,
Jesus showed that
reading God’s Word makes us happy.
He says:
“Happy is [he] who reads aloud
and those who hear
the words of this prophecy.”
Do you want to be happy every day?
Read the Bible every day.
In the book of Revelation,
Jesus proclaims seven happinesses.
Which ones?
Find out by rereading Revelation.
Number nine, we are also happy
because we serve in the spiritual temple.
In Revelation 7,
not just the anointed
but also the great crowd
are shown serving,
not near or before,
but in the temple.
David called the Levites happy.
He said at Psalm 65:4:
“Happy is the one whom you choose
[to] bring near to reside
in your courtyards.”
David arranged the Levites
so that they could serve at the temple
twice a year for one week.
However, in contrast,
all of God’s people serve him
in the spiritual temple all year long,
every day.
How happy we can be.
Number ten, Psalm 40:4 says:
“Happy is the man who trusts in Jehovah.”
Trust is a must to maintain happiness.
When you arrive in your assignment,
trust that Jehovah will support you.
Trust in Jehovah’s strength
rather than in your Gilead training
and your abilities.
If low on funds, trust in Jehovah.
He will care for you.
If you have to learn a new language, trust.
When you are being accused wrongly,
trust that matters will be clarified in time.
When you are discouraged,
trust in better times.
There is light at the end of each tunnel.
Number 11, we are happy
because we practice giving,
and Jesus said:
“There is more happiness in giving
than there is in receiving.”
Words well-known
—Acts 20:35.
And 12, we are happy
because of the wonderful promise
of a heavenly paradise for some
and an earthly paradise for billions.
We are happy because this is tied
to the promise of everlasting life.
How does happiness show?
It shows by a spirit of appreciation
and expressions of appreciation.
So beware of a complaining spirit.
When Jehovah liberated Israel,
the people were happy.
However, within just a few weeks,
they complained and even wanted
to return to slavery in Egypt.
To stay happy, have a positive outlook.
Don’t complain
about the thorns on rosebushes,
but be glad
that some thornbushes have roses on it.
Number two, when you go to your assignment,
radiate the happiness you feel.
Let others see it in your eyes,
in your face, in your smile;
but smile, not like a salesperson,
but smile from the heart.
Happiness is also shown by enjoying singing.
Happy people often sing.
Do we sing from time to time?
singing in the rain?
or maybe in the shower?
or wherever?
How can we deepen our happiness?
What others do affects our happiness,
and what we do
affects the happiness of others.
We simply cannot escape
the fact that our happiness
is intertwined with the lives
of many other people
—our families, our friends, and others.
Happiness is often in small things,
and unhappiness is the result
of neglecting small things.
Happiness is not the absence of challenges,
but the ability to overcome them.
Happiness does not depend
on outside circumstances,
but on your inner thoughts
and your relationship with our happy God.
Happiness is connected with joy,
and joy is part
of the fruitage of the spirit.
So avail yourself of the holy spirit,
and you will be happier.
You can be happy though hungry.
That was the title of a special talk.
Of course, you can be happy
if you’re not hungry.
Perhaps you take advantage
of the “happy hour”
in a restaurant where prices are reduced.
You can be happy though single.
You can be happy because of being married
and sometimes despite being married.
You can be happy without children,
and you can be happy despite children.
You can be happy though
you’re only 15 years old,
and you can be happy
although you’re 85 years of age.
You can be happy though you are sick
and even more happy,
of course, if you’re healthy.
You can even be happy
though you lost loved ones in death.
You will see them again.
You can be happy
though persecuted for Christ’s sake.
Jesus said at Luke 6:22, 23:
“Happy are you whenever men hate you . . .
Rejoice in that day and leap for joy.”
You can be happy if you lost your job.
You can be happy if you lost your wallet.
You can be happy if you lost your heart
in San Francisco
—according to one song—
or somewhere else.
You cannot be happy if you lost your mind,
or maybe you can be even happier then
because of not being aware
of all the problems
around you and affecting you.
If you are happy, you make others happy.
If you are unhappy, you make others unhappy.
If you are not happy with others,
others will not be happy with you.
Humor adds to happiness.
It makes pain and problems more bearable.
Find happiness in small things
—the sunset, the clouds in the sky,
the birds chirping,
the butterfly on the flower,
the dog chasing its tail.
Maintain happiness by meditating
on the Paradise to come.
Keep it in expectation.
Daniel 12:12 says:
“Happy is the one who keeps in expectation.”
In Paradise, there will be no more tears,
no emotional pain, no unhappiness.
Everyone will be happy every day,
all the time.
So let us maintain and deepen
our happiness despite challenges
by praising our happy God, Jehovah,
and making others and ourselves
ever more happy.
We certainly want to thank you,
Brother Lösch.
You made all of us happy
with that wonderful talk.
Our next speaker is Brother Gary Breaux,
a helper to the Service Committee
of the Governing Body
and a Branch Committee member.
His theme is
“Continue to Give Jehovah
Reasons Not to Forget.”
Well, we usually don’t think of Jehovah
as forgetting.
After all, he’s all-knowing,
and surely he doesn’t forget anything.
But you know, when it comes to humans,
it is possible to forget.
You remember the account in Deuteronomy.
Moses in this case
was giving caution to the Israelites
about life once they entered
into the Promised Land.
And we have Deuteronomy 6:12,
he says:
“Be careful not to forget Jehovah,
who brought you out of the land of Egypt,
[and] out of the house of slavery.”
So it’s possible for servants of God
to forget Jehovah.
But you know,
that street goes both ways, so to speak.
The apostle Paul introduces the idea
that Jehovah God can forget too.
It’s at Hebrews 6:10.
Hebrews 6:10,
notice Jehovah’s ability to forget here,
it says: “For God is not unrighteous
so as to forget your work
“and the love you showed for his name
by ministering and continuing to minister
to the holy ones.”
So he says there are two things
that Jehovah God says
that he will never forget.
What are they?
Well, it’s work and love.
Now, remember the theme
of this talk that I chose.
It’s not “Give Jehovah Reasons Not to Forget”
because that would imply
that you haven’t been doing that,
and that’s not the case.
But the theme is
“Continue to Give Jehovah
Reasons Not to Forget.”
And so it will be good for us
to look a little deeper
into these simple words of Paul
because it’s going to help us
not to forget about Jehovah.
And hopefully, he will not forget about us.
So we’re going to talk first about work,
and then we’ll come back and talk about love.
Now, it is interesting that Paul did not say
that God would not forget your assignment.
Jehovah says:
‘Oh, you’re a Branch Committee member.
‘Oh, I’ll never forget that.
‘Or you’re a pioneer;
you’re a special pioneer;
‘you’re an elder.
‘Or you’re at a service desk
in a service department.
I’ll never forget that.’
That’s not what Paul said in this verse.
What did he say?
He said it’s the work
that He will never forget.
Now, it’s true,
we need Branch Committee members,
we need elders,
we need pioneers, and so forth.
But what Jehovah is not going to forget
is the work that we do
and the various assignments
and the various ways
that we serve Jehovah God,
giving him whole-souled service.
I’d like to tell you about a brother
that really understands
this part of Hebrews 6:10 well.
A few years ago, we had five members
on an Assembly Hall Committee
and we were directed
to bring it down to three,
so we had to remove two members
of every committee.
And the Branch Committee decided
who was going to be removed
from the committee.
So the oldest brother
—one of the oldest brothers serving
and age wise—
it was decided
that he would come off the committee.
So we had to send someone to tell him.
We were not going to write a letter to him.
So guess what?
I was chosen to go tell him.
So I was sitting at the table
—conference table—
with the Assembly Hall Committee,
and I was nervous,
and I was using the Scriptures,
trying to get to their heart.
Finally, it got to the point
that I had to say,
“Now, you two brothers
are being relieved of your assignment.”
Immediately,
the elderly brother raised his hand and said,
“Can I read you a scripture?”
And I said, “Yeah, please do.”
And he read Hebrews 6:10.
And he said:
“Brothers, I’m here not for a title;
“I’m here to work.
Just give me work to do.”
It affects me every time
I tell that story because, really,
his comment captures what Paul is saying:
‘Jehovah will not forget your work.’
Well, let’s go back to Hebrews 6:10
because it talks about the second thing.
It says:
‘He is not going to forget the love.’
Well, what kind of love is he talking about?
‘Oh Jehovah, we love you.’
Jehovah looks down: ‘Thank you very much.
I’ll never forget you love me.’
Well, that’s true,
but that’s not what Paul is saying.
Let’s read it again.
Verse 10, after he says
He won’t forget the work, he says:
“And the love you showed for his name
by ministering and continuing to minister
to the holy ones.”
So there are a couple of words here
that are important to understand.
It’s “you showed” and “ministering.”
In other words,
‘Your love for your brother,’
Jehovah says,
‘ah, look at that, I’ll never forget it.’
You see, it’s not an intellectual love.
Now, you’ve been in class for what,
five months?
I would imagine you’ve read every scripture;
you’ve heard all kinds of examples
about showing love;
you have every reason to show love.
And now we encourage you: Go out and do it.
Practice what you have learned.
Remember if it’s only words,
what did Paul say?
It’s like a cymbal
—clashing cymbal.
So love means action;
it doesn’t just mean words.
I’d like to tell you another little story
about a brother that had
somewhat of a difficulty with this.
When I was a young circuit overseer,
the district overseer I had was—
I was afraid of him.
Everybody else was scared of him too.
At one circuit assembly,
his wife wasn’t there,
so he didn’t tell anybody
why she wasn’t there,
and we’d never ask.
And so anyway,
the closing talk on Sunday,
I decided,
without getting his permission,
to let everyone know what was going on.
And I said: “Now you notice
that his wife isn’t with him.
“I just wanted you to know that tomorrow
she’s going to have a major operation,
and so we should all keep them
in our prayers, OK?”
Then they introduced him.
He didn’t come out.
He was back behind the stage
and for a long time.
I didn’t know what to do, frankly.
Soon, this man comes out
very, very slowly,
and he gets to the microphone;
his voice is cracking.
He starts talking a little bit,
and he gives his whole talk
in this very low tone.
At the end of the program, you know,
we always have this heartwarming song.
Then he had to pray.
He couldn’t pray.
He started crying.
Finally, after a long time,
he said a word or two,
“In Jesus’ name, Amen.”
You know what happened next?
The circuit surrounded him.
They were hugging him.
Everybody was crying.
He told me later, he said:
“Gary, I love the brothers.
I just don’t know how to show it.”
Now if you relate to that experience,
learn how to show love.
You know, what can you do?
You know, it might be a need
to change your face.
Well, not your face, but have a softer face.
Maybe you need to soften your voice.
Maybe you need to develop
a more inviting personality.
Do things for people;
take care of the old brothers and sisters
in the congregations you’re going to be with.
Even if it’s not natural for you
and you feel awkward about it,
do it anyway because in time
it will become part of you.
Because when you walk in that front door
of your Kingdom Hall
or the front door of your branch,
the brothers should be drawn to you,
not because of your assignment,
but because you have worked hard
to show love.
So as you go to your assignments,
always remember that Jehovah knows
the work you have done
and the love you have shown,
and he will never forget it.
Thank you very much, Brother Breaux,
and we’ll keep those reasons in mind
if we don’t forget.
“Who am I, O Jehovah God?”
Do you know who asked that question?
I don’t.
So let’s give our attention
to Brother Patrick LaFranca,
a helper to the Personnel Committee
of the Governing Body
and a member of the Branch Committee.
He will give us the answer.
Gilead students,
have you ever asked yourself,
‘Who am I to have been invited
to Gilead school?’
That’s a good question, isn’t it?
Because very few of God’s people,
relatively speaking, have had that privilege.
So why you?
Was it because you were
smarter or better looking
than the average servant of Jehovah?
No, it was
because of your spiritual qualities.
And foremost among those was humility.
You have been humble.
But maintaining humility
is a definite spiritual challenge
—not just for you but for all of us, really.
We’ve all inherited the tendency
to exalt ourselves.
You think of Adam and Eve.
In the act of profound arrogance,
they wanted to put themselves in God’s place.
They seemed to forget who they were
—creatures made of dust.
So we all have to fight
against prideful tendencies.
Humility is elusive.
As soon as we think we are humble,
we’ve lost it.
However, Jehovah gives us help.
In the Bible, there are many examples
of those who did maintain humility,
and one of these is David.
Let’s just follow David’s life a bit
—different stages of his life—
and see, did he maintain humility?
Well, was he humble as a young man?
You remember how Jehovah
directed the prophet Samuel
to go to Jesse’s house
and annoint one of Jesse’s sons
as the future king of Israel.
Well, seven of his sons were there,
but not one of them was chosen.
And finally, Samuel said,
‘Are these all your sons?’
‘No, there’s David out in the fields
shepherding the sheep.’
So they called David,
and Samuel anoints this young man
to be the future king of Israel.
David must have been surprised
at this singular privilege that he had.
Now, did he become high-minded?
How would he have treated his brothers
—his older brothers—
had he become prideful?
Well, he could have said to Eliab:
‘Well, I guess you got taken down
a peg or two, didn’t you?
‘You better start respecting me.
‘And Abinadab,
‘isn’t it time for you to go out now
and shepherd the sheep?
‘I have a more important assignment.
‘I have to learn to be king.
Hmm, how can I get into the king’s court?’
No, nothing indicates
that David felt that way about himself.
He was content to wait on Jehovah
for future privileges.
Is there a lesson here for us?
Yes, you may get future privileges,
but you may have to wait for them.
Go back to your pastures;
shepherd the sheep.
So after some time,
David is still in the pastures,
and what happens?
An attendant of King Saul
recommends that David serve
in the king’s court.
Listen to this recommendation
at 1 Samuel 16:18:
“One of the attendants said:
“‘Look! I have seen
how a son of Jesse the Bethlehemite
“‘plays skillfully,
“‘and he is a courageous, mighty warrior.
“‘He can speak well, and he is handsome,
and Jehovah is with him.’”
My, what an impressive recommendation!
So, humble David goes from the sheepfold
to the king’s court as a court musician.
But more privileges followed.
You’ll see in verse 21b
that he became Saul’s armor bearer.
And later, David had many exploits in war.
He became famous.
Women sang about his victories.
So fame, good looks,
youth, eloquence,
musical skills,
military prowess, divine favor
—David had it all, didn’t he?
And any one of those things
could have made him arrogant and prideful,
but it seems that they did not.
Note David’s reaction when King Saul
offered David his daughter in marriage.
That is at 1 Samuel 18:18:
“At this David said to Saul:
“‘Who am I and who are my relatives,
“‘my father’s family in Israel,
for me to become son-in-law to the king?’”
Yes, being related to the king
might have given David reason to boast,
but his words “who am I” resonate with us.
David felt unworthy
of being related to the king.
Is there any lesson, perhaps, in this for us?
Well, we may work with and come into contact
with prominent brothers
in God’s organization.
In conversations with others,
do we drop their names,
trying to make ourselves,
perhaps, seem more important?
But now we come
to another period in David’s life.
He is now the king of Israel
with his capital in Jerusalem,
and he’s dwelling in a royal palace.
And he’s being—
He’s feeling very embarrassed
because here he is in a royal palace
and the ark of Jehovah,
who is the real king of Israel,
is in a tent.
And so he says to the prophet Nathan,
‘I want to build Jehovah a worthy house
—a temple.’
But Jehovah says,
‘No, not you,
but one of your sons will do that.’
However, then Jehovah did something
that took David completely by surprise.
God tells him,
‘Instead of you building me a house,
I am going to build a house for you.’
And he makes a covenant with David
so that the kingship would remain
in the family line of David forever.
Well, how did David react?
Please open to 1 Chronicles 17:16-18:
“At that King David came in
and sat down before Jehovah and said:
“‘Who am I, O Jehovah God?
“‘And what is my house
that you have brought me this far?
“‘As if this were not enough, O God,
“‘you also speak
about the house of your servant
“‘down to a distant future time,
“‘and you have looked on me
as if I were a man
“‘who should be further exalted,
O Jehovah God.
“‘What more can your servant David say to you
“‘about the honor given me
when you know your servant so well?’”
So this marvelous promise
that Jehovah made to David touches his heart,
and he sits before Jehovah in humility,
feeling so unworthy and insignificant.
And later, David made
an enormous contribution
for the building of the temple
that by today’s standards
would amount to over 1,200,000,000 dollars.
But in prayer to Jehovah, he says,
as recorded at 1 Chronicles 29:14:
“And yet, who am I . . .
“For everything is from you,
and what we have given to you
comes from your own hand.”
What a humble spirit.
And it’s true, isn’t it?
Whatever we give to Jehovah,
it’s something
that he has already given to us.
It’s no wonder that Jehovah God loved David.
He was a man really agreeable
to God’s own heart.
How can we cultivate and maintain
such a humble heart?
It’s not simply by saying,
“I am determined to be humble.”
No, but do as David did.
Once in a while, sit down,
take a long look at your life,
and see what blessings,
what undeserved kindnesses,
Jehovah has extended to you.
Ponder over his awesomeness.
And when we do so,
we will be moved to say to Jehovah:
‘Who am I, Jehovah God,
that you’ve honored me,
‘making me one of your fellow workers
despite my many flaws?
‘Who am I, Jehovah,
‘that you’ve given me health and strength
‘to serve in my assignment?
‘Who am I, O God,
to have this special privilege of service
when I know there are many more
and more deserving than I?’
Of course, there is a wholesome pride
in having the privilege
of being one of God’s servants,
but it is an unhealthy pride
that makes one feel superior.
And if we are looking down on others,
we cannot be looking up at Jehovah.
And that really is the secret
of maintaining humility
—to know what we really are.
We always keep Jehovah before us
as David did.
So students, we have every confidence
that you will keep your eyes
on your awesome God,
and that he will use you
and he will bless you
even more than he has
on this day of your graduation.
Well, I don’t know about you,
but I was enlightened
by “Who Am I, O Jehovah God?”
That was David that said that.
Well, live and learn.
Brother James Cauthon,
one of our Theocratic Schools instructors,
will speak on the theme
“Sympathetic Strings.”
Imagine that you had the means
to give everyone in your life
an expensive gift.
You know what would happen?
They would be happy.
You would be happier
because you would experience
what Jesus said is a greater happiness
—giving.
Actually, you can give others
something that is very special
—something they really need—
and it won’t cost you a cent.
What is it?
It’s your attention.
Romans 12:15,
the apostle Paul wrote this, he said:
“Rejoice with those who rejoice;
weep with those who weep.”
We need to learn to understand
and share another person’s feelings
whether it’s joy or sadness.
But why?
We need to understand it
because we’re living
in “critical times hard to deal with.”
And so when the Bible says
to “weep with those who weep,”
we can sum that up in two words:
Show sympathy.
Why should we do that?
Well, going back to Romans 12,
and this time in verse 5,
notice what we’re reminded of.
Paul wrote: “So we, although many,
are one body in union with Christ,
but individually we are members
belonging to one another.”
Now this, of course, was written
with those of the new covenant in mind,
but in reality all of us as Jehovah’s people
belong to one another.
Now, you might find it interesting to know
that in the Christian Greek Scriptures,
there are some 50 “one another” commands:
Love one another, encourage one another,
incite one another,
pray for one another, and other things.
The Watchtower said this, it said:
“We should be sensitive to the pains
and heartaches of our brothers and sisters.
“Often, we can bring much relief
to fellow believers
“who are suffering emotional pain
“if we take the time to listen to them
with a truly sympathetic ear.”
Sympathy is entering in
and sharing in the pain of others.
Now, sometimes in English we say “empathy.”
It’s also translated “fellow feeling”
or even “feel pity.”
But it’s in times of crisis, grief,
and doubt
when we need one another the most.
So how can we show that we care?
The answer is simple: Listen sympathetically.
The effect can be likened
to the sympathetic strings that are used
to enhance the sound and harmony
of certain musical instruments.
Now, all of these have strings
that are not played,
but they react
to the strings that are struck
or plucked, if you would,
thus they become sympathetic.
They produce a unique harmony.
It’s a oneness, really.
The effect of this
is something that is very special.
But now, how this actually works
can be demonstrated with the use
of two tuning forks.
Notice the one reacts to being struck.
The second, although not being struck,
reacts to the feelings of the first.
So the first fork is no longer alone.
It has become joined by a second fork
that is now also picking up the vibrations
and is said to be sympathetic.
It’s a harmony, really.
After the loss of a loved one,
one sister said:
“Tears became the language of my heart.
I so appreciated it when the friends
came over and just cried with me.”
Sure, it’s a oneness
—a harmony.
She felt it.
We recognize, though,
that there is a certain caution here
because sharing joy is one thing,
but sympathetically listening
to another’s pain of heart
can be emotionally taxing
and time-consuming.
As our illustration demonstrates,
even after the original fork is removed,
the sympathetic one
is still feeling the effects,
isn’t that right?
And that’s why,
whether we like it or not,
our actions will reveal
what’s really in our hearts
when it comes to our brothers and sisters.
Going back to Romans again,
this time Romans 12:10,
we’re reminded of this.
It says: “In brotherly love
have tender affection for one another.”
Listening is a simple gesture of affection.
Often the problem, of course,
is that we’re in such a hurry to fix things
that we feel that we can’t take the time
to listen to someone else
or to sympathize with them.
Or sometimes we’re so preoccupied
with our own hurts
that we’re caught up in that.
But self-pity will smother sympathy
for others.
And we need to be careful, frankly,
because sometimes we feel
that we just have to solve
the problem right away,
so we make statements
that are not helpful
to the person that is suffering.
‘You know, you need to just toughen up.’
Or here’s one of my favorites:
‘Others suffered, now it’s your turn.’
Or comparisons:
‘Well, at least you can walk.’
Well, we don’t mean those things
to be malicious,
but how do they come across?
You see, they come across as condescending.
And it’s another way of saying,
“I don’t care” or “I don’t care enough.”
Job tried ten times
to explain to his comforters his feelings.
And finally, after the tenth time, he said,
‘Oh, if someone would but listen to me.’
His hurt, his pain, was enhanced
because of his companions’ failure to listen.
How sad that is.
They neither cared about Job,
nor did they want to understand his feelings.
They shut him down.
Could we ever do
the same thing or something similar?
How sad that would be.
To share in someone’s grief and pain,
you must be willing to listen,
you must be willing to take the time,
and you must care more about them
than you do yourself.
We need to learn to take ourself
out of the equation.
Romans 12:10 continues:
“In showing honor to one another,
take the lead.”
We honor others by being nonjudgmental,
by taking them seriously,
and by giving sincere heartfelt attention
and consideration
to their words and their feelings.
We need to remember this point:
That is, that our relationship with God
and our relationship with our brothers
is one and the same.
Let me repeat that.
Our relationship with God
and our relationship with our brothers
is one and the same.
Jehovah cares deeply
about how we interact with one another.
Jehovah wants his people to be known
for their love for one another
more than anything else.
So your gift
of sympathetic concern
will be a powerful means of showing love
and restoring a measure of harmony
into the lives of others.
With talks like that,
I can see why I’m not one of the instructors.
The illustration of the two forks
just drove the point home, didn’t it?
Well, here’s another,
“The Glowing Coal” is the theme
Brother Mark Noumair has chosen.
He’s also one
of the Theocratic Schools instructors
and a helper to the Teaching Committee
of the Governing Body.
Brother Noumair,
we are burning with anticipation.
On joyous occasions as today,
your love burns strong, and rightly so.
Remember this day.
Etch indelibly in your minds
how you feel right now
because this love
that is burning brightly within you
will be tested.
When we undergo trials,
reviewing Bible accounts
of faithful men and women
can bolster our own faith.
And we can hear their words
ringing in our minds.
But what about those
who have never spoken a word
recorded in the Bible?
Can their silent examples of faith help us?
Let’s consider one.
Her name is Rizpah.
We know very little about her.
She is first introduced to us
as a concubine of King Saul.
No doubt, she must have been very beautiful
to catch the attention of the king.
However, her life was not an easy one.
In time,
Saul
—the father of her children—
is killed in battle.
She now becomes the property
of Saul’s son, Ishbosheth.
He too is killed.
Unfortunately, Rizpah’s most painful test
was yet to come.
Long after Saul’s death,
Jehovah tells King David
that bloodguilt remains on Saul’s house
because of his attempt
to annihilate the Gibeonites,
which violated an ancient covenant.
Thus, the entire nation of Israel is guilty
of shedding innocent blood.
How does David resolve this issue?
Second Samuel 21:3
shows what David did.
Second Samuel 21:3,
David asks the Gibeonites:
“What should I do for you?”
Verse 6, they answer:
“Let seven of [Saul’s] sons be given to us.
We will hang their dead bodies
before Jehovah.”
Verse 6 continues, David said:
“I will hand them over.”
Who does David hand over?
He hands over, in verse 8,
Rizpah’s two sons,
“the two sons of Rizpah,”
the two people in the whole world
that she loved most.
What a heartbreaking tragedy for Rizpah,
but she could do nothing about it.
The decision was made;
it was out of her control.
Eventually, all seven men are hung.
Now, under the Mosaic Law,
those executed upon a stake
should have been taken down
before nightfall and buried.
Burial would have brought closure
to this mother’s crushed soul.
And above all, it would conform
to Jehovah’s requirements
for the dignity of life
and that proper disposal of the dead body
would have been according
to Jehovah’s instructions.
Undoubtedly, Rizpah knows this,
but it didn’t happen that way.
So can you feel her anguish
as night approaches
and no one comes to take those bodies down?
And Rizpah could have been thinking:
‘But the Mosaic Law,
no one is following the Law.
It’s not right.’
But there was a catch.
It seems that the Gibeonites
were allowed to follow
a different procedure in this instance
because a national sin
had been committed by King Saul.
Now did Rizpah know that?
We don’t know.
But what we do know, one day goes by;
the Law is not followed.
The bodies are not taken down.
Two days go by; three days go by.
What does she do?
Well, according to verse 10,
Rizpah continues day after day
in the blaze of that scorching summer sun.
In fact, verse 10 says what she did do.
It says that “she did not allow
the birds of the heavens
“to land on [those bodies] by day
nor the wild beasts of the field
to come near by night.”
There she was out there, day after day,
shooing those birds away
—not to draw attention to herself,
not to get justice for her sons, no.
She understood, she appreciated,
and she upheld Jehovah’s view of human life.
She allowed Jehovah’s values
to shape her behavior
even at great personal cost.
You must love this woman.
Although Rizpah probably didn’t understand
exactly why things were happening this way
—why was it turning out in this way—
this different procedure
of not burying her sons
had a major impact on her personal life.
Yet, her conduct showed her love for Jehovah
and the loyalty that she had
for his arrangements
—that this love and loyalty
burned brightly within her.
Here’s your big lesson.
Now, at times, you might feel
that your life is outside of your control.
You may go through a trial
that allows Jehovah’s standards
and decisions to shape you,
perhaps at great personal cost.
For example,
you’re familiar with theocratic procedure;
you’re familiar with theocratic policies.
We know that.
But there might come a time
when an organizational direction
—an organizational procedure—
is modified for reasons
that you are not fully aware of,
and that decision affects you personally.
What will you do?
Like Rizpah, keep doing what you can
under your circumstances.
Shoo those birds away
—those negative thoughts.
Stir up that fire.
Don’t allow your warmth and glow
for Jehovah God to burn out.
Now, days go by,
according to verse 9 and verse 10:
‘from the start of the harvest to the rain.’
Now this implies that this may have been
five to six months
that she kept vigil over her sons’ bodies.
What could she have been thinking
about during this time
that may have been close to half a year?
What would she have been thinking about?
‘How could David be so uncaring
as not to command
‘to give my boys a proper burial.
‘And Jehovah,
‘after all that I’ve been through,
where are you, Jehovah?’
Now these might have been
natural thoughts, true.
Yet, if she did have them,
she did not allow these thoughts
to put out the fire
of her love for God or to make her bitter.
Perhaps others even tried
to discourage her saying:
‘Go home.
Give up.’
But she didn’t.
Nor did she start a campaign
by gathering others to her side.
There’s no record of her bad-mouthing David,
criticizing his decision as unfair.
Nor did she presume
to take the bodies down herself.
‘Well, if nobody is going to do it,
I’ll do it.’
No, in spite of all of these difficulties
—imagine—
that Rizpah was suffering,
she still had embers of love
for Jehovah God glowing brightly
that moved her to stay loyal,
remain in her place,
and wait on David to make the decision.
Did her faithful endurance really matter?
Did anyone notice her plight?
Verse 11:
“David was told
what Saul’s concubine Rizpah . . . had done.”
So imagine someone goes to David:
‘David, there’s this Rizpah;
she’s up there near these bodies.
She’s shooing these birds away.’
So, what did David do?
Did he now, finally,
give Rizpah’s sons a decent burial?
Actually, he did more.
Verses 12 through 14
show how David had the bones of Saul
and the bones of Jonathan brought
all the way from Jabesh-gilead
—which might have taken a journey
of about 100 miles (160 km)—
and buried those bones
with the bones of Rizpah’s sons
in Saul’s family plot in Benjamite territory.
So in the end,
Rizpah got more than she expected.
She saw the bones of her sons
and their father buried together.
Rizpah didn’t see that coming,
but it was worth the wait.
So, what’s the big lesson
we want you to remember here?
Rizpah’s love and loyalty and endurance
provides an example worth imitating.
When you go through a trial,
remember that others
are observing your conduct
—they’re watching.
And out of frustration, you might feel:
‘Well, why haven’t,
why haven’t the elders done anything?
‘Why aren’t the overseers
taking care of this situation?
Jehovah, why don’t you do something?’
And Jehovah is saying:
‘I am doing something.
‘I’m using your silent example
‘to show others that
when you endure a situation,
‘I will reward them.
‘I’ll reward them more than
they ever anticipated,
‘and it will be worth the wait.
Because I, Jehovah,
I love being a rewarder.’
What a noble and honorable way
to be used by Jehovah God.
Now, Rizpah was not a victim
of her circumstances.
Rather, she became a victor
over her adversities.
The intense heat of her trials
did not break her as a person
nor crush her desire
to please Jehovah God.
So little is known about her,
and yet we learn so much from her.
She never had one spoken word
recorded in the Bible,
yet Jehovah must have been very impressed
with this remarkable woman.
Her name and example earned a place
in his sacred Book
and is worthy of our examination.
She teaches you
—she teaches you
how to take life’s indignities with dignity.
So, what helped her endure successfully?
Perhaps a clue is in her name.
It literally means “Glowing Coal.”
Now, we don’t know why
she was given that name, true.
But like a piece of coal
glowing warm and bright,
Rizpah kept her thoughts focused
on love for her sons’ loyalty to Jehovah,
loyalty to his arrangements,
confident that relief would eventually come.
She was industrious.
She actively guarded her sons’ bodies
from being eaten by animals.
She didn’t allow negative feelings
to shut her down and extinguish her love.
Rather, in the face of what
she might have felt to be an injustice,
she did what she could.
So, what do we want you to remember?
What do we want you to go away with
to your assignments thinking about?
In the face of a perceived injustice,
keep working;
keep carrying out
your assigned work assignments;
keep doing what you can.
Shoo away those birds.
Stoke up the fire of your love
for Jehovah God and the brothers.
And wait on Jehovah
to resolve any pending issues,
confident that relief will come now
or in the new world.
It will be worth that wait.
And yet, above all, above all, be a Rizpah.
Under all circumstances,
keep your love for God
burning brightly like a glowing coal.
Those talks were inspiring
to the students of the 143rd class,
and I am sure that you feel much
the same way after viewing them.
But you probably are wondering,
‘What about the rest of the program?’
Wonder no longer.
Part 2 and Part 3 will be posted
on the Video on Demand section
of JW Broadcasting later this month.
In fact, Part 2 is a video entitled
The Inside Story.
It is scheduled to be posted
next Monday, December 11.
You will enjoy hearing experiences
from some of the graduates of the class.
Until the next monthly program,
this is JW Broadcasting
coming to you from the world headquarters
of Jehovah’s Witnesses.