We welcome all of you
to the January 2019 broadcast.
The 2018 annual meeting
of the Watchtower Bible
and Tract Society of Pennsylvania
was held on October 6, 2018.
The program consisted
of spiritually upbuilding talks
and encouraging reports.
It also included
faith-strengthening interviews,
such as one with a member
of the Governing Body,
Brother Gerrit Lösch.
Please enjoy the first part
of the 2018 annual meeting.
The theme for my opening talk is
“Appreciating Our Spiritual Paradise.”
And such a subject is very appropriate
on a special occasion like this.
But now let me ask you this:
When were Jehovah’s people
taken into spiritual captivity
by Babylon the Great?
Well, we know that we’ve learned recently
that it was sometime
in the second century C.E.
—after the death of the last of the apostles,
who were “acting as a restraint,”
and imitation Christians
began to infiltrate the congregation,
and the ugly baby Christendom was born.
But now, when did that captivity end?
Well, we know
—1919—
the year when
true anointed Christians
came out of captivity
and pure worship was restored.
And that means
that because this is the year 2018,
Jehovah’s people
have been set free for 99 years
—almost a hundred years now.
Now, what has been
the spiritual condition of Jehovah’s people
during these nearly 100 years?
Well, our condition
has become more and more paradisaic.
And today,
it is truly like an exquisite paradise,
just like the garden of Eden
was truly an exquisite physical paradise.
In fact, let’s compare—
Let’s discuss some similarities
between that original Paradise
and our spiritual paradise,
and we’ll see it is paradisaic
—this condition that we’re in.
Now, here’s the first similarity:
The garden of Eden, of course, had a land.
Well, our spiritual paradise has a land.
What is the land?
The July 1, 1995, Watchtower said
how “in 1919,
Jehovah brought the anointed remnant
out of captivity to Babylon the Great.”
And then it says that that anointed group
became a newborn nation.
But then it asks, What is the land, though?
Here’s the answer:
It is the realm of activity
granted to the newborn nation,
a place where Bible prophecies
have a modern, spiritual fulfillment.
So did you get that?
The realm of activity
where the anointed fulfill Bible prophecies.
Now here’s a second similarity:
Like the garden of Eden,
our spiritual paradise
has beautiful plants and trees.
Now, we certainly know
that was true of the garden of Eden
where Adam and Eve were,
but what about in our spiritual paradise?
Who are the plants and trees?
Well, the Bible likens God’s people
to plants and trees.
Here’s what 1 Corinthians 3:9 says:
“You [God’s people]
are God’s field under cultivation.”
Or think of Isaiah 61:3:
“And they [talking about God’s people]
“will be called big trees of righteousness,
the planting of Jehovah.”
And just like those plants
and trees in the garden of Eden,
these figurative plants
and trees bear much fruit
—the fruitage of lips,
the fruitage of the spirit.
And just looking in the audience,
we see many big, beautiful plants and trees
sitting out there,
and we’re happy to have you.
But now here is a third similarity:
Like the garden Eden,
our spiritual paradise has abundant food.
Jehovah foretold it would exist
and, as a contrast,
he said at Isaiah 65:13:
“Look! My servants will eat,
but you will go hungry.”
And especially today,
that contrast is more and more evident
—isn’t it?—
between what the people of the world
are being served
on “the table of demons”
and what we’re being served
on “the table of Jehovah.”
I mean, they’re served empty calories
—junk food, poison food—
but we have a smorgasbord
of spiritual things, don’t we?
We have these
not only nutritious but delicious things
served in our publications, meetings,
assemblies, conventions, jw.org,
and, more recently, JW Broadcasting.
“This is JW Broadcasting
“from the world headquarters
of Jehovah’s Witnesses.”
You can see,
I’m still working on that.
Here’s a fourth similarity:
The Bible tells us
that out of the garden of Eden a river flowed.
So it must have been a large river,
and it divided into four other rivers.
Well, there must have been abundant,
refreshing water in the garden of Eden.
Well, likewise in our spiritual paradise,
we have abundant spiritual water.
And again,
Jehovah foretold it and the contrast.
At Isaiah 65:13, Jehovah said:
“Look! My servants will drink,
but you will go thirsty.”
It makes me think of what one young man
who was learning the truth
—this is what he said, a young man
in Africa in his life story in The Watchtower—
said: “It seemed that my church
“had been giving me ‘acid’ to drink,
but now I was freely receiving the water of life.”
And he was so thankful to be set free
from the Trinity,
worship of ancestors, and so forth.
Jehovah gives the invitation
at Revelation 22:17:
“‘Come!’ and let anyone thirsting come;
let anyone who wishes take life’s water free.”
And we know that water represents
all of Jehovah’s provisions
for gaining everlasting life.
Now here’s a fifth similarity:
Like the garden of Eden,
our spiritual paradise
is a place that has
many harmless animals.
Now, what do we mean by this?
Well, here’s what The Watchtower
said about this,
or I should say Isaiah’s Prophecy,
concerning the scripture,
and we should read this first
—Isaiah 65:25.
Here’s what Jehovah
foretold about harmless animals
at Isaiah 65:25:
“‘The wolf and the lamb will feed together,
“‘the lion will eat straw just like the bull,
“‘and the serpent’s food will be dust.
“‘They will do no harm nor cause any ruin
in all my holy mountain,’ says Jehovah.”
Now, there’ll be a literal fulfillment
of this in the new world,
but there’s a figurative
—a spiritual—
fulfillment right now.
And here’s what Isaiah’s Prophecy said
concerning that scripture we just read:
“Those coming into this spiritual paradise
make remarkable changes in their lives.”
Ones that previously had beastlike personalities,
the book said that with the help of the holy spirit,
they make drastic changes
and they tame those undesirable traits.
So that was the explanation
of that scripture we just read.
And what a pleasure it is to fellowship
with you dear former wolves,
lions, bears,
and serpents also
—throw that in there.
Now, you notice I said former.
In your former condition,
I wouldn’t have wanted to meet
many of you in a dark alley,
and you would definitely say that about me
if I hadn’t been raised in the truth.
But what a pleasure to have
these figurative, harmless animals!
Now here’s a sixth comparison:
Like the garden of Eden,
our spiritual paradise
is a garden that needs maintenance.
Now, would you say that Jehovah is doing
maintenance in this spiritual paradise?
Well, here’s Jesus’ answer:
Look in John chapter 15,
John 15:2, Jesus said:
“He [Jehovah] takes away
“every branch in me not bearing fruit,
“and he cleans every one bearing fruit,
so that it may bear more fruit.”
Now, if you think
of taking away unproductive branches
and cleaning productive ones
to make it more productive,
is that not garden maintenance?
Well, what about us?
Are we expected to do maintenance?
Well, here is what
the Organized to Do Jehovah’s Will book said:
“Your faith has brought
you into a spiritual paradise.
“Benefiting from that paradise,
you have the responsibility
to help maintain it.”
And then the book went on to say
that by applying Bible counsel,
we help maintain our spiritual paradise.
Here’s one more similarity, number seven:
Our spiritual paradise,
like the garden of Eden,
has boundaries.
Now, regarding the garden of Eden,
here’s what the Insight book said:
“It seems to have been an enclosed area,
bounded, no doubt, by natural barriers.”
And then it went on to say
that it had an entrance on the eastern side,
and that, of course, was where
the cherubs were placed to block the entrance.
Well, what about our spiritual paradise?
What are the boundaries?
Well, here are a few examples:
1 Corinthians 5:11
—stop keeping company
with anyone who gets disfellowshipped.
We’re separate
—a boundary.
Revelation 18:4
—get out of Babylon the Great.
We’re separate
—a boundary.
What about John 17:14?
We must be no part of the world
as Jesus was no part of the world.
We’re separate
—a boundary.
But interestingly,
Satan the Devil was able to lure
Adam and Eve
out of their beautiful paradise home,
and he’s trying very hard
to lure every one of us here
out of the boundaries
of our wonderful spiritual paradise.
But we’re determined
that we’re not going to let that happen.
But there, we have seven similarities,
and I’m sure you can think of others.
But truly, the situation we’re in
—the condition as Jehovah’s people—
is paradisaic.
And it is proof,
the reality of this spiritual paradise,
is proof that a literal paradise
will likewise soon become reality.
But now moving ahead in our program,
we’re going to have
a privilege to look at a video.
The title of it is
Courage to Stand Firm in a Time of Trial.
And our video
will be narrated by Brother Rick Ford,
who serves as the overseer
of the headquarters Museum Department
at Warwick.
And you’re going to enjoy this.
Brother Ford is going to really tell you
about something
you’re going to look forward to visiting.
So let’s look at the monitors, please.
Courage to stand firm in a time of trial
—that’s the story of the Bible Students
from 1914 to 1919
and the theme of a new exhibit
at world headquarters.
The tests they faced
in those few pivotal years
are part of our spiritual heritage
that can strengthen our courage now
and for what lies ahead.
In the years just before 1914,
anticipation was high.
Since 1876,
Charles Taze Russell had published
that the Gentile Times
would end in October 1914.
Many believed it would mean
the end of their preaching work
and their being taken
to heaven to rule with Christ.
The Bible Students spread
their message by every means possible:
tracts, pamphlets,
and then in 1886
with The Plan of the Ages
—the first book in the Millennial Dawn series
(later called Studies in the Scriptures).
In December 1911,
Brother Russell embarked
on an around-the-world tour.
And he went on an 8,000-mile (12,900-km)
transcontinental train tour in 1913.
When 1914 came,
so did a new way to expand the work.
The “Photo-Drama of Creation.”
The Bible’s message
was now reaching millions.
Would 1914 turn out as they had hoped?
On June 28,
Austria’s Archduke Ferdinand
was assassinated,
triggering the start of the Great War.
The end of the Gentile Times
seemed to be fulfilling expectations.
We held a convention at Columbus, Ohio.
I recall how that on June the 28th
right in the midst of that convention,
why, there was a shot fired
that was heard around the world.
When we read the newspaper,
we said: “Aha!
“There it is, there it is.
The Gentile Times
are drawing to their close.”
But 1914 brought unexpected trials
that would test the Bible Students’ faith
as never before.
The year 1914 came, and it went.
Contrary to expectations,
the heavenly reward did not come.
As they wondered how much longer
they would need to preach,
they confronted
a devastating turn of events.
Brother Russell died suddenly
on October 31, 1916.
We did not know what to do.
It was so unexpected,
and yet Russell had tried to prepare us for it.
What would we do?
The first shock of our loss
of C. T. Russell was the worst.
For those first few days,
our future was a blank wall.
In time, some felt
that all that God saw fit to reveal
had come through Brother Russell,
and that the revelation
of truth had now ended.
After Joseph F. Rutherford
was selected as the new president,
dissent arose among the Society’s directors.
On July 17, 1917,
the tension exploded with the publication
of The Finished Mystery
—the seventh volume
of Studies in the Scriptures,
based largely
on Brother Russell’s earlier writings.
On that morning, a lengthy debate erupted
right in the Bethel dining room.
Vicious charges were hurled
against Rutherford and his oversight.
Although four Society directors
were soon dismissed from Bethel,
they soon began spreading their opposition
by an extensive speaking
and letter-writing campaign
that threatened to divide the organization.
To disorganize the congregation,
they tried to put Brother Rutherford out.
So my uncle, he said:
“Well, this didn’t happen in Brother Russell’s day.
“I’m going to quit the whole business
and just read Brother Russell’s books.”
I said,
“Well, I’m not going to quit the Society!”
I was convinced
that the Society was God’s arrangement.
Another threat soon emerged.
Distribution of The Finished Mystery
sparked renewed opposition
from religious and political leaders.
The book was banned
—first in Canada
and then in the United States.
How did the Bible Students respond?
They launched a courageous campaign
to distribute Kingdom News No. 1,
No. 2, and No. 3.
These boldly exposed clergy abuses
and defended
the Bible Students’ Scriptural position.
But with the war still raging,
the next challenge demanded attention.
In many countries,
brothers took a neutral stand
as conscientious objectors.
We were put into cells
that were more like dungeons.
Due to our refusal to undergo military drill,
a number of us
were taken to a secluded part
of the prison yard.
Lined up there were
a number of men in uniform
with canes in their hands.
One by one,
we were ordered
to run the length of the court.
If the pace was too slow, we were seized
and dragged the distance and subjected
to lashes on the back and legs.
Beyond those persecuted
for refusing military service,
others endured physical abuse instigated
by the clergy
because of their courageous preaching.
Any uncertainty
that our brothers may have felt
was only intensified by what happened next.
On May 7, 1918,
federal arrest warrants were issued
for Joseph Rutherford and seven associates.
They were charged
with causing insubordination,
disloyalty, and refusal of duty in the military
and naval forces of the United States.
A month later, they were pronounced guilty
and given concurrent sentences
ranging from ten to twenty years
in a federal penitentiary.
The Brooklyn Tabernacle was sold,
and remaining operations
were transferred back
to Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania.
These were dark and confusing times,
but Jehovah would not abandon
his courageous people.
On March 26, 1919,
Brother Rutherford
and his associates were released.
Seeking Jehovah’s will,
Brother Rutherford
scheduled a public meeting
in Los Angeles, California,
on May 4, 1919.
It was a test.
Were people still interested
in the Bible’s message?
Within 20 minutes after the doors opened,
the auditorium was filled to capacity.
About 3,500 showed up,
and another 600
were turned away with the promise
that an overflow meeting
would be held the following day.
An additional 1,500
showed up to hear the second talk.
There was clearly much more work to do.
Bethel operations
were moved back to Brooklyn.
Plans were made immediately
for the 1919 Cedar Point convention
which was held four months later
—a turning point
that reignited the preaching work.
New tools, including
The Golden Age magazine, were released.
A Service Department
was established at Bethel.
Service directors were appointed
to organize preaching in each congregation.
And as we now understand,
“the faithful and discreet slave”
was commissioned to feed God’s flock.
Isaiah 46:8 says:
“Remember this, and take courage.”
Remember how these faithful ones
preached an unpopular message,
how they moved forward
despite unrealized expectations,
how they stayed loyal
to God’s organization when others did not,
how they suffered
when staying neutral in the world’s wars.
Remember their courageous example,
and take courage now
and in the days ahead.
Thank you very much, Brother Ford,
for sharing
that very interesting theocratic history
concerning our spiritual predecessors,
the Bible Students.
And you’ve made us very eager
to visit our new museum exhibit.
But now we’re going
to get to enjoy another video treat.
Brother Gerrit Lösch of the Governing Body
is going to share with us
some fascinating experiences
from Eastern Europe.
I was serving at the Austria branch
from about the mid-1970’s to 1990.
We had a small department
that was assigned
to help certain countries in Eastern Europe.
And that included
visiting the brothers under ban,
bringing them spiritual food,
having secret meetings with them,
and also strengthening
the local organization
that was exposed
to persecution and ban.
We would print books on Bible paper
in miniature size.
This way, more books or literature
could be taken to these countries.
The couriers transported literature
to these countries
in their own private cars.
This way,
hundreds of books could be transported.
At the border, if a courier
would be found transporting literature,
they would interrogate the driver.
But these brothers were trained;
they knew what to say
to protect the work
and to not give away any secrets.
Usually, after a day or two days,
the officials would let them go back home
to their home country
but not with their car;
they had to use public transportation
because their cars would be confiscated.
But the brothers had the spirit of sacrifice;
they were willing to risk that.
But the majority got through,
and actually every year,
thousands of miniature books
were transported secretly
to Eastern Europe.
So it was not just a matter
of us being so clever in hiding things
and getting it to the brothers,
but we were always fully convinced
and had evidence
that it was Jehovah’s holy spirit
that helped us.
Also, we transported stencils
for local production
so that in their countries
they could reproduce the same material
with mimeographing machines.
In most cases,
the mimeographing machines
were transported secretly
by the couriers.
The other method
was to build it within the country.
I remember that there was a brother
who was a very skilled engineer,
and under his direction,
they decided to build it themselves.
So there were self-made
offset printing presses.
The brothers had a number
of underground printeries
that they had dug out
under their own homes.
In many cases, the brothers had to do
what they did during the night
because in Communist countries,
they had to go during the day
to a factory or whatever else
and do some secular work.
But it testifies to the great spirit
of sacrifice that the brothers showed
—to forfeit so much
of their private life as a family
to do at night the printing
of the spiritual food.
Some had only a few hours of sleep,
but they loved Jehovah
and the brothers so much
that they did it.
There was no Kingdom Hall.
The brothers
had secret meetings in private homes,
and they would not all come
at the same time
because if the neighbors
would see certain persons
all the time going to a specific house,
there could be suspicions.
And every week, they had the meetings
in a different home of the brothers.
And this helped to protect the work
so that it could be kept secret.
Singing was very important
for the brothers,
and they didn’t have to have
a songbook in hand.
They knew the text of the song by heart,
and immediately after saying a number,
they could sing the song.
That affected the heart
—the emotions of the brothers—
so they were strengthened
in their determination to be faithful.
A lot of pressure
was on the brothers in Romania.
The Communist Party tried
to sow distrust among the brothers,
meeting with them separately
and telling some brothers one thing
and telling other brothers something else.
Sometimes it happened
that an official posed
as an interested person
and was clever enough to disguise that
and pretend
to make progress in the truth
—not only to the point
of getting baptized
but even to the point
of becoming an elder.
But he was in reality an agent
of the secret police
with an aim to find out everything
about the organization.
So it did lead to, in one case,
the brothers starting to distrust someone
that was actually appointed by headquarters.
And these brothers then separated
from the organization that Jehovah used,
and some of them were separated
for not just a few years but for decades.
And they were a large number,
up to 5,000 publishers.
They continued to meet together.
They were preaching and using material
that they had left over from earlier years,
but they hardly got
any new material to study
because they were not in touch
with the organization
that was used by headquarters.
Attempts to bring the brothers back
into the organization
were made from time to time,
but it seemed that the brothers
from the separated organization
did not have sufficient trust.
But when we presented
to the leader of the separated group
that one
from the Governing Body would come,
he was happy about that
and he had enough trust in that case
to agree that we should have a meeting
and seriously talk about reunification.
And so from the separated group,
there were Brother Albu,
who was the leader,
and four of his main elders.
And from our side,
there was Brother Jaracz,
our translator,
and I was part of that group.
Also, there were several
from the Country Committee of Romania.
I remember that the first night
there were a lot of accusations
about what the others
had done or not done,
which did not create the best spirit,
and we mainly listened.
But everybody agreed
to meet another night.
And the second night,
Jehovah obviously wanted
the brothers to unite again
because the whole spirit was different,
and the brothers talked the matters over
and clarified some misunderstandings.
And at the end of the second evening,
I remember that the leader
of the separated group,
Brother Albu, said,
‘Let’s do it because if we don’t do it now,
we may never have
another opportunity again.’
And so the decision was made.
That doesn’t happen every day
that 5,000 brothers
come back to the organization.
From then on, all the practical things
were put in place
to accomplish this reunification.
They were asked to merge
with our congregations.
And that also took a lot of humility
on their part,
but they were willing to do it.
So they were really brothers
in their heart and loved the truth.
And so the reunification was accomplished,
and that was a wonderful victory
for Jehovah and against Satan.
Reflecting on the experience
with the brothers in Romania,
we can see that there could always be
misunderstandings among humans
and there could always be
even legitimate complaints
about the misconduct
of some responsible brothers.
But the important thing
is never to lose trust
that this is Jehovah’s organization.
That’s where Jehovah’s blessing is.
Jehovah sees it all.
Jehovah uses his holy spirit
to keep the organization together,
and what he wants
to have accomplished will happen.
If we work with the holy spirit,
then Jehovah will bless our efforts
and it will be successful to his praise.
Thank you so much, Brother Lösch,
for sharing those captivating experiences.
But now we’re going to get to show you
a one-minute video trailer
to whet your appetite
for something that is coming.
Since the beginning,
people have been given a choice.
Some have chosen to do what is wrong.
Others chose to make Jehovah happy.
What you do every day
can make his heart rejoice.
I know you will make Jehovah happy.
We’re looking forward to this new video.
But the question is,
When will we and our children
get to enjoy this video?
Well, we are happy to inform you
that in less than six months,
you’re going to be able to have this video.
Now, you don’t look
like you’re too happy about that.
Well, I was teasing you;
I was truthful, though.
In less than six months,
much less than six months,
in fact, right now,
you’re going to get to enjoy
the nine-minute epic video
Make Jehovah Happy.
From the beginning,
Jehovah has always cared about people.
Sadly, many of them
have caused him great pain.
But some have made him very happy.
Jesus always made Jehovah happy.
Satan didn’t like this.
He tried everything
to get Jesus to do what was wrong.
If you are a son of God,
tell these stones
to become loaves of bread.
It is written:
“Man must not live on bread alone.”
Grr!
Hmm.
If you are a son of God,
throw yourself down,
for the angels
will carry you on their hands,
so you may not strike your foot
against a stone.
Prove it to them.
Again it is written: “You must not put
Jehovah your God to the test.”
Grr.
Hmm.
See all this glory;
it is mine.
And I give it to whomever I wish.
And all these things I will give to you
if you fall down
and do an act of worship to me.
Hmm.
Go away, Satan!
For it is written: “It is
Jehovah your God you must worship,
and it is to him alone
you must render sacred service.”
Jesus was determined
to make Jehovah happy.
But this story isn’t over.
This is your story too.
What do you mean, Dad?
Well, what you do
can make Jehovah happy.
Our text this morning, Proverbs 27:11
—Do you remember what that says?
Oh, yeah!
It says: “Be wise, my son,
and make my heart rejoice.”
Good memory, Sophia!
That scripture is talking about you.
What you do every day,
not only big things
but also small things you do,
can make His heart rejoice.
Remember today’s text, children.
I know you’ll make Jehovah happy.
Let’s pray.
OK, kids.
It’s a pop quiz today!
Oh, man!
Yes!
Now, Sophia, if you ace this test,
you’ll be number one
in the whole class.
Oh, yeah!
You’re at the next level.
Keep going!
. . . number one in the whole class.
Hey!
You got this one?
Yeah, here.
Hey, Sophia!
You want the answer?
Oh, man!
That stinks. You lost!
Hey, Caleb!
You want to play?
Come on; it’s fun!
Um.
Forget it.
He’s a loser!
Let me play with it!
Are you going to play or not?
Yay!
Yeah!
Nooooo!
Caleb! Caleb! Caleb! Caleb! Caleb!
Caleb? Caleb? Caleb?
You going to play?
Hey, Sophia!
You want the answer?
And you too can have success!
That’s OK.
No, thanks.
There are certainly
a lot of powerful lessons in that video
for our young ones and even for us.
And we’re happy to inform you
that in less than six months,
you’ll be able to download—
I don’t think you’re going to fall for that again.
Here’s the real announcement:
“Some of you with nephews,
nieces, children,
“or grandchildren are wondering,
“‘When will these little ones
be able to see this video?’
“You’ll be happy to know that the video
Make Jehovah Happy
“will be posted in over 100 languages
“this coming Monday, October the 8th,
“on both JW Broadcasting
and on the jw.org website.”
In two days, you’ll have it.
But now we’re going to get to enjoy
an interview that will be conducted
by Brother Samuel Herd
of the Governing Body.
And he’s going to interview
four brothers who have a lot to tell us,
but he’s going to do his best
to hold them down to 19 minutes.
Look at the monitors, please.
We have four brothers with us—
Brother Stephen Hardy
is serving in the Britain branch;
Brother Lorence Shepp is serving in Peru;
Brother Reiner Thompson’s current assignment
is in the Dominican Republic;
and last, alphabetically, is Brother Leon Weaver
who is serving
on the United States Branch Committee.
All four of these brothers
have at least two things in common.
First, they’ve all served
as the Branch Committee coordinator
of their respective branches
for a number of years.
And second,
all four have hit a milestone in life
according to Psalm 90:10.
There, these brothers
are identified as being “especially strong.”
Why so?
Because their life span
is cresting 80 years of age.
It takes extra vitality and stamina
to still be walking and talking
at that age and to still be making sense.
Believe me, I know!
I asked to retire at 80.
The Governing Body said,
“Not until you lose it.”
I said, “Well . . . ”
Brother Weaver,
what did all four of you
find out on May 26, 2014?
All Branch Committees
got a letter from the Governing Body,
and that letter told us about a new policy.
And that new policy was
that once a Branch Committee coordinator
reaches the age of 80,
he would not be able to serve
as Branch Committee coordinator anymore.
But the Branch Committee
would look for a younger brother
who could qualify to do that
and then recommend the younger brother
to be the Branch Committee coordinator.
Would any of you
like to describe your first thoughts
when you read that new policy?
Well, Brother Herd,
I remember some words of my dad.
He worked in the circuit work
in his senior years
but would tell me,
“Now son, if you see
that I’m starting to lose it,
you be sure to tell me
and get me to stop.”
Oftentimes, we don’t realize
that age takes a toll on our effectiveness.
I remember as a younger man
looking how far would I be able to do this work.
I thought,
‘Well, maybe at 65
I should step off from being the coordinator.’
Everybody retires at 65.
When I was 65, I felt pretty good.
So I went on to 70.
When 70 was drifting by, I felt pretty good.
I went on to 75,
and I know if that new policy hadn’t come out,
I would probably have been setting
it up to 85 or who knows where.
But really, for the benefit of the work,
we need to have younger men.
Experienced?
Yes, but younger and vigorous
for the benefit of the work
and for the benefit of those
with whom we work with on the committee.
Much of the branch work,
especially with the work
of the coordinator, recently,
has to do with modern technology.
So as a result of this,
when I was serving as coordinator,
I had to use
a younger, spiritually-minded brother
to keep me up to speed,
as it were, to what was required.
So besides the aging process,
when the changes came,
I had no doubt that it was Jehovah’s decision.
And so then for me,
I was very happy to accept the change
without any questions or any doubts.
And then there was
an additional paragraph in that policy letter
that said that if a coordinator
is not yet 80 years of age
but he feels that now would be the best time
for a younger brother
to take on that responsibility,
then his request should be considered.
Well, I was just 75 at that time.
But I began to realize
that in the coming years,
after a couple of years
with the Britain branch construction
and relocation project,
I realized that the responsibilities
would become even more intense.
And because of the major
organizational adjustments that we’d have,
I realized that it would be good
to request a younger brother to take over.
I was just 79 when that change took place.
That was a very modest thing to do.
Thank you, brothers, for your comments.
I can’t help myself; I have to ask this:
What were your wives’ reactions
to the new policy?
Did they leap for joy?
Don’t answer that second question.
Well, Ruby thought
it was a loving arrangement for us.
And actually,
she thought that it would be
the best for her and for me.
And I agreed with her.
In our case, Brother Herd,
down through the years
we’ve been surprised
by many reassignments.
And Jeanne has always been
100 percent cooperative
with all theocratic assignments.
But as assignments would come,
she would pack or unpack,
whatever was the order of the moment.
With the new policy,
she accepted it wholeheartedly,
and she was happy that she
didn’t have to pack or unpack on this one.
And Ann’s reaction first of all was,
“What are you going to do?”
So she realized
that I’m always involved with my work.
I like to have plenty to do.
But she was fully supportive of the arrangement.
You know that was the same with Olimpia.
Of course, she was surprised.
We were all surprised.
But from the very moment,
just a few seconds after I told her of the change,
she accepted it.
And she was willing to cooperate,
because as she said,
she knew that this was
direction by the faithful slave.
Solomon asked:
“Who can find a capable wife?”
All four of you
just answered that question beautifully.
I’m sure you remember
the account of Barzillai
in 2 Samuel chapter 19.
He was very helpful to King David.
David offered for him
to be part of the royal court,
but Barzillai
had now turned 80 years of age.
He declined because he knew
he would not be
as useful in the days ahead.
Instead, the privilege
went to Chimham, a younger man.
Did that account come to your mind
with this policy change?
I was convinced
that the Governing Body was probably using
that to consider their new changes or policy.
I was 80 years of age.
I was still strong; I was still vigorous.
But I do have to admit
that it crossed my mind, many times,
‘There’s going to come a time, Shepp,
‘when you’re going to have to relinquish
your privileges to somebody younger.’
And so then when the change came,
I accepted it as coming from Jehovah
and I had no doubts
that it was the direction of the faithful slave.
Yes, I did think of Barzillai.
But then my mind
went to his replacement, Chimham.
And I realized that on our Branch Committee
we had several younger brothers
who were like Chimhams.
So I was at peace with that arrangement.
I must admit, Brother Herd,
that I reviewed this case of Barzillai.
But there was one thing
about what he said and did
that I didn’t agree with.
Well, he said that he’d like
to go back to his hometown and die.
Rather, I thought,
‘I’ll use my energies as much as I can
in other activities
connected with our assignment.’
I’m sure that is the spirit of all four of you.
At what age did you
dedicate your life to Jehovah?
And describe some of the privileges
you have enjoyed since then.
At 13, I was baptized.
By 17, I was in regular pioneer work.
At 21, my faithful wife, Jeanne,
and I graduated from Gilead
and were assigned to Puerto Rico.
We went into the missionary work
in Puerto Rico
for about a year and a half
to learn the language,
and then we had
the privilege of circuit work.
Later, the Governing Body invited us
—invited me—
to take up the Branch Committee work in Belize
when it used to be called British Honduras.
And from there,
we were transferred to Nicaragua
as Branch Committee members.
And from there,
we were deported
in the revolutionary years to Costa Rica.
I had the privilege
to work with Brother Shepp for six years
in Costa Rica on the Branch Committee,
and there was also
a branch building going on at that time.
And then, we’ve been
for the last 30 years privileged to serve
with the Dominican Republic Branch Committee.
Over the last eight years,
it’s been our privilege
to serve as headquarters representatives
in branch visits
and getting to know
so many faithful and hardworking Bethelites
in different parts of the world, it truly—
It’s a wonderful organization
to be working with.
And with me, Brother Herd,
I was 17 when I was baptized.
And in 1957,
I started to regular pioneer.
And in 1965,
the Governing Body
appointed me to be a traveling overseer,
and Ruby and I traveled for 12 years,
to 1977.
And in 1977,
they called us in to Bethel.
So we’ve been
at Bethel for the last 41 years,
and about 23 years ago,
they invited me to visit
other branches throughout the globe.
And we’ve had quite an interesting
and encouraging time doing that.
And we’ve had the privilege of you
being a helper to the Service Committee
of the Governing Body since 1992.
You’ve racked up
quite a life of dedicated service.
I was baptized at the age of 19.
I took up the full-time service
in 1958.
In 1960,
I was appointed to be a circuit overseer.
I served in parts of Ontario, Quebec.
And then while serving there,
I was assigned to northwest Canada,
which included part of Alaska.
And after getting there,
only four months or so,
we were called to Brooklyn
to attend
the newly formed Kingdom Ministry School.
During our visit at Brooklyn,
Brother Knorr talked to some
of us Canadians and he asked us,
“Would you be willing to accept
a missionary assignment
without going to Gilead?”
Well, this was a marvelous opportunity,
and I was accepted
and later assigned to Nicaragua.
So just after a couple of years,
I wanted to get married.
I wrote.
And Brother Knorr had kind of softened
his opinion
about getting married at that time.
So 55 years ago,
I married Olimpia,
and we’ve been serving together
in several countries.
We were assigned to Costa Rica
where we served together for 27 years.
And on the second of October,
we just completed another 25 years
of serving under the Peru branch.
I also consider it a tremendous privilege
having been assigned
the privilege of visiting other branches
and sharing encouragement with them,
and that we’ve been doing
for a little bit more than 20 years.
I’m getting tired out just listening to the work
you brothers have done over the years.
Brother Hardy, your story, please.
Well, I dedicated my life to Jehovah
when I was 11 years old.
And then I started pioneering at 18,
then special pioneered.
And when I was just 22,
my wife and I were invited
into the circuit work.
And then in 1963,
we got a surprise.
We were invited to Gilead
and from Gilead
we were assigned to Burundi in Africa.
Well, we never heard of Burundi.
So immediately we went
to get our Yearbook
to find out how many publishers
there were in Burundi.
We looked down the list,
but Burundi wasn’t even on the list,
so we suddenly realized
we were going into virgin territory.
But sadly, the authorities
in Burundi were not happy about that,
and after just four months,
we had to leave the country.
And we were reassigned to Uganda.
And then we served there for ten years,
and again,
there were difficulties in Uganda.
And so we were reassigned
this time to Côte d’Ivoire,
and we served there for another ten years.
But then, my wife
had gotten some medical problems,
and we had to return to Britain in 1983.
And after some years, she died.
But then a little later,
there was a commuter Bethel sister
in London Bethel,
and her desire was to become
a regular Bethelite.
And she knew the only way to do that,
according to her,
was to marry a Bethel brother.
Well, I found her personality very attractive,
and what’s more,
she was a really spiritual person.
So I succumbed.
And so Ann and I—
We’ve been serving happily
in London Bethel since 1989.
And like the other brothers,
I’ve had the privilege of serving
as a headquarters representative.
And we’ve visited some 60 branches
and have thoroughly enjoyed that.
Thank you
for that brief overview of your lives.
According to my notes, all told,
Brother Hardy has served
as a Branch Committee member for 38 years.
For the last 19 years,
he has been the coordinator
of the Britain branch.
Brother Shepp,
according to my calculations,
has served as a member
of a Branch Committee for 52 years
and 48 of those years
as the coordinator to a Branch Committee.
Brother Thompson has been serving
as a Branch Committee member
for some 50 years,
with 44 of those years
as the coordinator of a Branch Committee.
Some of you who are newer
to the organization might not realize it,
but there was not
an official Branch Committee
in the United States until April 1, 2001.
Brother Weaver was appointed
as a Branch Committee member from its inception.
So that is now 17 years
as a member of that Branch Committee,
and he has served
as the coordinator for the past 11 years.
Being the coordinator of a Branch Committee
is a full-time job
—and then some.
So I’m sure everyone is wondering
what your new assignments entail.
Brother Hardy?
Well, I work
in the Branch Committee Office,
and I do some proofreading
of letters to other branches
and to the different committees
of the Governing Body.
I’m one of the three brothers
assigned from the Branch Committee
assigned to work in the Service Department,
and one of my assignments
is to include shepherding.
I’ve had the privilege of calling personally
the 97 traveling overseers
and talking to them
and to many of their wives.
I’ve been able to call
the 52 field missionaries,
and I’ve been able to visit personally
every one of the Bethel family.
I have a goal.
We have 47 very faithful special pioneers
that are not able to do
as much as they used to.
So I’m starting to call them, and my goal is,
by the end of this calendar year,
to be able to talk to every one of them.
The Branch Committee has assigned me
to the area of what we call BRED,
which is Branch Real Estate Desk.
They’ve also given me the privilege,
having participated
in the construction of two branches,
to help the younger brothers
take advantage of the training programs
that we have in place for them.
Well, Brother Herd,
all of us are still on the Branch Committee,
and there’s still much work to do
in connection to the Branch Committee.
We have shepherding to do
of traveling overseers
and Bethel family members.
We also still give
our convention assignments.
We will do circuit assemblies.
And myself, personally,
I’d like to increase
my field service time
with my congregation
and with my wife, Ruby.
Thank you, brothers,
for your many decades
of loyal dedicated service
to Jehovah and to Kingdom interests.
And along with so many longtime faithful ones,
it is heartwarming
to hear that you fully embrace
the decision of the faithful slave,
even if it means
relinquishing a privilege of service.
But that in no way
has any bearing on your zeal, energy,
and enthusiasm for the Lord’s work.
The Governing Body
applies Paul’s words at 1 Corinthians 15:58
to the four of you and all of the others
who find themselves in similar circumstances.
There it says:
“Therefore, my beloved brothers,
“be steadfast, immovable,
“always having plenty to do
in the work of the Lord,
“knowing that your labor is not in vain
in connection with the Lord.”
Thank you for joining us,
and thank your wives
for their unwavering support
of your many responsibilities.
Thank you very much,
Brother Herd and company,
for that delightful interview.
We love you five brothers very much.
What an encouraging program!
Parts 2 and 3 will be released
over the next couple of weeks.
They’ll include talks given
by five members of the Governing Body.
So by the time you see all three parts,
you will have heard
from each member of the Governing Body.
To bring to an end this month’s broadcast,
we’ll travel to Croatia.
Croatia is nestled
between five other countries
in southeastern Europe.
It has many picturesque locations throughout,
ranging from a beautiful coastline
to towering mountaintops.
There are
around 5,000 publishers in the country.
In May 2018,
the first foreign-language group was formed.
The English group,
located in the capital city, Zagreb,
reaches out to the many foreign workers,
tourists, and refugees.
Croatia is also experiencing growth
in the sign-language and Roma fields.
This is the Zadar Congregation
in western Croatia.
The 120 publishers there
have been assigned a vast territory,
which includes many islands.
In 2015,
they were able to attend
the special convention held in Croatia.
And in the fall of 2018,
they participated in and hosted delegates
for a special preaching campaign
in their country.
In their local territory,
they make effective use
of public witnessing carts
to reach out to tourists and other passersby.
There are ten publishers in the congregation
serving as regular pioneers,
seven as elders,
and four as ministerial servants.
All our dear brothers and sisters
in the Zadar Congregation
send you their warm greetings.
From the world headquarters
of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
this is JW Broadcasting.