Welcome to JW Broadcasting®.
This month, we focus
on how we can refine ourselves as Christians
by imitating Jehovah’s holiness.
Do you sometimes say things you later regret
—something unkind,
perhaps critical of others?
We’ll learn from this dramatization
how to adjust
not only what we say
but also how we think.
If you’re a young person,
do you ever feel you’re in a fight
—a fight to please Jehovah,
a fight to be joyful despite opposition?
You’ll enjoy our new music video.
Some of Jehovah’s people have suffered
disappointing spiritual setbacks.
Jehovah lovingly wants
people to return to him.
We’ll see how he helped this man
turn his life around.
All of this and more
on JW Broadcasting for October 2019!
When I say the words “holy” and “holiness,”
what comes to your mind?
Many think of words like “clean” and “pure.”
But let’s change the question a little.
Who comes to your mind?
Likely, you think of Jehovah.
You might also picture
Jesus Christ and the holy angels.
But do you think of imperfect humans?
Can humans be described as holy?
Yes.
We know this because humans
were created in God’s image.
Just as we can reflect godly qualities
—such as love, kindness, and self-control—
we can reflect holiness.
How seriously should we take holiness?
It’s no small matter.
Today, the world around us
is increasing in badness.
Second Timothy 3:13 warns
that ‘wicked men
would advance from bad to worse.’
Undoubtedly, before the end,
Satan’s efforts
to promote wickedness will intensify.
So we must intensify our efforts
to be holy and reject all badness.
Who do you think are Satan’s primary targets?
We are.
He and the demons are
like a pack of hungry lions
looking to devour us.
Being a publisher of the good news
is a privilege that Satan seeks to attack.
Are you a parent with children?
Do you think Satan
wants you to become unclean?
Yes.
He knows that devouring a family head
could weaken an entire family.
In the congregation,
Satan would love to devour
you dear pioneers,
ministerial servants, and elders.
Are you in the circuit work?
a missionary? a Bethelite?
What a sacred privilege!
But remember, it also means
that we have a big target on our back.
Satan and the demons would love
to penetrate our clean and holy position.
Doing so could impact
the Kingdom work
or stumble others.
So we can’t be complacent.
We must intensify our efforts
to reject all badness.
Thus, holiness is a vital topic!
To that end,
the theme for this month’s program
is “Perfecting Holiness in the Fear of God.”
It’s based on 2 Corinthians 7:1.
To begin, we need to better understand
the Source of holiness, Jehovah God.
As we read the Bible, we see that holiness
is an important quality
that Jehovah wants us to know about him.
The Bible contains many verses
that associate God’s name
with the words “holy” and “holiness.”
Please open your copy of the Bible
to one example in Isaiah chapter 6.
We’ll start at Isaiah 6:1.
Now imagine that you’re the prophet Isaiah,
who received a divine vision.
What would you have seen and heard?
Let’s read verses 1 to 3:
“In the year that King Uzziah died,
“I saw Jehovah sitting
on a lofty and elevated throne,
“and the skirts
of his robe filled the temple.
“Seraphs were standing above him;
“each had six wings.
“Each covered his face with two
and covered his feet with two,
“and each of them would fly about with two.
“And one called to the other:
“‘Holy, holy, holy is Jehovah of armies.
The whole earth is filled with his glory.’”
Isaiah was likely filled with awe.
Verse 2 indicates that he saw seraphs,
spirit creatures evidently of very high rank.
What do we learn from their song?
Their repeating the word “holy” three times
teaches us that Jehovah
is holy to the superlative degree.
No one else is as holy as he is.
But what exactly is holiness?
What does it mean to be holy?
Let’s dig deeper.
We can do so with a helpful tool found
in the revised New World Translation.
If you don’t have
the revised edition in your language,
we’ll share the key point in just a moment.
In the revised printed edition,
the glossary is located
several pages after Revelation
and immediately after
the “Bible Words Index.”
The topics are arranged alphabetically.
So please find the entry
for “Holy; Holiness.”
If you are using JW Library®,
here are two ways to get to the glossary.
In the app, go to the Bible.
Then at the top of the screen,
tap on the magnifying glass
to start a search.
Then type in the word “holy.”
Soon you’ll see an entry from the glossary.
Tap on that.
Another way is to go to Publications
and then Books.
From there you can open the glossary
and find the entry for “holy.”
Ready?
Let’s read it:
“A quality possessed inherently by Jehovah;
“a state of absolute
moral purity and sacredness.
“When referring to humans, animals, things,
“places, time periods, and activities,
“the original Hebrew word conveys the thought
“of separateness, exclusiveness,
“or sanctification to the holy God;
“a state of being set aside
for Jehovah’s service.
“In the Christian Greek Scriptures,
“the words rendered ‘holy’ and ‘holiness’
“likewise denote separation to God.
“The words are also used to refer
to purity in one’s personal conduct.”
What did we learn?
First, we’re reminded that Jehovah is pure
in the absolute sense.
But what does it mean that holiness
is a quality that he possesses inherently?
Let’s illustrate.
Consider the words “human” and “imperfect.”
Today, those two words naturally go together.
Imperfection is within all of us
and affects everything we do.
Now consider another set of words
that consistently go together:
“Jehovah” and “holy.”
Holiness permeates Jehovah.
He doesn’t have to perfect
holiness like we do.
Everything about him
is inherently clean,
pure, and upright.
What a contrast
Jehovah’s holiness is to the world around us!
Today, virtually everything
about human society alienated from God
is polluted in some way,
either by inherited imperfection
or by outright wickedness.
But Jehovah
is completely removed from sinfulness.
He’ll never be polluted by badness.
He’ll never turn corrupt,
immoral, or abusive.
Because he’s absolutely holy,
he’s completely reliable.
This means that Jehovah is the ideal Father.
How encouraging and reassuring!
Jehovah’s holiness is beautiful.
Think about the physical world.
How do you feel about beautiful things?
Are you drawn to them or repelled by them?
For example, look at these landscapes.
How do they make you feel?
Would you like to spend time here?
Can you see yourself walking here,
filling your lungs with clean, fresh air?
Or how about drinking
from a river of pure, crystal-clear water?
How we yearn to live in such conditions!
And we will!
But have you ever wondered what it is
about these images that’s so appealing?
Simply put, everything is pure and clean.
On the other hand, if these same locations
were filled with garbage, graffiti, and smog,
would you still want to be there?
Likely not.
Pollution and filth are not attractive.
What’s the point?
We’re naturally drawn to beauty.
Beauty is associated with things
that are clean, pure, and bright.
That’s how Jehovah
wants us to view his holiness.
Meditating on this aspect
of God’s personality
draws us closer to him.
And though he hates all sin,
his Word confirms that he doesn’t hate us.
All of this stirs within us
a desire to perfect holiness.
Let’s now open to 2 Corinthians 7:1,
our theme scripture.
Though Paul wrote this to one congregation,
Jehovah preserved it for us.
It says:
“Therefore, since we have these promises,
“beloved ones, let us cleanse ourselves
“of every defilement of flesh and spirit,
perfecting holiness in the fear of God.”
The concluding part of the verse
serves as the basis for our theme.
What does it mean to perfect something?
According to one dictionary,
to “perfect” means
“to bring to a state of supreme excellence,”
to “rid of faults,” to “improve” or “refine.”
As an example, perhaps you enjoy a hobby
like drawing, taking photographs,
or playing an instrument.
If an expert in that field told you
that you should perfect  your talent,
what would he mean?
First, he’s confirming
that you have some experience already.
Second, he’s telling you:
“You have what it takes
to be even better in the future.
I can see your potential!”
Of course, perfecting a hobby takes time.
The same is true of our holiness.
The book
Word Pictures in the New Testament  notes
that the word “perfecting”
at 2 Corinthians 7:1
means “not a sudden attainment
of complete holiness,
but a continuous process.”
So Jehovah, the expert in holiness
and our best Friend, is appealing to us.
In effect, he’s saying:
‘I see your potential!
‘You have what it takes
to make progress in holiness.
Keep working to perfect it!’
Does such an appeal touch your heart?
We could ask ourselves,
‘Is there an area in my life
where I can refine my holiness?’
For example, consider the matter
of physical cleanness.
Chapter 8 of the book
How to Remain in God’s Love
discusses the need to glorify Jehovah
by keeping our body and clothing,
our home and surroundings,
and our place of worship clean.
Being physically clean
benefits us and those around us.
More important, it honors our Holy Father.
But our personal cleaning program
must go below the surface.
In our theme text, Jehovah urges us
to “cleanse ourselves
of every defilement of flesh and spirit.”
This involves every aspect of our lives.
For example, something we read in the Bible
or that we hear at a meeting may warn us
that our thoughts need further refinement.
Perhaps we detect
a tendency toward materialism.
Or we realize that our precious time
is being consumed by social media,
surfing the Internet, or playing video games.
At Ephesians 4:23, 24, we’re urged
to “continue to be made new
in [our] dominant mental attitude”
and to “put on the new personality.”
So our challenge might be
a deeply ingrained,
negative personality trait.
A sister named Cristina admitted:
“I often find myself
looking enviously at others.
I compare what they have
with what I don’t have.”
Well, these are just a few examples.
And these may not be our weaknesses,
but the lesson is clear:
All of us need to keep examining ourselves.
And, brothers and sisters,
when we identify a personal weakness,
what should we do?
For illustration purposes,
let’s use the example
of Cristina and her battle with envy.
A three-step program
to change our dominant mental attitude
was published on page 11 of the June 2019
study edition of The Watchtower.
What’s the first thing Cristina should do?
Step 1: She needs to talk to Jehovah,
admitting that she recognizes
the need to change.
If she prays regularly
for Jehovah
to “put within [her] a new spirit,”
our holy God will help her.
Step 2: She needs to meditate
so as to examine herself
in the mirror of God’s Word.
For example, she might think deeply
about the fact that “love is not jealous”
and “does not look for its own interests.”
This would help Cristina to hate envy.
Step 3:
She needs to assess her relationships
and choose good association.
Could it be that negative gossip,
either in person or online,
is shaping her thinking?
If so, she’d be wise
to choose better association.
Yes, Jehovah’s blessing
upon Cristina’s personal efforts
will enable her to perfect holiness.
These three steps can help us do the same.
Let’s now review our key points.
First, wickedness
is going “from bad to worse,”
so we need to intensify
our efforts to be holy.
Second, since Jehovah
is the Source of holiness,
everything about him
is clean, pure, and upright.
This beautiful quality draws us to him
and moves us to be holy.
Third and most important,
Jehovah appeals to us
to “cleanse ourselves
of every defilement of flesh and spirit.”
So may we accept Jehovah’s help
and work to perfect holiness in God’s fear.
Even as we strive to perfect holiness,
we don’t look down on people
who have been molded by the world around us.
In the following experience from Italy,
notice how a group of young men
who had a rough start in life
were drawn to the truth
and what a courageous sister did
to reach their hearts.
Our parents loved us,
but they did it in the wrong way.
They would often turn violent,
so we learned that way of life.
I remember that ever since I was young,
I was afraid of coming home one day
and not finding my parents together.
Because as far back as I remember,
they have always argued with each other.
So we grew up with those values
and those ways of thinking
that led us to become
a group that was known and feared
in the area
because of our violent, immoral lifestyle
that was devoted to drugs.
We had no rules!
We were people
that you should stay away from.
It was one of those regular mornings
when we were home alone.
And it became our hideout
—the place we would meet.
We had skipped school,
and our parents didn’t know.
I was with Federico
and Raffaele when two sisters,
two of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
rang the doorbell.
So we had them come in,
so we could make fun of them.
And as a matter of fact, that’s what we did.
I remember that Maria
and the sister that was with her
were two very sincere and genuine people.
They showed courage
as they brought us the truth.
I was surprised that they were so kind,
despite that my tone of voice was mocking.
And I really appreciated their kindness.
She didn’t let anything stop her,
not even the way we looked.
I was really touched
by the conversation with Maria,
but I thought I would never see her again.
Who would ever come back to people like us?
Maria didn’t give up.
She came back with an older pioneer brother
who wasn’t scared of us
and with courage started to preach.
I really started
to change my life and make progress.
Immediately, I started to speak
about what I
was learning with all my friends.
What surprised me was my mother’s reaction.
She wasn’t happy at all.
She reacted really violently.
They thought that I was going mad
—that I was being brainwashed.
I remember that they
would do everything to remind me
of the strong friendship that was between us.
So they would put pressure on me emotionally.
I had to make a choice.
Although I did love them
and was close to them,
I made the drastic decision to tell them
that from then on I would no longer
be staying in their company.
This situation made me really intrigued.
In fact, I ended up studying with Francesco.
His determination really made me think.
It was obvious
that the things he was telling us
were actually real—it was the truth.
And also, the strength
it took to go forward with this
—his determination to leave his friends—
was surely what made
all of us seriously interested
in the message he was preaching.
I would blame it on the truth
because it was taking my friend away from me
—a friend with whom
I used to do the things I liked.
However, inside I knew that even though
I told him he had gone mad,
I knew that inside
there must have been something powerful
because he was so convinced,
and we could all sense his conviction.
So I realized
that there was really something there.
To my surprise, one after the other,
all of my friends started studying the Bible.
As I studied,
I realized that it was the truth.
It used to be hatred
that always motivated my choices.
Now I act according to love,
and this makes me feel good.
I can now say that thanks to Maria
and Francesco,
Jehovah tried to draw me to Him.
I believe it’s been a miracle from Jehovah.
The truth helped me cultivate the qualities
of peace and joy
—the personality that has made it possible
for me to have the family I never had.
The greatest satisfaction I have in life
is to have a relationship with Jehovah.
When I see someone
like we used to be,
I feel motivated to speak to them.
The patience that Maria showed
motivates me to be patient.
Despite our reputation,
Maria did not give up.
She showed us
that in Jehovah’s eyes,
no one is beyond recovery
—no one.
Before they found the truth,
those young men were, as they put it,
“people that you should stay away from.”
Would you have hesitated to give a witness?
Our sister Maria didn’t.
And did you notice what our brother did
when he embraced the truth?
He went to his friends
and broke off his association.
He knew he needed friends
who shared his determination to serve God.
So do we.
We see the wonderful results.
All of them are now brothers.
They cleansed themselves.
And what was
the most meaningful transformation?
Our brother said it:
‘It used to be hatred
that motivated my choices.
Now it’s love.’
Whether we’re new in the truth
or have served Jehovah for decades,
we can perfect holiness
and move forward as spiritual people.
We’ll see that in our next segment.
Look for how our brothers
applied good suggestions from The Watchtower.
The challenge of serving
in a foreign country can sometimes be that
because you’ve made that move
and you’ve learned a foreign language,
you can feel like you’ve done enough.
I was brought up by a Witness mother,
so I studied the Bible since I was small.
So I thought I had
Bible knowledge to some extent.
My wife and I have enjoyed
the traveling work for 18 years.
As we get older,
trials that we never experienced
when we were young
have come up one after another.
After I got married and had children,
I had a hard time explaining
the backgrounds
of some Bible characters or Biblical history
when I studied the Bible with my children.
Then I realized
that I did not have enough Bible knowledge.
And another challenge can be
that you’re dealing
with a foreign culture in the territory,
but you also have
many different cultures in the congregation.
When I struggle
to fulfill various responsibilities
in a balanced way
—things such as caring for aged parents
and our own health issues—
it can be a source of stress
and cause tension between my wife and me.
The study article
“Move Forward as a Spiritual Person!”
in February 2018 was a big help.
The expressions:
“Once we have
identified areas for improvement,
we need to take positive steps”
and that “it is a life-and-death matter”
really touched my heart.
I realized
that I needed to scrutinize my life seriously
and make improvements
for my own future and that of my family.
The article had a quote
from Brother Barr that said:
“Many fail because they
are not diligent enough to grow mighty.”
This made me think,
‘Am I mighty enough
to overcome any challenges
‘that might come up,
difficulties with brothers and sisters,
in a way that pleases Jehovah?’
To move ahead as a spiritual person,
I realized that I needed
to get Jehovah’s thinking on matters
and really look at Bible principles.
And that means letting go of my pride;
and when it comes back,
letting go of it again
and really making
Jehovah’s thoughts my own thoughts.
I have a bad tendency to try to do everything
by myself and to not
delegate things to others.
I asked myself,
‘What decision will please Jehovah?’
“Make sure of the more important things.”
I felt the need to train
younger brothers in the congregation
so that I could delegate
responsibilities to them.
The article encouraged us
to look to Bible principles.
And two that really helped me
were Proverbs 15:28 and Philippians 2:4
because it helped me to think
about what is in the person’s best interests
before I respond to them.
I took time when reading Bible accounts
to meditate on how I would feel
if I were one of those Bible characters.
I can now explain things better
at my children’s study.
I’m very happy to see my children
truly enjoying Christian activities.
My son started doing “play meetings” for fun.
My daughter loves the ministry.
She talks to people willingly,
not because we as parents
are telling her to do so.
Compared to how it was when I was a child,
things are totally different now,
and that really makes me happy.
By applying this principle,
I can lighten my load
and reduce my stress level.
In turn, that helps me to maintain joy,
to strengthen our relationship as a couple,
and I feel I’ve become
more approachable
to those in the congregation.
Having the “mind of Christ”
has helped me in my assignment
because it’s helped me to form
really close friendships
with the brothers and sisters
in my congregation, and that’s brought me
a lot of joy in my service.
And also, when I don’t know
what to do (which often happens),
I have Jehovah’s principles to guide me,
and that makes me feel safe and secure.
Family heads, did you notice
how Yusuke took to heart
the suggestion to analyze his life
and look for ways to improve?
He realized
that while he had some Bible knowledge,
he needed to deepen it
through study and meditation.
That made him
a more effective teacher for his children.
Jane was doing fine work
as a pioneer in a foreign land.
Yet, ironically, she had difficulty
with brothers and sisters
from different cultures.
Do we?
What stood in her way?
She said, ‘I had to let go of my pride.’
Once she did,
Jehovah’s thoughts became her thoughts.
Perhaps, like Yutaka Kimura,
you’re dealing
with changing life circumstances.
What do we learn from his example?
He delegated responsibilities
and reordered his priorities.
That took humility.
The result?
Reduced stress and increased joy.
Often, honest self-examination
reveals the root cause
of something we need to adjust.
We’ll see that
in the following dramatization.
I embarrassed my wife tonight.
I knew when it happened,
and I didn’t want to talk about it.
But I knew in my heart that Yoomi was right.
I had become unkind.
There were lots of examples.
I’d complained about the way one brother
conducted meetings for field service.
I was jealous
of a ministerial servant
who received new privileges.
And I was pretty blunt
about how frustrated I got
with Yoomi’s parents.
I thought I’d gotten rid
of my old personality,
but it still lurked inside of me.
Some of my friends
were OK with and even encouraged
these bad qualities.
The change was so gradual
that I didn’t even realize
how far I’d fallen.
What do you think I need to do to change?
How about we search
for “good for building up”
from the ONLINE LIBRARY?
Sounds good.
Let’s take a look.
We considered Ephesians 4:29,
which says:
“Let a rotten word
not come out of your mouth,
“but only what is good
for building up . . . ,
to impart what is beneficial
to the hearers.”
I was struck by this powerful word picture.
Rotten words are as disgusting
as rotten food.
I didn’t want the things
coming out of my mouth
to disgust my wife or anyone else.
But to change,
I needed a plan.
Now I really try to think before I speak.
And I have a goal to give someone
real commendation at every meeting.
I have a goal for my conversations too.
I want to keep them
wholesome, true, and kind.
It’s amazing how speaking kindly to others
can make you feel so good inside.
I shouldn’t be surprised,
because it’s just another way
of showing God’s love.
I don’t think I’ll ever forget
that image of the rotten fruit.
But isn’t that the point?
No one wants their words
and conversations to be like that.
We want to perfect holiness
with clean conversations.
How do we keep our speech
upbuilding and kind?
Like our brother,
we need to look within ourselves.
What’s causing us to say hurtful things?
He discovered
the “old personality” still lurking inside,
and he realized that some of his friends
were actually
encouraging his critical attitude.
But he did more than analyze himself.
He made a plan and set goals.
As his thinking changed, so did his speech.
That drew people to him,
and he felt good inside.
As that brother realized,
sometimes even without noticing it,
we could move backward spiritually.
We need to move forward, perfecting holiness.
We’ll next hear from a brother
who took more than a step or two backward.
Notice what helped him
regain his relationship with Jehovah.
My first contact
with the Witnesses was in my 20’s.
As my knowledge increased,
I made drastic changes.
I quit smoking
and stopped swearing and using drugs.
I also changed my violent behavior.
I completely gave up martial arts,
and then I was baptized
as one of Jehovah’s Witnesses.
It was an amazing day
that I will never forget.
Shortly after my baptism,
I became quite involved
in my work at the theater.
The environment there
was very immoral, you know.
Even after several loving warnings
from brothers in the congregation
advising me to look for another job,
I chose not to follow their advice.
I’d worked there for a long time,
so I thought, ‘I can handle it.’
But I was wrong.
My conscience became dull,
and I committed
a serious sin against Jehovah.
When I left the truth,
several offers came my way.
I became a manager at a nightclub
that was open until six in the morning.
It was a lot of parties,
and it was a lot of drugs.
I also resumed martial arts.
I came in contact with serious criminals
and gradually became friends
with the most influential person
in the criminal underworld in Oslo.
Eventually,
I was imprisoned for my violent behavior.
A Christian movement
visited the prison where I was,
and all of the inmates were invited
to an event where there would be cake served.
That sounded very interesting.
I was tempted by a cake.
They also played music.
But after a while,
they started speaking in tongues,
and I felt very uncomfortable.
I didn’t want to be involved in that,
but I couldn’t get up.
Even though I was big and strong back then,
I physically couldn’t stand up from my chair.
I’ve experienced a lot in my life,
but at that moment,
I was genuinely scared.
So I cried out to Jehovah,
and immediately I was released,
and I was able to get up and leave.
This big man was now
in a fetal position, crying.
And then I called my wife
and asked her to bring me a Bible
and some literature.
I had to start studying again
and draw close to Jehovah.
The greatest challenge was prayer
—to start communicating with Jehovah again
after being so far away from him,
doing all these bad things.
You know, it was a long way to go.
One scripture I especially remember
is Isaiah 1:18, where He says:
“Come, now,
and let us set matters straight between us.”
That touched me deeply.
He also says
that if ‘your sins are red like scarlet,’
Jehovah will make them “white as snow.”
It felt like he separated the darkness
and stretched out his hand
and pulled me out,
back into the light again.
Six months after I was reinstated,
my wife decided to dedicate her life
to Jehovah and was baptized.
She has been a huge support during my return.
I was very nervous at first,
but when I entered the Kingdom Hall,
that feeling just disappeared.
God’s spirit is here.
The way the brothers and sisters
acted toward each other
was such a contrast to my former lifestyle.
We feel deeply blessed by Jehovah.
Of course, you make mistakes once in a while,
but now I feel confident
that Jehovah is merciful.
At his lowest point, Petter said
he felt ‘so far away from Jehovah.’
If you can relate
to his situation in some way,
be assured that you too
can “set matters straight.”
You can experience what Petter did
—Jehovah helped him
out of the darkness into the light again.
Remember, Jehovah is saying to you
and to all of us: ‘I see your potential.
You have what it takes.’
Today, some of the greatest challenges
are faced by our young people.
This month’s music video
was made especially for them.
It’s entitled
“Fight the Fine Fight of the Faith.”
Some days I feel I’ve had enough.
The war in my mind can get so tough.
There’s days I feel there’s no way out.
In a flood of tears, I’m sinking down.
In my despair, he sees me through.
When I am crushed, I know just what to do.
I need his words of truth.
I can hear Jehovah saying:
‘Just a little while longer,
And I will wipe out ev’ry tear.
The new world is in sight.
‘Just keep on holding tight.
‘I’ll help you win this fight—
Fight.
I’ll help you win this fight.’
Reading his Word
gives me the power.
When storms in life come,
he’s my strong Tower.
In my despair, he pulls me through.
When I am down, I know just what to do.
I need his words of truth.
I can hear Jehovah saying:
‘Just a little while longer,
And I will wipe out ev’ry tear.
The new world is in sight.
‘Just keep on holding tight.
‘I’ll help you win this fight—
Fight.
‘I’ll help you win this fight.
I’ll help you win this fight.
I’ll help you win this fight.’
‘I’ll help you win this fight,
Help you win this fight,
Help you win this fight.’
‘Just a little while longer,
And I will wipe out ev’ry tear.
The new world is in sight.
Just keep on holding tight.
I’ll help you win this fight.’
What a beautiful song
and a beautiful reminder!
Jehovah does help us
to win our “fight of the faith.”
In what ways?
As we saw in the video, he helps us
through our family and fellow worshippers,
through the ministry,
and through his Word, the Bible.
Preserving God’s Word and his personal name
has been a fierce fight over many centuries
—a fight that’s being won.
This is the subject of the Bible Museum
at world headquarters in Warwick, New York.
Let’s take a brief tour.
The Bible is a modern-day treasure.
It reveals the satisfying truth about God,
life, and our hope for the future.
What’s more,
it contains another priceless treasure
—God’s personal name, Jehovah.
How Jehovah preserved his name
in the Holy Scriptures,
against all attempts to remove it,
is a fascinating story.
And it’s told here in the Bible Museum
at world headquarters in Warwick.
Let’s take the tour.
At the museum’s entry,
the divine name is shown in various languages
a total of 7,216 times.
That’s how many times it appears
in the New World Translation
of the Holy Scriptures.
Jehovah always made his name known,
even to the very first humans.
When Cain was born,
Eve declared:
“I have produced a male child
with the help of Jehovah.”
After that time,
people knew and used God’s name.
The oldest example
of the divine name in Hebrew letters
is on the Moabite Stone
from the ninth century B.C.E.
Moabite King Mesha
boasted against Israel:
“I took from it the vessels of Jehovah,
and offered them before Chemosh.”
There’s also evidence that in ancient times
God’s name was used in everyday life.
This silver scroll
from the seventh century B.C.E.
is the earliest known inscription
of a Bible text containing God’s name.
It reads:
“May Jehovah bless you and keep you.
May Jehovah make his face to shine on you.”
Most important, God’s name
was in ancient copies of the Bible text.
The Fouad Papyrus
from the first century B.C.E.
is a fragment of the Greek Septuagint,
the first known translation
of the Hebrew Scriptures into Greek.
Here’s Deuteronomy 32:3:
“For I will declare the name of Jehovah.”
Although the text is in Greek,
the divine name is written in Hebrew.
Greek-speaking Jews
in Jesus’ day used the Septuagint.
So when Jesus read and taught
from the Scriptures,
people heard him use the divine name.
Sadly, though,
by the third century C.E.,
God’s name was removed
from the Septuagint
and replaced with the title “Lord.”
As an example,
the Vatican Codex
from the fourth century C.E.
includes the text
of the Greek Septuagint
but omits God’s name.
Deuteronomy 32:3 here reads:
“For I will declare the name of the LORD.”
But Jehovah
wouldn’t allow his name to be lost.
It was never removed
from Hebrew copies of the Bible.
The Aleppo Codex
was copied by Jewish scribes
around the year 930 C.E.
The same verse,
Deuteronomy 32:3, says in Hebrew:
“For I will declare the name of Jehovah.”
Still,
for centuries, most people didn’t have
a Bible in their own language,
nor one that contained God’s name.
The Latin Vulgate,
translated around 405 C.E.,
omitted the divine name.
It became the official translation
of the Catholic Church for over 1,000 years.
But a new technology triggered events
that would soon make
the Bible widely available
and in fresh translations
that returned God’s name
to its rightful place.
About 1453,
Johannes Gutenberg
produced an important edition
of the Latin Vulgate.
It was the first Bible
printed using movable type.
This is an original page
from a Gutenberg Bible.
While only some 180 Bibles were made,
his invention sparked a printing revolution.
Just 20 years later,
Anton Koberger was printing
up to 1,000 Bibles per run,
making it the first mass-produced Bible.
On display is an original copy
of the second edition
of Koberger’s Latin Bible from 1477.
Then, in the early 1500’s,
Bible scholars took a renewed interest
in the original Bible languages.
For the very first time,
the original-language Hebrew
and Greek Scriptures were printed together.
This is the Complutensian Polyglot,
printed between 1514 and 1517.
A polyglot is a book
with text in several languages
arranged in columns.
In the Complutensian Polyglot,
the Bible text appears in Latin,
Hebrew, Aramaic, and Greek.
Comparing the Hebrew text with the Latin,
scholars could see where God’s name
had been replaced
in the Latin Vulgate with “LORD.”
But would seeing the divine name
in the original Hebrew text
lead Bible translators to restore
God’s name in their translations?
Indeed, some did!
In 1551,
Sebastian Castellio published
his fresh Latin translation of the Bible.
He appears to be the first
to use God’s name consistently
in a Latin translation
of the Hebrew Scriptures.
Translations into other languages
were also using God’s name.
In 1530, William Tyndale
published his English translation
of Genesis through Deuteronomy.
It was the first time
that the divine name appeared
in any English Bible.
The popular Reina-Valera Spanish Bible
was published in 1602.
It contains the divine name
throughout the Hebrew Scriptures.
This is a rare original first edition
of the English King James Version
of the Bible, published in 1611.
It uses the name Jehovah
in just four passages.
Still, the King James Version became
the most widely printed book in the world.
Some 200 years later,
Benjamin Boothroyd,
a minister and Hebrew scholar,
set out to revise the King James Version.
His 1817 translation
was the first English Bible
to use the divine name throughout
the Hebrew Scriptures.
Meanwhile, church missionaries
were taking the Bible to new lands.
But without the divine name,
people couldn’t distinguish
the God of the Bible
from their own false gods.
So Bible translations
in many languages of Asia,
Africa, the Pacific islands,
and the Americas included God’s name.
The Chinese Delegate’s Version from 1854
is an example of a missionary Bible
that uses God’s name throughout
the Hebrew Scriptures.
Still, there was
one more place where God’s name
was not yet restored
—the Christian Greek Scriptures.
This is the Nuremberg Polyglot,
published by Elias Hutter in 1599.
It contains the Christian Greek Scriptures
in 12 languages, including Hebrew.
Here,
John’s Gospel
quotes Psalm 118:26:
“Blessed is the one who comes
in Jehovah’s name.”
In his Hebrew translation of the Gospel,
Hutter preserved the divine name
in the quotation
from Psalms.
He did this in many other places
in the Greek Scriptures.
Translators had a precedent
to use God’s name
in the Christian Greek Scriptures
where the name appeared
in verses quoted from the Hebrew Scriptures.
This is the 1864 sixth edition
New Testament translation
by Herman Heinfetter.
It’s likely the first published
English Bible to use God’s name
in more than 100 places
in the Christian Greek Scriptures.
The New World Translation
of the Holy Scriptures
was first published between 1950 and 1960.
Its translators benefited
from the scholarly work of those before them
who had chosen to preserve God’s name
in their Bible translations.
Today, the New World Translation
is available in whole or in part
in over 170 languages.
God’s name, Jehovah,
belongs in the Holy Scriptures he inspired.
This gallery holds just a small part
of the overwhelming evidence to this fact.
The Bible is a precious gift from God,
teaching us
about his works, his qualities,
and his loving purpose
for humankind.
He invites each of us to read it,
to draw close to him, and to know him
by his most holy name, Jehovah.
Our program has focused
on “perfecting holiness in God’s fear.”
“Perfecting holiness” may sound out of reach,
but remember, it’s a continuous process.
We saw this with those young men in Italy
who left behind
their violent and immoral ways.
And with Jane, Yusuke, and Yutaka,
we saw experienced Christians who found ways
to grow as spiritual people.
We learned how to make
our speech more upbuilding
by examining our motives and associations.
Petter Heinrichs’ experience demonstrates
that it’s possible
to return to Jehovah with His help.
Finally, our music video reminds us
that despite the unique pressures
our young people face,
they’re winning the fight.
We close with a visit
to our brothers and sisters in Puerto Rico.
Secluded beaches, lush valleys, mountains
—this beautiful island is home
to more than 3 million inhabitants
and nearly 24,000 Jehovah’s Witnesses.
But its location in the Caribbean
puts Puerto Rico in the path
of tropical storms and hurricanes.
One of the most powerful ever,
Hurricane Maria,
struck two years ago.
Lives were lost, and homes were destroyed.
The entire island
lost electricity for months.
To help with relief efforts,
thousands of brothers and sisters
from Puerto Rico
and from across the United States
branch territory volunteered.
They repaired and rebuilt
106 Kingdom Halls, 2 Assembly Halls,
and more than 800 homes of our brothers.
The Barahona Congregation,
located in the middle of the island,
was enjoying their circuit overseer visit
when the hurricane hit.
The body of elders and the circuit overseer
immediately organized and reached out
to everyone in the congregation.
Despite the devastation,
the Sunday meeting took place as scheduled.
In fact, despite dealing
with challenging conditions for many months,
the congregation
didn’t cancel a single meeting.
Within a few days of Hurricane Maria,
the organized preaching work resumed
and our brothers were back in the field.
The response has been encouraging.
Fifty Bible studies are now being conducted.
The 117 publishers
in the Barahona Congregation
send you
their warm Christian love and greetings.
From the World Headquarters
of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
this is JW Broadcasting.