Welcome to this month’s broadcast.
Here are a few highlights
of what we’ll enjoy on the program.
What if changing circumstances in the family
begin pushing mates apart emotionally?
This dramatization of Shaan and Kiara
may provide some timely guidance.
Also, the story of Grace Li
will be an encouragement to any who have faced
severe emotional challenges
for taking a stand for the truth.
You’ll see the effect
that her actions had on those around her.
And this month’s music video
will reassure us of the love, kindness,
and support we enjoy as Jehovah’s people.
All that and more on this February 2019 edition
of JW Broadcasting!
The theme of this program
is taken from the second part
of Romans 12:10:
“In showing honor to one another,
take the lead.”
What is honor?
In the Hebrew Scriptures,
the term translated “honor”
literally means “heaviness.”
So when we honor someone,
we’re acknowledging that he’s weighty
or that he amounts to something.
In the Greek Scriptures,
the word is related
to setting a price on something,
meaning that the one we honor
is esteemed or has value.
Whom should we honor?
Of course, Jehovah is worthy of honor.
Revelation 4:11 says this
and gives us the reason
for giving glory and honor to Jehovah.
It says because he “created all things.”
He is responsible
for us having life in the first place.
How do we give him honor?
There are many ways:
We honor him by doing his will
—obeying his laws and principles.
We honor him
by extolling his qualities and promises
—telling others
about these gifts from God.
We show him honor
by contributing financially
to the worldwide educational work
that he’s directing
through his Son and holy spirit.
And just as Revelation chapter 4 said
about Jehovah being worthy of the honor,
Revelation 5:12
says that his Son, Christ Jesus,
is worthy of the same.
Verse 12 says of Jesus:
“They were saying with a loud voice:
“‘The Lamb who was slaughtered
“‘is worthy to receive
the power and riches and wisdom
and strength and honor
and glory and blessing.’”
How do we show honor to Jesus?
One way is acknowledged
in the verse we just read.
He was “slaughtered”
like a sacrificial lamb
so that we might have the hope
of everlasting life.
We highly esteem,
and value, that sacrifice.
We honor Jesus
by recognizing his role
as an immortal
“King of kings” in the heavens.
And another
very practical way to honor Jesus
is to strive to imitate
his life and personality
as the model for us to follow closely.
If we take the lead in showing honor,
who else will we view
as highly valued
—to be treated with esteem?
Ephesians 6:1, 2 says
that children ‘honor their father and mother’
when they’re obedient to them.
Matthew 15:4-6
makes it clear that adult children
honor their parents and grandparents
by giving material assistance
to them as needed.
First Timothy 5:17
urges us to give elders “double honor”
because of their hard work in our behalf.
Romans 13:1, 7
even extends
the matter of showing honor
to governmental rulers
and others in authority.
First Peter 2:17
broadens the meaning
of honor even further saying:
“Honor men of all sorts.”
In addition to being kind
and respectful to people in general,
we also honor them
by being willing
to spend time
sharing the good news with them.
Ephesians 5:22-25
appeals to wives
to honor their husbands
by having Christlike subjection for them.
Husbands are to honor their wives
by showing them love
and treating them
just as Jesus treated the congregation.
And what about our theme text
for this discussion?
Who was Paul addressing
in Romans chapter 12 when he said:
“In showing honor to one another,
take the lead”?
Who are
the “one another” in that verse?
Look at Romans 1:7 with me.
Paul says he’s writing
“to all those who are in Rome
as God’s beloved ones,
called to be holy ones.”
So all of us
in the Christian congregation
are to have honor for each other.
I’d like to spend
the balance of my time
discussing two
of the many opportunities
we have to show honor
(they’re the last two
that I just referenced):
first, marriage mates
showing honor to each other,
and second, showing honor
to one another in our congregations.
Marriages in general today
are seriously lacking in honor.
Marriage mates
often demean one another
with harsh words
and disrespectful attitudes.
Some in the world resort
to physical violence,
as if that somehow
makes the abusive one right
in his view of whatever the issue is.
And infidelity on the part
of one or both mates is so common
it doesn’t even
raise eyebrows anymore.
All of this is a gross
lack of honor in marriage.
But what about marriages
of those professing
to be Jehovah’s Witnesses?
We’re blessed
with so many marriages
that are wholesome and honorable.
True, none are perfect.
But how blessed we are
to have the truth
and to have learned to be
more and more Christlike with each other.
We’ve learned to shed things
that we heard when we were growing up.
However, the matter
of honoring our marriage mate
needs to be discussed.
While relatively few of our marriages
end up with some kind
of physical violence
and relatively few
end up in divorce,
what about having honor
in the marriage?
After living together
as husband and wife
for many months
or for years or even for decades,
familiarity can cause us
to treat each other
with less respect or honor
than when we were courting.
That isn’t right.
It isn’t Christlike.
But with our inherited imperfection,
we may succumb
to dishonorable words and behavior
with the one
that we promised to treasure
“until death do us part.”
How can we get a grip
on this trait and minimize the times
that we have
a clash of spirit and words?
First, let’s consider
the two basic responsibilities
assigned to marriage mates.
This is the foundation
that we can then build on to improve.
The role of the husband
is clearly stated
at 1 Corinthians 11:3.
And while some wives in society
may bristle at this thought,
wives serving Jehovah
are to embrace this thought.
It’s the arrangement of God.
First Corinthians 11:3 says:
“But I want you to know
that the head of every man is the Christ;
“in turn, the head
of a woman is the man;
in turn, the head of the Christ is God.”
God’s Word says
that “the head of a woman is the man.”
However, the head of the woman
is not to be a domineering man,
not an abusive man
—verbally or physically.
He is to imitate his head.
And who is that?
What did the first part
of the verse say?
“The head
of every man is the Christ.”
In fact, Ephesians chapter 5
strikes this fine balance
between being a head of the wife
and being
a loving head like the Christ.
Ephesians 5:22, 23 says:
“Let wives be in subjection
to their husbands as to the Lord,
“[But what of the disposition
of the husband?]
“because a husband
is head of his wife
“just as the Christ
is head of the congregation,
he being a savior of this body.”
That verse says it all.
Verse 33 of the same chapter says this:
“Each one of you
must love his wife as he does himself;
“on the other hand,
the wife should have
deep respect for her husband.”
There’s nowhere in God’s Word
that says that if one mate
pushes the other mate’s button
—emotionally—
that it cancels
the offended mate’s obligation
to be Christlike.
The problem is that
when one mate is offended or hurt,
it’s so easy to roll the eyes in disgust
or to lash back with a verbal insult.
Then the other mate fires back
with another harsh, cutting remark.
It’s like wind on a forest fire.
Tempers blaze,
and the evening goes up in smoke.
It’s not at all Christlike.
There is no honor shown
in such a conflagration.
It has to stop sooner rather than later.
The January 15, 2015,
issue of The Watchtower said this:
“Remember that marriage
is not a competition
“to find out who is stronger,
who can shout louder,
“or who can think
of the most cutting remark.
“True, we all have flaws,
and sometimes we upset others.
“But there is never a justifiable reason
“for either a husband or a wife
“to use sarcastic and demeaning speech,
or worse, to shove or hit each other.”
How can we change the atmosphere?
Someone needs to put out the fire
with the water of God’s Word.
Romans 12:10b, again:
“In showing honor
to one another, take the lead.”
One of the mates must take the lead
even if at the time
they’re apologizing for their own behavior
by acknowledging that they
didn’t respond in a Christlike way saying,
“Forgive me.”
That same issue
of The Watchtower cited two scriptures:
one for the husband
and one for the wife.
We’ll first read Proverbs 17:27.
Husbands, listen to this
and apply it prior to a rift
or even during the conflict.
Proverbs 17:27:
“A man of knowledge
restrains his words,
and a discerning man will remain calm.”
Husbands, does that describe us?
Now wives,
please locate Proverbs 31:26.
Does this describe your speech
even when some altercation occurs?
Proverbs 31:26:
“She opens her mouth in wisdom;
the law of kindness is on her tongue.”
Usually after a misunderstanding
and rash words have been said,
we feel miserable and upset.
We often chastise ourselves
for adding fuel to the fire.
How much better
to train ourselves to restrain our words
and remain calm and to speak
in wisdom and with kindness of tongue.
Meet Emil and Firuca Gârbovan
from Romania.
They’re good examples
of how the power of God’s Word
can mold and change
the attitudes of marriage mates
who are willing to be guided by it.
It was in 1983 when I met Firuca.
I already had two little girls.
One was seven years old,
and the other one was three.
I accepted to study the Bible.
My husband worked
as a warrant officer for the police,
so at the beginning,
I studied in secret.
Then I decided to tell him the truth.
When I found out
that my wife was studying the Bible
in order to become
one of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
I became very sad.
And I realized that our marriage
and our family was in danger
because I only knew bad things
about Jehovah’s Witnesses.
He threatened
he would divorce me, and he did.
The divorce was
a very difficult time in my life
because I was seven months pregnant
with our third daughter.
Following the divorce, my husband
was given the house and custody
of our two daughters.
I had to leave the house,
and I stayed for almost a year
with two families of our brothers.
I saw Jehovah’s love toward me,
and I loved Jehovah very much,
but I loved my husband too.
One day, as I was walking
and holding the little girl’s hand,
I saw Firuca’s husband walking toward me.
My heart stopped,
and I said to myself,
‘He is going to hit me!’
But Emil was a gentleman.
And he took the little girl in his arms,
talked to her for a few minutes,
and then he put her back down and left.
When I saw him leaving, I thanked Jehovah
because he didn’t beat me.
In 1990, I looked for my wife
and I told her
that I would like to remarry her
to reunite our family.
And, after a while, she agreed
and step-by-step I started to study.
In 2003, I became
one of Jehovah’s Witnesses.
I am very happy that I made this change,
and I regret that I didn’t do it sooner.
I personally saw
how the truth can change a person’s life,
even in my own family.
Currently, I serve as an elder.
And in 2010, I became a regular pioneer.
When I see Emil conduct
the Bible study next to me,
I feel like kneeling rather than standing
to thank Jehovah.
So to married couples
who love Jehovah we repeat:
“In showing honor . . . , take the lead.”
The principles just discussed
can also be applied
when showing honor
to others in the congregation.
Like the husband and wife
that we just discussed,
all of us should be improving
in imitating Jesus
and in ‘following his steps closely’
in all of our interactions
with fellow believers
in the congregation.
How do we show honor
to one another?
One way is well described
at 1 Corinthians 10:23, 24.
We show honor
when we put the other person’s feelings
and needs ahead of our own.
First Corinthians 10:23, 24:
“All things are lawful,
“but not all things are advantageous.
but not all things build up.
“Let each one keep seeking,
not his own advantage,
but that of the other person.”
We show honor
when we suppress our own rights.
What we do or say might be lawful,
but is it advantageous?
Will it build up?
Verse 24, then, concisely says it:
“Keep seeking,
not [our] own advantage [or right],
but that of the other person.”
We show honor to others
when we do good deeds for them.
Possibly, it’s even a humble task
that an elderly publisher needs done.
It could be offering to clean the house,
take them to the store,
or fill some other need.
The principle is at Luke 22:26:
“You, though,
are not to be that way.
“But let the one
who is the greatest among you
“become as the youngest,
and the one taking the lead
as the one ministering.”
Earlier, I cited 1 Timothy 5:17,
where we’re urged
to give elders “double honor”
because of their hard work in our behalf.
They’re also part
of our congregation and deserve honor.
In our August program last year,
Brother Lett helped us consider
much of what is involved.
You’ll recall that his subject was
“Appreciating Our ‘Gifts in Men.’”
We minister to or honor others
when we readily forgive them
if they’ve embarrassed us
or hurt our feelings.
Overall, Jehovah’s people do quite well
in honoring one another
in the congregation.
But here is the question:
Are we improving in this aspect
of our Christian personality?
In our theme scripture,
Paul didn’t just say
to honor one another.
He said to “widen out” or reach out
in this aspect of our Christian life.
His words were to “take the lead.”
If Paul had just said
to show honor to each other,
that would be like a teacher
urging a group
of literate students to learn to read.
If they’re literate,
they don’t need to learn to read.
But what might the teacher
be urging them to do?
He might encourage them
to read better, or to improve.
Love is the identifying mark
of Christ’s disciples.
So honor is something
we’ve learned to show.
However, like the teacher,
Paul is urging us
to improve in this area.
He said take the lead
in showing honor.
The footnote says
this could be rendered
taking the “initiative”
in showing honor.
Instead of waiting
for some obvious reason
to do good for others
—to commend someone,
to check on a shut-in—
look for opportunities
to take the initiative
to show honor in the family
and in our congregations.
Yes, “in showing honor . . . ,
take the lead”!
At times, changing circumstances
can make it challenging to show honor.
In this dramatization,
note how the husband and wife
adjusted to a change while learning new ways
to continue showing
love and honor to each other.
My name is Kiara,
and that’s my husband, Shaan.
Our son Akil moved out recently
to help where the need is greater.
I didn’t realize
just how much he made us laugh.
I miss that.
It’s just more quiet now.
But more than that,
I felt we were growing apart.
I tried talking to him.
It didn’t go well.
Ever since Akil left,
things have been off
between Kiara and I.
She is so serious now.
I wish she would just lighten up
and laugh more,
like when Akil was still here.
As much as I hated to admit it,
it felt like we were growing apart.
Even Akil noticed.
Anyway, can I ask you guys a question?
Are you both doing OK?
Because you don’t look OK.
Of course, we’re OK.
OK?
We’re doing wonderful, right?
Yeah, we’re doing good.
Everything is good.
Yeah.
We weren’t fooling anyone
—except maybe ourselves.
And for the first time,
we both revealed to each other
just how we had been really feeling.
We knew we were headed down
a dangerous path.
We had to do something
—fast.
We read aloud the scripture
at Romans 12:10:
“In showing honor to one another,
take the lead.”
We thought about Abraham and Sarah.
They weren’t perfect,
but they worked hard
to show honor to each other
by listening and by caring.
I told Kiara, “I know I can do better.”
And I wanted to
because I love her so much.
I told Shaan,
“Let’s both try to do better.”
So we did.
A few months later,
we decided to pioneer together.
Now it seemed we had
a lot to talk about.
I felt like I was seeing
a whole new side of Kiara.
Like Abraham and Sarah,
our marriage wasn’t perfect.
There are going to be stressful times.
But by working hard
to apply Bible principles,
we got through that rough patch
and it drew us even closer together.
First Corinthians 13:4, 7 tell us:
“Love is patient and kind”
and “bears all things,
believes all things,
hopes all things, endures all things.”
Our dramatization helped us
to see how love can adapt
to changing needs and circumstances.
But wouldn’t it be nice
to talk with some real-life examples
of those who have developed such skills?
Well, we have a special treat.
A longtime faithful couple
has joined us in the studio
—William and Angela Samuelson,
who serve at Patterson Bethel
in the United States.
Now, of course,
we’ve known each other for decades,
and I know you as Bill and Angie,
so that’s the way I’ll refer to you.
So nice that you
could be here and be interviewed.
What’s helped you both
maintain a happy marriage?
Well, we work as a team,
so we always check
with each other
before making decisions,
even in areas
where we wouldn’t necessarily have to
—it would be OK to go ahead.
But just out of respect,
we talk with each other
about any decisions that we make.
And, you know, Brother Morris,
we’ve been married 60 years now,
and we’ve never really had
a real serious argument.
We’ve had some disagreements
but nothing ever serious.
And whenever we have
those kind of words, why, we never use
demeaning language or say
derogatory things about each other,
and that makes me very happy.
Yeah, that’s commendable.
Early in our marriage,
there was one occasion
when Angie was upset
with me about something
—it could’ve been anything—
and in the conversation,
it obviously showed in her tone of voice.
So I explained to her
that she could say anything she wanted
as long as she smiled
when she said it.
Well, she tried,
and we both had a good laugh.
It’s very hard
to stay mad when you’re smiling.
Smiling—very, very good advice.
What about in the congregation?
How have you been able
to show each other honor there?
Well, when we have assignments
from the platform,
either of us, we work together.
Angie is much better
with grammar
and pronunciation than I am,
and so I’ll check
with her to make sure
that I’m saying things
as correctly as possible.
And she checks with me
on prophetic significance, for example,
or theocratic understanding
or procedure and timing.
Yes, and something
that’s very important
is when we do check
with each other, we’re not thin-skinned
about the advice
that we want to give each other.
I’ll call it advice.
And that makes life a lot easier.
We don’t get angry
because we’ve been told
we need to improve on something.
That’s excellent.
You also spent a long time
in the traveling work
before coming to Bethel.
We knew you in the traveling work
—early ’70’s and then later
when we were down South
and you were assigned down there.
What did you learn
about showing honor
in that avenue of service?
Well, as you say,
we were in the traveling work
for 33 years, just over.
And for most of those years,
we would have other assignments.
I would be working with the district
—now regional—
convention organization
or other assignments,
and it meant
that Angie would be alone
in the congregation.
She never complained;
nor did she become unduly inquisitive
about my assignment,
which sometimes would’ve been confidential.
When we had
an unexpected move that came up,
a change of assignment somewhere,
Angie would just pack
and be ready to go.
That’s right.
That was my job—packing.
And in the field ministry, Brother Morris,
we would usually be
in separate car groups
because Bill would work with the brothers
and I would work with the sisters.
And I really appreciated the fact
that he always made sure
I had a safe driver.
It worked out most of the time.
And if we had a territory
that was a little scary,
why, he made sure
that we were safe in the territory.
So I appreciated that very much.
In one congregation,
(you know, things
don’t always go the way we plan)
the brother scheduling the meals
had scheduled two families
for the same noon meal for us.
The one sister was deaf;
and she had always had
the traveling brother on a certain day;
and she didn’t hear
when she was told it wouldn’t be that day.
So she had gone ahead
and prepared a meal.
In the meantime,
we had been assigned to another home,
where they served us a full course
—or courses—
of an Italian meal.
While we were eating, we found out
that the other sister was waiting for us.
She would’ve been highly offended
if somebody didn’t come.
So I went to the Kingdom Hall
and handled the meeting
for field service after the meal,
and Angie went to the sister.
That sister would probably
still be mad at me if Angie hadn’t gone.
Boy, was I sleepy
that afternoon after two big meals.
I bet.
Well, you handled that very Christlike.
Now, as we mentioned,
your current assignment is here at Bethel.
How have you navigated
the unique challenges
of this form of service
while still honoring one another?
Well, as you know,
we work in different departments,
but we respect that some things
are confidential to that department.
So we don’t make
the work of our department
a major part of our conversation.
We could have an energy problem
at the end of the day after working all day,
so Bill is very considerate
about accepting too many social invitations.
Isn’t that nice?
And so we respect
each other’s limitations
when it comes to physical
and just energy in general.
Well, that’s certainly honoring each other.
Well, Bill and Angie,
those were practical
and encouraging comments.
We really thank you so much
for taking the time
and allowing us to interview you,
and we really appreciate
your good example all these decades.
Well, thank you.
Thank you.
While the Samuelsons
are a wonderful example to try to imitate,
we know that many marriages
may have a more difficult start,
or in some cases,
the mates may not share
the same spiritual values.
What can be done if we find this
to be true in our case?
Notice how sister Grace Li
from Great Britain dealt
with these challenges in her marriage.
I was born in Hong Kong in 1952.
When I was just over 14 years of age,
my mother sat me down and said,
“Look, there’s a marriage maker,
“and the gentleman has agreed
to take you as his wife.”
I was absolutely petrified!
I had never met him before.
There was actually
a 20-year difference
between our ages,
but I was willing to go through with it
because I love my mum.
I wanted her to be able
to have a chance of happiness.
I came to England,
and not long after that,
we started our first
Chinese take-away in that little town.
I had to work very hard
seven days a week
to help my husband
run the business.
I was the only Chinese woman
in the entire town.
I had nowhere
to ask for help
or advice,
so I had a really bad time.
When my second daughter was born,
one night
she just stopped breathing.
And a few minutes later,
the nurse came out and said,
“God wanted a flower for his garden,
and that’s
where your daughter has gone.”
So at that moment in time,
I was very angry.
And I felt sad and sorrow and lonely.
And I had horrible guilt:
“It’s my fault.
Or it’s God’s; it’s his fault.”
So I stopped praying to God.
One day, there was one very kind lady
who came and knocked on my door.
And then, eventually,
one day, the ladies stopped
and had a conversation,
and the conversation led
to why people die
and what happens
when they’re dead.
Knowing it’s nobody’s fault
—it’s just our imperfection—
I found it a great relief.
God did not punish me for that.
And from then on,
I started a Bible study with her.
But my study
was progressing very slow.
By that time, I had six children.
I also had to work full-time.
And also,
the lady didn’t speak Chinese,
and my English was no better
than her Chinese either.
Since I dedicated my life to Jehovah,
it’s not been easy.
As far as my husband was concerned,
his wife should be concentrating
on looking after the family
and the business
and shouldn’t be wasting time
on religions like that.
My mum, as well,
was very much against me
becoming one of Jehovah’s Witnesses.
My husband shouted at me.
Often he gave me a hard time
because I wanted to take
all my children to the meetings.
One day,
he wanted me to choose
between him or Jehovah.
And I prayed to Jehovah.
I said, “Jehovah, now is the time
I need your holy spirit to help me.”
And I said,
“My husband is a good man,
“and he deserves to know why
I chose this life.”
And I just felt so calm,
and then I turned around
and asked my husband:
“What do you think of me
since I became a Witness?
Am I a better wife,
or am I getting worse?”
So my husband said:
“Oh, OK then.
If that is the case,
go serve your God, Jehovah.”
Before my mother died,
my mother actually prayed to Jehovah
to thank him and to say
that since I became
one of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
I became a better daughter.
I remember, one day,
one of my Bible students
came to my house,
and she was crying
because she suffered
persecution from her husband.
And my husband
was sitting next to me,
and he turned around and said,
“You just have to persevere,
“because my wife went through
the same experience,
and look where she is now.”
For the last ten years,
my husband has come
to all the meetings with me.
Seeing my children happy
is the most important thing for me.
And they are happy
not only for a short time
but they also have a happy future.
My life now—I’m no longer lonely;
I’m no longer a fatherless child,
because I know Jehovah cares for me.
Jehovah helped a little woman like me,
and I’m sure Jehovah will help anybody
whose heart is toward him.
Sister Li’s example helps us to see
that even in spiritually divided homes,
applying Bible principles in our life
can often soften the heart
of our mate toward the truth.
Having seen some beautiful examples
of showing honor within our marriage,
let’s now look at ways of showing honor
to one another in the congregation.
For example,
what if we’re serving in a foreign territory
where the customs and culture
are quite different
from what we’re accustomed to?
This is just one of many challenges often faced
by ones involved
in the international construction work.
What have they found to be helpful
when adapting to new environments?
Did you notice the beautiful thought
that every culture has its own strong points
that we can learn from and apply in our lives?
What an excellent way to cultivate
an attitude of viewing others as superior!
But what about ones outside the congregation?
Do we show honor to them as well?
Of course.
Galatians 6:10 tells us:
“As long as we have the opportunity,
let us work what is good toward all.”
The best way we can do this is
by helping them cultivate
and satisfy their spiritual needs.
We now visit a town in the state
of Oregon in the United States
where the congregations
had a unique opportunity to do just this.
An exciting event took place
in 2017 across the United States.
August 21, 2017,
has been on a lot of people’s calendars
for a long time because of the total eclipse.
As Jehovah’s Witnesses,
we are constantly on the lookout
for events where we can support
community outreach.
Brothers and sisters
prepared well in advance
to give a Bible education
to the many travelers.
What convinced us
that this was an opportunity
to give a great witness
was that we did a little research,
and we noticed the hotel bookings.
The town was packed,
so we could tell
that this was going to be a big event.
We needed to do something.
We wanted to be in a position to share
the wonderful things from the Bible with them.
We needed to take a global approach.
We had to identify
all the resources in Bend
and not just do it
by individual congregation.
So in our campaign we decided
to feature three primary tools:
first, What Does the Bible Really Teach?
because many people wonder;
second, Was Life Created?
because with an eclipse event,
people are thinking about the universe,
and it’s a good opportunity
to talk about our Creator;
and third,
jw.org,
since we expect a lot of visitors
from all over the world,
we can reach them in their language.
Over 200 brothers and sisters
attended two seminars
put on by local brothers to help prepare
individuals for the massive campaign.
We had examples
of what not to do and what to do
so as to benefit
as many people as possible.
We had an interview;
we had demonstrations on how to speak
to people in different languages.
We’re expecting people
from many different parts of the world.
It’s actually an opportunity
to be like a missionary
in our own hometown.
Some of the estimates
that we have heard are conservative estimates
of probably 200,000 visitors.
It may be more than that.
The local congregations
made themselves available
to work with city officials
to prepare the parks
for the large influx of people.
So many of Jehovah’s Witnesses
have volunteered
to help with all kinds of things.
These are really small communities
that are having a very large influx of people.
So all of that extra effort
and help in kind of preparing and cleaning up
is much appreciated.
We have been working with Jehovah’s Witnesses
for a period of years here at Smith Rock.
It’s been a good experience
for our staff and our volunteers,
and we want to accommodate that
in any way we can.
There’s been a lot of good things
happening with cart witnessing.
One of the friends had a nice experience
with an Arabic-speaking man,
and she said the seminar
is what helped her to be prepared.
She knew how to work the app,
how to find the video in the language,
and she already
had it downloaded and ready to go.
Paul spoke about his ministry.
He said: “Woe is me
if I did not declare the good news!”
So we don’t want to look back
and wish we would’ve done more.
Trying it for the first time can be scary.
It can be nerve-racking,
but it’s not so scary after you get started.
What’s really been fun
is what we are calling roving.
We go into an area
where there are a lot of people,
and we just start conversations.
We don’t carry any literature.
We just have our device
and the jw.org contact card.
And then, hopefully,
if the opportunity presents itself,
we may share with them a video
or tell them
we’re Jehovah’s Witnesses.
It’s just been a paradise for them
—a preaching paradise—
all these visitors coming in.
We may not see the results
of the seed that was planted
when they took a look at our cart,
but Jehovah knows
and the angels know
and can make that grow.
This endeavor
has really helped me to appreciate
the need to be alert
to ways to expand our ministry.
Most communities have a calendar of events.
Have we thought about looking at it
and then making plans to give a witness
by having our literature carts out?
And, really, events like this,
they have a bigger impact
on us as Jehovah’s Witnesses
because we have an opportunity to talk.
We get excited about our work.
We’re all working together shoulder to shoulder.
It really builds our faith.
Recently, a scripture
that stood out to me was 1 Chronicles 28:20,
where it says:
“Be courageous . . . and go to work.”
It helped me to realize
that I just need to take the initiative and try.
That’s what we all need to do,
and then let Jehovah
decide how things turn out.
Jehovah will no doubt bless your efforts
as you show an interest in others.
The interest we show
in others is most noteworthy
within the bounds of our own brotherhood.
Galatians 6:10, which we quoted earlier,
ends its thought
about working “good toward all,”
saying that we should do this
“especially toward those
related to us in the faith.”
Our music video entitled
You Can Count on Me
provides a touching example
of how this “good” can be shown.
Time and circumstance
Don’t always work in our favor.
What might have been
if we just had the chance
Is something
we may never know.
But God looks down and sees;
He knows us better than we do.
He sees what we are
and what more we could be.
It’s all in the way
that we go.
He values all of us,
No matter what talent or gift we possess.
He wants each one of us
To be as caring as he is.
So you’re my friend
’cause you’re always there
Through our ups and downs
and through all we’ve shared.
And I’m there
When you need someone,
when things
are hard to bear.
I’ll be the friend you need.
You can count on me.
We weep with those who weep,
Sharing the things that we’re feeling.
But sometimes our tears
may be all that can speak,
Expressing what words cannot say.
Troubles can bring us down.
Jehovah can lift us
and carry us through.
We all can do the same
And help each other as friends do.
And you’re my friend
’cause you’re always there
Through our ups and downs
and through all we’ve shared.
And I’m there
When you need someone,
when things
are hard to bear.
I’ll be the friend you need.
You can count on me.
And you’re my friend
’cause you’re always there
Through our ups and downs
and through all we’ve shared.
And I’m there
When you need someone,
when things
are hard to bear.
I’ll be the friend you need.
You can count on me.
We conclude this month’s program
by traveling to Indonesia.
Composed of more than 17,000 islands,
it consists of hundreds of distinct native,
ethnic, and linguistic groups,
with the largest being the Javanese.
Let’s visit the city of Malang,
which has some 370 publishers
in 9 congregations.
The territory here is productive,
with many who are open to the Bible’s message.
The largest challenge
our brothers face here is economic hardship.
It’s not easy to provide even basic necessities,
so many people in the territory work long hours.
However, the pioneers
have found an ingenious way to make a living
making milk, juice, and cakes from soybeans.
A typical day will have them up at 3:00 a.m.
making fresh soy products
and then selling them
on the street in the morning.
In the afternoon they preach
and go to the market that evening
to buy fresh ingredients
for the next day’s work.
While the brothers in Malang
have not yet been able to obtain a permit
for an official Kingdom Hall,
they often meet in private homes.
Although it can be cramped and hot,
attendance is
nearly always well over 100 percent.
The publishers in Malang
send their warm love and greetings
to our entire global brotherhood.
This is JW Broadcasting
from the world headquarters
of Jehovah’s Witnesses.