Let’s consider the account that’s referred to
in our Watchtower comments.
If you turn with me in your Bibles
to the book of Luke,
we’ll read this in its entirety.
Follow with me, please,
at Luke 10:38-42.
It says:
“Now as they went on their way,
“he entered into a certain village.
“Here a woman named Martha
received him as a guest in her house.
“She also had a sister called Mary,
who sat down at the feet of the Lord
“and kept listening to what he was saying.
“Martha, on the other hand,
“was distracted
with attending to many duties.
“So she came to him and said:
“‘Lord, does it not matter to you
“‘that my sister
has left me alone to attend to things?
“Tell her to come and help me.’
“In answer the Lord said to her:
“‘Martha, Martha,
“‘you are anxious
and disturbed about many things.
“‘A few things, though,
are needed, or just one.
“‘For her part,
Mary chose the good portion,
and it will not be taken away from her.’”
Did you note in verse 40,
it said that Martha
“was distracted
with attending to many duties”?
It’s quite likely that Martha
may not have felt that way.
After all, she was not engaged
in some sort of hobby
or materialistic pursuit,
and her duties were certainly not trivial.
She was tending to the needs of Jesus.
Now, we think about that
—taking care of the Messiah, the Son of God.
That had to be one of the greatest privileges
and one of the greatest honors
an individual could have.
So it’s no wonder that in verse 40
she encourages Jesus
to tell her sister, Mary,
to come and help her.
But this raises an interesting question:
Is it possible for Christians today
to become distracted
even while engaging
in worthwhile theocratic pursuits?
Well, consider three examples.
We want to do more in the ministry,
so we decide to learn a new language.
We focus on learning the language,
but in the process,
we neglect time to read
and study the Bible in our mother tongue.
Or perhaps we decide we’re going to move
and serve where the need is greater,
and we begin to occupy so much
of our time in learning about the country
—its customs and the food—
that that begins to overshadow
our family worship and personal study.
Or how about our Bethel assignment?
We love our assignment.
Our work is very interesting.
We enjoy working hard.
But we become so absorbed
in staying ahead in our work
and keeping things moving
that we begin to do
self-imposed overtime work
on a regular basis,
neglecting our meeting attendance
and perhaps even time with our mate.
Did you notice that each situation
began as a worthwhile theocratic endeavor?
But can we see how it’s possible
that each hypothetical situation
could become a realistic distraction?
Now, let’s just go back
for a moment to the account in Luke
because it’s important
to note that Jesus never said
that what Martha was doing was wrong.
Like our text mentioned, he loved Martha.
She was a spiritual woman,
and he was very appreciative
for what she was doing in his behalf.
But he very kindly reminds her and shows her
that her meal preparations
were distracting her
to the point
that it interfered with her receiving
what he refers to in verse 42
as “the good portion”
—a spiritual activity,
listening to his teachings.
Martha was not taking advantage
of a unique opportunity
to deepen her faith.
Very interestingly,
the September 1, 1999, Watchtower
elaborates on this account,
and it makes this comment.
It says:
“Moved by love, some [today]
“—much like Martha—
do their utmost to minister
“to the needs of fellow believers.
“They are practical-minded
and quick to take action,
“and Jehovah promises
to reward their labors of love.
“Others perhaps more closely resemble Mary.
“They are quiet and contemplative.
“Their eagerness to meditate upon God’s Word
helps them
to stay solidly rooted in the faith.”
But then it says this:
“Both . . . fill a vital need
in the Christian congregation.”
And by extension,
we’ll just add in the Bethel family as well.
It continues:
“In the end, however,
“all should ‘choose the good portion’
“by putting [spiritual or] primary emphasis
on spiritual things.”
Well, that helps us
to see the balance, doesn’t it?
It makes me think,
perhaps in a modern-day application,
what if the circuit overseer
came to visit our congregation
and everyone wanted to go out
and work with him in the ministry,
but no one was willing to stop
and provide him with a meal?
That wouldn’t be good,
would it, or hospitable?
Just like it wouldn’t be balanced
for him to have multiple meal invitations,
and then no one showed up
to support him and his wife in the ministry.
So the point is,
we want to make sure
that we care for our needs
and the needs of others
but also make sure
that we remember our priorities.
So, what’s the key to ensuring
that our endeavors
will not become distractions?
Well, notice how the Bible explains this.
Turn with me, please,
to Philippians chapter 1.
At Philippians chapter 1,
notice verses 9 and 10:
“And this is what I continue praying,
“that your love
may abound still more and more
“with accurate knowledge
and full discernment;
“that you may make sure
of the more important things,
“so that you may be flawless
and not stumbling others
up to the day of Christ.”
So before we undertake
any endeavor, any assignment,
you notice we want to pray,
reason things out,
use accurate knowledge, and discernment.
And if we’re able to use that insight
—good judgment—
then it’s going to help us
to discern, or perceive,
what is most important to God.
And when we know that,
well, then, we can harmonize our thoughts,
our actions,
and our decisions accordingly.
By making sure
of the more important things,
we gain Jehovah’s blessing and favor.
So think about those situations we mentioned.
If we’re going to learn a new language
or move where the need is greater,
well, that’s amazing!
It’s appreciated, and it’s definitely needed.
In fact, we’re encouraged to do it
if we have the circumstances.
And, of course, in our Bethel assignment,
who of us does not want to work hard,
to get to know our work well,
and give our all to Jehovah?
But we can appreciate
how Jesus shows us
a valuable and balanced lesson
—that even in worthwhile theocratic pursuits,
we should not let anything distract
or impede our spiritual progress.
We don’t want to miss
opportunities to strengthen our faith,
to bond with our brothers and sisters,
and, most importantly, to bond with Jehovah.
If we just go back to Luke,
notice how Jesus
concluded his words to Martha.
In verse 42, he says
that because ‘Mary chose the good portion,
it will not be taken away from her.’
So, what she learned that day
—the commendation,
the spiritual instruction from Jesus—
Mary would never forget that.
That would stay with her
for the rest of her life.
And likely,
we can recall a similar account
—maybe a talk, a meeting,
something that was said at the convention,
a spiritual discussion
that we had with someone—
and that conversation, or discussion,
had a profound impact on our faith
and our relationship with Jehovah.
Well, if you’ve had situations like that,
you know that those are precious;
they’re very special.
And those are things
that we want to hold on to.
So, what a beautiful reminder we had today.
And let’s not be distracted.
May we work to strengthen our spirituality
and relationship with Jehovah
by always choosing “the good portion,”
and if we do, we can be assured
that Jehovah will bless our efforts.