Forty years ago, in 1978,
the Computer Department
was formed in the United States.
Now overseen by the Coordinators’ Committee,
the Computer Department at headquarters
supports many organizational initiatives
of the Governing Body and its committees.
It also provides global technical standards
and unified software to all branches.
One such example of this software
is a program called HuB.
HuB is the replacement software for Admin.
However, replacing a program as extensive
and critical as Admin is no small task.
Well, what does it take?
Well, the Coordinators’ Committee is pleased
to share with you
the following seven-minute video,
which provides just a glimpse
into what is involved in the making of HuB.
Virtually every department at Bethel
is using a new computer program called HuB;
it replaces Admin,
the program previously tasked
with being the backbone
in organizing nearly every aspect of Bethel work.
Building and transitioning to this new program
would be the largest project
the Computer Department had ever undertaken.
The Admin program
really grew from small beginnings
to a program that today
is used by almost every department in Bethel.
It was custom-designed,
essentially, for the organization’s needs.
However, we’ve reached a point,
after these 20 years, where it’s based
on software that now we understand
is no longer going to be supported
by the company that produced it.
There were about 9,000
different custom forms and reports
that had been built into Admin.
Four and a half million lines
of code already existed,
and so now we
had to take all of that and convert it.
It’s like a building with 9,000 rooms
that you have to rebuild
and take a fresh look at from the ground up,
‘How are we going to do this
using a new set of technology?’
This was huge; this was their Warwick project.
Where we are today,
we have this replacement program called HuB.
At the same time as building this new system,
we also had to support
the existing Admin program.
Both of these systems
were accessing and reading and writing
to the same data source
at the same time, so it was very complex.
To date, we have
at least 12 million lines of code,
and that is growing by the thousands every day.
HuB, the replacement for Admin,
is already in full production
for most departments.
Many new organizational initiatives
require the development teams
to design new features
or at least modify existing ones.
In some ways,
it’s like living in a house
while it’s being renovated,
except in this case, the house
will be fully replaced from the foundations up
without the family ever moving out.
So developing a new program also meant
learning new programming tools
and new programming methods.
It’s a little bit as if everybody
was speaking Hebrew,
and now we had to get them all
to learn how to speak Greek.
We’ve had brothers and sisters
throughout the earth, actually,
pouring their heart into this project.
We have 15 different development teams,
and they’re based in eight different branches
in different locations around the world.
We’re also assisted by many remote volunteers
in the field also spread out around the world.
So, obviously, coordinating this global group
has required us as a department
to adopt new methodologies
—new ways of working—
in order for it to be a success.
We get our direction
from the Governing Body committees
and the world headquarters departments.
They essentially come to us
and tell us what features need to be built,
and they also tell us when
—or the priority as to what should come first.
The direction received
is translated into a format
used by the developers
to write the computer code.
We need to document
the technical requirements
so that a developer
will know what needs to be coded.
A lot of thought goes into the design
of the screens before development begins,
and this is important so that the many
HuB development teams around the world
can be working
on the same software project at the same time,
giving the user a consistent experience.
In the past,
branches had to perform their own updates,
sometimes working off compact discs
that had to be sent through the mail.
This could take weeks of work.
For this reason, significant updates
would generally happen only every six months.
Today, updating HuB
in all branches for all users
can happen several times a day.
We built a pipeline,
a virtual pipeline, that allows us
(every time we have code ready)
to ship, basically, the product
from world headquarters
to the branches through the network.
Every time code is added or edited,
the entire project
is automatically rebuilt and tested.
Everything has to be just right.
We have millions of lines of code behind this,
so every time we add a new line
or we modify a line of code,
we need to reinspect everything
and make sure that,
in an automated manner, it will still work.
HuB is already providing new features
that are assisting global initiatives.
As the number
of translated languages for our publications
grows by leaps and bounds,
so do the number of different items we print.
Branches need to know
when each new item is going to be printed
and which branch will print it for them.
In the past, this required hundreds
of pieces of correspondence every month.
With HuB,
all this information gathering is simplified.
Branches enter their information
directly into HuB, where it is processed,
organized, and shared worldwide.
This saves countless hours of work,
improves the accuracy of the data,
and results in a quicker response
to the current needs of the field.
Globally, the organization
cares for many properties.
Branches enter the location, size,
use, or condition of each property into HuB.
It’s forwarded
to world headquarters on a weekly basis.
The HuB data can be exported and viewed
as tables, charts, or maps,
showing trends that may be developing
for the best use of existing facilities
and planning for future growth.
The perceived need
for several thousand new Kingdom Halls
was resolved by making better use
of existing properties.
A project of this magnitude
is not without its growing pains.
It was a little challenging,
but I wanted to learn how to use it.
I looked for the positives;
I looked for the benefits of the program.
It’s easy to find what you want
because of the training that they have.
They have all kinds of references for us
to find the information we need
to do our work.
Globally, over 14,000 users
have already received live instructor-led training.
We encourage all those who use HuB
to work with those within their department
who provide training and support
because we work
with those individuals to give them updates
as to what’s new and how to use the product.
We’re very thankful to the brothers and sisters
who have taken the time to learn this program.
We realize that it’s a work in progress.
It’s a work in progress for them and a work
in progress for us who are developing it.
We value their feedback,
and we want to use that feedback
to try and improve the program together.
At Exodus 36:1,
we read how Bezalel worked along with Oholiab,
to whom Jehovah had given
“wisdom and understanding,” allowing them
to accomplish work to his praise.
In a similar way,
projects like this can be daunting
—even overwhelming—
and yet Jehovah’s spirit enables our success.