Welcome,
brothers and sisters, to JW Broadcasting.
In this month’s program,
we’ll learn ways to deal with worry and anxiety.
Here are some highlights.
From childhood, this brother found it a challenge
to attend meetings, go to school, hold a job,
and even leave his home each morning.
What can we learn from his experience
to help us cope with our anxieties
one day at a time?
These two sisters have worked
shoulder to shoulder in full-time service
for more than 60 years.
We’ll learn what has helped them to remain joyful
despite everyday struggles and unexpected trials.
Have you ever wondered what motivates
our brothers and sisters
to make themselves available for Bethel service?
We’ll hear from ones who are serving at Bethel,
and we’ll learn how to prepare and qualify
for this special form of full-time service.
There’s much to enjoy in this May 2019 edition
of JW Broadcasting.
Do you sometimes feel completely overwhelmed
when life’s problems cause you anxiety?
Just trying to provide the necessities
for one’s family can lead to anxiety.
At the same time,
you might be dealing
with a chronic or life-threatening illness,
caring for a sick or elderly relative,
grieving the death of a loved one,
loneliness, a natural disaster,
or maybe you’re struggling
with the devastating effects
of past or present abuse.
Now, you firmly believe
that God’s Kingdom will fix these problems,
but that’s in the future.
What about today?
Perhaps you feel like David,
who prayed at Psalm 13:2:
“How long will I have anxious concern,
with grief in my heart each day?”
A sister who has struggled
with anxiety for many years wrote this:
“Anxiety robs me of sleep,
impacts my health,
affects the way I treat others,
and makes me want to give up.”
She added: “Anxiety is like a monster
“that lives in my body
somewhere between my heart and my belly.
“I cannot wait for Jehovah
to kill that monster in the new world.
“But until then,
the monster snarls and tears at my insides
and tries to take over my life.”
Can you identify with her feelings?
We often hear a person say concerning anxiety:
“I’m just trying to take it one day at a time.”
But one brother put it this way:
“I try to take it one day at a time,
but sometimes several days attack me at once.”
For so many of us, anxiety is a daily struggle.
If you battle with anxiety,
please know this: You are not alone.
Do not give up the fight.
Jehovah and Jesus are aware of the anxieties
that weigh on your mind
and that are deep in your heart.
The Governing Body
knows that living in this system of things
is especially “hard to deal with.”
So the theme chosen for this program is
“Deal With Anxiety One Day at a Time.”
First, what is anxiety?
In the Christian Greek Scriptures,
the word “anxious” occurs 19 times.
The first occurrence
is in Jesus’ Sermon on the Mount.
Now, Jesus knew that people
worried about how to provide for their family.
So at Matthew 6:25,
he gave this wise counsel:
“On this account I say to you:
“Stop being anxious about your lives
“as to what you will eat or what you will drink,
“or about your bodies as to what you will wear.
“Does not life mean more than food
and the body than clothing?”
The Study Bible note for verse 25
says that “the Greek term for ‘anxious’
“can refer to worry that divides a person’s mind
and distracts him, robbing him of joy.”
At Luke 12:29,
Jesus says to “stop being in anxious suspense”
or to “stop worrying.”
The study note here says
that the Greek word
for “anxious suspense” was used
to refer “to ships being tossed at sea.”
It says that Jesus used it “figuratively
“for being anxious or unsettled,
“as if tossed about or wavering
because of doubt and anxiety.”
By saying “stop being anxious,”
Jesus recognizes
that anxiety is already in progress.
He is very aware of our imperfect nature.
He knows that we tend
to bring our worries from yesterday
(the would-haves,
could-haves, and should-haves)
and our imagined worries about tomorrow
(the what-ifs) to today.
But ask yourself,
‘How often have I worried myself
sick about what might happen tomorrow,
only to find that tomorrow
wasn’t nearly as bad as I feared it would be?’
Jesus also knows that anxiety can have real,
sometimes painful, consequences.
It can stop us from making spiritual progress.
Overthinking and overanalyzing our problems
can literally shut us down.
How, though, can we “stop being anxious”?
What’s the antidote?
Let’s consider four practical things we can do.
First, rely on Jehovah
and take one day at a time.
This is exactly what Jesus prescribed for us
at Matthew 6:33, 34:
“Keep on, then, seeking first the Kingdom
“and his righteousness,
“and all these other things will be added to you.
“So never be anxious about the next day,
“for the next day will have its own anxieties.
Each day has enough of its own troubles.”
Verse 34 has a study note
telling us that “undue anxiety
about what may happen in the future
“can adversely affect
a person’s relationship with God,
causing him to rely
on his own wisdom rather than on God’s.”
So, what’s the lesson?
Instead of relying on ourselves,
rely on Jehovah, and take one day at a time.
A cross-reference to Matthew 6:34
takes us to Exodus 16:4.
In this account,
Jehovah provided
the Israelites with enough manna
for every day of their 40-year trek.
Could Jehovah have provided
a week’s worth of manna?
a month’s worth? a year’s worth?
Of course.
So why did
he only provide enough for each day?
Well, think about it.
When they stepped out
of their tents each morning,
there was no question whether
there would be manna on the ground or not,
and there was
no question where it came from.
Jehovah never failed to provide for their needs,
not even for one day.
They also knew from the past that Jehovah
always provided for those who were loyal to him.
We too can look back
at how Jehovah provided for his servants.
We can have
complete confidence that Jehovah knows exactly
what we need when we need it
—for today, tomorrow, and for all eternity.
Even if we have such confidence,
why do we sometimes continue to feel anxious?
The simple answer:
We’re imperfect people trying our best
to serve Jehovah in Satan’s wicked world.
Daily challenges cause anxiety
that can make us forget to rely on Jehovah
and take one day at a time.
So we need to add
our second way to deal with anxiety:
Pour your heart out
to Jehovah in earnest prayer.
Read with me the reassuring words
at Philippians 4:6, 7:
“Do not be anxious over anything,
“but in everything by prayer
“and supplication along with thanksgiving,
“let your petitions be made known to God;
“and the peace of God that surpasses
“all understanding will guard your hearts
and your mental powers by means of Christ Jesus.”
Paul doesn’t simply tell us not to be anxious,
but he tells us how.
He said “by prayer and supplication,”
which is earnest and specific prayer.
With what benefit?
The “peace of God . . . will guard your hearts.”
“Guard” was a military expression referring to troops
assigned to protect a city.
The inhabitants could sleep soundly
knowing that soldiers were guarding them at night.
In a similar way,
when we have “the peace of God,”
our hearts and minds can rest.
This can prevent us from being
overwhelmed by anxiety or discouragement.
How reassuring are the words of the psalmist
at Psalm 4:8:
“I will lie down and sleep in peace,
“for you alone, O Jehovah,
make me dwell in security.”
So when we feel trapped,
like there’s no way out of our worries,
the peace from God gives us hope
that there’s light at the end of the tunnel.
What, though, must you do?
Turn your worries into deep, heartfelt prayers.
In fact, at 1 Peter 5:7,
Jehovah invites you
to “throw all your anxiety on him,
“[and leave it with him]
because he cares for you.”
Jehovah is the one person
who truly understands how you feel.
He knows every moment of your life
—why you feel or react a certain way.
He loves and values you personally
despite your imperfections, your anxieties,
your cares and worries.
He not only has
the power to help you, he wants to.
Knowing this
should move you to pray specifically,
expressing your deepest emotions
and pleading
that he grant you peace of mind and heart.
To the extent you do so,
1 Peter 5:10 promises
that “he will make you firm,
“he will make you strong,
he will firmly ground you.”
Never underestimate the power of prayer!
Jehovah is always ready to help you
—one day at a time.
Our third way to deal with anxiety
is to read and meditate on God’s Word.
Let Jehovah speak to you.
Allow Jehovah’s thoughts to become your thoughts.
At Psalm 94:19,
notice how the psalmist admitted his own anxiety:
“When anxieties overwhelmed me,
you comforted and soothed me.”
Yes, even servants of God
can feel overwhelmed by anxieties
or, as one translation says,
“burdened with worries.”
That in itself is comforting
that an inspired Bible writer
struggled with anxieties.
But Jehovah “comforted and soothed” him,
calming his troubled heart.
God can do the same for us
through his inspired Word, the Bible.
Remember,
the Bible is how Jehovah speaks to us.
Rather than allowing our emotions to run wild,
we can learn to focus
our mind on upbuilding things,
such as what
the apostle Paul listed at Philippians 4:8:
“Finally, brothers, whatever things are true,
“whatever things are of serious concern,
“whatever things are righteous,
“whatever things are chaste,
“whatever things are lovable,
“whatever things are well-spoken-of,
“whatever things are virtuous,
“and whatever things are praiseworthy,
continue considering these things.”
The footnote to verse 8 shows that “considering”
involves “thinking about” or “meditating on.”
We can and should
meditate on positive things from the Bible,
replacing negative things
that may enter our mind and cause anxiety.
Ask Jehovah to help you to find passages
in his Word that will soothe your heart.
Ask others what scriptures have calmed
their heart during anxious moments.
Make your own personal list.
Then set aside time to read
and meditate on those passages.
Meditation is the doorway to your heart.
Meditation lets God’s thoughts affect you
on the deepest possible level.
Imagine that Jehovah is speaking directly to you,
because he is.
Never underestimate the power of God’s Word
—of letting Jehovah speak to you.
Our fourth way to deal with anxiety
is to share your feelings with a trusted friend.
Proverbs 12:25 says:
“Anxiety in a man’s heart weighs it down
“[or, as the footnote says, ‘depresses him’],
but a good word cheers it up.”
“A good word” can come from a fellow believer
who is motivated
by God’s spirit and guided by his Word.
When the apostle Paul was alone in prison,
he prayed for encouragement
and Jehovah provided
what he needed to cheer him up.
With a heart full of appreciation,
he said at Colossians 4:11
that “my fellow workers  . . . have become
a source of great comfort to me,”
or “a strengthening aid.”
What can you do if you feel
weighed down or imprisoned by anxiety?
Like Paul, pray for encouragement.
Pray for someone you can talk to,
someone you can trust with your feelings.
The answer to your prayer may be an elder
or a mature Christian brother or sister.
But what if it’s difficult for you
to open up to others and confide in them?
Try the advice
in the March 1, 1997, Watchtower article
“Are You Afraid to Trust Others?”
When confiding in someone
it says: “Reveal your concerns gradually.
“If he [or she] responds in an appropriate,
“sympathetic, and discreet way,
you might then try disclosing more.”
Even if it takes some effort,
never underestimate the power of our brotherhood.
Jehovah can use a fellow worshipper
to ease your mind of “anxious concern.”
Even at times when there’s no one to talk to,
we can let the experiences,
upbuilding music,
and talks on JW Broadcasting® be like
an encouraging hug from a trusted friend.
Yes, when we make the effort,
we give Jehovah something to bless.
Jehovah can help us
conquer the seemingly unconquerable.
That may not mean
that we’ll completely eliminate anxiety,
but we can learn to take control.
How?
Remember our four ways:
First, rely on Jehovah
and take one day at time;
second, pour out your heart
to Jehovah in earnest, specific prayer;
third, read and meditate on God’s Word
—let Jehovah speak to you;
and fourth, share your feelings with a trusted friend.
With Jehovah’s help,
you can deal with anxiety one day at a time.
Earlier, I read a quote from the sister who described
anxiety as a monster living inside her.
I’m so pleased to say that the sister
who wrote that letter about her anxieties
is actually here with us in the studio
to tell us more about her experience.
This is Jordan Williams
and her husband, Robert.
Thank you so much
for coming here
to share with us your battle with anxiety.
Can you elaborate on that, please?
I feel ashamed of my anxiety.
I feel like there’s something
wrong with me, and I feel guilty about that.
I feel like I’m
letting Jehovah down by feeling anxious
and that I’m even being disobedient to Jesus,
when he says: “Stop being anxious.”
But I just can’t.
Thank you for sharing that.
Robert, what do you do
to help Jordan battle this anxiety?
It’s a monster
—sometimes a very stubborn monster—
that won’t go away.
Remembering that it’s not her fault
helps me be more compassionate
and caring—listening
when she’s explaining these anxieties
that I may not completely understand.
Jordan, are there other
practical things that help you battle anxiety?
The single biggest help
is walking with Jehovah every day.
I mean that literally.
I’ll wake up in the morning super anxious.
And I can’t breathe; and my chest is tight.
And I’ll get up, and I’ll read the chapter
of the Bible that the daily text comes from.
And then I’ll go on a walk
and talk to Jehovah for an hour,
and I try to use
the model prayer as an outline.
So I’ll talk to Jehovah about his name
and how I feel so privileged
to have that name on me.
And I’ll talk to him about his Kingdom
that’s going to solve
all of these problems, including anxiety.
And I’ll talk to him about his will
and specifically what his will is for me that day.
And most of the time,
those three things
cover the things that were worrying me.
But if there is another thing,
I’ll talk to him specifically about that.
What a nice walk you have with Jehovah.
Are there other things
that help you deal and battle anxiety?
Personal study projects help a lot,
especially if they
don’t have anything to do with anxiety.
If I do a study project
on the spiritual suit of armor or the ransom,
it kind of distracts the “anxiety monster”
so that my heart can calm down,
and then these pearls of wisdom will
come from Jehovah, and they can get in.
And some of those pearls are actually
just what I need to deal with my anxiety.
Are there specific things that help you?
Yes, I made an Anxiety tab
in the Personal Study section
of my Study Bible on my tablet,
and I collect scriptures and comments
that really help with my anxiety.
For example, in 2014,
there was a regional convention talk
about Matthew chapter 6
and six specific things that combat anxiety.
And it made me think
of the twelve-step program  to overcoming addiction.
These are the six steps to overcome anxiety.
What are those six steps?
The first one is to help those in need,
and then pray a lot, to be forgiving,
not to be hypocritical,
to store up treasures in heaven,
and then to focus on spiritual matters.
So when we got back from the convention,
she took those items and she wrote them down
and put them on magnets
and put them on our refrigerator.
I try to do each one
of those six things every day.
And when I accomplish one, I’ll turn the magnet
so that I can see what I still need to work on.
So when I come
to the refrigerator in the morning,
if the magnets are turned,
we know where she’s at.
If they’re not turned,
we know we’re in trouble.
It’s a bad day.
It’s time to do something else.
Very good—nice barometer.
So, what can others do or say
that would be helpful
to those going through anxiety?
For the friends,
it’s really nice when they’re understanding
and nonjudgmental
and respect my privacy (that’s really helpful)
and when they don’t freeze me in time
or decide that ‘Oh, she’s anxious,
and this is how she’s going to be all the time.’
That’s really helpful.
I even forget that Jehovah approves of me.
So reminding me of that
—reminding me that the things
that I do to please him are successful
and maybe even reminding me
of things that I have accomplished for Jehovah
in the past.
You know, you should
tell Ron about your broken dish.
Oh, yeah.
Yes.
I’d like to know about that.
So I just found out
about this Japanese art called Kintsukuroi.
And it’s basically taking
a broken piece of pottery
and fixing it by putting it back together
with gold or silver lacquer,
and the concept is that the piece
is more beautiful for having been broken.
And that really resonates
with me because I do feel broken by anxiety.
But Jehovah gave Jesus as a ransom,
and that ransom is just pure gold;
and He can take
all the broken anxious little bits of me
and put me back together.
And maybe I’ll even be more
useful to Jehovah for having been broken.
That’s very precious.
Thank you for sharing that.
Are there other things
that help you deal with anxiety?
I’ve learned to recognize
when anxiety is clouding my thinking,
and I’ll ask him,
“Can I borrow your brain for a minute, please?”
So, what we did is we went
and purchased a whiteboard and put it in my office.
And sometimes we’ll go to the whiteboard
and write out all
the anxieties that she’s dealing with.
As we are writing them out,
sometimes we realize that those
are yesterday’s anxieties
and that they’ve been cared for,
so we can erase those from the board.
Some of them are for tomorrow,
and so we don’t want
to borrow those and bring them to today.
They’re tomorrow’s anxieties.
And some anxieties
can be grouped in little clusters,
and you can realize,
‘The root is here; let’s focus on that.’
I fight anxiety every single day.
And anxiety is constantly
changing its tactics, so I have to be adaptable.
But Jehovah never
leaves me to fight anxiety alone—ever.
I don’t understand
what I’ve done to merit all of his attention,
but I do realize that I don’t
need to understand why he loves me.
I trust him, and he never lies,
so I just need to accept it
when he shows me that love.
We appreciate
you sharing those personal feelings.
And again, we know
that Jehovah and Jesus are so proud of you.
And we know that those
who are listening in to this interview
will benefit so much
from listening to your personal expressions.
Thank you very much.
Anxieties can surface at any time in our lives,
even when we’re very young.
Imagine, though, if the stress
of growing up in this system
was made worse by a chronic disorder,
one that made anxiety feel impossible to overcome.
We’ll be encouraged
by the experience of Brother Steing Dott,
who never gave up on Jehovah.
See if you can identify what has helped him cope
one day at a time.
My name is Steing Dott.
I was born in 1988 in Darwin,
Northern Territory.
When I was eight years old,
I realized that life
was getting very difficult for me.
I was diagnosed with ADHD,
obsessive-compulsive disorder,
Tourette syndrome.
And on top of all of that,
I was diagnosed with severe anxiety as well.
My mum said this affected the entire family
because I would repeatedly
yell out “Good night!”
to each individual person in the family.
And on top of that,
I used to constantly go
around the house,
checking the locks and the windows.
My school life was the hardest thing
I’ve ever had to deal with.
My school was approximately
500 meters from my home.
It would take me
at least two hours to get to school
because one of my obsessions was
that if there were cracks on the footpath
and if I stepped on one,
I’d have to go all the way back home
and start again.
Well, I found life
to be a constant struggle,
and as I got older,
it only got worse.
Even at ten years old,
I decided that I wanted to end my life
so that it would make
everyone in the family’s life a lot easier.
But then we decided
to use some medication,
which eased my problems a little bit.
Despite having medication,
life was still completely unbearable for me.
I had a constant struggle
every day within myself.
I used to wash my hands
hundreds of times a day.
I couldn’t leave the home;
I couldn’t get a driver’s license;
I couldn’t even get a job.
A major turning point in my life
was my mum’s unwavering faith in Jehovah.
She used to iron
my clothes for the meeting
and hang them on the doorknob,
even though I wasn’t ready
to attend the meeting.
But what she didn’t know
was that when my mum
went to the meeting with my sister,
I’d get a Bible,
and I’d try and start to read it.
I also began to pray to Jehovah.
And then one day, I thought,
‘I’m going to give this a shot.’
So I put my suit on, I got ready,
and I went to the meeting.
When I went to the Kingdom Hall,
I was absolutely terrified.
I was so nervous.
But when I got there, I saw an elder
who used to come and visit me,
and he made me feel very relaxed.
And then the amazing welcome
by the brothers and sisters
—it made me feel like I was part
of Jehovah’s organization again.
The scripture that really helped me
was 1 Peter 5:7 because it says:
“While you throw all your anxiety on him,
because he cares for you.”
So this made me feel like
I had a very powerful Friend,
and Jehovah wanted me to throw
my anxieties on him because he loved me.
On September 4, 2010,
it was my most important day of my life.
I got baptized
as one of Jehovah’s Witnesses
at Adelaide Entertainment Centre.
I now serve as a ministerial servant.
I’ve had the privilege of giving public talks,
which is something I never thought
I’d ever be able to do.
I completed pioneer school
after three attempts
because the pioneer school
environment made me feel
like I was back at school
and made me have anxiety again.
So the third time I completed it.
And none of this would ever have been
possible without Jehovah’s help.
On the 6th of August 2016,
I married my beautiful wife, Laura,
who helps me serve Jehovah,
and we can serve
Jehovah every day together.
I, like the apostle Paul,
still feel like I have
a war inside me sometimes.
But definitely,
Jehovah has never let me down.
Never give up on serving Jehovah
because Jehovah
will never give up on you.
Did you notice what Steing
considered the turning point in his life?
It was the unwavering faith of his Mum,
the warmth of the congregation
and, most of all, help from Jehovah.
He called Jehovah “a very powerful Friend.”
That’s so true!
Brother Dott overcame monumental challenges,
but is his struggle with anxiety over?
No.
He said that like the apostle Paul,
he sometimes still feels a war within himself.
Do you ever feel that way?
This month’s music video reminds us
that we can find peace and joy despite our burdens.
It’s entitled Each Day Has Its Own Anxieties.
I know about the Paradise
under God’s Kingdom,
And I believe with all my heart
that better days will come.
But sometimes in this life, for me,
It’s hard to see the things unseen,
To feel the love I know is there
when my heart is in despair.
But I know Jehovah’s near.
So I say a prayer from the heart.
When worries overtake my mind,
On his strength I can rely.
I’m not alone; I know he’s there.
I have his words of comfort
And true friends who really care.
Yes, each day has its own anxieties.
So I take one day at a time;
Leave tomorrow until tomorrow;
Peace is what I find
One day at a time.
So take these words I’ve said, my friend,
And know that I care.
Focus on the joys in life,
Not the burdens that we bear.
Think about what God has done.
To show his love, he gave his Son.
So never doubt; keep trusting him.
He gave his best so we could live.
So don’t give in to fear.
Say a prayer from the heart.
When worries overtake our mind,
On his strength we can rely.
We’re not alone, for he is there.
We have his words of comfort
And true friends who really care.
Yes, each day has its own anxieties.
So take one day at a time;
Leave tomorrow until tomorrow;
Peace is what we’ll find
One day at a time.
Say a prayer from the heart.
When worries overtake our mind,
On his strength we can rely.
We’re not alone, for he is there.
We have his words of comfort
And true friends who really care.
Yes, each day has its own anxieties.
So take one day at a time;
Leave tomorrow until tomorrow;
Peace is what we’ll find
One day at a time—
One day at a time.
“We’re not alone, for he is there.
“We have his words of comfort and true friends
who really care.”
What an encouraging thought from that song!
Yes, true friends who share
our love for Jehovah are invaluable.
We’ll see that in this story from Japan.
Sisters Takako Sato and Hisako Wakui
have worked together as pioneers since 1957.
Let’s learn how their friendship
has helped them serve Jehovah with joy.
We are pioneer partners.
We’ve been working together
for over 60 years.
In 1956,
I was the only Jehovah’s Witness
in Nagano prefecture.
It was lonesome,
but I applied for regular pioneer service.
Surprisingly,
I was appointed
as a special pioneer.
I was so happy that I found myself
rolling around on the tatami-mat floor
with the appointment letter in my hand.
That was the way
I expressed my joy and appreciation.
When I was invited to serve
as a special pioneer,
I was sent to Nagano,
and that’s where I met Hisako.
Takako and I focused on our ministry.
When an isolated group was established,
since there were no brothers,
I would wear a head covering
and conduct the meetings.
Sometimes the outlines were in English.
We didn’t understand anything.
But people were delighted to hear
even just the scriptures and went home satisfied,
and that strongly impressed on me
the power of God’s Word.
We were assigned
to a territory in the city after that.
We found so many not-at-homes,
but we were determined to meet people.
So we changed the times we preached,
and we talked to people on the street
who were going to work.
We cherished even small opportunities.
When we had a chance to meet a householder,
we always tried to have a conversation
that we could link to the next visit.
Before long, I had ten Bible studies.
Takako acts like she’s cheerful,
but she’s been fighting various illnesses.
At times, it was so bad
that I could not even go out in service.
I had a serious skin condition.
I could not bear
to look at the illustration of Job in the magazine,
and I covered it up with paper.
But Jehovah helped me
to look to Job’s example.
I learned
that our endurance under trial
would become praise to God.
I have often had health problems.
Just at one of those times,
I received a letter from the branch.
It said:
“What you
can accomplish now may be limited.
“However, think
about all that you have done up to now
“to give praise to Jehovah
“and about the people
you were able to help learn the truth,
and be joyful knowing
that you have been used by Jehovah fully.”
I couldn’t stop crying
because I really felt the care and concern
from the organization and from Jehovah.
Hisako also
took really good care of me
and prayed with me.
Our thinking and personalities are different,
but we made efforts to talk things out.
Our heartfelt desire
to want to serve Jehovah full-time
has always been the same.
For 60 years, we’ve enjoyed
a truly wonderful life of service to Jehovah.
Jehovah has supported us in difficult times
through the Bible, the organization, and friends.
I have tasted the truthfulness of the words:
“When I am weak, then I am powerful.”
‘When I said: “My foot is slipping,”
your kindness, O Jehovah, has supported me.’
I can say that too.
Although we don’t have energy or ability,
we’ve been able to enjoy
full-time service together up until now.
I’m really content now.
It’s all thanks to Jehovah.
Like the apostle Paul,
our sisters cultivated singleness
and focused on full-time service to Jehovah
for more than 60 years.
Yes, they face everyday challenges
and the extra ones that come with age,
but their heartfelt desire
to serve Jehovah whole-souled
brings Takako and Hisako
real joy and contentment.
Whole-souled service
for nearly 20,000 brothers and sisters
is a full-time assignment at Bethel.
What motivates them
to reach out for this special privilege?
What blessings do they experience?
And what’s the best way
to prepare and qualify for Bethel service?
I’d like to invite my friend Patrick LaFranca
to discuss these and other questions.
Welcome, Pat.
Thank you, Ron.
How heartwarming it’s been
to see millions take their stand for true worship!
Thousands more are joining us every week.
Jehovah is speeding up the ingathering work,
and this makes us very happy.
But who will work
to provide the Bibles, Bible literature,
and the audio and video publications
that sustain us spiritually
and help us to accomplish
our Kingdom preaching and teaching work?
Bethel is a unique place.
It’s where mature Christians
render sacred service to Jehovah
in close association with Christ’s brothers.
They minister to the needs
of our worldwide brotherhood
and support the preaching work.
The Bethel family is a group of dedicated,
baptized servants of Jehovah
who live and work together closely.
So they experience in a special way
what Psalm 133:1 says:
“Look! How good
“and how pleasant it is for brothers
to dwell together in unity!”
We’re very pleased to see
that many have expanded their service
to Jehovah by making themselves available
for the special privilege of Bethel service.
Have you considered this as a goal?
Making yourself available
for Bethel service
is like knocking on a door that leads
to many other privileges of service.
Of course, to serve at Bethel requires
a self-sacrificing spirit
and a willingness to serve
wherever there is a need,
in harmony with the attitude displayed
by the prophet Isaiah at Isaiah 6:8:
“Then I heard the voice of Jehovah saying:
“‘Whom shall I send, and who will go for us?’
And I said: ‘Here I am! Send me!’”
When Isaiah learned about an opportunity
to do more in Jehovah’s service,
he responded eagerly,
even though he did not know exactly
what he was going to be assigned to do.
It was enough for him to know that Jehovah
was extending an invitation
to serve in a special way,
and Isaiah wanted to volunteer.
The same spirit is shown
by Bethel family members worldwide.
What especially motivates
so many to serve at Bethel?
Love for Jehovah moves us
to put Kingdom interests ahead of self-interest.
As stated in the Proclaimers book, page 295:
“This is not work in which they gain
“personal prominence or material possessions.
“Their desire is to honor Jehovah,
and they are satisfied
“with the provisions made for them
“in the way of food, lodging,
and a modest [allowance]
for personal expenses.”
Are there any rewards
that come from serving in this unique way?
Those who have offered themselves willingly
for Bethel service have truly been blessed.
The love and unity we feel here is incomparable.
It’s not like in a company out in the world
because here you can work
with your friends every day.
Like-minded people
have the same goals and support each other.
That is what you can feel here.
Maybe you’re assigned a task
that you’ve never performed before,
but there are
many experienced brothers and sisters
who can help
—professionally as well as personally.
Whether it is the consideration of the daily text
or the Watchtower Study with the Bethel family,
listening to the practical, valuable comments
of our brothers and sisters is really refreshing.
You really feel that they love Jehovah,
and their comments help you to feel the same.
Here in Bethel, you have the best Employer
that there is—Jehovah.
No other employer
is as grateful and considerate as he is,
so out of love for Jehovah,
you’re simply happy to give him your best.
Whenever I think about what
is being done at Bethel
—publications are being
produced and shipped,
videos for our conventions are being made,
and translation is being done
into so many different languages—
I keep getting goose bumps.
No matter what I can do here,
knowing that by doing it
I am supporting Christ’s brothers
makes me feel very, very good.
So how does a young person
qualify for Bethel service?
My parents raised me to have
a spiritual focus.
So during the school holidays
and growing up,
our life revolved around the ministry
—doing spiritual activities.
And it really helped us
keep focused spiritually as a family
and helped me stay focused
on the goals that I wanted to achieve.
I really enjoy reading,
and one day my Dad just said to me,
“Why don’t you read the Bible?”
And I know it sounds obvious,
but at that point, I had never read it
from Genesis to Revelation.
So when I finished reading the Bible,
it really changed my thinking,
and it really proved the truth to myself.
And this helped me to keep
a spiritual focus, and it really was the first step
in reaching out and achieving
the spiritual goals that I wanted to achieve.
In the congregation, I was able to help out
with doing the magazines
and the sound and the platform.
And these privileges really helped me to build
a good work ethic and give in ways
that I could give more to Jehovah.
So the elders used to work
with me a lot in the ministry.
So when I felt
that ‘I can’t do this’
or ‘This is too much’ or ‘It’s too overwhelming’
or ‘I’ll never be able to reach this goal,’
an elder showed me
a scripture in the Bible where Jehovah
was encouraging Joshua to be courageous.
And that really impacted me,
so that I was able to be courageous,
too, and to reach my goal of Bethel.
So when I visited Bethel,
I saw that they were normal people,
and they had so many good qualities
that I wanted to imitate
—very hospitable, very warm,
very inviting.
That helped me to want to reach my goal,
so that I could be like them.
To serve at Bethel
there are qualifications that need to be met.
You should have a deep love for Jehovah
and the organization, which is demonstrated
by living in harmony with Bible standards.
You must have a fine reputation
as a spiritual person.
You should have respect
for Jehovah’s moral standards,
avoiding uncleanness and sexual immorality.
You should have a clean conscience
before Jehovah and be at peace with yourself
and with Jehovah’s organization.
Your dress and grooming should be exemplary,
befitting a Christian minister
even during leisure time.
Styles that are faddish
or extreme or that identify us
with undesirable elements of the world
are not acceptable at Bethel.
The applicant should not read, listen to,
or view any type of material
that is inappropriate for a Christian.
Such unwholesome material
certainly would include pornography,
debasing music, or any kind of entertainment
that features sexual immorality,
spiritism, or violence.
Bethel applicants should be
from 19 to 35 years of age.
Occasionally, there is an opening
for someone over 35 years of age
who may have specialized skills
that are needed at Bethel,
such as those with certain technical
or medical experience, translation skills,
or building trades such as plumbing, electrical,
heavy equipment mechanics, or carpentry.
Those with such capabilities and training
are welcome to apply.
In view of the unique demands
of a full-time assignment at Bethel,
you should be mentally and emotionally sound,
physically strong, and able to work long hours.
You should be able to read, write,
and speak the primary language
of the branch territory.
This will enable you to communicate well
with others serving at Bethel,
to receive needed training, and to work safely
in the Bethel environment.
Bethel applicants agree to serve
for a minimum of one year,
during which time you will receive training
for continued Bethel service.
With regard to secular skills,
we do not encourage individuals
to obtain university education
or training with the thought that this will improve
their chances of being called into Bethel.
The best way to prepare for Bethel service
is to first serve in the full-time pioneer ministry.
The greatest need is for single brothers.
However, all who meet
the qualifications, including sisters,
are encouraged to apply
for temporary volunteer service.
Serving as
a temporary volunteer at Bethel may open
the way to other opportunities
to expand your service to Jehovah.
If you are interested
in applying for Bethel service,
which application should you request
from a member
of your Congregation Service Committee?
Since there are two types
of applications available, first give careful
and prayerful consideration
to your circumstances.
Thereafter, decide whether
you will request from the elders
the Application for Volunteer Program (A-19),
which is available for those interested
in serving on a temporary basis
for as brief as one week or as long
as several consecutive months.
Or you may decide to request
the Application to Become
a Member of the Worldwide Order
of Special Full-Time Servants
of Jehovah’s Witnesses (A-8).
This application is for those interested
in serving on a long-term basis
for one full year or longer.
If the Branch Committee
determines that there is a need
for your services, they will decide
where you can best be used, whether at Bethel
or perhaps on
a theocratic construction assignment.
Submitting your application may open
a door of opportunity to serve Jehovah
and his organization in a variety of ways.
Of course, not all of us
who have such a self-sacrificing spirit
have the circumstances in life to serve at Bethel.
But we can encourage others who do.
Parents, follow the example
of God-fearing parents
such as Hannah and Elkanah,
who willingly made their son available
for expanded theocratic privileges.
Continue to place the goal
of Bethel service before your young ones,
and stimulate
their interest in the full-time ministry
by your example and your positive expressions.
If possible,
bring them on tour
of world headquarters in New York, U.S.A.,
or make arrangements
to bring them on a tour of the Bethel
in the branch territory in which you live.
Such visits can help
young ones to witness firsthand
the work that’s being done
at Bethel to promote Kingdom interests.
Elders, help young ones in your congregation
who have the potential to expand their service
to Jehovah to meet the qualifications.
Jehovah continues to look
for those willing to respond
to his invitation to expand their service to him.
As in Isaiah’s day, He asks:
“Whom shall I send, and who will go for us?”
Will you answer as did the prophet:
“Here I am! Send me!”
We encourage you to progress to spiritual maturity
and serve Jehovah whole-souled.
In due time, you may qualify to serve at Bethel
or in another form of exciting theocratic service
that permits you to use the health and strength
that Jehovah has granted you in an expanded way,
all to his praise.
Please be assured that we love you
for the willing spirit you show
as you continue to reach out in Jehovah’s service.
Thank you, Pat.
We hope
that the information Brother LaFranca shared
motivates many more to have
the prophet Isaiah’s willing and self-sacrificing spirit.
So much of what Jehovah provides encourages us
to keep busy with spiritual things.
For one,
we’re looking forward to our upcoming conventions.
The theme for this year is “‘Love Never Fails’!”
Would you like a preview of the program?
Let’s take a look.
Love
—is it gone?
Have we lost it?
Is it the possession of the wealthy?
the strong?
Or is it somewhere else?
At the 2019 convention of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
you will learn what real love is,
where to find it,
and how to show it
and have it shown in return.
God cares deeply about you.
And he wants you to know
that in this hate-filled world,
love can be found.
It is not lost.
And that love will never fail.
As we’ve discussed,
we should never underestimate the power
of our brotherhood
to help us overcome worries and anxiety.
Our conventions are wonderful opportunities
for us to encourage one another
by the hundreds,
thousands, and tens of thousands.
And this year, we’re especially excited
that 24 international conventions
will be held throughout the world.
Use the opportunity
to get to know more of your brothers and sisters
at the regional
or international convention you attend.
To conclude this month’s program,
let’s visit our brothers in Turkey.
Turkey is a nation of more than 80 million people
and a land rich in Bible history.
Turkey occupies a unique geographic position,
bridging Europe and Asia.
It’s here that Noah’s ark
came to rest near Mount Ararat,
Turkey’s highest mountain.
This is the land
of the congregations in Colossae and Galatia,
as well as all seven congregations
mentioned in Revelation.
The territory is diverse and vast,
with a publisher-to-population ratio
of 1 to more than 26,000.
In the capital city of Ankara,
a single congregation is working hard
to reach almost 5.5 million people.
Many congregations in Turkey
focus on public witnessing, with encouraging results.
Let’s visit the Hatay Congregation,
near the ancient city of Syrian Antioch.
Paul used Antioch
as his home base for his missionary tours.
And it was here
that the disciples were first called Christians.
Today,
this part of Turkey is known for its food
—such as spices, herbs, fruits, and sweets.
In recent times,
unrest and war have disrupted the region.
Some of our brothers and sisters
have been so near to the conflict
that they could hear
explosions from bombs and gunfire.
Despite these threats and anxieties,
the 56 publishers, including 11 regular pioneers
and 2 special pioneers, attend the meetings
and preach without letup.
Our brothers and sisters
in Turkey send their love and greetings
to the worldwide brotherhood.
Our love goes back to them
for their zeal and steadfast faith.
From the World Headquarters
of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
this is JW Broadcasting.