Welcome to another edition
of JW Broadcasting!
This month we will see examples
of what young ones
around the world
have done to seek
the Kingdom first.
Also,
you will meet a brother
who got into a lot of trouble
early in his life.
But how did the truth help him
to straighten out his life?
We look forward to his story.
We will also visit
a language course in Ecuador.
What is it like
to learn a new language
to expand our ministry?
We will find out.
This is the March program
of JW Broadcasting!
My theme for this month’s broadcast is
“Young Ones
—Build Your Future With Jehovah!”
If you do,
1 Timothy 6:19 assures
that you will
‘safely treasure up for yourself
a fine foundation for the future,’
and you will
“get a firm hold on the real life.”
Obviously, we will be directing
many of our comments
directly to you dear young ones
in Jehovah’s organization.
Yet, if we think about it,
all of us figuratively
are very young ones
compared to eternity
—how long we hope to live.
So, in a sense,
our comments during this broadcast
have application to all of us.
Personally, I am so thankful to Jehovah
that positive peer pressure
was put on me
to enter the pioneer ministry
right out of high school.
What a blessing and a protection
it was to enter
the regular pioneer work
at age 17
and to be able to go to Bethel at 18.
Even though there was considerable
worldly pressure put on me
to pursue university education,
I am so happy that with Jehovah’s help,
I decided to build my future
with Jehovah.
Truly, I have no regrets.
And this is always true of young ones
who serve Jehovah from their hearts
—they have no regrets.
In fact, you will enjoy
these expressions from young ones
who are building
their future with Jehovah.
Before I started pioneering,
I was really nervous that I wouldn’t be able
to get my time in every month.
It was a bit hard when I started pioneering
because I didn’t have a car.
My boss,
he didn’t give me part-time work.
I found it really hard
to balance schoolwork
and pioneering
at the same time.
My biggest struggle was fear of man,
so that really hindered me
because I wasn’t very good
at talking to people.
Having a good routine was a struggle.
My brother and I are
the only ones in the truth.
My family didn’t understand
why we wanted to go preaching.
I didn’t think
that I’d make a good pioneer.
I’ve had Type 1 diabetes
since I was five.
So I was always worried
about whether or not
I could balance that health condition
with pioneering.
The challenges
don’t seem that big now,
but back at that time
they were a really big deal.
But the coolest thing
was how Jehovah helped me.
Prayer to Jehovah
helped me overcome my fears.
My family was
a massive help from Jehovah.
Because my dad was the one
who first encouraged me to pioneer,
when I did start pioneering,
he promised that I would have
the full support of my family.
When I spoke to brothers and sisters
who spent their youth
in the full-time service
that really helped me
because it was really encouraging,
and it really motivated me
to want to make my own memories
and my own experiences
in the full-time service.
So there were
practical things I could do.
I didn’t have a car;
I just walked or I caught the bus.
I had to work out
what my priorities were first.
So I had to find out how many hours
would I have to go witnessing every week.
So then I just sat down
and I looked at every day
and planned out which days
I could go witnessing,
which days I had to go to school,
and also allocated time
so that I could do my homework and study.
Having a schedule
was really good
because I could see it
all out in front of me,
and I could see
that the hour requirement
was actually attainable,
so that made it a lot less daunting.
I first set short-term goals of pioneering
in the special months of activity.
Then I was able
to begin continuous auxiliary,
and then eventually
I started regular pioneering.
One of the best things I did
to prepare myself for pioneering
was to auxiliary pioneer beforehand.
It really set me up
to be able to overcome
any challenges
that I faced while I was pioneering.
I thought about Malachi 3:10.
I knew I trusted in Jehovah,
but this was my chance
to test him out.
I prayed,
put my trust in Jehovah,
and put my application in.
After my form
was in for pioneering,
a brother, with time,
a brother called me and offered me work.
I had unemployment
for three months,
which wasn’t a good time.
But during that time,
I had Jehovah as my main focus.
And so he supported me,
and he didn’t let me down.
Asking brothers and sisters to come
and work with me,
maybe on days that I knew
that I wouldn’t get as much support,
really helped.
That helped me to organize
my hours a little bit more,
and also I’d get to know
my brothers and sisters more as well.
One of the greatest joys of pioneering
has been to pioneer with Mum.
And we had the privilege of going
to the pioneer school together,
which was really special.
Psalm 16:8 reminds me
that Jehovah is right beside me.
When I’m preaching,
it’s like Jehovah is holding my hand.
So with full-time service,
I love making Jehovah happy.
With everything that he has given me,
I’m finally able to give something back.
Looking back
—pioneering—
it was the best decision
I’ve ever made.
It’s opened up
so many different avenues
of service to Jehovah,
and it helped me also
to have that real desire
to want to stay
in full-time service.
Helping someone
on the road to everlasting life,
it’s the best feeling ever;
and it’s really irreplaceable.
The only thing I can say,
“As a young person, start pioneering!”
What a fine attitude
those young ones have!
They are clearly following
in Jesus’ footsteps.
Jesus was the wisest man
who ever walked the earth.
He could’ve pursued any career
and truly excelled at it.
He could’ve been
the greatest carpenter who ever lived.
Think about it,
he helped his Father
build the physical universe.
Can you imagine
what kind of houses he could’ve built?
Or what if he had pursued
being an inventor?
With his perfect brain,
he probably could’ve invented
the telephone,
automobile, or computer
in the first century.
Or what about becoming
a businessman?
With perfect intelligence,
he likely could’ve come out on top
of every business transaction
that he entered,
becoming the richest businessman
who ever lived.
Or have you ever thought about
if he had pursued becoming
an athlete?
And excelling in athletic contests
was a huge endeavor in Jesus’ day.
With a little training,
it is likely that his perfect body
would have outperformed all people
with imperfect bodies,
enabling him to become
the most famous athlete who ever lived.
Or one more example,
what if he had decided to become a doctor?
He could cure sick people
—even raise the dead.
Can you imagine how much
he could’ve charged rich people
to raise their dead loved ones?
But Jesus pursued none of these careers.
Why?
Because he knew
that any of such endeavors
would have only very limited
and temporary benefits.
Instead, he pursued something
he knew would bring far-reaching
and everlasting benefits:
the full-time ministry.
If this is how the wisest man
who ever walked the earth—
If this is how he reasoned,
we are wise if we strive to think
the same way.
That makes me think of the comments
of a well-adjusted teenage brother
whom we served
while in the circuit work many years ago.
This young brother went straight into
the regular pioneer work
out of high school,
and I asked him why he did so.
He explained that he knew
he could’ve gotten a full-time secular job
and bought a new car for himself,
but he reasoned that in a few years
that car would rust out and break down,
and he would have nothing.
But he knew that he could go
into the pioneer work
and build a close relationship
with Jehovah
and perhaps even find
an honest-hearted person
and be able to teach that one the truth.
And he knew that would last forever.
Now, that is some wise thinking
on the part of that young brother.
And today, that brother
has a beautiful Christian wife
and several spiritual children,
and he is serving as a fine elder.
But if you young ones
are going to think this way
and continue to pursue spiritual goals,
it is vital that you wisely choose
your associates.
In a sense, our associates
can be likened to an elevator.
What do we mean?
Well, they can take you up
or they can take you down.
If you choose wisely,
they will take you up
—elevate your good qualities
and make you a better person.
But if you choose poorly,
they will take you down.
Depending on how badly you choose,
they can take you way down
—to the basement,
even the subbasement.
At Proverbs 13:20,
our loving heavenly Father,
who made us,
explains how it works.
Jehovah tells us there:
“The one walking with the wise
“will become wise,
“but the one
who has dealings with the stupid
will fare badly.”
“Walking with”
and “having dealings with”
mean “associating with.”
And who are the “stupid” ones?
Well, this scripture contrasts
such a person
with those who are wise.
It is not talking about someone
who lacks mental intellect.
It is talking about someone
who does not make
wise decisions spiritually
from Jehovah’s standpoint.
And if we think about it,
anyone who is not really serving Jehovah
—at least right now—
that one is unwise indeed.
And if we associate closely with such ones,
Jehovah says that we “will fare badly.”
We could use another illustration.
Think about someone who is physically sick
and is running a high fever.
If we spend a lot of time with that person,
we will probably catch the same sickness.
Or worse,
if we spend a lot of time
near a dead body—a corpse—
we will probably pick up a disease.
Well, it is similar
with spending time with a person
who is spiritually sick,
or worse, spiritually dead.
On the other hand,
if we choose as our associates
those who love Jehovah
and who are building
their everlasting future with Jehovah,
we will benefit greatly.
Please observe carefully
this variety of young ones
who are busy storing up
treasures in heaven
with Jehovah.
How heartwarming it is to us
—and we know it is to Jehovah—
to see these beautiful young people
doing what Jesus encourages
at Matthew 6:20, 21.
There, Jesus encourages:
“Store up for yourselves
treasures in heaven,
“where neither moth nor rust consumes,
“and where thieves do not break in and steal.
“For where your treasure is,
there your heart will be also.”
And if we think about it,
in the final analysis,
after all is said and done,
whether we are younger or older,
our net worth will be
what we have stored up
in heaven with Jehovah.
We will not be able to take
material treasures with us
through the great tribulation.
And if we die,
we certainly will not be able to take
material treasures with us,
but we can take spiritual treasures
with us through the great tribulation
and even through death and resurrection.
It is true with all of Jehovah’s people,
as it is with the anointed,
what is stated at Revelation 14:13.
It says there:
“The things they did go right with them.”
And how encouraging it is
to see young ones getting baptized
—publicly demonstrating
that they are giving their lives to Jehovah.
And we sincerely hope
that you young ones
who are not yet baptized
will not hold back from getting baptized
as soon as you qualify.
The sooner you can get baptized,
the sooner you will receive
greater protection
and blessings from Jehovah.
Not long ago,
it made me very happy
to observe a little ten-year-old brother
get baptized!
And young ones,
never be afraid to identify yourselves
as one of Jehovah’s Witnesses.
Never allow the fear
of what others may think
to cause you to hesitate to do so.
Jehovah tells us
at Proverbs 29:25:
“Trembling at men is a snare,
“but the one trusting in Jehovah
will be protected.”
Many years ago when I was in school,
I can remember being
at times somewhat worried
about how my fellow classmates
would view me.
But then a little while later,
I got out of school
and never ever again even saw
most of those former classmates.
Then it dawned on me
that it doesn’t really matter
what people think about us.
It is Jehovah’s rating of us
that truly counts.
Humans cannot add
even five seconds to our lifespan,
but Jehovah can add
or subtract eternity.
And he alone
can also give us true happiness.
And as Proverbs 29:25 indicates,
what a protection
it is to courageously identify ourselves
as one of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
fully trusting Jehovah
and taking our stand solidly with him.
Never be ashamed of who you are.
You are one of Jehovah’s Witnesses.
And please, dear young ones,
we warmly encourage you
to listen to those who love you.
Jehovah loves you very much;
the Governing Body loves you very much;
the elders love you very much;
your Christian parents love you very much.
And these ones will tell you the truth,
even though at times
it may not be what you want to hear.
They will not ‘tickle your ears,’
perhaps like ones at school
or in the neighborhood
who don’t really love you
or have your best interests at heart.
But please believe those
who will tell you the truth
because they love you.
And never view
Jehovah’s laws and principles
as depriving you of something good.
View them as protecting you
from what will hurt you.
If you recall,
Satan convinced Eve
that she was being deprived by Jehovah
and was missing out on something good.
Now, it is true that Eve
was missing out on something.
But what was she really missing out on?
A tormented conscience,
her beautiful hair turning gray,
her teeth falling out,
her perfect skin wrinkling up like a prune,
being bent over from old age,
hobbling around on a cane,
and finally dying!
But Satan convinced her
that Jehovah was depriving her,
so foolishly she reached out to get
what she thought she was missing out on.
Well, Satan will try to use
the same kind of strategy on you,
but please don’t let him do it!
This also makes me think
of an experience a brother once related.
He said that he was visiting
an animal observatory,
and a large lion lunged toward him
but was prevented from reaching him
by a thick glass pane
separating the animals from the observers.
As the lion stood on his hind legs,
clawing the glass
and baring his massive teeth,
the brother came to realize in a special way
the protective value of that barrier.
Previously, he said
that he somewhat viewed the glass pane
as a restriction
because the smudges on it
partially blurred his view,
but now he viewed it
as a real protection.
Well, in a similar way,
Jehovah doesn’t want Satan,
who is described
as ‘a roaring, devouring lion’
at 1 Peter 5:8—
He doesn’t want him
to gobble down you young ones.
And His laws and principles
are designed to keep that
from happening to you.
So please listen to Jehovah.
He loves you!
You would probably agree
that having good friends
is of great encouragement
in your service to Jehovah.
You may also recognize
that there is more
to being a friend
than simply clicking links
on a computer screen
or a smartphone.
But where can you find
good friends
when there seems to be
no one to choose from?
In this dramatization,
consider the example
of this young brother
who struggled
with this very question.
My name is Akil.
When I was 18,
my family moved to a new city.
It was bad enough
leaving my friends behind.
But now,
I wasn’t sure
if I could make new ones.
My parents seemed really happy.
I didn’t want
to make them feel bad
by telling them how I really felt.
The new school
wasn’t much better
until I met Cameron.
He seemed
like a pretty cool guy.
Soon, his friends
became my friends.
. . . something that David
believed was true,
he actually proved it
by the association that he kept.
We think about one
of the closest friendships
recorded in the Scriptures,
and it was
that of David and Jonathan.
What was it that David and Jonathan
shared in common?
It wasn’t their age.
Akil,
you were texting in the meeting.
I shouldn’t have sent the text.
I’m sorry.
But Cameron is a good person.
He might even study one day.
I understand that, Akil.
But we all have to be careful
with how much time
we spend with people
that don’t love Jehovah.
See,
their values are just different.
You know
what Proverbs 13:20 says:
‘Walk with those who are wise.’
So why don’t you seek out
friends who love Jehovah?
And you will make friends
that last a lifetime.
How am I supposed to do that?
There’s no one my age
in the congregation.
Akil, good friends
can come from unexpected places.
Mom,
I had good friends
—back home.
We all felt bad that night.
The next day,
Cameron posted pictures
of a party he had.
My parents were right.
I broke off my association
with Cameron
and his friends,
but I still felt
lost.
Hi, Akil?
Do you have
field service plans for Saturday?
Ah, no.
Good.
Now you do.
I’ll see you
at the 9:30 a.m. meeting, OK?
After service,
Max had the group
over for refreshments.
Did you take these?
Do you like them?
Yeah.
My wife,
she was always the photographer.
She loved photography.
And then one anniversary
she went out and bought me a camera,
and from that moment on,
I was hooked too.
Time flies so quickly.
It’s hard to believe
she passed away 12 years ago now.
I’m sorry.
It’s OK.
But you still take pictures?
I do.
I really enjoy photography.
There’s something about being close
to Jehovah’s creation.
It reminds me
that we’re never really alone,
you know?
Good friends can come
from unexpected places
and unexpected ages.
As I spent more time with Max,
I realized it was
just like David and Jonathan.
Their friendship was based,
not on age,
but on their love for Jehovah.
And they helped each other.
And with Max’s help,
I was able to keep
a good spiritual routine
without interruption.
Although we weren’t the same age,
Max became my good friend.
I just needed to see
what was right
in front of me.
Yes, friends can come in various ages.
And the best kind of friend
is one who encourages us
in our service to Jehovah.
We all need to work hard
on making spiritual progress
—learning new things
about Jehovah and his qualities.
So we want friends
who will help us do that.
There is a saying
that experience
is the best teacher,
but that is not
really accurate.
Experience is often
the hard way to learn.
Brother Fernando Casillas
was born in Mexico,
but when he was a baby,
his family moved
to the United States.
The neighborhood he grew up in
had a lot of gang influence.
This had
a very negative impact on him.
But despite these circumstances,
notice how the truth attracted him.
I used to love violence;
I dreamed of violence.
My gang was my religion.
I got into the prison system
at a young age.
At first, they sent me
to a juvenile facility,
but I got kicked out of there
for a riot.
Basically, they deemed me a threat
to the safety and security
of the institution,
the guards, and other inmates.
And I was sent
to solitary confinement
to finish off my prison term.
Me thinking
I was violent back then
was nothing compared to
what I came out with.
Basically,
what you try to come out to be
is the best killer out of all.
After my incarceration,
I was deported to Mexico.
I used to carry a weapon
with me everywhere I went.
After a while, we started getting involved
with bad people.
Eventually,
my girlfriend got in trouble.
Once that was over,
she saw a Kingdom Hall.
My girlfriend had been
to meetings as a child,
so she basically dragged me
to the Kingdom Hall.
They treated me nice.
And that’s when I started
to get to know Omar.
So I started hanging around
with him and his wife
—me and my girlfriend at the time—
and going to meetings.
But it wasn’t till I found out
this guy
used to be one of my rivals
—I was very, very upset.
I felt betrayed because he never told me.
Everything that was going
through my head was,
‘I’ve got to find a way to get him over here,
so I can hurt him.’
After thinking about all the things
that I wanted to do to him that night
—I’d been running it through my head
over and over again—
I decided to just stay friends with him.
And eventually,
we decided to start studying together.
Being the way I was,
I thought that there’s
no way a God can forgive me.
The scripture at Isaiah 55:7
really helped me,
where it says:
“Let the wicked man leave his way
and the evil man his thoughts;
let him return to Jehovah,
who will have mercy on him.”
As time went by,
I started understanding clearly
that Jehovah does forgive.
By that time, I had already
kind of made a decision
that I was done
with doing time in prison.
I just decided to cut all ties with everybody
that had anything to do
with anything illegal.
I felt like a free person.
And after progressing
and quitting the habits that I had
of smoking and drinking a lot,
I became
an unbaptized publisher.
But my father passed away;
I started hanging around
with bad association again,
and eventually
I had my privileges removed.
And as that was happening,
Satan attacked me again.
So one day,
my wife was crossing the border
to go take care of
some paperwork for the kids
and was surprised
by the border patrol
telling her that there
were drugs in the vehicle.
We did not know
that the previous owner
had stashed drugs in the truck.
Even though later they proved
that the drugs were not my wife’s
and she was released,
they still decided to keep my kids.
What I was thinking of doing
was going back to my old ways
—organizing a plot with my old friends
to bring my kids
back to Mexico to me.
But I decided to rely
on Jehovah instead
and on the brothers
coming to visit me
on a regular basis
and giving me encouraging thoughts
of how Jehovah
will take care of everything.
Eventually, our kids were returned to us,
with Jehovah’s help.
After a little struggle,
of course, I had my privileges back.
A few months later, I was baptized.
I’m a lot happier now
than what I was back then.
One day as I was preaching
in the rehab centers,
I ran into a person
I once knew before, growing up.
Once he found out who I was, he said:
“You’re the reason why I left town.
Every time you would see me,
you would shoot at me.”
So after a while,
I was able to convince him
that actually my purpose there
was not to hurt him anymore
but to teach him the truth
and how to gain everlasting life.
I’m no longer a violent person.
I enjoy the privileges
that Jehovah now gives me.
I have now been serving
as a ministerial servant
for the past two years.
I’m in charge of the accounting
for the Kingdom Hall,
instead of stealing money
as I used to do before.
What I do for a living
is I do gardening work.
Now I don’t carry around knives,
but I carry around my tools.
You could say that I did beat
my pistols into plowshares now
—or weed whacker or lawn mower.
I’m glad that I’m
now serving a great God
who is loving,
caring, and forgiving.
Fernando and his family
are serving
in an English congregation in Mexico.
With everything
Brother Casillas went through,
he could see
that Jehovah is the best teacher.
If you listen to Jehovah,
you won’t have to learn
the hard way.
Jehovah is
“the One teaching you
to benefit yourself.”
Jeremiah 17:13
conveys the thought
that those
who do not serve Jehovah
will have their names
“written in the dust.”
But by building
your future with Jehovah,
you young ones are ensuring
that Jehovah will keep
your individual names
written in his “book of life”
that is mentioned
at Philippians 4:3
and Revelation 3:5.
Earlier in the program,
we saw some examples
of how young ones
are building a future
with Jehovah.
But what impact are such efforts
having on the organization?
Let’s look at one example:
the construction
of the new world headquarters
at Warwick, New York.
Jehovah’s Witnesses built
1.6 million square feet (149,000 sq m)
in less than four years.
Of the 27,035 volunteers,
3,247 were between the ages of 19 and 25.
I thought this was a project
that was going to strictly need
very experienced brothers and sisters.
Early on, I realized I was wrong.
It was also going to take youthful energy
because of the volume of work.
The mix of older and younger ones
was really a helpful thing
on the Warwick project.
The older ones
brought skill and experience.
The younger ones
brought the energy, the muscle,
and the diligence to stay
with hard physical tasks
all the way through the project.
Whether it was in the kitchen
or night watch
or the early 5:00 a.m. start
with the concrete crew
at 10 degrees Fahrenheit (-12°C),
their joy and their humility was outstanding
to accept any work that needed to be done.
And a lot of young ones,
brothers and sisters,
moved into the area
so they could commute.
And they would work
day after day tirelessly,
into the evenings even,
to have the project ready for the next day.
Their energy was just astonishing.
Jehovah loves young ones,
and he’s willing to invest in them
and train them and make them
a part of his organization.
And I saw that so much.
We had a lot of young people
who offered themselves
with technical skills.
But if the humility of these
very technically-skilled young people
didn’t match
or exceed their abilities,
then, really,
Jehovah couldn’t use them.
And they were willing to adjust,
and we really saw the benefit.
We knew and they knew
that they were building
not just a project at Warwick
—they were building
a spiritual project for Jehovah.
You could see Jehovah’s spirit
operating on them.
You could see them
mature so quickly.
These young brothers
are the next generation
of elders
and traveling overseers.
They’re to be commended
and highly respected
for the contribution
they made as young men.
They all talk about the effect
that their Bethel service
has had on their outlook
and how they don’t want
to get caught up
in this world
and its daily pursuits.
Use the skills you’ve learned
here on this project and in Bethel.
You are needed.
Continue to keep your spirituality up
and to keep your association
at a high level.
The highest quality of life is when,
as clay, we put ourselves
in the hands of the Great Potter, Jehovah,
and we say:
“Here I am! Send me!”.
And I’m fully confident
they will have no regrets
building their future
with Jehovah.
Yes, young ones
truly had a beautiful impact
on the construction project
of world headquarters!
By the way,
you may find it interesting to know
that the Warwick
and Wallkill construction projects
were not funded
by the donations
that you have made
to the worldwide work.
Your donations are being used
to support the work
in the worldwide field.
The massive construction projects
at Warwick and Wallkill
were funded by the sale
of properties in Brooklyn.
In effect,
we just traded locations.
We traded the value
of the properties in Brooklyn
for the beautiful facilities
at Warwick and Wallkill.
And I must say,
the Governing Body is truly enjoying
the new facility at Warwick,
thanks to the hard work,
both of the young and the older ones
who labored in our behalf,
and we truly appreciate it.
The apostle Paul said of Timothy
as recorded
at Philippians 2:20-23:
“For I have no one else
of a disposition like his
“who will genuinely care
for your concerns.
“For all the others
are seeking their own interests,
“not those of Jesus Christ.
“But you know the proof
he gave of himself,
“that like a child with a father
“he slaved with me
to advance the good news.
Therefore,
he is the one I am hoping to send.”
It is obvious that Paul
loved the young man Timothy very much
because of his unselfish hard work
in behalf of Kingdom interests.
Well, the Governing Body
feels exactly the same way
about you dear young ones
who are working hard
in your various theocratic assignments.
In addition to the many avenues
of full-time service
we mentioned earlier
in the program,
making yourself available
when a need arises locally
is a fine way
to seek the Kingdom first.
For example, in San Antonio,
in the state of Texas,
in the United States,
a large convention
with over 20,000
in attendance was planned.
However,
the venue could only provide
about one third of the chairs needed
for the convention.
Where would our brothers
find the needed chairs?
Well, Jehovah provided,
and many young ones
were eager to help.
When I heard
that this needed to happen,
I was thinking,
‘How are we going to do this?’
I thought, ‘It’s a big job!’
It was amazing!
The first thing I was asked to do
was try to find a storage place
that we could use
for six to eight thousand chairs.
A sister manages a storage place,
and we saw Jehovah’s blessing
because the owner said,
“You can have this stall
“at no charge for a year
as long as you sign a contract
that it’s
for Jehovah’s Witnesses’ organization.”
Truckload after truckload
after truckload came in.
We had to unload the trucks.
The brothers had
to unstack the chairs,
repair the chairs, clean the chairs,
put them back on pallets,
restack them,
load them onto trucks,
and that was half of it.
Those were the ones
in the warehouse.
On the other side,
we got permission to ask
the San Antonio congregations
if we could use their chairs
for the convention.
We were hoping
to get three thousand chairs.
And then the numbers
grew for the audience,
so we had to increase
our numbers.
So we were able to gather
six thousand chairs
from the willing volunteers
of congregations around San Antonio.
So we prayed about it and the brothers
started asking for volunteers,
and it was a great cooperation
right at the beginning.
As soon as
we let the friends know
that this was going
to be the case,
all of them—
all of them said,
“We’re going to get off
of work early.”
We immediately wanted
to clear our schedules
so that we could be available
to help in any way that we could.
It was a privilege to know
that our congregation
was going to be part of it.
We are so grateful to Jehovah
that he has given us
this privilege to do.
We had thousands of chairs
of every color
—green, red, brown, blue.
We even had some bright orange ones
left out of the ‘70’s,
and we’re putting those in the back.
But it was not just the colors
but the sizes.
They were all different sizes.
And so how do you make
sections with straight rows
when the chairs
are all different sizes?
But I knew somehow,
as Jehovah’s people, we’d get it done.
And we definitely—
As you see, a lot of volunteers,
and we’re here getting it done.
And it’s made
for a beautiful experience
because the friends have gotten to know
each other as never before.
And they’re willingly
working together,
and the excitement is there.
It doesn’t matter whose venue it is,
it’s all for Jehovah,
and that’s been
the attitude everybody has had.
It just tells you
that Jehovah is a God of order.
It’s good to feel
that you’re doing your best for Jehovah.
Well, it reminds me of Psalm 127:1,
where it mentions
that ‘unless Jehovah builds the house,
it’s in vain that his workers
even work hard.’
So it’s because of Jehovah’s hand
and his blessing
—that is why everything
runs so smoothly.
What other organization!
No one else can do that
except Jehovah’s people.
It truly is a fine witness
when our young ones
wholeheartedly give
of their time.
Proverbs 20:29 says:
“The glory of young men
is their strength.”
And commendably,
you young men and women
are using your strength
to make a name
with Jehovah.
Have you ever considered
helping out in a foreign-language field?
Perhaps there is a need
in your local circuit.
All over the earth,
the organization
provides language courses
with the goal of reaching
every nation, tribe, tongue, and people
with the good news of God’s Word.
Brother Juan Carlos Chacón
serves as a special pioneer
in the rapidly growing Shuar language field
in Ecuador.
He was recently asked to attend
a course at the local branch
to become a language teacher
so that he could help
willing publishers
learn the language.
[Speaking Shuar]
It has been said before,
“This is a language of the Devil”
—that it should be forgotten.
It serves no purpose.
But to Jehovah,
no nation is insignificant.
I grew up in an area
of the Ecuadorian jungle
where there is
a large community
of Shuar people.
Like many native languages,
Shuar is very complex.
We need many, many workers in the field.
But if we don’t give them a foundation,
if we don’t help them
or give them a little push,
it’s difficult for them to enter this field.
I received an invitation to attend
a seminar for language instructors.
There were 58 students in the class,
representing 16 different languages
or language groups.
We are learning
fantastic teaching techniques,
real techniques that work.
The instructor told us how humor helps
our minds to create a world of connections,
which stimulates our brain.
Yeah, I’m like a small child
when it comes to drawing.
I never learned to draw well.
We draw a scene,
and starting with our native language
along with large gestures,
we act out a dialogue.
Little by little,
we convert the scene
into the new language.
What scares me?
That I’ve never done this before.
This will be my first time.
I don’t have any experience
teaching languages.
Although I felt intimidated by this,
I knew that with Jehovah
all things are possible.
Welcome to the first day
of the Shuar language course.
The techniques they offered us
in the course were like a box of tools
that we need to study more carefully
and see how to apply them
in each circumstance.
When we are in the territory,
we see how people’s eyes
light up when they learn
the name of God.
Just seeing that there is so much need
for them to learn the truth,
that has motivated us to come here
and continue serving here.
Since God has created us,
we know that he will
never abandon us.
He thinks about us all the time,
and he loves us very much.
I didn’t know that before.
I feel so happy now
because I can really understand
the Word of God.
Being in an isolated group
far from other congregations,
my wife and I
have felt every day
how real Jehovah is.
Jehovah is now looking
and giving his attention
to these small places,
no matter how small they are.
If people have a good heart
and want to serve Jehovah,
he will send workers
to give the help that is needed.
And in reality, this moves us
to say to him with all of our heart,
“Thank you, Jehovah.”
There is a lot to do
in Jehovah’s organization
regardless of our age.
Even if our circumstances
may restrict us,
Jehovah sees and values
all of our efforts
to expand our ministry
and to build
an everlasting future with him.
Our music video for this month
is appropriately entitled
Building My Future With Jehovah.
At times, I wish I could see
exactly what my future will be
And how my life will turn out
and which road is the right one for me.
But one thing’s for sure,
no matter what comes along,
I live for Jehovah,
to him I belong.
Of all the people and things
my life could be filled with,
The best one of all,
the best one to build with,
Is pleasing Jehovah each day
with the choices I make.
He gave me all that I have;
I’ll never forget it.
I’m safe in his hands;
I’ll never regret it.
I’m building my future with him
ev’ry step that I take.
At times, the chance comes along
to take a path I know to be wrong,
A path that leads me away
from the place that I know I belong.
But keeping in mind
the dedication I made
Can give me the firmness and faith
that won’t fade.
Of all the people and things
my life could be filled with,
The best one of all,
the best one to build with,
Is pleasing Jehovah each day
with the choices I make.
He gave me all that I have;
I’ll never forget it.
I’m safe in his hands;
I’ll never regret it.
I’m building my future with him
ev’ry step that I take.
I’m building a future
that never will end
If I build it with help
from Jehovah, my Friend.
The happiest moments,
the best life can give,
Come from pleasing Jehovah
each day that I live.
Of all the people and things
my life could be filled with,
The best one of all,
the best one to build with,
Is pleasing Jehovah each day
with the choices I make.
He gave me all that I have;
I’ll never forget it.
I’m safe in his hands;
I’ll never regret it.
I’m building my future with him
ev’ry step that I take.
I’m building my future
with him ev’ry step that I take.
An encouraging song indeed!
We encourage all young ones
to take the message of this program
—to build a future with Jehovah—
to heart.
Prayerfully consider what you can do
to expand your ministry.
Always safeguard
your most valuable possession
—your precious relationship
with Jehovah.
Never forget
that there are more with you
than there are against you.
It is true that Satan, the demons,
and this world are against you.
But your brothers and sisters,
including the Governing Body,
are with you;
the angels are with you;
the resurrected immortal anointed ones
are with you;
Jesus is with you;
and most important,
Jehovah is with you.
You are never alone!
To conclude,
we have greetings
to share with you
from the special convention
that was held
in July of last year
in Paris, France.
I had the privilege
of attending this convention
with Brother Kenneth Flodin,
a helper to the Teaching Committee.
While most of the convention program
was in French,
it was simultaneously interpreted
into Croatian, English,
and Polish
for the benefit
of the international delegates.
You will be happy to know
that 71 new sisters
and 41 new brothers
symbolized their dedication
through water baptism.
The oldest baptismal candidate
was an 80-year-old sister
and the youngest
was a 10-year-old.
The young candidates
had to overcome
various challenges in order
to reach their goal
of baptism.
Four of them took this step
even though their parents
are not Jehovah’s Witnesses.
Many of these dear young ones
had to overcome
peer pressure at school
—pressure to do things
Jehovah does not like.
Two of the young brothers,
also fleshly brothers,
used to play
violent video games.
Through their personal Bible study
and the personal interest
shown in them,
they came to understand
Jehovah’s viewpoint on violence
and made the necessary changes
to progress spiritually.
By taking this first step
of getting baptized,
these brothers and sisters have shown
that they want to build a future
with Jehovah.
Let us all do everything
we can to continue making
spiritual progress,
which will bring
Jehovah’s smile of approval.
Brothers and sisters,
we love you very much.
This is JW Broadcasting
from the world headquarters
of Jehovah’s Witnesses.