Hello, everyone.
We’re so happy to have you with us
for this month’s broadcast.
As you can see,
I have a friend with me as cohost.
We are friends, aren’t we?
Yes, we are, David.
Oh, that’s so good to hear.
This is Herman van Selm.
He’s a helper to the Writing Committee,
and we work together
every day in the Writing Department.
Herman has quite a background.
He was born in the Netherlands
and spent a number of years
as a missionary in South America.
What was that like, Herman?
Thank you, David, for asking.
My wife, Kay, and I
served in three different lands.
Now, to sum up that part of our life,
three words come to mind:
challenging,
amazing, rewarding.
In one challenging assignment,
we lived in a remote area in the rain forest
where there were no other Witnesses.
We wondered: ‘Will we be able
‘to find people who want to serve Jehovah?
Where do we start?’
We got on our bikes
and visited all the villagers.
In time, we conducted about 25 Bible studies.
Wow!
Now,
despite fierce opposition from neighbors,
the Bible students made amazing progress.
For example, one woman, with her children,
worked hard to build this beautiful hut,
and it brought us to tears when she told us:
“This hut, we made it for our meetings.
It is for Jehovah.”
Amazing!
One day, a group of courageous Bible students
showed us the letters they had written
to resign as members of their church.
Now, that week, the church’s pastor
in that tiny village received
a lot of mail!
I guess, mail he didn’t want to receive.
It was no fan mail.
It was such
a rewarding experience for Kay and me
to see close up
how Jehovah made that little group
grow into a congregation.
In fact, it strengthens the faith
of all of us, wherever we may live,
to see how Jehovah cares for people
who are often viewed
as insignificant by the world
but who are precious in God’s eyes.
Great pictures—I love it!
Now, what can the friends
look forward to this month?
Well, David, this month
we’ll meet Andrey Nesmachniy,
a retired professional
soccer player whose story
may help us to analyze
our own priorities in life.
Later, we’ll see how Thomas learns to balance
his secular work with his spiritual needs.
And we’ll enjoy an upbeat music video
that reminds us all of the wonderful “family”
we enjoy in Jehovah’s organization.
Sounds exciting, let’s get started!
This is the September 2019 program
of JW Broadcasting.
This month,  I’m going to talk
about two different subjects.
First, I’d like to talk about the translation
of our publications,
and there’s a particular aspect
of translation I’d like to comment on.
Now, I know
that quite a number of you have moved
to a country
where your mother tongue isn’t spoken
—either to find work
or to serve where the need is greater.
And others are serving right at home
but in foreign-language congregations.
At times, you may have compared
an article in your mother tongue
with the same article in your second language
and found differences in the translation,
and you might wonder why that is.
Well, we’d never conclude
that the translators
had been unfaithful or careless
or that they were running
ahead of the organization.
No.
We trust
our hardworking brothers and sisters.
So we know there must be
good reasons for the differences,
and the purpose of this brief discussion
is to suggest what some
of those reasons might be.
First, a word about one
of the principles our translators follow.
They’re expected not only to render
the thought in the English text accurately
but also to keep in mind
the way people speak.
So accuracy, clarity,
and naturalness are needed
while maintaining the dignity of our message.
Now, what’s involved
in preparing a translation
that’s both accurate and natural?
It’s not as if the translators
are like the Jewish scribes
who made copies of the Hebrew Scriptures.
To make sure that the copies they made
were accurate in every detail,
they would count not only every word
but also every letter
they copied from the source text.
Translation is not like that.
It’s not as if there must be
seven words in the target language
if there are seven words in English.
Every word in English may not be translated,
but the complete thought
of the English has to be there.
English makes effective use of repetition.
What do we mean by that?
Well, you can write one sentence in English
and then repeat the same thought
in slightly different words
in the next sentence,
and it sounds fine.
But in some languages,
to repeat a thought
would be viewed as poor writing,
and that wouldn’t reflect well
on our publications.
So in such cases,
the translators are allowed to combine
two sentences into just one sentence
as long as the thought
is completely conveyed.
Or they might make two sentences
out of one long English sentence
if that’s more natural in the language.
So you can’t always compare
the length of an English paragraph
with the length of the paragraph
in the target language and say,
“Hey, this paragraph
is shorter than that paragraph.”
Sometimes we hear brothers
who have learned a second language say:
“I don’t see why the translators
didn’t follow the English word for word.
After all,
you can say that in the language.”
Well, you may have the words.
It may be possible to “say” that,
but would a literal translation
sound strange to native speakers?
No matter how well a foreigner
has learned a language,
native speakers who speak
the language well
are usually the best judge
of what is natural.
Modesty will help foreign speakers
to recognize that.
There’s another thing
that foreign speakers need to be aware of.
If they’re vocal
in their criticism of a certain translation,
how would that affect
the confidence of native speakers
who have to rely on the translation
for their spiritual food?
Of course, nobody is perfect,
and as long as translation
is done by imperfect people,
it won’t be perfect.
But rest assured that our translators
take their work very seriously.
The subject of translation is complex.
And I’m surely no expert.
Let’s hear from some brothers
who have worked in the field for many years
and see what we can learn.
Meet Nick Ahladis,
Nick Exarcheas,
and Saki Marais.
As we have just heard,
the goal of translators is to convey ideas
accurately, naturally, and clearly.
This isn’t an easy thing to do.
Let’s discuss
a few of the challenges of translation.
We will focus on three areas
and see why translators
make the choices they do:
Bible expressions,
illustrations,
and vocabulary.
So our first point is Bible expressions.
Nick, could you please tell us
why translating some expressions in the Bible
can be very challenging?
Well, before our brothers and sisters
receive the New World Translation
in their language,
they have to use Bibles
produced by Christendom.
Often, these Bibles
contain false religious ideas
and terms that reflect those ideas.
So when we produce the New World Translation,
great care has to be taken
not to allow such terms
to distort our translation.
Can you give us an example of an expression
that was translated the wrong way
in the Bibles produced by Christendom?
Well, one example is the term “holy spirit.”
In many Bibles produced by Christendom,
the term gives the idea
of a spirit creature in heaven,
even a “holy ghost,”
sometimes even a “holy demon.”
That must be very confusing to the readers.
But what can the translators do about that?
In many languages,
our translators have found
that the closest way
to translate “holy spirit”
is to say “holy power” or “holy force.”
This may sound very different,
but it conveys the same idea.
And even the English New World Translation
describes the term “holy spirit”
as “God’s active force” at Genesis 1:2,
while other English translations
say “God’s holy spirit.”
Good.
So now the brothers
can use an expression
that is understood
by the field and the audience.
But it must be a wonderful thing
to have the New World Translation.
Yes, it’s a wonderful thing.
But still, the brothers
have to get used to the new terms.
Remember that they’ve been using
the original terms
in their local Bibles for years
to teach people the truth.
But as they get used to the new terminology
in their personal study,
at meetings, and in the ministry,
they begin to see
the benefits of the new terms,
and afterward they really embrace
the New World Translation.
Thank you.
Now let us go to the second challenge,
illustrations.
Why are illustrations
particularly difficult to translate?
An illustration that works in one culture
might not work in another.
Illustrations are only effective
if the reader can relate to them.
And that’s why Jesus used illustrations
based on everyday things
that his audience was familiar with,
such as farming, building, fishing.
And today, our publications
also use illustrations
that people can relate to.
I remember an article
that discussed the need
for us to be patient in difficult situations.
And it used the illustration
of a driver who is stuck in traffic.
Now, one translation team
wrote to the Translator Help Desk,
and they explained that most of their readers
were not familiar with traffic jams.
For someone who lives in a big city,
that sounds unbelievable, but it’s true.
So the team wanted to use
a different illustration.
They are familiar with the idea
of people standing in long lines,
waiting for their maize, or corn,
to be ground at the milling machine.
And this illustration was approved
because it would help
their readers to get the point:
They need to be patient.
Now, these are
completely different illustrations,
but the point
—or the message—
is the same, for example,
then, about being patient.
Now, when we read in our language edition
of The Watchtower or other publication
a different illustration
than the one we read in English,
we can be confident
that the translators received approval
to make this adjustment
so that the right message is conveyed.
Well, that was very helpful.
Thank you.
Now let us go to our third challenge
—that of vocabulary,
that is,
the words that are used in a language.
Now, we might assume
that for every important word
in our language
there will be an exact equivalent
in another language.
Well, translation
is much more complicated than that.
Take, for example, the word “peace.”
Some years back,
we had a convention about godly peace.
And one might think,
‘Well, that’s an easy word to translate.’
But that word was used about 350 times
in talks on the convention
—sometimes referring to peace
between God and man,
sometimes referring to peace
in family or with our neighbors,
and other times
referring to peace of mind.
Now, in some languages,
there’s simply no way
to use just one word
to convey all those aspects of peace
because they have one word
for the kind of peace that God gives,
a different word for when there’s no war
in a country (that kind of peace),
and a different word to indicate that people
are getting along with one another.
So those translators
need to understand the point
of each usage in the context
and then convey
the right translation accordingly.
Now it opens our minds
to how wonderfully Jehovah made us,
with the capacity to think and feel
and have many concepts and ideas
and to have the ability
to express them in our language
—in words—
to use words for that.
But we express them
in so many different ways.
Yes, it’s so true.
Every language has its own vocabulary
and way of expressing things.
What I find very interesting
is how other languages
render standard expressions
that we use as Jehovah’s Witnesses.
For example,
“field service,” “circuit overseer,”
“Kingdom Hall,” “special pioneer”
—those expressions
were first used in English,
and then translators
had to come up with equivalents
in their languages
so that it would make sense.
But that wouldn’t be difficult
—would it?—
because for the word “kingdom”
surely we have
another word in another language,
and for the word “hall”
we have an equivalent word.
And all you have to do
is put the two words together
to translate “Kingdom Hall.”
They may have the words,
but a literal translation of “Kingdom Hall”
could mean something totally different.
Now, some countries still have a king.
In those places,
this “Kingdom Hall” could mean
“government office,” or it could mean
“hall belonging to the kingdom
of Jehovah’s Witnesses.”
So that would be totally misleading.
And that’s why the Governing Body
has given approval to say
the “Meeting Place of Jehovah’s Witnesses”
or the “Hall of Jehovah’s Witnesses.”
Even though the expressions
sound a little bit different,
the basic intent is the same,
and people get the right idea.
So it is obvious
that the challenges of translation are huge.
But now the question is,
How can a newly formed translation team
or one in a very remote location
have the confidence
and have the assurance
that they produce
the highest standard possible?
Well, all translation teams,
regardless of size or location,
benefit from regular communication
with the Writing Committee
of the Governing Body.
Well, we understand that the Governing Body
directs matters from headquarters,
but do they really know
what the translators are doing?
Well,
the Writing Committee trusts the translators,
but at the same time,
they don’t try to micromanage their work.
What they have done
is set in place training programs
to teach translators
basic translation principles
to help them to understand
how to apply those principles
when translating the publications.
And this ensures that the same message
is being conveyed regardless of language.
And when they’re not sure that their solution
is exactly right on target,
they can write to the Writing Committee
and ask for direction
to inquire whether this solution
conveys the right idea in the context.
Also, the Writing Committee answers
hundreds of translation questions every week
as part of the ongoing training of the teams.
All of the translators
have access to these answers
so that they can learn from one another
how to solve problems
that are delicate and difficult.
This effective communication system
really helps to unify
the thinking of all the translators
and to make sure
that they all produce the same message.
And that unifies
the thinking of the worldwide field.
Well, thank you very much
for explaining those factors
affecting translation,
and it is impressive
that Jehovah has an arrangement in place
that reverses the effect of Babel.
And it is also so wonderful
that by means of his holy spirit,
Jehovah unifies his people around the earth
regardless of what language they use.
Thanks, brothers.
You’ve given us an even deeper appreciation
for all of the work involved
in making a quality translation.
I learned a lot.
I’m sure our audience did too.
Now, the following video
relates an experience
that is very dear to my heart.
You see, in the 1970’s,
my wife and I were in the circuit work
in Montreal, Canada.
Now, one Tuesday evening after the meeting,
I was approached by a ministerial servant.
He was very excited!
He said: “David, I work with a man
who is the head of a small church.
He has invited me to his home!”
“That’s nice,” I said.
He said: “No, no, no, you don’t understand!
“They never invite anyone to their home
unless they are members of the church.
I think this is going to be big.”
“Well,” I said, “if he’s interested,
“invite him to come
to the meeting this weekend.
I’d love to meet him.”
Well, that weekend
I was on the lookout for the man,
but he didn’t show up.
But neither did the ministerial servant.
Soon after, on a Monday morning
—fairly early—
I received a phone call
from Brother Laurier Saumur,
who was well-known in Montreal
and was a special pioneer at the time.
Laurier said: “We have a problem.
“A thousand people want Bible studies,
and many of them are going to be attending
our meetings this week.”
They were the members of that church.
I asked Brother Saumur
to take the lead in organizing the studies.
Now, here’s what happened:
The ministerial servant
had been to the man’s home
and he’d given a good witness.
Then,
the brother met
with the other responsible men of the church.
They were interested in what the Bible says,
and they wanted other members of the church
to learn about the Bible too.
So about half the members of the church,
around 1,000 people,
accepted the invitation
to have a Bible study.
But what moved the leader of the church
to invite the brother
to his home in the first place?
Watch the following video,
and I’ll answer that question at the end.
In the mid-1970’s,
several brothers from the Montréal area
were approached to help
with a unique situation that was unfolding.
A special pioneer,
who was taking the lead at the time,
said that about a thousand people
—all from the same church—
wanted to study the Bible
with Jehovah’s Witnesses.
And it was all because of an informal witness.
The story began this way:
A brother in the local congregation
approached me one day
to tell me about an experience
he had with one of his workmates.
This man was responsible
for a small local church,
and the brother had been able
to give him an informal witness.
The man indicated
that he would like a Bible study,
and he wanted to convince
the other members of his church
to also study the Bible
with Jehovah’s Witnesses.
The fact was that this person
had a certain influence in the church.
So he talked to the church members
about the message
he had heard from the brother,
and he convinced them
that what they were missing
was a better understanding of the Bible.
Many people heard about it
because it was an exceptional event.
From what I heard,
there were around a thousand people
who wanted to study
the Bible at that time.
We didn’t have
the brothers and sisters
that were needed
to conduct all these Bible studies.
So they formed groups
of 10, 12, 15 people.
And once or twice a week in Kingdom Halls,
they conducted Bible studies.
It was questions, questions.
Everyone was asking questions.
But the Bible could always answer
all these questions in a logical way
—one verse would explain another.
And we came to see
that the Bible in its entirety
could explain every subject.
At the beginning,
groups of two or three families studied together.
And, yeah,
they answered with the Bible.
That amazed me because
I didn’t know the Bible at all.
But I thought, ‘The Bible talks about this;
the Bible talks about that.’
It was like a discovery for me.
That was the parents.
The children weren’t there.
So when we accepted it,
then we’d teach it to our children.
Everyone was disciplined while sitting at the table.
The children were very quiet
with their Truth book
in front of them and their Bible.
When these families
came to the Kingdom Hall,
the children were sitting beside their parents,
not moving, paying attention
to what was being said.
I was young when they started coming.
I remember it very well.
A lot of them were my age.
I saw them like future potential friends.
It was really touching.
The first meeting
I attended was here in Laval.
It really contributed to me
one day taking a stand
and Jehovah becoming my God
and the truth becoming my way of life.
When I was young,
I was very afraid of death.
It was such a relief to learn
that we don’t suffer when we die.
It’s like a sleep.
The ambitions I had before,
that may have been attainable,
became second place.
Now it was to have a simple life,
to walk with the organization,
and to raise my children in the truth.
Today, these brothers
are really doing a lot in the organization,
helping in different areas,
shouldering great responsibilities.
My father always strived
to set the example for all his children,
and it made an impression on me.
Now my wife and I have the privilege
of serving here at the Canada branch.
I was eight years old
when my family started attending meetings.
I have really good memories of how
the local congregation at the time
took care of us and looked after us.
At the age of 15,
I started reading my Bible every day
and studying it too.
From that point on,
I knew what I wanted to do with my life
—serve Jehovah full-time.
I really think Jehovah could see us on the inside.
Jehovah helped us a lot.
You can’t have anything better than that.
On our own,
we never would have got out of that situation.
But Jehovah found a way
to find “rightly disposed” ones.
A simple informal witness
led to Bible studies that touched so many.
The brother was able to give a good witness,
but what motivated the church leader
to listen to him in the first place?
It was the brother’s conduct.
He was a very loving brother,
and the way he dealt with others
in the workplace really impressed the man.
The poet said: “I’d rather see a sermon
than hear one any day.”
Those words certainly proved true
in this exciting experience!
That’s an excellent transition
into the next part of our program.
In this dramatization,
we’ll see for ourselves
how a Christian’s conduct, even at work,
can have a powerful effect
on those around them.
Sometimes I really hate my job.
I don’t know how Jason stays so positive.
I asked Jason why he refused the money,
and I found out
that he’s one of Jehovah’s Witnesses.
My wife is too,
so I know a lot about them.
But what Jason did really surprised me.
I wondered why he didn’t feel like
he was entitled to the extra money.
He’s such a hard worker,
and most of our supervisors accept bribes.
Jason showed me a Bible verse:
“Whatever you are doing,
work at it whole-souled
as for Jehovah, and not for men.”
Jason’s relationship with God influences
every aspect of his life,
even his attitude toward work.
He couldn’t participate
in something dishonest, even if others did.
I could see that Jason really lived by his beliefs.
Jason invited me to see the construction project
he’s been volunteering at.
I felt like I had entered another world.
People of different races
worked alongside each other
without prejudice,
and they were all volunteers.
Jason offered to study the Bible with me.
Emma has asked me to study in the past,
and I’ve always refused.
But this time, I accepted.
I liked my study
and even enjoyed going
to the Kingdom Hall occasionally.
But I had to work overtime
to support my family.
I couldn’t go to meetings every week.
Hey, Jason,
how do you do it all
—work, family, meetings, even volunteer work?
I try to keep in mind
Jesus’ words at Matthew 6:22.
Jesus compared our eyes to a lamp.
He said that if ‘our eye was focused,
our whole body would be bright.’
It’s impossible
to focus on more than one thing at a time.
Jesus wanted his followers
to focus on a single purpose:
that of doing God’s will.
Rather than being distracted by material things,
my wife and I lead a simple life,
avoiding unnecessary debt
or acquiring possessions
that consume a lot of time and attention.
This way of life allows us
to have time for what’s truly important.
If you asked Emma,
which do you think she would prefer:
that you made more money
or spent more time with her at the Kingdom Hall?
Jason’s example really impressed me.
He was an honest and diligent worker,
but he also kept secular work in its proper place.
It made me think about the choices I make,
and I decided that I too
wanted to ‘work whole-souled for Jehovah.’
James 2:17, 18, in part, states:
“Faith by itself,
without works, is dead. . . .
“Show me your faith without the works,
and I will show you my faith by my works.”
Now, the faith that Jason
displayed “by works” at his secular job
motivated Thomas to accept a Bible study
and to continue to make spiritual progress
despite setbacks.
Seeing this
and hearing of real-life examples,
such as in our previous video,
are excellent reminders
of what a powerful witness
our actions can be.
But what if we’re in a situation
where displaying faith
calls for us to give up something
we previously loved or enjoyed?
The story of soccer player Andrey Nesmachniy
may help us to see what action to take.
Soccer was my reason for living.
I always dreamed of becoming
a professional soccer player.
I thought that happiness came from fame,
a good career,
money.
When I was six,
my parents signed me up for soccer.
I really loved playing soccer.
I spent all my time at the stadium,
even late into the night.
When I was 12,
I learned about Jehovah from my mom.
At that time,
she started studying the Bible.
And after about a year,
I began to preach from door to door.
When I was 17 years old,
I finished school
and I received an invitation
from the Dynamo Soccer Club in Kiev.
Oh, that was unforgettable!
Yes, my emotions were running high
because since childhood
I had always dreamed of playing for Dynamo.
From that moment on,
all my energy and all my time
were devoted to my career.
Every day we either trained or there was a game.
There was no time left for spiritual things.
Of course, being around people like that,
I became just like them.
I led an immoral lifestyle
because huge amounts of money
opened up many opportunities.
Going to nightclubs, the nightlife
—it was so immoral.
Everyone wants to be
your friend and to meet you.
And, of course, this was tempting.
I also invested huge sums
of money in real estate.
I wanted to create a foundation
for the future and wealth for myself,
my family, and my relatives
so that no one would be in need.
Yes, I was sure that this really was happiness.
This continued for nine years.
The turning point
was a conversation with management
when an issue came up,
and they hurled insults at me.
At that moment, I felt worthless,
like a disposable cup
that you use and then crush
and throw away.
Besides, a new generation
of soccer players was arriving
—many young guys.
I stopped being included in the starting lineup.
Also, the financial crisis began,
and real estate prices fell drastically.
I panicked; I didn’t know what to do.
And I started to think about the meaning of life:
‘What really is the meaning of life?
‘If it’s not a career, not money
—then what is it?’
And then I remembered everything that I learned
about Jehovah when I was a teenager.
I began to study
the Bible again along with my wife.
After a year, I started preaching again,
and in 2009,
I was baptized as one of Jehovah’s Witnesses.
And this brought me so much joy and satisfaction.
These feelings can’t be compared
to winning any medal or cup.
I realized that I couldn’t slave for two masters,
but I still had to play
two more years for Dynamo Kyiv.
Although it was a difficult time,
I took advantage of this opportunity,
and I am thankful to Jehovah that a good witness
was given about his name.
There were some soccer players
who showed interest in the truth.
In 2011 when my contract ended,
I finished my professional career.
First Timothy chapter 6
encourages us “to place [our] hope,
not on uncertain riches,
but on God,” and “to be rich in fine works.”
People ask me: “Do you regret it?”
“Maybe you’d like to come back;
do you miss soccer?”
And I honestly and sincerely say no.
I don’t miss it, and I don’t want to go back
because my relationship with Jehovah—
Well, it can’t be compared to anything.
Everything that this world offers is all short-lived,
and it’s only an illusion.
People see only one side of the picture
—the fame and the money.
The other side are
the injuries and disappointments.
It’s very hard psychologically and emotionally;
you have no freedom.
That’s why it’s better
to give the very best to the One
who appreciates it.
What you do for Jehovah
will always bring you happiness,
joy, and satisfaction.
Did you notice how Andrey mentioned
that he couldn’t “slave for two masters,”
and this led him to eventually
abandon the world of professional sports?
Yes, often our faith moves us to leave behind
careers and activities we once loved.
But to quote Paul’s words at Philippians 3:8:
“I have taken the loss of all things
“and I consider them as a lot of refuse
“[or as the footnote states,
“garbage; rubbish.”],
that I may gain Christ.”
We can have confidence
that anything we throw away
for the sake of our spirituality
has no real value
when we compare it to the blessings
we enjoy as Jehovah’s friends.
Back to you, David.
Thanks, Herman.
That was great.
For my second discussion on this broadcast,
I’d like to talk to you
on the theme “Do the Math.”
Yes, you heard right: “Do the Math.”
Now, math may not be your favorite subject,
but as we’re going to see,
someone has to do it.
Sometimes doing the math
is the only way we can make a time line
or get interesting background information
that makes our Bible reading more enjoyable.
And you do want to make
your Bible reading more enjoyable, don’t you?
Of course you do!
Well, let’s start with a number
we might quickly skip over
in our Bible reading.
Let’s turn to Matthew 19:28,
and let’s see how a number
can sometimes tell us
more than what’s written on the page.
Matthew 19:28:
“Jesus said to them: ‘Truly I say to you,
“‘in the re-creation,
“‘when the Son of man
sits down on his glorious throne,
“‘you who have followed me
will sit on 12 thrones,
judging the 12 tribes of Israel.’”
Did you see anything interesting there?
I’ll give you a hint:
These words were spoken near the end
of Jesus’ earthly ministry.
Does that give you a hint?
I’ll give you another hint: the number 12.
At this point, Jesus knew
that only 11 of his apostles
were going to be faithful.
Yet, he said there would be
12 thrones in the Kingdom, not 11.
What did it mean?
It meant that Judas
would have to be replaced as an apostle.
And sure enough, he was.
Well, that was easy, wasn’t it?
There was no math involved.
It was just a number.
But, let’s see how doing the math
can help us to answer a few questions.
During family worship, one of the kids asks
whether Noah and Abraham knew each other.
How are you going to handle that?
Do you know?
You might just say,
“The Bible doesn’t say” and leave it at that.
But you could figure it out
if you did the math.
Now, here’s what we know:
The Flood occurred in 2370 B.C.E.
Now, that date is absolutely solid.
And if you’d like
to figure it out for yourself,
you can look it up under “Chronology”
in the Insight book—2370 B.C.E.
That’s the Flood.
And Noah lived for 350 years after the Flood.
So by subtracting 350 from 2370,
we learn that Noah died in 2020 B.C.E.
But remember the question?
The question is,
Did Noah and Abram know each other?
Abram entered the land of Canaan
in 1943 B.C.E.
Now, once again,
if you want to prove that to yourself,
look in Insight under “Chronology.”
You’ll find everything
you need to prove it to yourself.
So in 1943 B.C.E., Abraham
(Abram in that case)
enters the land of Canaan
and he’s 75 years old at the time.
So Abram must have been born
75 years before 1943 B.C.E.
Add 75 to 1943,
and you find that Abram was born
in 2018 B.C.E.
So Noah died in 2020 B.C.E.,
and Abram was born
two years later, in 2018 B.C.E.
They never knew each other, but it was close.
Our publications have often said
that Jonathan was
at least 30 years older than David.
But the Bible doesn’t say that.
Your progressive Bible student
(you know, the one
who makes you prove everything)
asks you about that.
Can you prove it?
Can you?
You can if you do the math.
King Saul ruled Israel for 40 years.
Then David became king.
Now, how old was David
when he became king?
The Bible says that he “was 30 years old.”
That means that when David was born,
Saul had already been ruling
Israel for ten years.
But when Saul became king,
Jonathan was a grown man.
He was probably already in the army.
You had to be
at least 20 years old to be in the army.
So if Jonathan was at least 20
when Saul began to rule
and David was born 10 years after that,
what difference in age would there have been
between Jonathan and David?
About a 30-year difference
—20 plus 10 equals 30.
Now, the next one
is a bit more complicated;
it’s the last one.
And we can do this.
Insight on the Scriptures says
that Moses and Job lived at the same time.
But the Bible doesn’t say that.
How can we be so sure?
Once again, what do we do?
Do I hear it?
You’re right; we do the math.
Job’s test must have occurred
sometime after the death of Joseph.
We know that because in Job chapter 1,
Jehovah told Satan:
“There is no one like [Job] on the earth.”
“No one.”
Now, if Joseph had still been alive,
Jehovah would have said that there was
no one like Joseph and Job on the earth.
And if the test had occurred earlier,
Jehovah would have said
that there was no one like Jacob and Job,
Isaac and Job, Abraham and Job.
And remember, there were
only two years between Noah and Abraham,
so we can conclude that the test of Job
occurred after the death of Joseph.
When did Joseph die?
The date is solid.
It’s 1657 B.C.E.
How do we figure that?
If you don’t like math, trust me,
you don’t want to know!
But Insight and the Bible will give you
all the information you need
to figure it out for yourself.
But let’s keep it simple.
Let’s go with 1657 B.C.E.
That’s 144 years before Israel left Egypt
under the direction of Moses in 1513 B.C.E.
So Job’s test must have occurred
sometime within that 144-year period.
Now this is a big hint:
144 years before Israel left Egypt.
Are you beginning to put it together?
Here is the clincher:
Job lived for 140 years
after he passed the test,
so he was probably still alive
in the land of Uz
when Israel left Egypt.
Conclusion: Job and Moses
definitely lived at the same time.
So, what have we learned by doing the math?
Superficially, we might say:
“Well, we’ve learned that Abraham
was born two years after Noah.
“And we’ve proved that Jonathan
was at least 30 years older than David
and that Moses and Job
definitely lived at the same time.”
Superficially, we got the answers
to those questions, yes.
But the fact is
that probably none
of those questions ever kept you up at night.
There’s a broader picture here.
What we’d like you to take away
is the fact that sometimes a number
is more than just a number.
It can provide information
that we couldn’t get any other way,
and if we can understand that,
this discussion will have been
well worth having.
So when you see a number in the Bible,
don’t run the other way.
Embrace it; stop and think about it.
You may be glad you did.
Well, after all that math,
how about a little music?
This month’s music video
will let us experience some of the joy
of traveling to an international convention
and meeting our spiritual family members
from around the globe.
Touching down in a foreign land
With a thousand miles behind us—
Since we left our home,
It’s Jehovah’s hand
That is blessing ev’ry move.
And the work that we do isn’t easy,
But it’s all for Jehovah.
And the love that we feel
for this fam’ly is real,
So this we say to you:
“We’re all Jehovah’s people;
United, we are family.
“And though your land is far away,
We love you.
We’re your family.”
Waiting there as our plane came in,
You were reaching out to greet us.
Then the music starts, and the day begins,
And our love grows even more.
But we know that it’s only Jehovah
Who can cause this to happen.
So we’ll praise him together
and love him forever
On ev’ry distant shore.
“We’re all Jehovah’s people;
United, we are family.
“And though your land is far away,
We love you.
We’re your family.”
Silver wings fly across the sea
To a land so unfamiliar.
But we bring good news, and the ones we meet
Are so gentle, kind, and good.
And the love we receive from our brothers
Makes us feel we belong here.
So wherever we are and no matter how far,
We love our brotherhood!
It’s good to know
That we have family ev’rywhere we go—
From Mali to Mexico,
From Japan to Jamaica.
“We’re all Jehovah’s people;
United, we are family.
“And though your land is far away,
We love you.
“We’re your family.
“From ev’ry tribe and nation—
United, we are family.
“These bonds of love are plain to see
Because we’re Jehovah’s family!
“Fiji, Tahiti, and New Caledonia—
Navajo, Blackfoot, and Cherokee—
“Azerbaijan, Kazakhstan, and Estonia—
We love you.
We’re your family.”
That song really captures
the excitement that we feel
when we meet new members of our family.
I certainly agree.
It was great.
Well, this month we saw how our actions
can help motivate
right-hearted ones to accept the truth.
We peeked behind the scenes
to learn how translation work is done.
And we even did a little math.
Herman, I love working with you
in the Writing Department,
and I loved working with you
on this project this month.
Thank you, David.
Well, thank you.
I really appreciate your help.
Now, I’ve been informed
that many of you will be notified
of the dates
for your regional convention this month.
Would you like to know the theme
for the 2020 convention program?
I’ll lower my voice,
and I’ll let you in on it.
The program is based on Philippians 4:4
and the theme “Always Rejoice”!
Isn’t that a great theme?
We’re going to have a great time
advertising this convention theme.
Can you imagine having that
on your convention badge?
And people will look at that badge
and they’ll say,
“What do you have to be so happy about?”
And then we’ll tell them.
But before we end the program,
let’s join Herman
on a short visit to the country of Botswana
in the southern part of Africa.
Botswana is home to many natural wonders.
Among them is the Okavango Delta,
a natural haven for wildlife.
This country is also the home
of the highest concentration
of elephants in the world.
However, when it comes to people,
there are only
about two and a half million residents
spread out over this very large country.
And with only 2,316 publishers,
the ratio of Witnesses to residents
is about 1 to 1,000.
So they always enjoy it
when need-greaters offer to come
and assist them as they cover hundreds
of kilometers of unassigned territory
on preaching trips that can
last for days or even for weeks
in order to reach the most remote villages.
Currently, there are 45 congregations
and 2 isolated groups.
The Etsha Congregation,
located in the Okavango Moremi area,
is small with only
seven publishers and no elders.
But the zeal of these publishers
is amazing as they travel long distances,
often on foot, just to attend meetings.
This travel isn’t only difficult
because of the distance
but also because wild animals
roam freely in the area.
Regardless of the challenges,
the brothers and sisters
enjoy coming together
to serve Jehovah
and to share in the ministry.
This congregation is just
one of many examples
of the faithful brothers and sisters
throughout Botswana
who are spreading the truth
into even the most remote locations.
And they want to share
their love and greetings with all of you.
We send our love to all
of our brothers and sisters in Botswana
and to all of you wherever you might be.
We love you all very much.
Until next time,
this is JW Broadcasting
from the World Headquarters
of Jehovah’s Witnesses.