A key factor that promotes unity
among Jehovah’s people
is the fact that we receive
very clear direction
and regular reminders.
Just think about what we receive each month
from Jehovah’s organization.
Unfailingly, we receive
a study edition of The Watchtower;
we receive a public edition
of The Watchtower or Awake! magazine,
the Life and Ministry Meeting Workbook,
and an hour-long program
on JW Broadcasting.
Almost daily, we receive new articles,
news, and legal updates posted to jw.org.
Are you having a challenge
keeping up with it all?
How good to have that button
on the home page
of jw.org that’s entitled “See What’s New.”
Like a gourmet multicoursed meal,
these regular provisions
from Jehovah’s organization
not only delight us
but they keep us alive spiritually
—energized to move on
in our service to Jehovah.
What about those of us
who are entrusted with responsibility,
whether in the congregation
or here at Bethel?
We are not lacking for clear direction
and regular reminders.
You might find it interesting to learn
that during the 2016 calendar year,
headquarters prepared 80 letters of direction
that were sent to the brothers in the field
—such as elders and circuit overseers.
For the benefit of the branch committees
in 90 branch offices,
during that same time period,
the six Governing Body committees
sent out 240 letters to help these brothers
carry out their work in a unified way.
And, of course, that’s in addition
to the thousands of letters
that are sent each month in reply
to the individual questions
that come from the branches.
Such clear and timely direction
is a key factor that contributes
to our unity as Jehovah’s people.
But for a few minutes,
let’s discuss a second factor
that strengthens our unity.
Our commenters all touched on this.
It’s our personal willingness
to cooperate with theocratic direction.
In this regard, I invite you
to open up your Bible
to Hebrews 13:7.
Here we’d like to ask the question:
What type of relationship
does Jehovah want us to cultivate
with our overseers,
with the hardworking elders?
Verse 7 in Hebrews chapter 13 says:
“Remember those
who are taking the lead among you,
“who have spoken the word of God to you,
“and as you contemplate
how their conduct turns out,
imitate their faith.”
Let’s focus
on the first action word—remember.
To remember means to keep in mind
the good work an elder does.
Doing so will help us
to cultivate warm feelings
—feelings of love and appreciation
for the elders.
A recent study edition
of The Watchtower says
that the word “remember”
could also be translated “mention.”
So our heartfelt interest
in the elders taking the lead
moves us to mention them
in our prayers to Jehovah.
Think about that relationship
that God encourages us
to cultivate with our overseers.
What a contrast that is
to the rebellious, contentious attitude
that many in the world have
toward those in positions of authority.
Notice in this same chapter,
Hebrews chapter 13, what verse 17 adds.
We’re told: “Be obedient
“to those who are taking the lead
among you and be submissive,
“for they are keeping watch over you
as those who will render an account,
“so that they may do this
with joy and not with sighing,
for this would be damaging to you.”
Here we’re admonished
to obey and be submissive.
Of course, obedience is easier
when we understand the direction given,
when it suits our personal preference.
But what if some theocratic direction
we receive does not make sense,
takes us by surprise,
or doesn’t suit us personally?
In such cases, the latter part
of that verse comes into play
where we’re directed to be submissive.
Why?
As the verse highlights,
because in the long run,
yielding to theocratic direction
is for our own good.
Of course, this does not make
following direction easy
—knowing that it’s for our good.
To illustrate the challenge we face,
you might imagine yourself
trekking in the wilderness
with the Israelites
during that 40-year period.
Imagine that you and your family
have been walking for some days,
and all of a sudden,
the pillar of cloud stops.
You stop; you look around;
you’re obedient to the direction.
But you do ask yourself,
‘How long will we be here?
a day? a week? a few months?’
You ask yourself, ‘Should we pack,
unpack all of our belongings now?’
So at the beginning, you decide
to unpack just a few things.
Then a few days go by, you get tired
of hunting through all your belongings,
so you decide to unpack everything.
Guess what happens next?
The pillar of cloud
starts lifting up and moving.
Now it’s time to start packing.
Is it easy to follow through
on theocratic direction?
Not always.
In this regard, notice how the Israelites
responded to the movements
of Jehovah through that cloud.
In Numbers chapter 9,
please turn your attention to verse 17,
and then we’ll read verse 22.
Numbers 9:17 says:
“Whenever the cloud lifted from the tent,
“the Israelites would promptly depart,
“and in the place
where the cloud would remain,
there is where the Israelites would encamp.”
Verse 22: “Whether it was two days,
a month, or longer,
“as long as the cloud
stayed over the tabernacle,
“the Israelites remained encamped
and would not depart.
But when it lifted, they would depart.”
Are you working to cultivate a similar spirit
toward theocratic direction?
The Bethel family sets
an outstanding example in this regard.
When preparing these comments,
I couldn’t help but think of an overseer
that I worked closely with at Brooklyn Bethel
who always carried in his pocket
a pen and a notepad.
As soon as someone asked him
to follow through on something,
out came the pen and notepad
and he was making a note.
And in many cases
before the day was over,
he would have followed through
on all those action items.
The principle of Luke 16:10
was true of this brother:
“The person faithful in what is least
is faithful also in much.”
And as a result, it’s obvious
that Jehovah’s organization
has been able to entrust this brother
with many weighty responsibilities.
Well, that brother is not unique.
We have many brothers and sisters
in the worldwide brotherhood
who demonstrate such an interest
in following through
on theocratic direction.
Recently, while visiting
a branch office in Africa,
the overseer
of the Local Design/Construction Department
told me that his department meets
for 15 minutes three times a week
to read out loud a portion
of the LDC department guidelines.
If you like mnemonics, that’s the DC50.
Why does he feel that’s necessary?
As he told me, he has found that a review
with the entire department,
of the printed direction,
helps the whole department to be sure
they’re on the same page
—that they understand the direction clearly.
The regular review
has also brought to their attention
points that they may have overlooked
when they first read the guidelines
or that they now understand even better
in the light of changing circumstances.
Again, another heartwarming example
of willing cooperation
and prompt follow-through.
Well, what does this teach us today?
Today, we are being provided
with an abundance
of clear direction and timely reminders.
Jehovah is leading us through the elders,
who are taking the lead among us.
His presence is as clear to us
as it was to the Israelites
who were following
‘the pillar of cloud by day
and the pillar of fire by night.’
So as we finish up the final leg
of our wilderness journey,
may we all be resolved to cooperate fully
with any theocratic direction we’re given.