None of us like to contemplate
being in a serious accident or receiving news
that we have a very serious illness
that may even be life threatening.
When the blood issue also arises,
at such times,
of course we’re all determined
that we’re going to keep our integrity.
But we also feel the need
for comfort and for support
so that we can remain faithful.
Now, Jehovah never promised
for this period of time
that we would receive miraculous healing.
But he did promise that we would receive
something very significant.
Would you open your Bibles with me?
Let’s look together at Psalm 41:3.
It says: “Jehovah will sustain him
on his sickbed;
during his sickness
you will completely change his bed.”
Well, now, The Watchtower, back in 2008,
the September 15 issue,
just made a nice little comment
on this verse.
It said:
“David did not expect Jehovah
“to perform
a miracle and remove [his] sickness.
“Rather, David felt certain
that Jehovah would ‘sustain him’
“—that is, give him support and strength
while he was lying on his sickbed.”
Well, that’s what Jehovah has promised.
He’s promised that he’s going to provide us
with the support and the strength
that we need
so that we can keep our integrity.
Well, Hospital Information Services (HIS)
here in Brooklyn,
the Hospital Information Desks
at each of the branches,
and the Hospital Liaison Committees (HLC)
have been very powerful tools
in the hand of Jehovah
to provide this support and strength
when the blood issue arises.
Did you know that now worldwide
there are some 1,700
—that is 1,700—
Hospital Liaison Committees
with over 13,000 members?
This is not easy work.
The vast majority of these brothers
are not physicians;
they’re not connected
to the medical community in any way.
Often, they have to get up
in the middle of the night
to go to the hospital.
Sometimes they deal
with very confrontational situations.
Usually all of the situations
that they deal with are emotionally charged.
Their work is very seldom seen by others.
They are not in the spotlight.
Well, when we reflect on the work
of these wonderful brothers
who are willing to accomplish this work
of giving assistance and
support and help to our brothers,
we can’t help but think of this scripture
in Jeremiah chapter 23,
where Jehovah says—
Jeremiah 23:4:
“‘And I will raise up over them shepherds
“‘who will really shepherd them.
“‘They will no longer be afraid
or be terrified,
and none will be missing,’
declares Jehovah.”
Well, that’s exactly
what the Hospital Liaison Committee
brothers do.
They are wonderful shepherds
who are there to help the brothers
to have the information
and the assistance they need
so that they can maintain their integrity.
I recall one experience when I was working
with the Hospital Information Desk in Canada.
A sister in a northern Canadian city,
she had been very, very seriously injured.
She had to be airlifted to a larger center
where she would be able to receive
more intensive care.
A Hospital Liaison Committee member
was immediately notified;
he went to the hospital.
And so, as soon as the aircraft landed
and the sister was being taken off
and wheeled into the hospital,
there the brother was waiting in the hallway.
And so, when he approached her
lying on the stretcher,
the sister was trembling with fear.
Well, when he looked down at her,
she looked up and she said,
“Are you a doctor?”
And he said,
“No, I’m your brother.”
Well, immediately the sister
—this huge sigh of relief
because now there was someone
who could give her the practical help
that she so much needed.
Well, what are some of the ways
that this arrangement
does provide practical support?
Well, I’m not sure if you know this,
but at 89 branch offices around the world
—including the United States and Canada—
we have brothers who are on call
24 hours a day, seven days a week
to answer calls
from Hospital Liaison Committee members
and also from doctors
who request assistance
on how to treat Jehovah’s Witnesses
without the use of blood.
This is an amazing arrangement.
When I worked with HIS,
I recall many times
in the middle of the night,
we would receive calls
from a brother or a sister
or from an HLC or from a doctor
about someone who
was desperately in need of assistance.
And the organization
had provided such wonderful tools.
For example,
a database has been assembled
of literally thousands of medical articles
from respected medical journals.
Now these articles can be sent
to a doctor or to a medical team,
and they explain very specifically
what can be done to address a situation
without the use of a blood transfusion.
Often, when a doctor
receives an article like that
—he sees it’s from one of his peers,
it’s been published in a respected journal—
he is much more willing to cooperate.
And also, he sees
in a practical way what can be done.
But even better,
each Hospital Information Desk
maintains a list of consulting doctors.
Now, these are
very well-respected physicians
who are not afraid
to confer with other doctors
and explain to them how
even very complex, very difficult cases
can be managed without the use of blood.
I recall one time in the middle of the night,
we received a call about a sister
who had just given birth,
and she had lost
a significant amount of blood.
The doctor managing her case
was very interested in receiving help.
Well, we called
a very, very well-respected professor
of obstetrics and gyneocology
in Canada
who was always willing
to provide assistance.
Well, I started off the call by saying,
“I’m so sorry to call you so late at night.”
Well, the doctor said:
“Please don’t apologize, Mark.
I’m always happy to do anything
I can to help the sisters.”
Well, of course,
he was not a Witness himself.
But he viewed those dear ones
as his own sisters,
and he was willing to help them.
Well, such courageous and skilled physicians
all around the world
have done so much to help our brothers.
And the tools just keep on improving.
Many of you may know
that now we have a section
for medical professionals
on our jw.org website.
Now, I’ll reiterate:
This is not a site or an area
for Jehovah’s people;
it’s specifically designed
for medical professionals.
But that area,
although it’s only recently been established,
is already having a wonderful effect.
Let me relate this experience.
A sister wrote this into the branch.
She said: “Recently my husband took me
to the emergency room,
“and we discovered
I had a mass of some sort near my appendix
“and that a huge
and possibly messy surgery
“was needed to discover the problem.
“When I told the surgeon
that was assigned to me
“that I was one of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
“he became agitated when I reinforced
“my nonnegotiable stand.
“He never became rude or harsh,
“but I could tell that he was very troubled.
“My husband left
to make a phone call to the brothers.
“Five minutes later,
a resident came to tell me
“that the surgeon
had just gone to the jw.org website
“and was downloading information.
“We had never mentioned the website.
“How he knew or who told him,
we’ll never know.
“But ten minutes later,
he came back with copies of the information.
“He had read it,
he had marked the pages,
“and he went over everything
with my husband and me.
“Then he took my hand, and he smiled.
“He asked if I was ready,
“and he promised to do his very best for me.
“He said he too had made
“some nonnegotiable decisions
with God in his lifetime.
“He saw me about 12 hours after the surgery,
“and I teased him about being a trouble.
“He said, ‘No, it was extraordinary.’
“We know he meant what he had just learned
“about the Hospital Liaison Committee
and Jehovah’s provision
for information for His people.”
The sister concluded by saying,
“I have never felt
such a wave of peace from Jehovah
in all my years in the truth.”
Well, Jehovah did not promise us
miraculous healing at this time,
but he did promise
that he would provide us
with support and strength
when we are sick.
What a beautiful gift Jehovah
has given his people
through the fine work
of the Hospital Liaison Committees!
Truly, this has been
a strengthening aid for us
“to keep abstaining from . . . blood.”