“He does not go back on his promise.”
Now, those words say a lot
about a person, don’t they?
What Bible examples are there of those
who please Jehovah by keeping their promise?
And what is in store for those who do so,
even when it is bad for them?
Well, we know Jesus, of course,
is the foremost example
of one who kept his promise
to do Jehovah’s will.
But imperfect people too
have displayed loyalty
by keeping their promises.
For instance, in Joshua chapter 9,
we read that the Gibeonites
tricked the chieftains of Israel
into concluding
a covenant of peace with them.
Unwittingly, the Israelites
promised not to destroy Gibeon.
What makes this of special interest
is that those disguised men
were part of the Hivite nation,
which was considered
to be a threat to Israel.
At Joshua 10:2,
it says
that ‘all of Gibeon’s men were warriors.’
What happened when Israel learned the truth?
Joshua 9:18 tells us:
“The Israelites did not attack them,
“because the chieftains of the assembly
“had sworn an oath to them
by Jehovah the God of Israel.”
Did Jehovah approve
of their decision not to attack them?
Yes, he did, as events recorded
in Joshua chapter 10 go on to prove.
And we’ll come back to that in a few minutes.
In another example,
Mordecai urged Esther
to go in before King Ahasuerus
and plead for his favor
on behalf of the Jews.
Now, Esther knew
that going in unannounced
could mean her life.
Mordecai, however,
reasoned with her about the matter
and the importance of doing so,
and Esther gave him her word
that she would go in.
Please notice what she says
in Esther 4:16,
in the final part of that verse.
She’s really giving her word.
She says:
“I will go in to the king,
“which is against the law,
and if I am to perish, I will perish.”
Well, we know how it turned out
for Esther, Mordecai, and the Jews.
Esther kept her word,
and they were all blessed for it,
weren’t they?
Why did such ones live up to their word?
Because, among other things,
they had qualities,
such as faith, loyalty,
and love for Jehovah and for others.
The chieftains of Israel had faith
and viewed Jehovah as real
and were aware
of their promise to the Gibeonites.
Out of faith and loyalty,
they would not go back on their word.
Also, Esther was moved by love
to see the greater good
and to put her own life at risk
in order to help her people.
Now, going back to our second question,
What is in store for those
who keep their promises
even when it is bad for them?
Let’s look at the principle
found at Mark 4:24.
Now, here Jesus said in part:
“With the measure that you are measuring out,
“you will have it measured out to you,
yes, you will have more added to you.”
Well, what is the principle here?
As the context shows,
Jesus was speaking about a person
receiving information and enlightenment
by paying attention to his words.
But this thought of having “more added”
can be seen in many ways.
For example,
when we’re loyal to Jehovah,
he often blesses us
with more than we might expect.
At times, even a surprise.
Psalm 84:11 says of him:
“Jehovah will not hold back anything good
from those walking in integrity.”
Now, going back to what happened
with Israel and the Gibeonites,
we read in Joshua chapter 8
that in an earlier battle against Ai,
Jehovah helped Israel
with a strategy that led to victory.
But the account does not say
that He performed
astounding miracles in doing so.
On the other hand, in Joshua chapter 10,
we find something more.
After the Gibeonites
tricked the chieftains of Israel
into making that covenant of peace with them,
the Gibeonites were threatened
by an alliance of five kings of the Amorites.
What would the Israelites do?
Well, as we know, they kept their promise
and went out to defend the Gibeonites.
In verse 7 of chapter 10,
we read that Joshua
and all his fighting men went out to do this,
and as they kept their word,
Jehovah blessed them.
In verse 8, he said to them:
“Do not be afraid . . .
Not one of them
will be able to stand against you.”
Well, Jehovah was pleased
with their decision, wasn’t he?
He showed his approval in a marvelous way.
Giant hailstones
dropped down on their enemies,
and even the sun
remained motionless in the sky
for about a whole day.
Chapter 10 and verse 14 says:
“There has never been a day like that one,
“either before it or after it,
“when Jehovah listened to the voice of a man,
for Jehovah was fighting for Israel.”
Yes, Jehovah really loved the Israelites,
didn’t he
—for keeping their promise?
And when the Israelites went to war
for Gibeon, He supported them.
Or as they say, “He poured it on.”
Have you ever sensed
Jehovah doing that for you
when you stick to a difficult task,
to a promise?
Isn’t it true that when we do so,
we often look back and see blessings
that we never anticipated?
Among other things,
we might be surprised
at how our faith has grown,
how our love has deepened,
and how things that we
may have once viewed as overwhelming
are now manageable.
One Bethelite who endured in his assignment
in spite of the loss of his mother said this
—he also included
some mistreatment by others—
he said:
“Sometimes we go through something
“we’ve never experienced before,
“and we may not understand why Jehovah
“does not do a specific thing we request.
“But when we endure, we see,
“one, his greater comprehension
of the overall situation
“and, two, his desire for us to rely on him
“and know that he’s there for us,
“and that we’ve not lost his favor
“when we experience
a difficult time in our life.
“As Jehovah helps us,
“we have to do as Genesis 24:21 says
and ‘stare in amazement’
as he answers our prayers.”
Well, that’s a beautiful thought.
And so the blessings may take a while,
but we can trust that Jehovah
will be there to help us
at the right time.
That happened with Job.
He once said: “Until I die,
I will not renounce my integrity!”
And he lived up to those words, didn’t he?
So much so that after enduring
great sorrow and suffering
he was able to say:
“My ears have heard about you,
but now I do see you with my eyes.”
Yes, Job’s faith grew.
And, as we know,
Jehovah eventually restored Job’s health,
doubled his wealth,
and blessed him with a beautiful family.
We benefit from such Bible accounts.
Like Jehovah’s servants in the past,
we may suffer from persecution,
injustice, disasters, grief,
disappointments, or serious illness.
In addition,
we may have to work hard
to fulfill our promise
to be a good husband, wife,
or a friend in time of need.
The list is long.
And despite the difficulties
or even the pain at times, we can do it.
We can imitate the faith
of past and present examples
and live up to our promises
—including, of course,
our dedication vow to Jehovah.
Since Jehovah often does more
for us than we might expect,
we’re confident
that what he holds out for our future
is greater than we can now imagine.
As Psalm 31:19 says of Jehovah:
“How abundant your goodness is!
You have stored it up
for those who fear you.”