The whole obligation
and privilege of mankind
is to develop a relationship
with our God and Maker, Jehovah.
But the question is,
How do we develop that relationship?
And then, How do we keep it?
Well, let’s start with,
How do we develop it?
If you open to Ecclesiastes 12:13,
note the two components
mentioned in this verse
—Ecclesiastes 12:13.
It says:
“The conclusion of the matter,
“everything having been heard, is:
“Fear the true God
and keep his commandments,
for this is the whole obligation of man.”
So the obligation begins
with fearing the true God
and then keeping
his commandments.
So, what does it mean to fear?
What kind of fear are we talking about?
The Insight book says this:
“The fear of God is healthful;
“it is an awe
“and a profound reverence for the Creator
“and a wholesome dread of displeasing him.
“This fear of incurring his displeasure
“is a result of appreciation
“of his loving-kindness and goodness
“together with the realization
that he is the Supreme Judge
and the Almighty.”
So how does one
come to have this awe of God?
Well, as the text says today
that we’ve already read,
‘we first hear about his fame
and about all he has done.’
Now, it’s of interest
that just simply hearing
and knowing what he does
does not necessarily lead to awe
or to the kind of awe
that will help us develop
a relationship with him.
The Scriptures explain this
if you go to Joshua chapter 9,
where we read
about a group of Canaanite kings.
In Joshua chapter 9
and in verse 1, it says:
“When all the kings
who were on the west side of the Jordan
heard what had happened.”
Well, what did they hear that had happened?
Well, of course, the stories
of the Exodus of Israel out of Egypt
was one thing they heard
and also the mighty acts of Jehovah God
in connection with his people.
And then when Israel
first penetrated Canaan
after crossing the Jordan,
they set up a camp at Gilgal,
which was not far
from the walled city of Jericho.
And these Canaanite kings
had heard about what
Jehovah did at Jericho
—the great destruction there
in behalf of his people.
And remember, Rahab was spared,
and her family was spared,
because when she heard
about the mighty acts of Jehovah God,
it moved her to put faith in him.
Now, if you just glance
through Joshua chapter 8,
we find that following
that great destruction,
they went to Ai
—the city of Ai.
And Jehovah God had instructed them
how to ambush that city,
which led to the destruction there.
So after hearing those acts of Jehovah
and then many other acts of Jehovah,
what did it do to the Canaanite kings?
Were they moved with awe?
Well, let’s read chapter 9, verse 2.
It says:
“They formed an alliance
to fight against Joshua and Israel.”
So it had the opposite effect
upon them, didn’t it?
But now, notice the different reaction
it had upon the Gibeonites.
Now, they heard the very same reports,
and in chapter 9 and verse 9, it says:
“At this they said to him:
“‘Your servants have come
from a very distant land
“‘out of regard for the name
of Jehovah your God,
“‘because we have heard about his fame
“‘and about all he did in Egypt
and about all he did
to the two kings of the Amorites.’”
So in this case,
they heard it and it led to their awe,
which led to their developing
a relationship with Jehovah God.
Well, today, the same thing is true
that the mighty acts of Jehovah God
are all around us.
And those that are “rightly disposed”
recognize them
and are moved to this awe
that leads to a good relationship
with Jehovah God.
We have a number
of experiences in this regard
that are related to the relief efforts
going on right now.
I’d like to share one of them with you.
It was in the middle of the night,
Monday, October 9, 2017,
and the wildfires began to engulf areas
around the city of Santa Rosa, California.
The elders began to call, text,
and even personally alert
those in the congregation
that they needed to evacuate immediately.
And in time, hundreds of friends
made their way to the Kingdom Hall,
and from there arrangements were made
for these displaced publishers to be housed
with their brothers and sisters
in unaffected areas,
especially to the south.
Well, there was one Spanish family
that hesitated to accept the hospitality
that was being extended to them,
and they did not want to be relocated.
And upon the loving inquiries of the elders,
it was learned
that the father was a non-Witness
and he felt uncomfortable
staying in another Witness home.
And he was embarrassed
at the way he looked,
the way he was dressed,
and how dirty he was
because of the circumstances.
So he requested to stay overnight
at the Kingdom Hall with his family.
Well, temporary beds
were set up at the Kingdom Hall.
And during the night, the circuit overseer
had children
singing Kingdom songs on the platform
which really encouraged all.
The next morning,
after experiencing
the loving atmosphere in the Kingdom Hall
and seeing how well
Jehovah took care of this man’s family,
as well as the other publishers,
the man stated
that he was going to call the brother back
who studied with him many years ago
and he would resume his Bible study
and he would never ever miss a meeting again.
Yes, those “rightly disposed”
become in awe of Jehovah God,
and that moves them
to have a good relationship with him.
Remember,
‘the whole obligation of man is to fear God.’
So the question is,
Now that we have developed
this relationship with Jehovah God,
how do we keep it?
Well, for sure,
we must continue to be observant
of Jehovah’s mighty acts
in connection not only with ourselves
but in connection with his people worldwide.
Never should we allow
the wonderful experiences that we hear
—the outstanding World Service Report
or the support and comfort
that Jehovah God is giving those in need—
to become commonplace to us.
We must stay in awe of our God and Father.
Now, you remember the first scripture
we read in Ecclesiastes
where it says that in addition
to fearing the true God,
we’re told to keep his commandments.
So it would be good
to ask ourselves this question:
‘What commandment of Jehovah God
do I have difficulty keeping?
‘Is it a commandment
that involves my self-control,
‘my zeal,
‘my humility,
or perhaps my honesty?’
If so, then we should give
immediate attention
to improving
the spiritual person that we are
so that keeping God’s commandments
will become as easy as being in awe
of what Jehovah is doing
in behalf of his people.
Brothers and sisters,
we stand at the threshold
of the promised new world,
and may we heed the words
here at Hebrews 12:28
(by not only developing
but by keeping a relationship
with Jehovah God),
where it says
—Hebrews 12:28:
“Therefore, seeing that we are to receive
“a Kingdom that cannot be shaken,
“let us continue
to receive undeserved kindness,
“through which we
may acceptably offer God
sacred service with godly fear and awe.”