Sight, hearing, taste,
touch, smell:
Well, as you know,
those are the five primary senses
with which the Creator has endowed us.
But now,
which one of these five
is perhaps related the closest
to our being able to gain
the prize of everlasting life?
Well, is it not hearing?
It’s interesting that throughout history,
the churches of Babylon the Great
have put the main emphasis,
not on hearing,
but on seeing or perhaps touching
—seeing an image of their God,
maybe touching or kissing that image.
But Jehovah has always put
the emphasis on hearing.
“Hear, O Israel.”
“Give ear and listen.”
With commanding calls such as this,
the Israelites were summoned together
to hear Jehovah’s words read and explained.
Well, similarly today,
we have many opportunities
to hear Jehovah’s words read and explained.
But now, here’s a question:
Is it sufficient that we just hear
the sounds of Jehovah’s words?
Well, you know that’s not sufficient.
Here’s an experience that illustrates this.
Many years ago,
I was working in service with a brother.
It was his turn to talk.
He was very nervous.
The lady came to the door.
He said, “How are you?”
She said, “Not very good.”
He said, “That’s good.”
And he proceeded with his presentation.
Well, he heard sounds
coming out of her mouth,
but he didn’t hear
so as to perceive what was said.
Well, obviously,
Jehovah expects us to do
a whole lot better than that
when it comes to hearing his words.
At Matthew 13:16,
today’s scripture text,
Jesus commended his disciples
by saying:
“Happy are . . .
your ears because they hear.”
Now, he wasn’t commending them
for just hearing
sounds coming out of his mouth,
but he was commending them
because they heard with understanding.
They grasped the meaning,
and then they were in a position
to make application of what they had heard.
Well, do we want Jehovah and Jesus
to pronounce our ears happy?
Do we want figuratively happy ears?
We do, don’t we?
Well, then, we must listen
—like those disciples—
in a way that we grasp the meaning
and are in a position to make application.
Open up to Mark chapter 4, please.
And here’s an interesting scripture
in this vein.
Notice the words of Jesus.
Mark chapter 4,
beginning in verse 23, he said:
“Whoever has ears to listen,
“let him listen.
“He further said to them:
‘Pay attention to what you are hearing.’”
Now notice this:
“With the measure
that you are measuring out,
“you will have it measured out to you,
yes, you will have more added to you.”
So notice, Jesus was saying
that if you measure out
little interest and attention,
don’t expect to gain much.
In contrast,
if you measure out
your full attention
and interest to what I am saying,
then I will give you generously,
even beyond your expectations.
Well, it works the same way today,
doesn’t it?
We actually reap enlightenment
in direct proportion
to how much interest
and attention we measure out.
Go to Hebrews chapter 2.
Here’s another scripture—
very familiar scripture in this regard
—Hebrews chapter 2,
and notice that we’re not
to just pay casual attention
or even usual attention,
but notice how it’s worded.
Hebrews 2:1:
“That is why it is necessary for us to pay
“more than the usual attention
“to the things we have heard,
so that we never drift away.”
So it’s absolutely required
that if we’re not going to drift
away from Jehovah or the truth,
we’ve got
“to pay more than the usual attention.”
Now, let’s illustrate this point.
I’d like you to imagine
that you’re trapped in a building
that is engulfed in fire.
A fireman makes his way to you,
and he says:
“I only have time to tell you this once;
I’ve got to go help other people.
“But there’s only one way to escape:
“You’ve got to go
down the stairs very quickly.
“When you get to the bottom,
“drop down on your stomach
and begin crawling.
“You have to stay
within three feet of the floor
“because above that
there are poisonous gases.
“Crawl, though, to the right,
“and you will see a small hallway
—a narrow hallway.
“Crawl through that hallway.
“When you get to the end,
you’ll be in the lobby.
Stand up, turn left,
run out the exit doors.”
Now,
while those instructions were being given,
would you allow your mind to wander?
Would you be thinking:
‘I wonder what I’ll have for supper tonight?
I wonder what will be on TV?’
No,
your attention would be riveted
because one missed detail
could cost you your life.
And even after the fireman left,
you probably would still hear
—ringing in your ears—
his words as you
reviewed them in your mind, see.
‘Down the stairs,
crawl through the hallway,
go out the left of the lobby
through the exit doors.’
You’d be reviewing that information
with the idea that you
were truly going to make application.
Well, that’s how we want to listen.
And if you think about it,
we’re in a similar situation, aren’t we?
Satan’s world is on fire around us
and very soon it’s going to totally burn up.
But Jehovah is giving us escape instructions.
In fact, at 2 Peter 3:12
it says about this system
that it’s going to “be destroyed in flames
and the elements
will melt in the intense heat!”
But we want to survive.
We don’t even slightly want
to be like the idols
mentioned at Psalm 115:6
who ‘have ears but they don’t hear.’
Or like the cobra mentioned at Psalm 58:4
“that stops up its ear”
and refuses to hear
“the voice of [the] charmers.”
Or like the disobedient Israelites
described at Isaiah 6:10
as having “unresponsive” ears.
Or those disobedient Israelites
that are described at Jeremiah 6:10
in the literal Hebrew
as having ‘uncircumcised ears.’
We don’t even want to be
like the Hebrew Christians
who were described at Hebrews 5:11
as being “dull in [their] hearing.”
We want to do our very best
to ‘uncover our ear.’
Now,
that’s an interesting expression
in the literal Hebrew at Job 33:16.
And, apparently,
it comes from the fact
that the Orientals wore a headdress.
But to hear more clearly,
they would partially remove that headdress
and uncover the ear.
Well, we want to do that ourselves.
We want to “incline [our] ear,”
Psalm 78:1,
‘awaken our ear,’
‘open our ear,’ “give ear,”
as different verses in Isaiah say.
And all of that is pay attention
with a view of making application
of what we have heard.
Now, if we do this
—use our sense of hearing wisely
as we’ve discussed—
then we’ll be in a position to survive
the cataclysmic end
of this system of things.
As recorded at 2 Kings 21:12,
Jehovah said:
“Here I am bringing such a disaster
on Jerusalem and Judah
“that it will make both ears
of anyone who hears about it tingle.”
Well, it’s true.
During the great tribulation,
people of this world,
when they hear
about the calamitous events
of the great tribulation,
undoubtedly both of their ears
—figuratively for sure
but perhaps even literally—
will tingle.
But the ears of Jehovah’s people
will continue to be inclined
toward Jehovah’s directions
that will come at that time,
such as found at Isaiah 26:20,
where Jehovah will say:
“Go, my people, enter your inner rooms,
“and shut your doors behind you.
Hide yourself for a brief moment
until the wrath has passed by.”
And as Jesus declared
the ears of his disciples happy,
Jehovah and Jesus will be able to declare
the ears of the surviving great crowd happy.
They will say to them:
“Happy are your . . .
ears because they hear.”