‎What do you need?
‎What do you want?
‎There’s a big difference between things
‎that are absolutely necessary
‎and things that we might enjoy
‎or things that would make our life
‎a little more comfortable,
even though they’re not essential.
‎In 1956, a newspaper columnist
made an interesting observation.
‎He estimated that 100 years earlier, in 1856,
‎man basically had 72 wants,
‎ of which only 16 were necessities,
‎and men of that day
were being urged by advertisers
‎to buy about 200 items.
‎But by 1956,
‎the number of wants had grown to 474,
‎of which 94 were viewed as necessities,
‎and men were being bombarded with ads
‎to buy about 32,000 articles.
‎The columnist’s conclusion:
‎Man’s necessities are few;
‎his wants, infinite.
‎Now, if he’d made the same estimates today,
‎I’m sure the figures would be a lot higher.
‎The commercial world constantly pressures us
‎not only to buy things
but to view as necessities
‎things that should really be classified as wants.
‎Seeing the clear difference
between our needs and our wants
‎is a key to avoiding the snare of materialism,
‎and we appreciate the frequent reminders
‎that we receive
from “the faithful and discreet slave.”
‎These help us to have
the proper view of material things.
‎For example,
the text today is taken from an article
‎that had the very clear title
“Seek the Kingdom, Not Things.”
‎And the theme scripture
was Luke 12:31, where it says:
‎“Keep seeking his Kingdom,
and these things will be added to you.”
‎It’s essential
that we have faith in those words.
‎We fully trust
that Jehovah is going to provide
‎for our physical needs
‎as long as we put
his worship first in our lives.
‎There was a simple definition
of materialism in the study article;
‎it’s found in paragraph 3.
‎Now, it didn’t say that materialism
is having a large bank account,
‎living in a big house,
or driving a fancy automobile.
‎Rather, it said:
‎‘Materialism is the preoccupation
‎‘with material things
‎rather than with spiritual riches.’
‎So materialism really is a condition
‎of our mind and our heart.
‎So it’s good to ask ourselves:
‎‘What am I constantly thinking about?
‎When I get together with my friends,
what is the subject of our conversation?’
‎As our commenters pointed out,
‎the spirit of materialism can infect anyone
‎—even pioneers, even Bethelites.
‎It infected Christians in the first century.
‎Please open your Bibles to Revelation chapter 3,
‎and we’ll notice here
that apparently many in the congregation
‎had become contaminated
by the materialistic environment
‎in the city of Laodicea.
‎And notice the strong counsel that Jesus gave
‎to those who were putting
their trust in material riches.
‎Revelation 3:17 says:
‎“Because you say,
‎“‘I am rich and have acquired riches
and do not need anything at all,’
‎“but you do not know that you are miserable
‎and pitiful and poor and blind and naked.”
‎Now, were these Christians materially rich?
‎Yes.
‎But Jesus said they were in spiritual poverty.
‎Did they wear fine clothing?
‎No doubt.
‎But in Jesus’ eyes, they were naked,
‎so we can see that they
were in a bad spiritual state.
‎Was there any cure
for the Laodicean’s spiritual sickness?
‎Yes.
‎Look back at chapter 3
and the first part of verse 18.
‎Interestingly, Jesus told them that the remedy
‎for trusting in riches was to ‘buy gold.’
‎But what kind of gold?
‎He said: “I advise you
‎“to buy from me gold refined by fire
‎so that you may become rich.”
‎Yes, spiritual riches are what are important.
‎Only spiritual treasures are lasting.
‎Material possessions
are merely a means to an end.
‎We need them to keep on living,
‎and we need them
to carry out our worship of Jehovah.
‎So we need to ask ourselves:
‎‘What are my priorities?
‎Where is my focus?’
‎Sally and I found ourselves
asking these questions
‎during a recent branch visit.
‎We met brothers in countries
‎where the Kingdom work
is under various degrees of restriction.
‎They have no witnessing carts.
‎They can’t offer literature door to door.
‎In one country, brothers can be arrested
‎and fined the equivalent of six weeks’ wages
‎just for witnessing in public.
‎In some places, police would confiscate
your phone or your tablet
‎if they found that it contained
the JW Library® app.
‎In another country, when police
would find JW Library® on your device,
‎they would just erase the app
‎and then give the device
back to the publisher.
‎But in spite of these obstacles and threats,
‎our brothers are finding
true joy in serving Jehovah.
‎And you can imagine,
it was inspiring
‎to be able to work
with them during this time.
‎In one country,
we met with circuit overseers
‎from three different language groups.
‎I asked them the question,
“What do our brothers need most?”
‎In unison, they immediately replied,
“Armageddon.”
‎That really put things in perspective for me.
‎These brothers
are not preoccupied with material things.
‎For them,
every day is a matter of spiritual survival.
‎Stay faithful,
meet regularly, and preach informally
‎—these are the most important things,
the things that really matter.
‎So how fitting is the reminder
at Proverbs 11:4, where it says:
‎“Wealth will be of no benefit on the day of fury,
‎but righteousness
is what will rescue from death”!
‎Yes, we may have some possessions
that we view as very valuable.
‎We may treasure them.
‎Maybe it’s something
we received as a family heirloom,
‎but we should not expect
that any of our possessions,
‎regardless of how treasured
or how valuable they may be,
‎will survive with us
through the great tribulation.
‎Please open your Bibles
to Jeremiah chapter 45.
‎We’re going to read verse 5,
‎and this scripture will help us to maintain
the proper viewpoint
‎of material things.
‎These are words that were directed
to Jeremiah’s secretary, Baruch.
‎Jeremiah 45:5 says:
‎“‘But you are seeking
great things for yourself.
‎“‘Stop seeking such things.
‎“For I am about to bring a calamity on all flesh,’
‎“declares Jehovah,
‎“‘and wherever you may go,
‎I will grant you your life as a spoil.’”
‎Whether these “great things”
Baruch was seeking
‎were material possessions,
we do not know.
‎What we do know
is that when the great tribulation breaks out,
‎all of us will be grateful
to come out of that tribulation
‎with our “life as a spoil.”
‎And whether we survive
that great tribulation or not,
‎could very well depend on how
we answer these two questions right now:
‎What do I want?
‎What do I need?