David’s prayer teaches us
an important lesson,
especially since we know
that David enjoyed Jehovah’s favor.
And the key point is:
It was his attitude.
In willingness,
he sacrificed to God.
His motive was good;
it was from the heart.
And when we study David’s life,
we realize that it was a constant.
Even when he sinned,
it still was a constant
that he would approach Jehovah
with an open heart,
willingly sacrificing to him.
Let’s read Psalm 54:6,
the entire verse.
Psalm 54:6,
it starts out
as we have already considered:
“I will sacrifice to you willingly.”
But then it says:
“I will praise your name,
O Jehovah, for it is good.”
More directly said, really, it’s:
Jehovah is good.
His name is good,
but he is good.
And everything he requires
of us is good.
There’s no command from God
for his servants that is bad.
It’s always for our benefit.
Even the elimination of the wicked,
really, is good
because it shows love for those
who just want to live in peace
and worship their great God
in joy and happiness.
So that’s also something that’s very good
—what he’s going to do.
So why wouldn’t we want
to offer sacrifices
to our great God willingly?
And as we know,
Jehovah looks at more
than what we offer to him
or what we give up for him.
In each case, it’s sacrifice.
He can see why
we’re making sacrifices to him.
And this is undoubtedly
one of the reasons
why Jehovah rejected
Cain’s sacrifice.
It wasn’t just
because it was a vegetable,
but the scripture says
he didn’t look with approval
on Cain and his sacrifice,
but on Cain, because Cain,
evidently, had a bad attitude.
There was something wrong
in his motive
and why he was offering
sacrifices to Jehovah.
And this ties in with what Amos
wrote about the Jews in his day.
If you’d like to look up the scripture,
it’s Amos chapter 5
and we’re going to read
verses 21-24,
Amos 5:21-24,
to see what Jehovah’s feelings were
about sacrifices
that the Jews were making
during the time of Amos.
Verse 21:
“I hate,
I despise your festivals,
and I take no pleasure in the aroma
of your solemn assemblies.”
Perhaps it was incense,
whatever it may have been.
Then he says in verse 22:
“Even if you offer me
whole burnt offerings and gift offerings,
“I will find no pleasure in them;
“and I will not look with favor
on your communion sacrifices
of fattened animals.”
So, what we learn here is
that it’s not what was offered to God.
The great God of the universe
doesn’t need
some dead animal on an altar.
It has more to do with the attitude
of people and their worship of Jehovah,
why they were honoring him
or doing these things.
And then what’s interesting
is the way verse 23
expresses the feelings of Jehovah.
He says:
“Spare me the din of your songs;
and let me not hear the melodies
of your stringed instruments.”
And then after that
he tells us what he wants:
“Let justice flow down like waters,”
well, that has to do with the people
and their attitude
and their service to God,
“and righteousness
like an ever-flowing stream.”
“The din of your songs”
and the music
—you know,
the word din means “loud.”
And it was apparently loud
—the music that they played,
the din of their songs,
their musical instruments.
And The Watchtower made
an interesting comment on this.
Today, Christendom has a number
of celebrations where they use music,
and there’s the din of their songs.
They blend pagan customs
with the name of Jesus;
“we honor God.”
And what you think of almost immediately
is Christmastime,
the din of the music
in all the big stores everywhere.
And the owners of the stores most likely
are either nonbelievers, atheists,
or perhaps Jewish
or some other background;
that they have no concern
for the Lord Jesus
or honoring “the Mighty God.”
It’s all commercial.
And so it makes us think of those things.
An interesting item also
about sacrifice in the first century
was published
in The Watchtower of February 1, 2014.
And this is the point it made:
“God’s Law stated
that all the sacrifices offered
“at the temple were to be
of the best quality possible.
“According to the first-century C.E.
“Jewish writer Philo,
“[he stated that] priests at that time
“scrutinized animals ‘from head to foot’
“to ensure that they were sound
in all respects
and ‘without spot or defect of any kind.’”
So before they went
into the temple or they sold it
—the animal—
the animal had to be sound.
Now, this is what scholar E. P. Sanders
has to say about it
—he states
that “possibly the temple officials
“‘authorized reliable sellers
of sacrificial victims
“‘to sell only animals and birds
“‘that priests had previously inspected.
“‘In this case,
the seller would have to give the buyer
“‘some kind of chit,
[or token, a guarantee]
indicating that the victim
[the sacrifice sold] was unblemished.’”
And then the article
goes on to say the following:
“In 2011, archaeologists found
“just such a chit, or token,
“in the vicinity of the temple
“—a coin-size clay seal dating
from between the first century B.C.E.
and 70 C.E.”
So it covered the period of time
when Jesus walked the earth.
It says: “Its two-word Aramaic inscription
“has been rendered ‘Pure for God.’
“[And] it is thought that temple officials
would have attached such tokens
“to products for ritual use
or to animals intended for sacrifice.”
That’s pretty interesting.
Hebrews 13:15 says
that we make sacrifices, doesn’t it,
praise from the lips,
sacrifices to Jehovah God?
So, what might be our chit, or token,
that says that our sacrifices
are pure for God?
Well, I’m not aware
that the chit has any antitype,
so I’m not going to go into that.
But we’re thankful that we do not have
to get a chit, or a token,
every time we put a few hours in service,
work at a construction site,
make a return visit,
or conduct a Bible study.
And remember,
no, your chit is not
your field service report
at the end of the month.
Not at all!
Isn’t it wonderful?
No human has been appointed
to scrutinize our sacrifices
and determine whether or not
we merit a chit of approval
stating that our sacrifice
was pure to God.
We just keep doing what David did;
willingly, we give of ourselves
to honor our great God, Jehovah.
And we acquire a good conscience that,
if properly trained in harmony
with the Scriptures,
in a sense,
it might be considered the chit
in that we feel comfortable
because of a good conscience
and knowing that we’re giving
Jehovah God our best.
We are not worried
about some quota in itself,
feeling that that justifies us
or makes us holy or honorable,
no, just always
giving Jehovah God our best.
And The Watchtower of December 15, 2013,
said the following:
“When we live up to Bible standards,
“our sacrifices bring much joy
and satisfaction to us,
and they are ‘especially acceptable’
to Jehovah.”