As Jehovah’s Witnesses,
we truly love the Bible.
Why?
Because we know it is God’s Word.
That’s why we love reading it,
we love studying it,
and we love learning about its history.
When we pause
for a moment and reflect on
the many efforts that have been made
through the centuries
to hinder and even stop
the distribution of the Bible,
it becomes obvious
that its Author, Jehovah,
has been personally involved
in preserving
and making known
his precious Word.
This is very much
in harmony with the thought
in Isaiah 40:8:
“The green grass dries up,
“the blossom withers,
but the word
of our God endures forever.”
With that in mind,
I’m happy to speak
with you this month
on a theme
that’s very close to my heart:
“The Word of Our God Endures Forever.”
The more we come to appreciate
the value of God’s Word,
the more we’ll be moved to read it
and, even more important,
to apply it in our lives.
Jehovah gave us an outstanding gift
when he inspired
faithful men
to record his precious Word.
It’s through the pages of God’s Word
that we learn
just how much God loves us.
Thus, his Word contains
guidance on how to live.
It outlines his purpose
in creating us.
It gives us his precious promises
for life everlasting
in peace and happiness.
No wonder the apostle Paul
was inspired to write
at 2 Timothy 3:16, 17:
“All Scripture is inspired of God
“and beneficial for teaching,
for reproving,
“for setting things straight,
for disciplining in righteousness,
“so that the man of God
may be fully competent,
completely equipped for every good work.”
Of course, Satan the Devil
does not want people to have access
to these precious truths
from our heavenly Father, Jehovah.
It’s no surprise
that there have been many obstacles
to making the Bible available.
While Satan may not have been
directly behind all of these,
he certainly
has made use of them.
What are some
of these obstacles,
and how have they been overcome?
Let’s consider the first obstacle:
language barriers.
The first 39 books of the Bible,
which are often called the Old Testament,
were written primarily
in the Hebrew language.
These books were known
by Hebrew-speaking servants of Jehovah.
However, as time went on,
particularly after
the destruction of Babylon,
many Jews established communities
in other nations of the earth.
Many of these Jews spoke Greek.
They no longer used Hebrew.
That meant that many Jews
no longer had access
to the Scriptures in a language
they could understand.
Consider what had happened.
As Alexander the Great conquered
more and more
of the then-known world,
Greek gradually became
the common language
of commerce and government
throughout his empire.
If the Bible
was to be understood
by the Jews and by Jewish proselytes
who were scattered throughout
this vast Greek-speaking territory,
it needed to be translated into Greek.
Beginning in about the year 250 B.C.E.,
the Hebrew Scriptures began
to be translated into Greek.
In time, that Greek translation
came to be known
as the Septuagint.
It was widely and frequently used
by the Christians
in the first century who spoke Greek.
In fact, the writers
of the Christian Greek Scriptures,
which is often called
the New Testament,
frequently quoted directly
from that translation.
So that obstacle had been overcome.
But there were many more
language obstacles ahead.
As the Roman Empire
began to flourish,
Latin replaced Greek
as a common language.
Now it was necessary
to translate the Bible into Latin.
Some Latin translations
of the Bible books began to appear.
But it was in the year 405 C.E.
that Jerome completed
the definitive Latin translation
of the Bible.
It came to be known
as the Latin Vulgate.
Jerome’s translation
would become
the standard Bible
used by Christendom
for the next nearly 1,000 years.
However, Latin soon became
the language of the learned and the elite,
so the common people
could no longer understand
the Bible’s message.
During that long period,
there were sincere men
that translated portions of the Bible
into some additional languages,
but these translations were,
of course, all made by hand.
Such handwritten copies of the Bible
were rare and expensive.
Therefore,
access to the Bible in vernacular,
or common languages,
was very limited.
But language was not
the only obstacle
that threatened to prevent
the distribution of God’s Word.
Consider a second factor:
direct opposition
to Bible translation and distribution
from religious leaders.
That opposition
started to increase in 1229
when the local church
Council of Toulouse decreed:
“We prohibit also
that the laity should be permitted
to have the books
of the Old or the New Testament.”
In 1234,
the Council of Tarragona decreed:
“No one should possess the books
of the Old or the New Testament
“in the vernacular [language],
“and if anyone possesses them,
“let him deliver them, within eight days
“from the promulgation of this decree,
to the local bishop,
so that they may be burned.”
Thus, during
a very long period in history,
there was limited access to the Bible
in the languages
spoken by common people.
But did that mean
that the Word of God
would not continue to endure?
Neither language barriers
nor opposition from religious leaders
could stop God’s Word
from being made known.
Even in those dark times,
there were individuals
who loved God’s Word
and who worked hard
to translate it
and to make it available to others.
Consider John Wycliffe
and his followers
who were called the Lollards.
John Wycliffe and his associates
completed the translation
of the Bible
into English
about the year 1382.
They eagerly
hand copied the translation
and then traveled
from village to village
reading the Bible
to the common people.
Despite tremendous opposition
from the church,
Wycliffe and his followers
made the Bible available
to many honesthearted people
in the English language.
After Wycliffe died in 1384,
great opposition
came to his followers.
Many had land
and property confiscated.
Others were burned
at the stake.
In response to the work
of Wycliffe and the Lollards,
in 1408,
Thomas Arundel,
Archbishop of Canterbury, declared:
“We therefore decree and ordain
“that no man shall, hereafter,
by his own authority,
“translate any text of the Scripture
“into English,
or any other tongue,
. . . upon pain
of greater excommunication.”
Did such opposition
wipe out efforts
to translate and make
the Bible available?
Absolutely not!
The work of Wycliffe
and his associates
stimulated interest in the Bible
throughout England
and even as far as central Europe.
Religious leaders were not able
to silence the Word of God.
In fact, within just a few decades
after Wycliffe’s death,
two factors
led to a tremendous increase
in the availability
of the Bible.
The first,
about the year 1454,
was the development
of printing with movable type.
This invention would
in time allow for the printing
of large quantities
of Bibles in many languages.
The second factor was
the compiling and printing
of the Hebrew and Greek
original language text
of the Holy Scriptures.
This allowed many translators
to have access
to the original language texts
so that they then could produce
high-quality translations
in their own languages.
What was the result?
In the 1500’s across Europe,
fresh translations
were made and printed
in vernacular,
or common languages,
including German, English, Italian, French,
Dutch, Czech, Danish, Swedish,
Spanish, Slovenian, and many others.
However, opposition continued.
Bible translators were frequently hounded
by the Inquisition,
and some translators like
William Tyndale and John Rogers
were even put to death
for their work.
Nonetheless, the Word of God
continued to endure
and be made available
to more and more language groups.
By the early 1800’s,
Bible translation
began to speed up.
Bible societies
and intrepid translators
began to work
in many parts of the earth
so that the Bible began
to appear in languages
of Asia, Africa,
the Pacific islands,
as well as in indigenous languages
of the Americas.
From 1800 to 1899,
some portions of the Bible
were translated
into some 400 languages,
and from 1900 to 1950,
more than 500 languages
were added.
Consider what has been accomplished
with the New World Translation.
As of this month,
the New World Translation
has been produced
in whole or in part
in 149 languages,
with an additional
37 languages approved.
It’s obvious
that neither language barriers
nor opposition
from religious leaders
was able to stop
the distribution of God’s Word.
Jehovah has protected it
through the ages.
It’s just as Psalm 12:6, 7 says:
“The sayings of Jehovah are pure;
“they are like silver refined
in an earthen furnace,
“purified seven times.
“You will guard them, O Jehovah;
“you will protect each one of them
from this generation forever.”
Yes, Jehovah
has protected each one
of his precious sayings
down through the ages.
But consider a third obstacle.
Although the Bible is now available
in whole or in part
in almost 3,000 languages,
many people are no longer interested
in reading it.
In our modern age,
people have become
increasingly skeptical and irreligious.
Scientists have extolled
the theory of evolution
and have made it appear intelligent
to doubt the existence of God.
At the same time,
secular philosophy has encouraged people
to make life decisions
according to what feels right to them.
What is the result?
A world where people
are often guided
by their own selfish, fleshly desires.
Instead of leading to happiness,
many people are left
feeling empty and dissatisfied.
How is this third obstacle overcome?
Around the world,
people are opening
God’s Word, the Bible,
and reading it
for themselves.
They’re recognizing
that its thoughts
are not simply human wisdom.
As they apply
its principles in their lives,
they find
contentment and joy.
They develop
self-respect and dignity
from living according to
the upright moral standards
outlined by our Creator.
As Psalm 119:97-100 states:
“How I do love your law!
“I ponder over it all day long.
“Your commandment
makes me wiser than my enemies,
“because it is with me forever.
“I have more insight
than all my teachers,
“because I ponder over your reminders.
“I act with more understanding
than older men,
because I observe your orders.”
What a powerful proof
that the Word of God endures forever.
While the advice of human philosophers
is frequently flawed,
the Bible’s counsel works.
If we apply it,
it can help us either
to overcome or to cope
with any problem
or situation that we may face.
What is more,
by explaining
God’s purpose for the future,
it gives us a solid hope
this earth will be restored
to the Paradise
that it was
when it was first created.
It will be filled
with peace and righteousness.
What a wonderful gift
Jehovah gave us through the Bible!
Yes, languages barriers,
opposition from religious leaders,
and even
an increasingly irreligious world
cannot stop God’s Word.
How can you be part
of the evidence
that the Word of God
endures forever?
Read it every day,
study it,
meditate on the deep thoughts
that it contains,
and then apply
those priceless teachings in your life.
In this way,
not just on the printed page,
not just on the library shelf,
but in our minds,
in our own hearts,
in our own lives
the Word of God
will truly endure forever.