But now, continuing down this path
that Brother Morris started us on,
Brother Sanderson
is going to develop the theme,
“Are You Ready?”
And we’ll find out
what we’re supposed to be ready for
in this talk by Brother Sanderson.
And to begin his part,
please look at the monitors.
There’s a short video clip
at the beginning of his part.
Are you ready?
What you just saw occurred
in the Kostroma region in Russia.
The home of a very young couple was raided.
And why?
Simply because they wanted to worship
the only true and living God, Jehovah.
Now, why is this of interest
to all of us who are here today?
And why is it that we all need to be ready?
Well, Daniel chapter 11
foretold of a rivalry between two kings
—“the king of the north”
and “the king of the south.”
This rivalry has stretched out
over thousands of years,
and it continues down to our day.
The king of the north
has manifested a hatred
for God’s people.
For example, in the 20th century,
and particularly during
the time of the second world war
when Nazi Germany
was acting then as the king of the north,
we remember
that there was a high concentration
of anointed Christians in the area
who were being ruled
over by Nazi Germany.
Well, how did the king
of the north treat them?
We remember.
They were cruelly persecuted,
sent to concentration camps,
and as a result of this, as foretold
in Daniel 11:31,
persecution from that
German king of the north
resulted in the removal
of what Daniel 11:31 calls
“the constant feature”
—that is, the public preaching activity
of God’s people was suspended
for a period of time.
Well, what happened
when the second world war ended?
A new king of the north emerged.
And who was that?
Well, of course, it was
the Soviet Union and its allies.
And they too
cruelly persecuted God’s people.
They banned our worship of Jehovah,
they imprisoned many in work camps,
and they exiled our brothers to Siberia.
But what happened?
In time,
as Daniel 11:34 says,
“a little help” was given.
Now, what was
that little help that was given?
Well, as the Soviet Union collapsed,
bans were lifted
across the former territories
of the Soviet Union
as well as in other lands
that formerly had been
a part of the Eastern bloc
behind the Iron Curtain.
Well, what happened then?
As we well know, the preaching work
opened up in that whole region of the earth,
and hundreds of thousands
of honesthearted ones
flocked to Jehovah’s organization.
Well, brothers,
where do we find ourselves now?
Well, as Brother Morris
so beautifully explained,
after prayerful consideration,
the Governing Body believes that Russia
and its allies today
represent the king of the north.
And that “pushing” that we are seeing
between the king
of the north and the king of the south
—through these trade wars
and cyber espionage
and even through Russia’s seizure
of neighboring territories,
such as Crimea—
demonstrate that we are living
at a time when this prophecy
is undergoing fulfillment.
Well, is there anything more
that the Governing Body can say at this time
about Daniel chapter 11?
Let’s consider together the words
of Daniel 11:41.
It says: “He will also enter
into the land of the Decoration.”
Now, let’s stop there.
We have long held
that “the land of the Decoration”
is the spiritual estate of Jehovah’s people.
Well, what have we seen
over the last approximately 18 months
in the country of Russia?
Please watch.
On April 20, 2017,
Russia’s Supreme Court
ruled to terminate the activity
of all legal entities
of Jehovah’s Witnesses in Russia
and to confiscate their property.
On May 25, 2017,
Dennis Christensen
was the first brother to be arrested
following the Supreme Court ban.
He has been in detention since then.
After over 20 court sessions,
his trial continues.
On July 17, 2017,
the Supreme Court rejected
our appeal against the ban.
On December 14, 2017,
authorities broke
into the Assembly Hall in St. Petersburg
and took control of the property.
Legal proceedings to seize hundreds
of Kingdom Halls have begun.
The branch property
is now officially registered
in the name of the Russian Federation.
On December 20, 2017,
the Leningrad Regional Court
upheld an earlier ruling
that declared
the New World Translation “extremist.”
And it just continues.
Just look at these faces.
These are the faces of some
of the 71 brothers and sisters
who are presently
under criminal investigation in Russia
—21 are presently imprisoned
and 15 more are under house arrest.
Well, now, brothers, what can we say
about all of these events
that have taken place
in such a short period of time?
Well, truly, if you’re a student
of the history of God’s organization,
you can say these events
are unprecedented in our history.
We’ve never seen a country or a territory
with 175,000 Witnesses of Jehovah
go under ban.
We’ve not seen such
a large branch seized by a government,
as well as all of our Kingdom Halls
—and even declaring
the New World Translation “extremist.”
Well, then, based on all of these events,
what can we say?
The Governing Body believes
that these and other actions
of Russia and its allies
constitute a part of the fulfillment
of the king of the north entering
the land of the Decoration.
Well, now, what can we expect?
It would not be surprising
if Russia and its allies
continue to persecute God’s people
and that that persecution
spreads to other lands.
Already, just a little more than one week ago,
on September 26, 2018,
the Supreme Court
of the “Donetsk People’s Republic,”
(that’s one
of the breakaway republics from Ukraine)
declared the religious association
of Jehovah’s Witnesses to be “extremist.”
Well, now, brothers,
this raises a very important question.
Does this mean
that the attack of Gog of Magog has begun?
Well, we’re not ready to tell you.
Pay attention.
The annual meeting is not yet over.
By the end of this meeting, you will have
the answer to that important question.
But let’s come back to our question:
Are you ready?
Of course, we want
to be ready when persecution comes.
And quite frankly, brothers,
when ban or opposition comes
on a level like we have seen in Russia,
there are things that we need to know
in order to be ready.
Let’s consider four.
The first:
We must follow direction
from Jehovah’s organization.
Hebrews 13:17 says:
“Be obedient to those . . .
taking the lead among you.”
And why?
Because Jehovah
will use his appointed channel
to provide us
with the direction that we need,
so that we can maintain our spirituality.
And, brothers, it is vital
that we adhere to that direction closely
in order to preserve our spirituality
and the spirituality of others
who may worship with us.
Here’s the second:
Don’t panic,
trust in Jehovah,
and don’t ban yourself.
Now, what does Deuteronomy 7:21
tell us about our opposers?
It says: “Do not be struck
“with terror because of them,
“for Jehovah your God is with you,
a great and awe-inspiring God.”
You see, our opposers
would love for us to panic.
They would love for us to hear the report
that 21 of our brothers are in prison
and, as a result, become terrified.
They would like
for us to stop meeting together
and to stop preaching the good news.
In effect, we could actually ban ourselves.
But what does Isaiah 28:16 say?
It says: “No one
exercising faith will panic.”
So, brothers, we must not panic.
Yes, it’s true, there are 21
of our dear brothers and sisters in Russia
who are in prison at the present time.
But, on the other hand,
think about how many tens of thousands
of our brothers who are not in prison.
You see, that’s what
we need to focus our minds on.
And what if we do face arrest
or imprisonment
because we faithfully serve
our God, Jehovah?
Then we must remember
that Jehovah will be there to support us.
In fact, I would just love
to be able to tell you more,
but our brothers in prison in Russia,
and many other places,
are doing just fine.
And why are they doing fine?
Because Jehovah God is with them!
There is no prison wall
that can be built so high, so wide,
or so strong that it can cut us off
from our heavenly Father, Jehovah.
Number three:
Protect your spiritual food.
Brothers, have a secure place in mind
to hide your Bible
and other precious spiritual food,
whether in printed or in electronic form.
If you’re worshipping Jehovah right now
in a country where the work is under ban,
do not leave your spiritual food
where it can easily
be discovered and taken away.
Number four:
At 1 Peter 1:22,
the Bible tells us
to “love one another intensely from the heart.”
And our brothers in countries
where the work
is under ban are doing just that.
In many court hearings in Russia,
our brothers have risked
their safety to be in the courtroom
to support their brothers.
And when the brothers were charged
and when they emerged from the courtroom,
what did those brothers
who were there to support them do?
Just watch.
Are you determined, brothers and sisters,
to be like our brothers and sisters in Russia
and to stand together
as one and support one another
through the challenging times
that will be coming in the future?
Then remember these practical steps:
Follow direction,
don’t panic, trust in Jehovah,
and don’t ban yourself.
Protect your spiritual food,
and support your brothers and sisters.
Stand together with them as one.
If we are all determined
to do these practical things right now,
then, my dear brothers and sisters,
you are ready.
Thank you so much, Brother Sanderson,
for lighting that fire under us in a good way.
And also,
thank you so much for removing the veil
concerning ‘the king of the north
entering the land of the Decoration.’
But now we’d like to say, if at all possible,
do not go to the restroom during this next talk.
If you do,
you’re going to really miss something.
So Brother Geoffrey Jackson
is going to give us the powerful talk now:
“They Will Have to Know That I Am Jehovah.”
So we’re all thinking
of that very important question:
Has the attack
of Gog of Magog already started?
The simple answer is no, not yet.
Why can we say that?
Well, if you turn with me again
to Daniel chapter 11
—and I’m sure many of us
will be turning there in the next few weeks,
thinking over and over again
about the significance
of these explanations—
you’ll notice
that what is happening now
is part of the fulfillment
of Daniel 11:40-43.
But you’ll also notice
that it continues on with verses 44 and 45.
Now, these two verses
apply to something
that will occur
after the start of the great tribulation.
And as we have understood
up to now and continue to understand,
the attack of Gog of Magog
does not occur
before the outbreak
of the great tribulation.
In fact, it doesn’t even start
just as the great tribulation commences
but, rather, it is toward the end
of the great tribulation.
So, what do we know
about the attack of Gog of Magog?
What will lead up to that?
Well, let’s consider
this visual time line to help us.
Over the centuries, Babylon the Great
—the world empire of false religion—
has committed spiritual immorality
with “the kings of the earth.”
In the near future,
these religious leaders
could very well have
a part in causing people
to say that they have attained
a measure of “peace and security.”
What happens next?
Jehovah will put it
into the hearts of the nations
to empower the United Nations
to attack Babylon the Great.
The great tribulation starts at this point.
However, this will not be the attack
of Gog of Magog on God’s people.
How do we know?
Jesus said that
the days of this initial attack
would be cut short
“on account of the chosen ones,”
that is,
Jesus’ spirit-anointed brothers still on earth.
During all these events, Jehovah’s people
will continue to enjoy
the spiritual prosperity
that they have experienced
ever since pure worship
was reestablished in 1919.
But whatever respite
we may experience at that time
will only be the calm before the storm
—the final storm.
Our spiritual prosperity
will not go unnoticed.
How can it?
All other religious organizations
will have been destroyed.
We will be the only ones on this planet
who are openly serving God.
Gog of Magog
—a coalition of all the nations,
yes, a combination
of “the king of the north,”
“the king of the south,”
and all other nations—
will make plans to attack God’s people.
At that time, we will stand out as different
and will appear to be defenseless.
For this reason,
Gog “will devise an evil plan”
in a futile attempt
to wipe out pure worship from the earth.
But in his rage,
Gog will not take into consideration
one vital fact.
His attack on God’s people
is an attack on Jehovah himself.
What a mistake that will be!
Gog will enrage the Sovereign
of the universe, Almighty God.
This will start the battle of Armageddon.
During “the war
of the great day of God the Almighty,”
Jehovah will use his heavenly forces.
Included among these
will be all of the 144,000,
who by that time
will have received their heavenly reward.
Then, in a spectacular way,
Jehovah will no doubt unleash both natural
and supernatural forces
to protect his loyal servants
and eliminate his enemies.
That destruction of the wicked
will usher in the Thousand Year Reign
of Jesus Christ.
After the final test
at the end of the thousand years,
what will be the situation?
All creation in heaven and on earth
will be completely united
in the pure worship
of our loving heavenly Father, Jehovah.
Hallelujah!
What a time that will be!
We look forward to the time
when you’re there
and you’ll say, “This is it!”
But in the meantime,
as we think to the future and we realize
that Gog of Magog
will attack God’s people
—this coalition
of all the nations of the earth:
the king of the north
and the king of the south—
should we dread anything?
Should we be fearful about that?
Let’s turn to the book of Ezekiel,
Ezekiel chapter 38,
and let’s read
for ourselves the reassurance
that we get
from these words in Ezekiel 38.
Let’s start with verses 18 and 19:
“‘On that day, the day
when Gog invades the land of Israel,’
“declares the Sovereign Lord Jehovah,
‘my great rage will flare up.
“‘In my zeal,
in the fire of my fury, I will speak;
“‘and in that day
there will be a great earthquake
in the land of Israel.’”
Then verses 21 to 23:
“‘I will call for a sword against him
on all my mountains,’
“declares the Sovereign Lord Jehovah.
“‘Every man’s sword
will be against his own brother.
“‘I will bring my judgment against him
“‘with pestilence and bloodshed;
“‘and I will rain down
a torrential downpour
“‘and hailstones and fire
“‘and sulfur on him and on his troops
“‘and on the many peoples with him.
“‘And I will certainly
magnify myself
“‘and sanctify myself
“‘and make myself known
before the eyes of many nations;
and they will have to know
that I am Jehovah.’”
Aren’t those words reassuring?
Yes, Jehovah will turn his rage
on Gog of Magog
because he upholds his name
and protects his name people.
So we have nothing to dread.
Over the past few years,
you’ve probably noticed
that at a number
of the annual meetings,
we’ve had some clarifications
with regard to the prophecy of Ezekiel.
Wouldn’t it be nice if we had
all those clarifications
together in one location?
Well, you’ll be pleased
to know that ten years ago,
in the year 2008,
the Governing Body
commissioned the Writing Committee
to start preparing a book
on the prophecy of Ezekiel.
Of course, in the meantime,
the text of the book of Ezekiel
was refined and revised
and many, many things
have happened on the world scene.
Do we have to wait another ten years?
I’m not even
going to go down that track with you.
You’ll be pleased to know
that today we’re releasing
a brand new publication:
Pure Worship of Jehovah
—Restored at Last!
Now, you all seem
very excited about this;
all you saw is the front cover.
What can we expect
when we open the pages
of this new publication?
Well, let’s take a sneak preview
of what you’ll find in this publication.
First of all, you’ll be happy to see
that it contains
all the recent clarifications
that we’ve had with regard
to our understanding of the book of Ezekiel.
And we can say
there are a few more
clarifications as well in this book,
Pure Worship of Jehovah
—Restored at Last!
On pages 238 to 240,
you will find a summary of clarifications.
So no doubt most of us
will be turning there first
to read through those.
Numerous charts and time lines
appear throughout the book.
The teaching boxes help us gain
a deeper understanding of Ezekiel
and his writings;
these are designed to help us
to get the overall background
and setting of these prophecies.
Scattered throughout this book
are beautiful illustrations
—illustrations that bring to life
the fascinating prophecies
that Ezekiel was inspired to record—
all for our benefit.
As you meditate
on these instructive pieces of art,
you will no doubt start
to visualize for yourselves
the exciting visions
and the amazing things
that Ezekiel describes
in this prophetic book.
Brother Lett will tell you
when you’ll receive your copies.
Now, I know all of you are thinking
at this point: ‘OK, you can go now.
We’d like to hear
when we’re going to get them.’
But before we finish this part,
we’d like to mention
that in the digital version
of this publication,
there’s a new feature.
There are 22 chapters in the book.
And at the beginning of each chapter,
there’s a little video clip
that introduces the chapter.
And these video clips
are presented by either members
of the Governing Body
or helpers to the Governing Body.
Would you like to see
a little summary of some of those?
Pure Worship of Jehovah
—Restored At Last!
What spiritual gems will we find in this book?
Will there be clarifications of understanding?
Yes!
Will we see beautiful illustrations
of vivid prophetic visions?
Yes!
The better you understand Bible principles,
the greater will be
your desire to reject Satan’s traps
and to give Jehovah exclusive, pure worship.
Why do the faces of a man, a lion, a bull,
and an eagle especially reflect
Jehovah’s strength and mightiness?
What does the chariot
that Ezekiel saw represent,
and how do we know that?
What promises of restoration
did Jehovah make through Ezekiel,
and how have they been fulfilled
on true Christians during the last days?
What can we learn from Ezekiel’s prophecy
about Jerusalem’s destruction?
How does Ezekiel’s vision of the man
with the secretary’s inkhorn
highlight Jehovah’s mercy?
What lies ahead for false religion,
and what action should we take now?
Jehovah asked the prophet Ezekiel
to do some strange things.
But they conveyed an important message
that has meaning for us today.
Do you enjoy picturing yourself
and your loved ones in Paradise?
A study of Ezekiel’s visionary river
will help you to make
that picture even more vivid.
It’s true that understanding Bible prophecy
requires humility, hard work, and holy spirit.
But the rewards are worth the effort.
The material you’re
about to discuss will give you courage,
and it will help you
to do your part in upholding pure worship.
The better you understand this material,
the stronger your determination will be
to give Jehovah pure worship.
It’s our hope that what you’ve learned
from the Pure Worship book
will strengthen your determination
to give Jehovah
what he so richly deserves
—your exclusive worship.
May this new publication
enhance our appreciation for pure worship,
may it continue to build within us
a feeling of urgency with regard
to the times in which we’re living,
and may it help us to have a longing
for the time when all creation
in heaven and on earth
will not only know Jehovah
but love and worship him
for all eternity!
What a powerful part, Brother Jackson!
And we thank you very much.
And thank you for removing the veil
from Gog, a coalition of nations,
including the king of the north
and the king of the south.
But now,
regarding our wonderful publication
that Brother Jackson told you about
—and he put the pressure on me;
I’ve got to give you
the right announcement this time,
so here’s the right announcement—
The Pure Worship book in English
will be made available on jw.org,
Watchtower ONLINE LIBRARY,
and JW Library®
on Monday, October 8, 2018.
So Monday is going to be a big day.
If you will be making use
of a hard copy of this publication,
one copy of the printed edition
will be available after the program
at the various annual meeting locations,
including the main lobby of your complex
for those watching
from their personal rooms.
Additional printed copies
may be requested
through the congregations,
including the large-print edition.
But now we move to our final talk,
and Brother David Splane
is going to give us this comforting talk,
“Do Not Be Anxious, for I Am Your God.”
And Jehovah knows
we need this comforting talk
after the powerful preceding trilogy
we just heard.
So Brother Splane, please.
I told some of the brothers that my job
is to cheer you up after the preceding talks.
Well, bad things happen.
They happen to us,
and they happen to those we love.
So here’s the question:
Is it possible to remain calm
when it seems that our life
is being turned upside down?
And the answer is yes.
And let’s consider
four reasons why we say that.
And this is simple
because all of these reasons
are contained in one Bible verse
—Isaiah 41:10—
that’s Isaiah chapter 41.
If you can’t find Isaiah,
try “Isaiah” 41:10
—four reasons why we can be calm.
It says:
“Do not be afraid, for I am with you.
“Do not be anxious, for I am your God.
“I will fortify you, yes, I will help you,
“I will really hold on to you
with my right hand of righteousness.”
You can leave your Bibles open.
We’re going to be returning to this book,
and we’re going to be staying
in Isaiah for the duration of this talk.
Now, more than 100 years
after these words were written down,
a very bad thing happened.
The king of Babylon
invaded the city of Jerusalem.
And the Bible says of him
that he felt no compassion
for young man or virgin, old or infirm.
He burned down the house of the true God,
tore down the wall of Jerusalem,
burned all its fortified towers with fire,
and destroyed everything of value.
Now, there were survivors.
Bear in mind,
we’re not talking about our friends
Daniel, Ezekiel, Shadrach,
Meshach, and Abednego.
They were already in Babylon,
but there were survivors.
But can you picture in your mind’s eye
what was happening to the survivors?
Just try to picture it.
There they are bound in chains,
being dragged through the rubble
—the smoldering rubble—
of the holy city.
Can you see them?
Can you see them pass a widow
who is cradling
the lifeless body of her only son?
Now a soldier approaches,
and he orders the woman
to drop her son and to get on her feet.
But she can’t;
she just can’t let go of her son, her precious son.
With one stroke, the soldier ends her life.
And those looking on
wonder what fate awaits them.
And you can imagine
faithful ones among them
repeating the words of Jehovah,
by means of Isaiah,
over and over again:
‘Do not be anxious.
‘I am your God.
‘I will fortify you.
I will hold on to you.’
Well, those same words
have been a source of great encouragement
to Jehovah’s people throughout the ages.
And they can be a source
of strength for us today.
So let’s take a closer look at Isaiah 41:10
and discuss the four reasons
why we needn’t be overly anxious
when bad things happen.
So keep your Bibles open to Isaiah,
and let’s look at the first reason.
What does Jehovah say?
“For I am with you.”
Now, what’s the first word in that phrase?
“I.”
Jehovah doesn’t say:
‘Don’t be anxious because you’re real smart.
You’ll figure something out.’
No.
We needn’t be anxious if Jehovah is with us.
If we put our trust completely in Jehovah,
that’s the very best way to calm our fears,
and that’s been repeated to us
during the program of this convention.
But now, isn’t Jehovah
just interested in the big picture?
Is Jehovah really interested
in you and your problems?
He assures the Israelites that he is.
Just turn to Isaiah 43,
and notice what he says in verse 2
(he’s speaking to you):
“When you pass through the waters,
“I will be with you,
“and through the rivers,
they will not flood over you.
“When you walk through the fire,
“you will not be scorched,
nor will the flame singe you.”
Now, Jehovah doesn’t say
there won’t be challenges.
There will be rivers,
but Jehovah will not allow
those rivers to flood over us.
There will be fire,
but Jehovah will not allow the flames
to consume us.
Jehovah has the power over fire and water,
and Jehovah says that he will be with us.
So we will leave every trial
—we will go out of every trial—
with our integrity intact
with the help of Jehovah.
But Jehovah does something else.
Jehovah can also help quiet our fears
so that we’re not afraid
of the trials that beset us.
Now, this was evident
in the case of a sister named Yoshiko.
The doctor gave her very bad news.
She had only a few months to live,
but Jehovah was with her.
What did He do?
Did He provide a miraculous cure?
No.
Her daughter said:
“We were impressed
with how calm Mom was.
We truly saw
that Jehovah gave her inner peace.”
Well, I’m sure you could relate
many, many experiences
when Jehovah has given you
that same peace of God
that has helped you to endure trials.
Now, let’s note the second reason.
Go back to Isaiah 41:10,
and let’s note the second reason
why we can remain calm.
He says:
“Do not be anxious,
for I am your God.”
Now, in this verse,
the word for “be anxious”
conveys the thought of looking
over your shoulder and expecting trouble
or being in a constant state of alarm.
Now, is that really helpful?
It reminds me
of the American writer Mark Twain;
he said, ‘I’m an old man
‘and I have known many troubles,
but most of them never happened.’
And that’s really true, isn’t it?
So often the things we expect to happen
—the things we worry about—
don’t happen at all.
Well, what’s the point?
Nothing is gained by trying to imagine
what form persecution might take
or how we might react under a certain trial.
Why?
Because we know our God,
and we know what Jehovah can do for us.
How do we know that?
Because of his past record.
We’ve seen how he
has already intervened in our life.
He’s done it before, and he can do it again.
Remember the song?
“You promised him in prayer to do his will;
he helped you then, and he will help you still.”
And that is so true.
Now, think about the first trial
that you encountered
when you were coming into the truth.
Maybe it was your relatives.
You were studying,
and you were wondering
how you were going to break the news
to your relatives that you
were studying with Jehovah’s Witnesses.
And you begged Jehovah
to give you just the right words
so that you’d know
how to break the news.
It didn’t go well.
And you felt as if you
were walking through fire.
But did the fire consume you?
Well no, look at you;
you’re here.
Jehovah helped you.
He gave you the peace of God,
and he helped you to endure.
And now you have
a better relationship with your relatives
as long as you don’t talk about the truth.
He helped you then,
and he will help you still.
Well, looking back,
you might not see that as a very difficult test
because since that time,
you’ve been through a lot worse.
But it was a test nevertheless,
and you passed that test successfully.
And so when you went
through much worse later,
you were able to encounter that test
and pass it because your faith was stronger.
Jehovah has built your faith little by little.
Now, Jehovah
won’t always remove our problems.
If you have a problem
and there’s something
you can do about it,
then pray for wisdom.
If there’s nothing
you can do about the problem,
pray for peace.
But in any case, pray.
The next best thing to solving a problem
is not to be worried about the problem.
Now, let’s go back to verse 10
and consider the third assurance
that we get from Jehovah.
He says:
“I will fortify you,
yes, I will help you.”
Now, what does that word “fortify” mean?
It means to make us stronger.
Now, this morning, we’ve heard a lot
that could be scary on some levels.
And we might catch ourselves saying,
‘I don’t think I’d do very well under persecution.’
What’s wrong with that statement?
‘I don’t think I would do well
under persecution.’
Jehovah is not in the picture,
and yet he should be.
Who says we have to face persecution alone?
Jehovah says that he is going to fortify us.
He is going to give us the inner strength
that we didn’t know we had
because we don’t have it
if we’re not facing persecution.
You may not be strong enough
to encounter persecution now
if you’re not going through it.
But when the time comes
—and it will come—
Jehovah will give you the strength you need.
He says:
‘I will fortify you.
I will make you strong.’
Well, let’s consider the last phrase in verse 10.
Jehovah says:
“I will really hold on to you
with my right hand of righteousness.”
Now, The Watchtower of July 2016
clarified this verse for us.
We used to often think of ourselves
walking hand in hand with Jehovah,
but that’s not really what he’s talking about.
How do we know?
Well, it’s because of what he says in verse 13.
It says:
“For I, Jehovah your God,
am grasping your right hand.”
But what does he say at the end of verse 10?
“I will really hold on to you
with my right hand of righteousness.”
If we were walking side by side with Jehovah,
our right hand would be in his left hand
or our left hand would be in his right hand.
But he says,
‘No, I will hold on to you with my right hand,
and I will hold on to your right hand.’
So, what is the picture?
You’re down; and you can’t get up;
and Jehovah God extends his right hand.
And what do you do?
Don’t just lie there.
Extend your right hand;
allow Jehovah to help you to get up.
Maybe you’re battling depression right now.
Or perhaps you’ve lost
a cherished privilege of service,
and you just can’t get over it.
Extend your right hand,
and allow Jehovah to help you.
Maybe he’ll use an elder
as his right-hand man.
But he’s going to use somebody to help you
if only you are willing to accept
the help that Jehovah will give.
Well, there they are:
Four reasons why we can keep calm
no matter what the future holds.
Jehovah says: “I am with you.”
He says: “I am your God.”
“I will fortify you.”
And “I will really hold on to you
with my right hand.”
What a beautiful assurance that is!
And we’re going to have a whole year
to consider these words in depth
because part of this text,
as you have probably guessed,
constitutes our yeartext for the year 2019.
And here it is:
“Do not be anxious, for I am your God.”
Thank you so much, Brother Splane,
for that balsam of Gilead,
and also we appreciate
that yeartext, Isaiah 41:10.
What a beautiful scripture
we’ll focus on during 2019!
But now I’ve been apportioned five minutes
for some concluding comments.
And even though we’re overtime,
I’m going to take my five minutes.
I’ll probably hear about it later, though,
from the Governing Body brothers.
So if I leave out of here
real quick after the program,
you’ll know what the problem is.
Near the beginning of our program,
we focused just for a few minutes
on appreciating our spiritual paradise.
And to substantiate
how truly paradisaic it is,
we made comparisons
between that original Paradise
and our spiritual paradise.
And we discussed seven similarities.
Now, just to review,
our spiritual paradise,
like the garden of Eden,
exists on a land.
It is filled with beautiful plants and trees.
It has abundant food and refreshing water.
It has many harmless animals.
It needs maintenance,
and it has boundaries.
But just briefly,
let’s discuss one more
—an eighth similarity.
Our spiritual paradise
is expanding
to embrace more and more people.
Originally, Jehovah intended
the garden of Eden to expand—didn’t he?
We know that Jehovah
told him in Genesis 1:28:
“Become fruitful and become many,
fill the earth and subdue it.”
So as Adam and Eve had children
and as their children had children,
the garden of Eden would become
too small eventually—wouldn’t it?
It would have to grow;
it would have to expand bigger and bigger.
And finally, the east would meet the west;
the north would meet the south;
the planet Earth
would become the garden of Eden.
But now, we know that
that original procedure Jehovah had in mind,
you could say, was blocked
by the rebellion in the garden of Eden.
Of course, Jehovah’s original purpose
for the earth to be a paradise
like the garden of Eden
certainly will be accomplished.
But now, here is the point:
Just as Jehovah intended
the garden of Eden to expand,
he desires our spiritual paradise to expand
—to embrace more and more people.
And that definitely is happening
—isn’t it?—
as all of us focus on making disciples.
And right now our spiritual paradise
embraces some eight
and a half million sheeplike individuals.
And only Jehovah
knows how many more will come into it
before the great tribulation begins
as all of us do our best to make disciples.
And Jehovah expects us to do that
—to do our very best
to expand this spiritual paradise,
this wonderful,
beautiful place where we are.
And this will happen until,
we know, the spiritual paradise
will go through the great tribulation.
And then resurrected ones
and ones born in the new world
will come into this spiritual paradise
if they exercise faith in Jehovah’s provisions.
But there will be many that’ll do that.
They’ll come into this spiritual paradise.
This will happen over and over again,
until the spiritual paradise
will cover the entire planet.
And this exquisite paradise
will actually be more beautiful,
more exquisite, than the literal Paradise
that will coexist with it.
So there we have eight similarities
between the original Paradise
and our spiritual paradise.
And we never want to take it for granted.
And as we touched
on a little bit in the beginning,
we never want to allow Satan
to do what he did to Adam and Eve.
He got them out
of their wonderful place, didn’t he?
Well, he’s trying
to lure us out of the boundaries
of our wonderful,
exquisite spiritual paradise,
but we are not going to let him do this.
And we’re determined
that we’re going
to help others that are of honest heart
to join us in this spiritual paradise.
And this wonderful annual meeting
has truly helped us in this regard.
I know all of us are so happy we were here.
Now, there are many things
you could do on a Saturday,
but we did the best thing
we could have done this Saturday.
We were here
at this wonderful annual meeting.