This morning I’d like you to imagine
for a few moments
that you’ve been asked to write
your life story for The Watchtower.
Well, once you get over the shock,
how would you go about doing that?
You’ve probably noticed with many
of the life experiences in The Watchtower,
usually the first paragraph,
have a defining moment in that person’s life.
For example, Brother Eric Beveridge,
who serves with us here in the United States,
he started off this way:
“‘I hereby sentence you
to six months in prison.’
“With those words ringing in my ears,
I was taken off to . . .
“[p]rison in Manchester, England. . . .
“I had just faced
one of the toughest tests of my young life
—I had refused to be conscripted
for military service.”
Or another brother, Brother Harley Harris,
who served as a missionary
in Ecuador for many years,
he referred to the date September 2, 1950.
He said: “We were at a circuit assembly,
surrounded by a mob.
“The mayor brought in the National Guard
to protect us from the unruly crowd.
“Soldiers with drawn rifles
and bayonets lined the street.
“Amid insults,
we walked to our cars and drove to . . .
“the remaining sessions of the assembly.
It was there
that I was baptized at the age of 14.”
Or another brother, Brother Don MacLean
—who serves
on the Branch Committee in Australasia,
a brother originally from Canada—
made this comment.
He started his life experience:
“There I sat, hour after hour,
“with one of the Royal Canadian
Mounted Police by my side.
“I was his prisoner.
“We were headed
for the prison camp at . . . Ontario, Canada,
“and it seemed
[that] the 1,500-mile train trip
would never end.”
Well, those certainly were defining moments
in the lives of those brothers.
What about you?
What is your defining moment?
Well, you might be thinking,
‘No one put a gun
to my head and said,
“Decide now whether
you’ll serve Jehovah or not.”’
But for many of us, there have been
defining moments in our lives.
Perhaps it’s the moment
you decided to serve Jehovah
or the moment you decided
to become a full-time servant.
Perhaps it involved some decisions,
such as selling a home,
selling a business,
deciding to move to Bethel,
or perhaps leaving your country
and going somewhere else.
Or it may have involved
certain tests or trials,
perhaps giving up
opportunities for education
or for lucrative job opportunities.
Well, whatever the case,
I’m sure most of us
have had some defining moments
in our lives that we remember
—the decisions that were made
that resulted in much good.
Let’s think for a moment
about the faithful man Abraham.
What was the defining moment in his life?
Well, if you take your Bibles
and turn with me to Hebrews chapter 11,
of course, here we see
the apostle Paul giving us an outline
or history of many
of the defining moments
in the lives of faithful ones.
At Hebrews 11:8,
it says of Abraham:
“By faith Abraham, when he was called,
“obeyed by going out to a place
“he was to receive as an inheritance;
he went out,
although not knowing where he was going.”
Yes, that was a defining moment
in the life of Abraham, wasn’t it?
He decided to obey Jehovah,
to leave Ur,
and to travel to a distant country
that he didn’t really know about.
But was that all that was involved
with Abraham receiving the reward?
No.
Let’s read on a little further in verse 9.
There it says:
“By faith he lived as a foreigner
“in the land of the promise
as in a foreign land,
“living in tents with Isaac and Jacob,
the heirs with him
of the very same promise.”
Now, this is not a defining moment, is it?
This is a course of faithfulness,
day in, day out.
So, what’s the point?
Well, in the case of Abraham,
we remember
that eventually he and his family
crossed the Euphrates River
and into the Promised Land
in the year 1943 B.C.E.
But he had to wait 25 years
before his son Isaac was born
and then another 60 years
before his grandsons
Esau and Jacob were born.
And eventually,
he died after being in the Promised Land
as a foreigner for about 100 years.
So, what’s the point?
Although there was
a definite decision he made
—a defining moment in his life—
that was backed up as verse 9 says,
by his faithfulness
—day in, day out—
serving Jehovah.
So the lesson we learn from that is
that it’s not just the defining moments
that define who we are.
Rather, those moments and those decisions
need to be backed up by faithful service.
Let’s be quite frank.
Many of the life experiences
that we read in The Watchtower
may have a very exciting first paragraph.
“Yes, they put a gun to my head.
“Make your decision.
“Will you die?
Would you be willing to die for Jehovah?”
But then,
when you read the rest of the article,
nothing really exciting
happened in that person’s life.
I’m sorry to say it.
That includes my life experience as well.
Why?
Because the majority of our lives
are not involved with defining moments
—exciting things that are happening.
Rather, they involve
our faithfulness to Jehovah.
So we can’t just rely
upon these defining moments and say,
“Well, I made this decision
to serve Jehovah;
I passed this test,
so everything is good.”
No, we need to continue
to back up those defining moments
with faithful service.
Remember that in the Scriptures,
there were many who had
defining moments in their lives.
Take, for example, Solomon.
He had a defining moment, didn’t he,
when he prayed to Jehovah
and he was praised for the fact
that he asked for wisdom rather than wealth?
But that wasn’t backed up by faithfulness.
Eventually, that defining moment in his life
really wasn’t as valuable as it could’ve been
because of his lack of faithfulness.
And what about Judas Iscariot?
Were there some defining moments in his life?
Obviously, he decided
to follow Jesus at one point.
And during that time,
when he faithfully followed Jesus,
no doubt, there were very exciting,
interesting things that happened.
But again,
those defining moments in his life
proved to be of little value
because of the lack
of faithfulness on his part.
So that helps us to understand
why the apostle Paul
said some very interesting points
just before he started this list
that he gives us in Hebrews chapter 11.
Let’s turn to Hebrews chapter 10,
Hebrews 10:35-39.
Notice, this is the point
that we should gain from this lesson.
Paul says starting in verse 35:
“Therefore, do not throw away your boldness,
“which will be richly rewarded.
For you need endurance,”
now, that reminds us of what Jesus said
about ‘the one who endures
to the end will be saved,’
“so that after you
have done the will of God,
“you may receive
the fulfillment of the promise.
“For yet ‘a very little while,’
“and ‘the one who is coming
will arrive and will not delay.’
“‘But my righteous one
will live by reason of faith,’
“and ‘if he shrinks back,
I have no pleasure in him.’
“Now we are not the sort
who shrink back to destruction,
but the sort who have faith
for the preserving of our lives.”
What a very positive comment that is.
So when we think of our life experience,
don’t be disappointed if you
don’t have some spectacular things
that you can mention as defining moments.
Remember, the important thing
is not just the decisions
that we make along the way
but the fact that we remain
faithful to Jehovah
day in, day out.