A little deeper study
helps you to draw close to Jehovah.
The interactions that Jehovah
has with his faithful servants
—we think about them,
we meditate on them,
it actually becomes a personal matter.
Drawing close to God becomes personal,
and then we can use that
in our circumstances in life.
If we are dealing with a sickness
or the illness of a mate
or even with the great tribulation
in the offing,
how are we going to handle
our relationship with Jehovah?
How are we going to stay strong?
Well, we had this beautiful drama
“O Jehovah, . . . I Trust in You,”
the Hezekiah drama,
that we had for our regional convention.
Since that is still ringing very clearly
in our minds and hearts,
let’s open our Bibles
to 2 Kings chapter 19.
Let’s review a few thoughts
from the life of Hezekiah
and that time period with Sennacherib
—the king of Assyria—
the attack on Jerusalem
in the year 732 B.C.E.,
and Isaiah’s words to Hezekiah.
Again, with the focus of:
‘How can I draw close to Jehovah God?
What can this account
continue to teach me?’
So chapter 19,
let’s start with verse 6:
“Isaiah said to them:
‘This is what you should say to your lord,
“This is what Jehovah says.”’”
Now this was to Hezekiah:
“Do not be afraid.”
Four words, but so powerful.
Why?
Because positive assurance, Hezekiah,
that Sennacherib will be defeated.
‘Do not be afraid
because I’ve heard all the things
that Sennacherib has said,
and he’s blasphemed me.’
“Do not be afraid.”
Think about that.
It engenders confidence.
It engenders in us
to approach Jehovah God.
He wants to help us.
He wanted to help Hezekiah.
He saw his situation.
Hezekiah was emerging
as one of the greatest kings of all Israel.
He was beating the odds.
He had an apostate father.
And yet, Jehovah had his eye on Hezekiah
and wanted to help him.
“Do not be afraid.”
You see, trusting in Jehovah
as Hezekiah did is an act of worship.
It’s something that gets Jehovah’s blessing.
When Jehovah tells us
under our circumstances:
“Do not be afraid.
I will help you.
I want to help you,”
that helps us to be loyal to him.
We draw close to him.
Now when we show loyalty to Jehovah,
then he acts in loyalty toward us.
There’s an action; it’s not passive.
He acts in loyalty toward us.
He gives us his holy spirit.
He draws closer to us.
We feel his support;
we can sense that he has helped us.
Our personal relationship with Jehovah
becomes more keen, you see.
And that is because Jehovah
is telling us as our heavenly Father,
“Do not be afraid.”
He did that to Hezekiah,
and he does it with us.
It’s part of drawing close to him.
Next, Hezekiah senses
what really is important,
and this is so valuable to you and me.
Let’s go now to verse 19:
“But now, O Jehovah our God,
please save us out of his hand,”
now that is Sennacherib’s hand,
we know that,
“so that all the kingdoms
of the earth may know
that you alone are God, O Jehovah.”
So “all the kingdoms of the earth,” see,
Hezekiah was interested in Jehovah’s name
—the sanctification of that name.
He was interested
in the reputation of Jehovah God.
Now, he didn’t talk about himself,
but he just spoke about Jehovah God.
And again, that is the lesson
that we can learn.
If we’re going to draw close to Jehovah,
we think about his reputation, his name,
we think about the issue
of universal sovereignty,
we think about what that Kingdom
is going to do to cleanse the earth.
Now, I know that oftentimes
we think about our own suffering
and ‘I need to get into the new world.’
And we think about the relief
that we’re going to have,
and that is, of course, important.
But the core issues
—the greater issues—
are Jehovah’s name,
proving the Devil a liar,
our loyalty at this time.
This is what Jehovah is looking at.
This is the real issue.
Imagine as the great tribulation approaches
how delightful,
how exciting, it’s going to be
as we see even
“the sign of the Son of man.”
There at Matthew 24:30,
some supernatural demonstration
displayed of Christ’s kingly power
as Jehovah demonstrates His sovereignty.
“All the kingdoms of the earth”
must know that Jehovah is God.
Again, thinking about these things
really brings our attention
to the important things in life,
and it helps us
to draw close to Jehovah God.
Let’s go a little bit further.
Let’s look at verse 28.
Now here,
Sennacherib is going to learn
a big lesson, we know.
Verse 28: “Because your rage,”
now, Jehovah is speaking to Sennacherib,
of course, through Isaiah.
‘Because your rage against me
‘and your roaring
have reached my ears.
‘I’m going to put a hook in your nose
and a bridle in your lips,
‘and I’m going to lead you back
to the way you came,’
right back to Nineveh.
Sennacherib,
you made a big mistake
by planting yourself in the land
that I gave my people.
You made a big mistake.
You shouldn’t have done that.
You’re used to putting hooks
in the noses of other people
and bridles in their lips.
Well, I’m going to put a hook in your nose
and drag you right back,
yank you back to Nineveh.
This is encouraging.
This helps us to see exactly
what Jehovah God is going to do
to this modern-day Assyrian
as they try to attack us
in the near future.
Whether it be the modern-day Assyrian
or ‘Gog of Magog,’
“the king of the north,”
“the kings of the earth,”
they don’t stand a chance.
This helps us to draw close
to Jehovah God.
Now verse 29.
Imagine this time period as we saw
through that beautiful drama.
How are they going to eat?
What are they going to eat?
With the Assyrian invasion,
it’s not possible
to have a harvest to sow seed.
What would they do?
Verse 29:
“And this will be the sign,”
a miraculous sign,
“for you,” Hezekiah,
“This year you will eat
what grows on its own.”
So imagine that!
Jehovah says: “Don’t worry!
“From those spilled kernels
from last year,
“I’m going to have food shoot up
from the old grain from last year.”
That is amazing!
A miraculous provision of food.
And then notice it goes on, it says:
“And in the second year
you will eat grain
that sprouts from that.”
So again, even the second year,
but what is even more interesting,
according to Bible chronology,
that second year would be
a Sabbath year of the Jubilee cycle.
And the Sabbath year of the Jubilee cycle,
the faithful Jews would not be able to plant;
they wouldn’t sow seed;
they would let the land
lay dormant or let it rest.
And Jehovah said,
“I’m still going to provide for you.”
And then, of course,
it goes on and says:
‘In the third year you can sow seed
and reap a harvest.’
You see the faith it must have taken
on the part of these faithful Jews
at that time.
Would they really trust
that sufficient crops would be available
for two years in a row
without working their fields?
How would you have felt?
Maybe it was going through their minds:
‘Well, maybe we should go to Sennacherib.
‘He’s offering us food.
He’s offering us survival.
Maybe we should surrender.’
This was portrayed
in the drama so beautifully.
So again, what’s the big point for us?
Jehovah wants to help us,
and we draw close to Jehovah God knowing
that as the great tribulation
even approaches,
geographical location has no bearing
on Jehovah rendering assistance
to his people.
But now is the time:
As we study these accounts,
we draw close to Jehovah,
we gain confidence—trusting him,
being loyal,
knowing that he will loyally support us
under any circumstances.
So meditating on these accounts
should help us to continue
to stay loyal,
not be afraid
as God’s enemies will not succeed,
keeping focused
that “all the kingdoms of the earth”
must know that Jehovah is God
and that his sovereignty
will be the main issue in the universe,
and that Jehovah’s fatherly eye is upon us
as we continue to draw close to God
and serve him for an eternity.