‎You know, our text today
‎and the comments that we just heard
‎center our attention on our Christian hope.
‎Very soon, our loving Father, Jehovah,
‎is going to eliminate pain, suffering, death,
‎and indeed, as has been commented on,
‎the happy memories
‎will just push out all the bad memories.
‎“The former things
‎[will indeed] have passed away.”
‎Now, when I thought about Revelation 21:3, 4,
‎I thought to myself,
‎‘I’ve heard those words hundreds of times,
‎‘and I’ve probably shared those words
‎hundreds of times in our ministry.’
‎And while most of us through repetition
‎have probably memorized
‎those sacred thoughts,
‎a good question I thought
‎would be helpful to think about is,
‎Are these basic Scriptural truths
‎still strengthening me now?
‎Are they, as Brother Cotton just mentioned,
‎still serving “as an anchor for [my] soul?”
‎With that thought in mind,
‎let’s consider three questions:
‎What is the hope
‎as described in the Scriptures?
‎Second, why do we need hope?
‎And third, how can we strengthen our hope?
‎First, how would you define hope?
‎Back in 1993, The Watchtower
‎quoted a writer who said this:
‎“Most people seem to think that hope
‎is just a dopy form of denying the truth.”
‎Others today would equate hope
‎with optimism or wishful thinking.
‎And, of course,
‎the Scriptures encourage positive thinking,
‎and there are benefits
‎—emotionally and perhaps even physically.
‎But what do we call a desire or a wish
‎that’s not based on truth?
‎What is a desire or a wish
‎that does not take Jehovah into account?
‎Well, that’s a dream; that’s an unreality.
‎And, of course, none of us as true Christians
‎want to live in La-La land,
‎or in a dreamworld, do we?
‎Of course, the Bible
‎does not use the word “optimism,”
‎but it does encourage us
‎to strengthen our hope.
‎What is hope according to the Scriptures?
‎The original language words
‎used in the Bible that are translated “hope”
‎mean “to wait eagerly” and “to expect good.”
‎In the Scriptures, hope involves
‎not only the desire for something good
‎but it includes the basis
‎for believing that good will come.
‎That’s much more meaningful than optimism.
‎Hope, like our faith, is based on evidence
‎—convincing facts.
‎And though hope involves
‎our eager desire for something good,
‎it does not start with our desires
‎—what we want or what we wish for.
‎It’s first rooted in what God wants
‎with regard to his purpose
‎and what God wants for us individually.
‎Romans 5:5 tells us
‎that such “hope does not lead
‎to disappointment.”
‎So in a brief definition,
‎we could say that Scriptural hope
‎is eager expectation based on future realities,
‎rooted in what Jehovah has taught us.
‎Our second question:
‎Why is hope essential for all Christians?
‎Please open your Bible
‎with me to Hebrews 11:1,
‎and notice our well-known definition of faith,
‎but then notice how hope is associated.
‎Hebrews 11:1 says:
‎“Faith is the assured expectation
‎“of what is hoped for,
‎“the evident demonstration
‎of realities that are not seen.”
‎So just as faith is a requirement
‎for us to serve Jehovah acceptably
‎and for our worship not to be in vain,
‎hope, as an essential element of faith,
‎is also necessary for all Christians.
‎To see the connection
‎between faith and hope a little better,
‎we might think about the example of Abraham.
‎Now, from a human standpoint,
‎Abraham and Sarah
‎were way past childbearing age
‎when Jehovah promised them a son.
‎It’s interesting that in the Scriptures
‎both Abraham and Sarah
‎laughed at the angelic announcement.
‎It was an amazing and tickling prospect to them
‎to think that they
‎would have a baby in their older years.
‎But how did Abraham respond to the promise?
‎Notice, please, in Romans 4:18
‎what the Bible says,
‎linked to this discussion of the need for hope.
‎Romans 4:18 says:
‎“Although beyond hope, yet based on hope,
‎“he had faith that he would become
‎the father of many nations
‎“according to what had been said:
‎‘So your offspring will be.’”
‎Faith “based on hope”
‎—we see the connection better, don’t we?
‎You see, Abraham’s God-given hope
‎gave his faith that he would have a son
‎a firm foundation.
‎His faith, in turn,
‎brightened and strengthened his hope.
‎So it was not only this conviction in his heart
‎but it was the eager anticipation of seeing
‎what Jehovah had promised come to fulfillment.
‎Another reason that we need hope
‎has to do with the storms
‎that you and I are undoubtedly facing now
‎or will face
‎before the end of the system comes.
‎In Paul’s letter to the Hebrews,
‎he illustrated hope
‎“as an anchor for the soul,
‎both sure and firm.”
‎So when confronting storms,
‎what do sailors,
‎both in ancient times and today, often do?
‎They lower the ship’s anchor.
‎Why?
‎Well, if the anchor
‎takes hold of the firm seabed,
‎it helps the ship ride out the storm.
‎It keeps that ship
‎away from dangerous reefs or the shoreline.
‎Interestingly,
‎when the apostle Paul was on that ship
‎en route to Rome in the year 58 C.E.,
‎the ship was in danger of running aground.
‎The Bible tells us
‎that the sailors cast out four anchors
‎—not just one, four—
‎from the stern,
‎and as a result,
‎the ship safely rode out the storm.
‎Well, it’s not hard to see the connection
‎with hope and our stormy times today, is it?
‎Our “sure and firm” hope,
‎our setting our mind with eager expectation
‎of what Jehovah has promised,
‎keeps us emotionally, mentally,
‎and spiritually balanced
‎no matter what
‎is raging around us in our life
‎—in full-time service, with our family,
‎with our finances, with our health.
‎We can weather the storms
‎because of our eager expectation
‎of what Jehovah has promised.
‎Really, few things
‎could be more stabilizing in our life
‎than this eager expectation of what Jehovah,
‎the God who does not lie, has promised to us.
‎Well, that leads to a third question:
‎How can we strengthen our hope?
‎Well, as has been commented on beautifully
‎by our four commenters,
‎we need to think specifically
‎about how Jehovah’s promises apply to us
‎and what they will mean for us and our family
‎in the near future.
‎Though we serve Jehovah out of love
‎—and that’s our principal motivation—
‎Jehovah wants us to think about the rewards
‎that he has outlined for us in the Scriptures.
‎He wants us to visualize
‎and meditate on such blessings.
‎One sister, in referring to the beautiful artwork
‎that’s in our magazines, said this:
‎“When I see pictures
‎of the coming Paradise . . . ,
‎“I examine them closely,
‎as one would a travel brochure.
‎“I endeavor to see myself there
‎“because this is where I truly hope to be
‎in God’s due time.”
‎Daydreaming?
‎No.
‎Meditation on truths
‎and on precious promises that will not lie?
‎Yes.
‎Notice, please,
‎with me at 2 Peter 3:11, 12
‎how the inspired counsel encourages us
‎to strengthen and build up
‎our hope in view of what’s coming.
‎Second Peter chapter 3,
‎let’s read together verses 11 and 12:
‎“Since all these things
‎are to be dissolved in this way
‎“[with regard to what
‎we’re expecting in the near future
‎“with the great tribulation
‎leading into Armageddon],
‎“consider what sort of people you ought to be
‎“in holy acts of conduct
‎and deeds of godly devotion,
‎“as you await and keep close in mind
‎“the presence of the day of Jehovah,
‎“through which the heavens
‎will be destroyed in flames
‎and the elements
‎will melt in the intense heat!”
‎Notice in verse 12 that expression,
‎“keep close in mind”
‎—“eagerly desire,” literally, “speed up.”
‎Do you see how our positive meditation,
‎our visualizing what’s to come,
‎will strengthen us?
‎Yes, meaningful prayer,
‎meaningful Bible study,
‎meaningful reflection
‎will help us to keep
‎Jehovah’s day close in mind.
‎It will help us to “rejoice in the hope,”
‎and then we will experience the realization
‎of all that we’ve hoped for
‎from the God “who cannot lie.”