Welcome to JW Broadcasting.
Here are some highlights
from this month’s program.
What should we do if we encounter spiritism
in some form?
And how can we help
others break free from it?
This dramatization will provide
some valuable principles.
We’ve all beheld the wonders of creation.
This month’s beautiful music video
will move us to pause,
think, and thank Jehovah
for his magnificent works.
And we go to world headquarters
to visit another museum.
We’ll see how, in our time, Jehovah is
blessing “a people for his name.”
This is the August 2019 edition
of JW Broadcasting.
Our broadcast this month has the theme
“Cherish Your Privilege of Prayer.”
Do you think it’s appropriate
to label prayer as a miracle?
Miracles are described
in our New World Translation
“Glossary of Bible Terms”
as “actions or phenomena
“that surpass all powers
“known to humans and are attributed
to a supernatural agency.”
Does prayer fit that description?
The moment you say a prayer,
your innermost thoughts and feelings
are communicated instantly to the Creator
from wherever you are
—even if you pray silently.
That’s certainly
beyond any power that humans know.
Therefore, the fact that a human
can call out to God in prayer
and be heard by him
is truly a miracle.
It’s only
by the undeserved kindness of Jehovah
that we can approach
his heavenly throne in prayer.
Today our lives are very complicated
and, in some cases, very troubled.
Whether young or old, there are times
we may feel overwhelmed with our problems.
At other times,
we may simply feel alone and helpless.
What can we do?
The apostle Paul says that prayer will help.
Please open your Bible to Philippians 4:6
and listen
to his spirit-inspired recommendations:
“Do not be anxious over anything,
“but in everything by prayer and supplication
“along with thanksgiving,
let your petitions be made known to God.”
So Paul is saying
that in all circumstances of life,
prayer is essential.
While no one around us
can see the inner struggles we may be having,
Jehovah sees them.
What will he do?
Let’s read verse 7:
“And the peace of God
that surpasses all understanding
“will guard your hearts
and your mental powers
by means of Christ Jesus.”
This incomparable “peace of God”
is an unusual tranquillity
enjoyed by Jehovah’s dedicated servants,
even in the most trying circumstances.
Have you felt that inner peace
that results
from intimate communication with Jehovah?
How much we benefit from prayer
is closely related to the strength
of our personal relationship with Jehovah.
A key factor in that relationship
is found at Psalm 37:3:
“Trust in Jehovah and do what is good;
reside in the earth,
and act with faithfulness.”
Likely you’d agree that when we need
to talk to someone about our worries,
we go to a trusted friend.
Why?
It’s because we’ve developed
a relationship with him.
He knows us and our situation,
and we know we can count on him.
More than ever,
we need
a close personal relationship with Jehovah.
For that to be possible, we must be convinced
that Jehovah knows
who we are and that he understands us
—our situation, our worries,
our concerns, and our needs.
Notice what Jehovah promises
in verses 4 and 5:
“Find exquisite delight in Jehovah,
“and he will grant you
the desires of your heart.
“Commit your way to Jehovah;
rely on him, and he will act in your behalf.”
Jehovah does know who we are.
He understands us better than anyone else,
even better than we understand ourselves.
He invites us to trust him,
and he promises to act in our behalf.
The miracle of prayer lets us experience
Jehovah’s love in a truly intimate way.
Our Father personally
takes the time to listen to us;
he has not delegated that to anyone else.
However, you might be wondering,
‛Why would the Creator
of the universe want to listen to me?’
The inspired answer at 1 Peter 5:7 says:
“Because he cares for you.”
Your determination to keep doing
the best you can to serve him
in spite of all the problems you face
endears you to him.
He feels for you and is eager to help.
How does that make you feel?
At Psalm 116:1, it says:
“I love Jehovah
“because he hears my voice,
my pleas for help.”
Even though we can’t see him listening to us,
it’s as if we feel
Jehovah’s loving arms around us when we pray.
As a result, the more we pray,
the more our love and trust in him grows.
What else will help us
to build our love
and trust in our God, Jehovah?
It’s more than recognizing
that he hears our prayers.
We must be convinced
that he answers our prayers.
What evidence do we have
that Jehovah answers prayers?
Let’s look at some
specific answers to prayers,
both past and present.
Open your Bible to 2 Chronicles chapter 20.
When Judah was threatened
by the combined forces
of Ammon and Moab
and the mountainous region of Seir,
King Jehoshaphat
humbly prayed for Jehovah’s help.
In verse 12, he prayed:
“O our God,
will you not execute judgment on them?
“For we are powerless
“before this large crowd
that is coming against us;
“and we do not know what we should do,
but our eyes are toward you.”
What was Jehovah’s answer?
There was no voice from heaven.
Jehovah caused a prophet to speak up.
Verse 15 says:
“Here is what Jehovah says to you,
“‘Do not be afraid or be terrified
because of this large crowd,
for the battle is not yours but God’s.’”
Then verse 17 continues:
“You will not need to fight this battle.
“Take your position, stand still,
and see the salvation
of Jehovah in your behalf.”
Did you note the formula?
Jehovah’s dedicated servant
is facing a serious problem.
He prays specifically,
and then he remains attentive to the answer.
The answer may have seemed
strange to Jehoshaphat.
Jehovah didn’t provide a battle plan.
As strategies go, just walking out
to meet the enemy
doesn’t sound like a very good one.
But Jehoshaphat discerned
that this was the answer from Jehovah,
and he let it direct his actions.
What happened?
Jehovah fought for Judah
by striking confusion
into the ranks of the enemy
so that they slaughtered one another.
Jehoshaphat’s prayer was answered
in a mighty way.
We have examples in the first century
of collective prayers being answered.
One occasion was when King Herod
was out to gain the favor of the Jews,
so he had the apostle Peter imprisoned
and placed under heavy guard.
What would the congregation do?
Acts 12:5 gives us the answer:
“So Peter was being kept in the prison,
but the congregation
was intensely praying to God for him.”
Did Jehovah answer their prayers
in behalf of Peter?
The account in verses 7-11 tells us
that an angel of Jehovah
led Peter out of jail
and delivered him to safety.
Imagine how these events must have drawn
the Christians in Jerusalem closer to Jehovah
when they saw
that he had answered their prayers.
What about today?
Consider the example
of our brothers in South Korea.
Over the years,
more than 19,000 of our brothers
have been imprisoned
as conscientious objectors
to military service.
Did you personally pray
in behalf of these brothers
that they might endure in their faith
or that they might be released from prison
if it was Jehovah’s will?
We’re sure that you did.
In fact, many of you prayed
for these brothers by name,
just as the congregation in the first century
prayed in behalf of Peter.
With what result?
In 2018, a series
of court rulings in South Korea
finally recognized conscientious objection
to military service for religious reasons
as a fundamental human right,
and our brothers
were gradually released
from their prison bonds.
What do you think?
Did Jehovah hear our prayers
in behalf of these dear brothers?
As a worldwide brotherhood,
there can be no doubt
that our incessant prayers to Jehovah
were a major factor
in these marvelous developments,
and we praise and thank Jehovah
that he’s heard our prayers.
What does this review
of how Jehovah answered the prayers
of his servants
in the past and present do for us?
Doesn’t it build confidence that Jehovah
is listening to and acting on
the prayers of his people?
The apostle John had that confidence.
He wrote at 1 John 5:14:
“And this is the confidence
that we have toward him,
“that no matter what we ask
according to his will,
he hears us.”
But now the question is:
When was the last time
that Jehovah answered
one of your personal prayers?
We spend much time on learning
how to pray and what to pray for,
but do we put forth enough effort
in identifying the answers to our prayers?
For us to have the closeness to Jehovah,
we must be certain that he’s listening
and responding to our personal prayers.
It may not always be readily discernible
just how some prayers are answered.
So, what can we do?
Take time to meditate on Jehovah’s response
to your prayerful requests.
If you’re married,
freely discuss matters
that you have prayed for in common
and how Jehovah
may be answering those prayers.
Be observant and alert to things
that are happening around you,
and learn to connect these things
with the answers to your prayers.
Make your prayers more specific,
and you’ll become
more keenly aware of Jehovah’s answers
—even though they may be subtle.
Identifying your answered prayers
will make Jehovah more real to you.
This process
of identifying answers to our prayers
should be learned early on
in one’s spiritual development.
We cannot take it
for granted that our children
or our Bible students
will connect the answers
they receive to the prayers they’ve offered.
One Witness said,
“I find that people feel closer to God
“if I help them to recognize
answers to their prayers.”
What if we can’t identify
the answer to one of our prayers?
Does that mean
it wasn’t according to Jehovah’s will?
Not necessarily.
There are two important factors
that might be involved.
One is that Jehovah knows
the best time and way
to answer our prayers.
He takes all matters into consideration.
The answer may not come
according to our timetable, but it will come.
So we must be patient
and keep looking for the answer.
The second factor that Jehovah considers
is the issue raised by Satan
regarding man’s integrity.
Listen again to the challenge Satan makes
as recorded at Job 1:10, 11:
“Have you not put up a protective hedge
“around him and his house
and everything he has?
“You have blessed the work of his hands,
“and his livestock
has spread out in the land.
“But, for a change, stretch out your hand
“and strike everything he has,
and he will surely
curse you to your very face.”
Jehovah permitted this issue
to be raised out of love
for his intelligent creatures.
He permitted Job to undergo a test
by Satan before the entire universe.
Jehovah gives his creatures the privilege
of proving the Devil a liar
and of removing the slander
not only from God’s name
but also from their own.
So Jehovah, seeing the entire issue,
may allow his servants to endure trials.
But that doesn’t mean
he’s not answering
the prayer of the afflicted.
When we are under trial,
we may have prayed for relief,
but we may have also prayed:
“Let your name be sanctified.”
We must remain convinced that Jehovah
will not simply answer a prayer;
he will provide the best answer.
Isn’t it true that
when we maintain our integrity,
even through serious illness,
it can be a tremendous witness to others?
That was the case with Jerod Septer.
God’s Word says:
“Remember, then, your Grand Creator
“in the days of your youth,
before the days of distress come.”
And “the days of distress”
—they arrived early on Jerod at 11.
Jerod was diagnosed
with lymphoma cancer in the middle of 1991.
We started trying
to figure out how we could get him
the treatment that he needed,
of course, but in no way would we accept
a blood transfusion, and neither would Jerod.
When Jerod was in the hospital,
Child Protective Services
did investigate us.
They were concerned there was negligence.
It was just adding to the pain.
The way it turned out,
they backed completely away from that.
They realized that we hadn’t been negligent.
So as we faced different situations,
we’d pray at the time,
not to have miraculous answers,
but for Jehovah to open our eyes
and to be able to find things.
And it seemed as though
he was really directing us,
so that we could take care
of ourselves spiritually
through this situation as well as take care
of Jerod’s medical needs.
I remember
many times falling on my knees
and praying and thinking: ‘This is it.
I’m tested beyond what I can bear.’
And Jehovah would strengthen me.
And someone would come,
or they would say something.
And they fed us.
The brother made a schedule, and he said,
“You’re going to feed these friends.”
And the brother’s instructions were:
“You don’t bring it
and just drop off the food.
You stay with those friends.”
It made me cry
—the love and the care that we experienced.
One time, I remember
the hallways of this hospital
—1,500 miles (2,400 km) away from our home—
started filling up with people.
To me, that was answering prayers too.
It was hard for us
to get out of the hospital,
so they recorded talks.
They would look us in the eye,
and they’d say:
“Now, you need to listen to this.
It will keep you strong.”
Jerod was worried about us,
and he made it clear
that he was going to be fine.
He just didn’t know if we were going to be.
He died
in June of 1992.
He was at home.
And the last thing he said to us was,
“Work hard so we can all be together again.”
It’s numbing
because it’s almost like
you’re living a nightmare
because you never think
that those things will happen to you,
but it did.
I didn’t want people to see me cry.
I didn’t want pity, and I didn’t—
Because of that
—those negative feelings—
my imagination ran wild.
What helped me, I know,
was Gary putting into my heart and mind
that this is a fight.
It’s been a challenge for all mankind.
‘If you make it hard on them,
they won’t love you’
—Satan said that
about Jehovah and individuals.
So I would be giving in to that.
The strong feelings I had
and my sorrow almost made me stop.
I prayed a lot
to go back to the Kingdom Hall.
The congregation cried;
they lost a little boy.
It wasn’t just Gary and Beth.
They lost a little boy.
They cried,
and I didn’t feel alone.
And then we hugged; we cried together.
It really benefited us to get right back
into spiritual focus
and to get our minds off ourselves.
And I could’ve given in
to my pain and thought,
‘Well, I’m too heartbroken.’
It made me have more joy
because I realized that now they have a hope.
People around us were vital
—the support system Jehovah has—
and his Word, his spirit.
Jehovah answered those prayers.
Our goal was really to stay
in the full-time ministry
(maybe doing something else),
but we never, ever thought
we would be in the circuit work.
But to have our daughter
working with her husband in the circuit work
—it’s almost hard
to believe that it’s happening.
We look forward to seeing Jerod again,
having him back with us.
So I’m waiting,
and I know I’m not going to be disappointed.
How encouraging to know that Gary and Beth
are able to take vacation time
to travel occasionally
to see their daughter and her husband,
who are also serving in the traveling work.
And did you notice how Gary, Beth, and Jerod
felt Jehovah’s loving support as they prayed
throughout this heart-wrenching trial?
They asked for wisdom
when seeking medical treatment for Jerod.
Jehovah put his arms around them and listened
when they felt overwhelmed
with grief and negative feelings.
He strengthened
Jerod’s hope in the resurrection
and helped Brother and Sister Septer
stay spiritually strong.
Can there be any doubt
that Jehovah was answering their prayers?
Doesn’t that strengthen our conviction
that Jehovah will also answer Jerod’s prayer
that they all will be together again?
No, Jehovah didn’t miraculously cure Jerod.
But through his endurance and strong faith,
Jerod gave a witness to the universe
that even a child that trusts in Jehovah
can prove his loyalty to death.
Now, other situations
may turn out differently
and not end up in death.
If an individual feels that relief
was because of Jehovah’s intervention,
he should certainly give thanks.
However, we must recognize that Jehovah knows
the best way to handle matters
so that it results in honor to his name
and to the lasting good of his servants.
Finally, it’s worth mentioning that the Bible
often connects
our remaining spiritually alert
with our need to pray.
At Matthew 26:41,
Jesus said:
“Keep on the watch and pray continually.”
At 1 Peter 4:7,
Peter wrote:
“But the end of all things has drawn close.
“Therefore, be sound in mind,
and be vigilant with a view to prayers.”
Indeed, our prayers are so important.
Our personal prayers will help us
to remain spiritually alert
and active in God’s service
as we await the great tribulation
that lies just ahead of us.
So in summary, our prayers to Jehovah
reveal the closeness
of our relationship with him
and the degree of our dependence upon him.
They show the trueness of our faith,
the depth of our devotion,
and the genuineness of our appreciation.
Our prayers also help us
to remain spiritually alert
as we endure these last days
before the great tribulation.
We’ll be drawn even closer to Jehovah
when we learn to recognize
his answers to our prayers.
Yes, we can be assured that Jehovah
will not fail in giving us
the desires of our heart
as we continue rendering him sacred service.
May we all cherish our marvelous,
miraculous privilege of prayer.
Let’s look at one practical example
of when prayer is of utmost importance
—when confronted
with the powers of wicked spirits.
Spiritism is very real and dangerous.
Yet, with Jehovah’s help,
people can break free from its hold.
In this dramatization,
notice how one sister
helped her Bible student to do that.
Emma and I were so worried
about her Bible study, Palesa.
She had spent another sleepless night
after again hearing
her dead grandmother’s voice,
plus the sound of slamming doors
and items crashing in the house.
Palesa had put an amulet
on her baby’s wrist for protection,
but the terror continued all night long.
Of course, it wasn’t really her grandmother,
and nothing in the house was broken;
but the attack was real.
Stories about the spirit world weren’t new to me.
Our neighbors, the people I work with,
the people in our territory
—almost everyone believes in spirits,
whether they admit it or not.
No—more than believe—they fear them!
I had only been studying the Bible
about six months longer than Palesa.
But my study had proved to me
that wicked spirits are here on earth,
that they try to interact with people,
and that they are dangerous enemies.
Emma called the elders for help.
She didn’t want us to handle
the situation on our own.
As Emma told the story,
I had to speak up and tell the elders
that she was leaving things out.
But I was surprised when the elders
said they didn’t need all the details.
They explained that while we are aware
of the danger the demons pose,
we do not spend time
talking about their activities.
Even Jesus, when he was on earth,
could have told his disciples many stories
about the doings of wicked spirits,
but instead,
he focused on Jehovah and His activities.
We should do the same
instead of telling stories about what the demons
may or may not have done.
The elders skillfully used the Bible,
shepherding everyone.
We read Ephesians 6:11:
“Put on the complete suit of armor from God
“so that you may be able to stand firm
against the crafty acts of the Devil.”
Those instructions were so important.
A soldier would be vulnerable
if he only wore part of his armor
or if he didn’t keep it in good repair.
Then we read Ephesians 4:27:
“Do not give the Devil an opportunity.”
The elders explained to Palesa
that the string around her daughter’s wrist
is not part of the armor from God.
Instead, it is giving Satan
an opportunity to continue to harass the family.
The brothers reminded us
that anyone who wants Jehovah’s protection
must completely break free
from anything associated with superstition,
spiritism, and demon worship.
Who would ever choose to side
with wicked spirits instead of with Jehovah?
Emma reminded Palesa
of how urgent the situation was.
But only Palesa could decide what she would do.
I want to be a loyal servant of Jehovah.
That’s why I’m getting baptized.
I’ve decided not to listen to or tell
any more stories about the demons.
But more than that,
I need to look at other parts of my life.
Am I doing anything
that would “give the Devil an opportunity”?
Clearly,
there are still changes I need to make.
Did you notice how they prayed
for Jehovah’s direction?
They followed the principle of Psalm 37:5:
“Commit your way to Jehovah;
rely on him, and he will act in your behalf.”
And as you noticed,
as he’s committing
his life course to Jehovah,
Thomas’ Christian conscience
has now started to guide him.
And he likely realizes
that he has to safeguard his heart
from things that may tempt him.
In this Bethel Morning Worship,
Brother Morris of the Governing Body
helps us to see why it requires
effort to protect
our relationship with Jehovah.
This morning, I thought we’d talk about accepting
the facts about our figurative heart
and how that safeguards
our relationship with Jehovah.
Let’s read the day’s text
in its entirety
in Jeremiah chapter 17.
And what a sobering inspired thought
from our heavenly Father!
Jeremiah chapter 17
and we’ll read verse 9:
“The heart is more treacherous
than anything else and is desperate.”
So there we have it.
That’s the truth.
That’s what Jehovah makes very clear to us
—that each and every one of us
has to deal with a treacherous,
or deceitful, figurative heart.
And how encompassing
the expression here
“more treacherous than anything else.”
And what complicates it even more
is that it’s desperate.
It always wants its way
—so a lot to meditate on.
And now,
Jehovah put it here for the very reason
that we have to accept this fact.
And to safeguard our relationship with him,
we have to accept that this is the case.
And you could be a fine Christian for many years
—mature, nice outlook, nice attitude.
But if you ever find yourself
forgetting Jehovah’s estimation
of what we have within us,
in our figurative heart,
then we’re in danger
because the Devil will always exploit
the fact that our imperfect figurative hearts
are treacherous and deceitful
more than anything else
and are desperate.
So accept that fact.
It’s not that we want to dwell on it,
and you start feeling,
‘Well, what a miserable person I am!’
Even though that is something
the apostle Paul acknowledged,
it’s just accepting the fact.
And then we’re cautious about allowing
the treacherous heart to lead us astray.
Now, perhaps you haven’t thought
about this in a while,
but notice what Jesus said
—a fundamental truth for all of us—
here in Matthew chapter 6
and what we sometimes
refer to as the model prayer.
Matthew chapter 6
(and a lot of spiritual food for thought,
of course, anything Jesus said
is spiritual food for thought)
and verse 13 of Matthew chapter 6:
“And do not bring us into temptation,
but deliver us from the wicked one.”
So it’s been there for all these years.
We could personally reflect on,
‘When was the last time we mentioned
that in a prayer to our Father, Jehovah:
‘“Do not bring us into temptation
but deliver us from the wicked one,”
or “rescue us from the wicked one”?’
What are we really saying there?
Well, we’re asking our heavenly Father
to guide and help us
so that we’re not “overreached by Satan”
—very simple.
But the closer we get to the end,
make no mistake, it’s even more urgent
to keep in mind the need
to beg Jehovah not to bring us into temptation
and to guide us so that we’ll be delivered
from this wicked one
who wants to exploit the fact that we have
a treacherous,
traitorous figurative heart
that can ruin our relationship
with Jehovah personally.
Now, the apostle Paul recognized this,
and it’s quite interesting what he wrote
to his beloved brothers
in Thessalonians, that first letter.
So if you’d find 1 Thessalonians,
in chapter 3,
I found this quite revealing.
And tying in with the thought
of accepting the facts
about how our figurative heart
safeguards our relationship
with our God and Father, Jehovah,
at 1 Thessalonians 3:5,
Paul writes: “That is why,
when I could bear it no longer,
“I sent to learn of your faithfulness,
“[now notice] in case somehow
“the Tempter might have tempted you,
and our labor
might have turned out to be in vain.”
So he didn’t get into any specific detail.
But it helps us to appreciate
that there’s this danger that somehow
the Tempter, Satan the Devil,
might tempt us,
and this is connected with the need to beg
Jehovah to deliver us, or rescue us,
from the wicked one
in his effort to tempt us to break our integrity
and have our cherished relationship
with Jehovah be damaged.
So he knows the heart is treacherous.
And whoever we are and however long
we’ve been in the truth,
remember what Paul wrote to the Thessalonians
—“somehow”—
because he’s always looking
to somehow lead us
into breaking our integrity to Jehovah God.
Now, if you think of Revelation chapter 12
and where we are in this stream of time,
(this occurred to me
when preparing these thoughts here)
Revelation chapter 12
has very familiar thoughts here.
The Devil is expelled from the heavens,
he and the demons, and notice
the familiar verse 12
of Revelation chapter 12:
‘On this account be glad, you heavens
and [boy, they’re rejoicing]
those that reside in them!’
And that’s an exclamation.
Notice, though:
“Woe for the earth and for the sea,
“because the Devil has come down to you,
having great anger,
knowing that he has a short period of time.”
Well, if that was true
after he was ousted from the heavens,
what do you think about now?
So it’s sobering.
We want to safeguard
our relationship with Jehovah
because notice verse 17 of the same chapter:
“So the dragon became enraged.”
Great anger—he’s enraged,
and he’s waging war with the remnant,
as it brings out here.
And those that observe
the commandments of God
—anyone supporting the remnant—
this is a war.
And the war
is that he’s out to somehow
cause us to break our integrity to our precious
heavenly Father,
so this helps us to appreciate that,
even though it was long before
the thoughts here in Revelation
and what Jesus taught us.
In Proverbs chapter 4,
it still helps us:
“More than all else that is to be guarded,
safeguard your heart,
for out of it are the sources of life.”
So even back then,
there was the recognition
that we have to safeguard our heart
and accept the fact that our heart,
our figurative heart, is treacherous
—that’ll safeguard our precious relationship
with Jehovah God.
Now, to help us with that,
notice what Paul wrote
—very familiar verses in 2 Timothy chapter 3.
And we’ve used this
in the ministry many times,
and yet think about it as it connects
with safeguarding our hearts
and accepting the fact that it’s treacherous
—that we won’t break our integrity
or allow the Devil
to somehow cause us to break our integrity.
Second Timothy chapter 3
and you’ll notice what we’re emphasizing here.
The fact is in verse 16:
“All Scripture is inspired of God.”
But notice the benefits.
So it’s “for teaching,” it’s “for reproving,”
“setting things straight”
—see the point here, though?—
“for disciplining in righteousness.”
So you think of that maybe on your Bible study.
‘I use the Bible to discipline
my Bible study to get God’s thinking.’
And it’s appropriate that elders
use the Scriptures to discipline.
However, we want to emphasize here for you
that when you’re doing your
personal Bible reading (many of us),
let the Scriptures discipline
that treacherous heart.
It’s a mirror.
When something hits you
because maybe you’ve had wrong thinking
(could be all sorts of things,
anything that could lead us astray
and cause us to break our integrity),
just face the fact.
It’s just between you and Jehovah.
You’re reading it,
and let it discipline you in righteousness.
And that’s what’s going
to enable us to protect
our precious relationship
with Jehovah God.
So we all have to face that fact,
as we mentioned,
our figurative heart is treacherous;
it’s a traitor.
What’s wonderful is we’re confident
that Jehovah loves us.
So when he made that estimation in Jeremiah,
it’s motivated by his love.
So that helps us to protect
our relationship with him
—facing that fact.
That’s the way it is.
So indeed, we accept the fact
about our figurative heart,
but we’re determined
to protect and safeguard
our precious relationship with Jehovah God.
Yes, praying for Jehovah’s help
is an important tool
in safeguarding our heart.
And having a desire
to protect our relationship with Jehovah
is closely linked to how much
we appreciate what he’s done for us.
Our appreciation moves us to action
and strengthens our faith in him.
Such appreciation
is highlighted in this month’s
music video which is entitled Thankful.
Dandelions growing
on top of the hill,
Mountains in the distance,
wind blowing through the field,
Warmth of the sun
casting down from the sky,
Birds fly up above,
Clouds rolling by—
What did I do
To see such beauty?
And what do I do
To show how much I care?
I’ve got to be thankful,
Tell Jehovah in prayer
That I’m thankful
For the love that he shares.
Stop,
look around,
Take a moment,
and let it sink down in my heart.
Never take for granted
all he’s done.
I’ve got to be thankful.
So many colors
now painted in the sky,
What a beautiful canvas
you’ve laid before my eyes!
The sound of the river
running into the night,
The stars are dancing
in the moon’s spotlight—
What did I do
To see such beauty?
But I know what to do
To show how much I care.
I’ve got to be thankful,
Tell Jehovah in prayer
That I’m thankful
For the love that he shares.
Stop,
look around,
Take a moment,
and let it sink down in my heart.
Never take for granted
all he’s done.
I’ve got to be thankful.
I see your wisdom
and your strength,
Your goodness in ev’rything,
And how much you love.
And I’m so thankful;
I’ve got to be thankful.
I’ve got to be thankful,
Tell Jehovah in prayer
That I’m thankful
For the love that he shares.
Stop,
look around,
Take a moment,
and let it sink down in my heart.
Never take for granted
all he’s done.
I’ve got to be thankful.
We’ve got to be thankful.
Did you notice one way
of expressing our gratitude to Jehovah?
Yes, by means of prayer.
Having that channel
to the Sovereign of the universe
is a benefit of being his people.
And speaking of being Jehovah’s people,
in last month’s program,
we had an opportunity
to visit one of the museums
at world headquarters in Warwick, New York.
But there’s more to see.
Let’s join Brother John Ekrann,
a helper to the Coordinators’ Committee,
on another visit, and this time,
we’ll stop by a museum called
“A People for Jehovah’s Name.”
Do you enjoy a good story?
If so, you’re in for a special treat.
“A People for Jehovah’s Name”
at world headquarters in Warwick
is more than a history museum.
It’s the modern-day story of a people
seeking to know the true God
and to do his will.
But this isn’t just any story
—it’s our story.
So let’s take
a thrilling journey back in time.
The story unfolds on the narrative wall
and in several galleries along the way.
We begin in the 1870’s,
when a small group
in Allegheny, Pennsylvania,
decided to reexamine the Bible.
As C. T. Russell reasoned:
All the creeds of Christendom
claim to be founded on the Bible;
and these are conflicting.
Is it possible that the Bible
has been misrepresented?
The more they learned,
the more they wanted to share.
So in 1879,
they began publishing Zion’s Watch Tower.
Readers were soon taking a stand
for the truths that they were learning.
Listen.
What I want to tell you is this,
I am free!
The truth has made me free!
To-day I was excluded
from the Baptist church . . .
So I am all alone in the ‘flesh,’
but not in the ‘spirit.’
They became known as the Bible Students,
and they soon realized that people
everywhere should hear the good news.
But how could this small group
preach the Bible’s message earthwide?
Transcontinental and international tours
helped them to see how they could expand
their preaching work even further.
In just one tour
beginning in December 1911,
C. T. Russell and his associates
traveled completely around the world.
Let’s imagine what it was like
to live in those exciting times.
In this gallery,
you can experience what life was like
for a pilgrim,
or what we today call a circuit overseer.
Here’s a pilgrim’s formal jacket
that he’d wear when giving a public talk.
The Bible Students offered the Studies
in the Scriptures series in the ministry.
And they carried lists to locate
and visit Watch Tower subscribers.
Then in 1914,
they presented
the exciting “Photo-Drama of Creation.”
Its purpose was to build faith in the Bible
as God’s inspired Word.
It was an innovative combination
of moving pictures,
sound recordings,
and beautiful, hand-colored glass slides.
Hundreds of people reenacted Bible scenes,
some with live animals!
Was this enormous work worth all the effort?
DEAR BROTHER RUSSELL,
I want to thank you;
oh, . . . so much, for the privilege
of seeing the PHOTO-DRAMA OF CREATION!
I had never thought to live to see
the everlasting Gospel preached
to those who dwell on the earth . . . !
Yet so it is.
Words cannot tell you how my heart rejoices!
—Your sister, F. E. Riley.
By the end of 1914,
over nine million had viewed it.
But with such success,
the Bible Students didn’t realize
what tests lay ahead.
The Gentile Times have ended;
their kings have had their day!
So we know not what awaits us.
World War I broke out in 1914.
Then in 1916,
the death of C. T. Russell
left the Bible Students in shock.
It was a unique time of testing.
Inside the organization,
some struggled over who should take the lead.
Outside,
governments tried to force them
to take sides in the war.
Then in 1918,
J. F. Rutherford
and seven of his close associates
were imprisoned.
Was this the end for the Bible Students?
Or would they prove to be
a people for Jehovah’s name?
The joy that came
with the release of our brothers
from the Atlanta Federal Prison on Tuesday,
March 25, 1919, knew no bounds.
Their further devotion to Jehovah
was shown in the fact
that they immediately set to work to herald
forth to the people of God everywhere
the knowledge of Jehovah’s deliverance.
—Thomas Sullivan.
The Bible Students
moved forward with renewed zeal.
But the opposition didn’t end there.
In this gallery,
you will see how our brothers and sisters
have stood firm for their faith.
In Russia, a father imprisoned for ten years
encouraged his young daughters
with hand-drawn postcards.
In Greece,
a son used the same blanket in prison
that his father used
when imprisoned before him.
It was an encouraging reminder
of his father’s integrity.
In Korea,
Witnesses were locked in tiny cells
for up to 30 days at a time.
When you stand in the lighted outline,
you get a sense of what it was like.
All of these brothers and sisters
looked beyond the prison bars
to their firm hope for the future.
As light from God’s Word increased,
the Bible Students humbly let go
of cherished but unscriptural traditions.
Songs used in worship were examined
in the light of what the Bible taught.
The people for Jehovah’s name
were becoming even more evident.
So in 1931,
they were thrilled to take on their new name
—Jehovah’s Witnesses.
Then in 1935,
Brother Rutherford identified
the great multitude of other sheep,
who served alongside the anointed.
At the climax of his talk, he asked:
Will all those who have the hope
of living forever on the earth please stand?
With this new understanding,
they saw the true scope
of Jesus’ commission to make disciples.
New and innovative methods were needed.
Our third gallery shows the preaching
methods used in the 1930’s and 1940’s.
Radio was a powerful way
to spread the Kingdom message
to large audiences.
They also used large phonographs,
called portable transcription machines,
with loudspeakers mounted on sound cars.
Brothers played recorded talks
wherever people gathered.
Lighter phonographs
were also designed and produced so publishers
could take the recorded message
directly to people at home.
These methods
helped bring unity to the message,
but the time had come to train each one
of Jehovah’s people
to be an effective Witness.
Schools were started.
The Course in Theocratic Ministry
trained publishers in the congregation.
And the Bible School of Gilead
began training missionaries
for global expansion.
We had entered
into a new era of divine education.
And we were about to receive an amazing tool.
In 1950,
we received the New World Translation
of the Christian Greek Scriptures.
And by 1961, the complete Bible was released.
Since then,
we’ve seen our tools continue to improve
with the wise use of modern technology.
From high-speed printing
to the Internet and video,
these methods help us to stay unified,
to reach millions with the good news,
and to glorify God.
Yes, this museum’s story is about people,
but not just any people.
We are “a people for Jehovah’s name.”
Only one question remains:
What will you contribute
to this wonderful story?
This month, after discussing the theme
“Cherish Your Privilege of Prayer,”
we saw how we should act
when we encounter spiritism.
When counteracting wicked spirits,
praying for Jehovah’s guidance
is very important.
Next, Brother Morris
showed us the importance of praying
to protect our heart.
And the music video
reminded us
of not forgetting to thank Jehovah
for everything he’s given us.
The provision of communicating with Jehovah
is a privilege we have of being his people.
A visit to Warwick Bethel
showed us how Jehovah
has guided his people in modern times.
Before we conclude,
we’ll visit the remote translation office
in Chinle, Arizona, in the United States.
Located
in the southwestern part of the country,
the region is home
to many native peoples and tribes.
European settlers arrived in the 1500’s.
Throughout the many years since then,
many of the tribes were able
to retain their culture and language.
Currently,
the United States branch translates
into several indigenous languages, including
Cherokee, Hopi, Lakota, and Navajo.
To help with that work,
in 2015, a remote translation office, or RTO,
was built in Chinle,
which is in the heart of the Navajo nation.
Over 100 volunteers,
of which 13 are full-time servants,
work at the RTO.
The Navajo field has over 430 publishers,
including approximately 130 regular pioneers
and some 20 special pioneers.
The literature, videos,
and audio publications translated
at the RTO
are distributed to 8 Navajo congregations,
11 groups, and 5 pregroups.
For the past five years,
three-day regional conventions
have been held in the Navajo language.
In 2018, they had a peak attendance of 471,
with one baptized.
The volunteers at the RTO in Chinle
send their warm Christian love
to all of us around the world.
And we love them dearly.
This is JW Broadcasting
from the World Headquarters
of Jehovah’s Witnesses.