We look forward to
Brother Anthony Morris’ thoughts
presented in his talk entitled
“We Have Work to Do!”
It was a great pleasure
to hear all of the excitement
when the Ramapo project
was announced to all of you here,
and I’m sure that was true
for the other thousands that are tied in.
And then you saw with these videos
all the construction projects
going on all over
—all over the earth.
So it’s quite interesting,
if you think about it
from an imperfect, human perspective
(frankly, not thinking spiritually),
you’d say:
“Well, we just dedicated the Warwick property
“along with Wallkill recently.
Now here we go down the road.”
Well, the preaching work
obviously is premier.
And that’s what this is really about
—the preaching work.
To support the preaching work
and to continue to feed
Jehovah’s precious sheep
the way he wants them fed
involves all this construction.
So God wants us to have it clear.
He wants you to spread this and,
of course, it’ll come up in January.
Keep in mind, we have work to do.
Period.
So get over it.
Don’t get me going on vacation.
I’ll just tell you—
And I know my friends on the Governing Body,
and I know that you need your time.
I’m not trying to put you on a guilt trip,
but we have a whole lot of days.
How do you do it
with the work that’s going on?
You try to rest up when you can;
Jehovah wants us to.
But we have so much work to do.
And we thank God for it.
So just to give us
a little Scriptural reminder
of the proper attitude about work,
find John chapter 5.
And these are
very familiar verses to all of you,
particularly the audience here in Newburgh
with all these decades of faithful service.
We treasure your service
and, of course,
Jehovah certainly does.
And you’ve worked hard for decades
—a lot of you to whom
I was talking to earlier
have decades in the traveling work—
so many wonderful,
hardworking brothers and sisters.
So here he is, Jesus, (in John chapter 5)
facing these judgmental religious leaders
persecuting him over curing on the Sabbath.
Well, what we’re after here
is something he reveals to us in verse 17,
when he’s answering them:
“My Father has kept working until now,
and I keep working.”
So the hardest worker
in the universe is Jehovah God,
and Christ Jesus is right there with him.
Jehovah is a worker.
His people have to be workers.
That’s what he expects,
and it’s such a pleasure
to serve the true God and work.
And another familiar verse
in 1 Corinthians chapter 15
shows the proper spirit
when it comes to this matter
of being workers,
with all the work we have to do.
And Jehovah is seeing to it
that we have all this work
—very familiar,
verse 58 of 1 Corinthians 15:
“Therefore, my beloved brothers,
“be steadfast, immovable,
“[notice] always  having plenty to do
“in the work of the Lord,
knowing that your labor
is not in vain in connection with the Lord”
—plenty of work “in the work of the Lord.”
And then when we’re doing the work
(and this is crucial),
as we engage in it
—whether it’s the preaching work
or other work assignments,
if you’re in a Bethel assignment
or a construction assignment—
there’s a proper spirit.
And find here Romans chapter 12.
And this we see in God’s people,
but we want to individually apply the counsel
and make sure we keep this spirit
or talk to God about it
if it’s lacking at the moment.
Romans chapter 12
—and here’s what Christians are all about
when it comes to working for Jehovah,
verse 11:
“Be industrious, not lazy.”
See, Jehovah does not approve of being lazy.
“Be aglow with the spirit.”
So you’re just absorbed with it.
There’s this zeal
—just alive with it—
as we slave for Jehovah.
So he appreciates
an industrious, hardworking spirit,
and that’s what he wants from his people.
Now, with all of the announcements
and the videos
with construction going on,
I just thought I’d share this with you.
It’s a very special item of mine,
and it came up recently.
You can see here the best you can.
The camera can pick it up,
and up here it says “Building Permit.”
And it’s a special memory for me, personally,
because as we had in some of the videos
when we were involved with the construction
or before construction started
with the Warwick project,
we’d be at Tuxedo,
and a lot of work was going on
—preparatory—
looking for that day
when they could get started.
So the Governing Body
would do their best to get up
and be encouraging
(always wearing the high-vis outfits)
and then give a spiritual talk.
I think it’s the only time
I’ve given a talk in high vis.
So this particular day was special
because things
were moving along with the community.
They liked us,
but I noticed Zeny (in the one video),
he mentioned “shovel to the ground,”
and that’s OK.
We’re different.
I’m calling it “shovel in the ground.”
Zeny is not from America,
so it means the same thing, Zeny,
so forgive me.
I appreciate all your hard work.
But any who
have been involved with construction
(and you have a lot of folks I know here
from the former Regional Building Committee
—all the hardworking construction),
it’s always been special
to work on these spiritual projects.
Well, this particular day,
there were a lot of things going on.
So I’m up there; it’s July 26,
and that date is up here in the corner.
It’s a Friday,
and it’s the year 2013 (quite a while ago).
So I have a talk to give to them
at 1:30 p.m. after visiting some.
Two hours before
(so it must have been around 11:30),
they got the building permit.
So the Construction Project Committee
(and how much we love
those men and their wives)—
They’re there, and they said,
“Well, would you mind
making this announcement?”
And I thought:
‘Boy, that timing worked out good.
‘That’s quite an honor,
the construction, you know,
and “the shovel-in-the-ground” announcement.’
So I gave them a little spiritual side.
You know, a little glory is all right
for a human sometimes, you know.
So it was very exciting.
But the memory is clear
to those who were there.
Because of the operation of holy spirit
and the brothers
being “aglow with the spirit,” industrious,
when they made the announcement,
I’m telling you (those who were there),
there was joy
—the thunderous applause.
It wasn’t anything to do with me.
It was that they got
“the shovel in the ground.”
And the excitement!
So I was able to easily walk out of there,
and they were all busy
—thrilled
over the “shovel-in-the-ground” approval.
Now, the day is coming, God willing,
for the Ramapo project
to have the “shovel in the ground.”
You heard when they hope that happens.
But it’s that beautiful spirit
that glorifies Jehovah
when they work so hard.
And so we have to keep that spirit.
And some could say
(well, it happens on occasion,
not with a lot
of God’s spiritually-minded folks):
“Do you believe the end is coming?
“So, what are you doing all this for?
“If the end is really close,
what are you doing?”
Well, the end is going to come
when Jehovah is satisfied
with the preaching work.
But there is also a reminder here
in Revelation chapter 7;
this is always something you can forget.
I noticed Brother Butler
touched on it in his opening prayer
(which, of course, we don’t record
the prayers for the presentation in January),
but Bob touched on it.
And Jehovah gives us
enough to keep us focused on:
‘You just stay busy and do my will.’
However, this is quite fascinating
at chapter 7 verses 1-3:
“After this I saw four angels standing
on the four corners of the earth,
“holding tight the four winds of the earth,
“so that no wind could blow on the earth
“or on the sea or on any tree.
“And I saw another angel
ascending from the sunrise,
“having a seal of the living God;
“and he called
with a loud voice to the four angels
“to whom it was granted
to harm the earth and the sea,
“saying: [and it’s loud]
“‘Do not harm the earth
or the sea or the trees,
“‘until after we have sealed
the slaves of our God in their foreheads.’”
Now, some individual anointed
have to have a final seal
before they die,
and we’ve had a number of them
die during the last days.
But this is talking
about right before Jehovah starts,
or has put it in the hearts
of the governments to destroy Babylon,
that all of those who are left on the earth,
the remnant
—genuine, anointed disciples of Christ—
get the final seal.
And this is what’s going to take place.
And then after that,
the great tribulation breaks out.
And if you keep an eye
on the news to some degree
(if you can stomach it,
to at least know what’s happening),
the end is definitely close.
There’s just no denying it.
We eagerly look forward to it taking place.
The great tribulation
—it’s close.
However, as we eagerly await it,
we want to have Jehovah’s mind
on the matter and wait patiently.
And I think about all of those
here in Newburgh
with so many years in the truth,
especially corporate members
and their mates (if they’re married).
This Watchtower,
we want to share it with you from 1976
—profound statements.
To this day, they ring true
about this matter of the end.
It shows you where
we are in the stream of time.
And Jehovah’s spirit was on them
(not inspired,
but he captured it with them, helping them),
and it was just ringing,
and it still rings to this day.
Now notice what
that 1976, November 15, Watchtower  said,
pages 688-689.
And in the 17th paragraph,
notice, I’m quoting it:
“The end does not come
“just because we might think
it is the due date,
“or because we feel that our territory
has been well worked.
“It comes when Jehovah has carried through
“the great work of Kingdom preaching
to the extent he wants,
and then he will bring
the ‘great tribulation.’”
Now listen, back in 1976:
“Until that time there is work to do!
“And we as Jehovah’s Witnesses
are the ones assigned to do it!
“The arrival of the ‘great tribulation’
“should find the preaching work
at the height of its forward movement,
“at the very peak
of its momentum throughout the earth.
“The arrival of the Lord Jesus
“to execute judgment
will come as a complete surprise
“—even to Jehovah’s people,
“for it will no doubt find them
at their busiest time of activity!”
Think about it.
Have you been busier
since you’ve been in the truth
than you’ve been recently?
So we’re the busiest we’ve been
—hands down.
So it’s amazing how the slave
captured that right attitude in 1976.
And, of course, some in the truth then,
at least in certain parts of the earth,
they were thinking the end is coming in 1975.
And look at all the growth since the 1970’s.
You had about two million back in the 1970’s
who were Witnesses of the true God.
Now we’re approaching nine million.
So in conclusion, as closing thoughts,
and this is priceless
from that same Watchtower:
“Jehovah’s advancing theocratic society
“will be a going concern,
a go-forward organization,
right down to
and through the ‘great tribulation.’”
So like I’ve told brothers for a long time,
the recent changes from RBC to now—
This is all new world construction
going on here.
You’re taking this over.
After Armageddon,
you’re going to just keep on working,
and others will be trained.
And then further:
“The worship of God,”
The Watchtower  said,
“with spirit and truth is positive,
enthusiastic, spirited and progressive.”
And then this is profound:
“More and more sections of the earth,
“in Western lands,
in the Orient and elsewhere,
“are now receiving a thorough witness,
“and who knows how much farther
the ‘glorious good news’
will be sounded . . . before the end!”
Well, God knows.
And look at the sound of the good news
being all over the earth
—‘the most distant parts of the earth.’
So may all of us beg Jehovah
to continue to empower us
to keep worshipping him
“with spirit and truth”
and enthusiasm and zeal
because we have work to do!
Thank you, Brother Morris.
In the words of 1 Chronicles 28:10,
we will “be courageous and go to work.”
At this time, we ask the question,
“What Do We Have to Fear?”
Brother Mark Sanderson
will address that question now for us.
At Revelation 12:17,
the Bible makes clear
that all of God’s people,
every one of you here in this room
and every servant of God around this earth
who support Jehovah’s anointed ones,
are in a war.
Now read this thought with me
at Revelation 12:17.
It says:
“So the dragon
became enraged at the woman
“and went off to wage war
with the remaining ones of her offspring,
“who observe the commandments of God
“and have the work of bearing witness
concerning Jesus.”
Well, what does it mean?
As our dear Brother Morris would say:
“Cheer up!
Things are only going to get worse.”
Well, if we are in this spiritual war,
what do we expect?
With every war
comes intense, intense hatred.
Not surprisingly,
Jesus made it clear
that his servants
would not just be disliked,
but what did Jesus say?
Let’s read it together at Matthew 24:9
—Matthew 24:9.
He said:
“Then people
will hand you over to tribulation
“and will kill you,
“and you will be hated by all the nations
on account of my name.”
So, brothers, what do we expect?
We expect the hatred of all,
as Jesus said, “all the nations”
—not just Eritrea, not just Russia,
but “all the nations.”
But there is something else
that we also must expect in a war.
There is a very famous quote that says,
“In war, the first casualty is truth.”
And that is exactly what Jesus warned
would happen to God’s people.
Let’s read it.
In Matthew chapter 5,
Matthew 5:11, he said:
“Happy are you when people
reproach you and persecute you
“[and then notice this]
“and lyingly say every sort of wicked thing
against you for my sake.”
Brothers, what’s the point?
We are in a war.
And we expect
to “be hated by all the nations.”
And we expect that people
will “say every sort of wicked thing”
against us.
Well, with that in mind,
it’s good for us to ask this question:
What do we have to fear?
Well-known statesman Franklin Roosevelt said,
“The only thing
that we have to fear is fear itself.”
Well, he’s not completely correct,
but there’s certainly
a note of truth in what he said.
You see, fear is a powerful weapon
in the hand
of our great adversary, Satan the Devil.
He will use that weapon against us.
And what is the danger?
You see, brothers,
when we are afraid, or we are terrified,
we can then be controlled by our enemies.
The apostle Paul made this very clear
in what he said here
in Hebrews the second chapter.
Will you read this with me, please?
Let’s look in Hebrews chapter 2;
let’s look in verse 14.
He says:
“Therefore, since the ‘young children’
“are sharers of blood and flesh,
“he also similarly shared in the same things,
“so that through his death
“[now notice this, through his death]
“he might bring to nothing
“the one having
the means to cause death,
“that is, the Devil,
“and that he might
[do what? that he might]
“set free all those who were held in slavery
all their lives by their fear of death.”
You see, the apostle Paul
praised Jehovah for the gift of Christ Jesus.
And why?
Because he knew that all of those
who would put faith
in the ransom sacrifice of Christ Jesus
would be set free.
But set free from what?
Paul says that it’s from the slavery
to the “fear of death.”
Now, why is that significant?
You see,
people who are in fear of death
are constantly afraid.
And, as a result,
they can be manipulated and controlled.
Now, take, for example,
the Nuremberg trials
that occurred at the end
of the second world war.
Various Nazis who
had committed horrible, terrible atrocities
were brought to justice.
And when these individuals,
both men and women,
were asked the simple question,
“How could you do these terrible things?”
what did they say?
“We had no choice.
“If we didn’t obey,
they would put us to death.”
Those people could be manipulated;
they could be controlled;
they could even get them
to do the most wicked things
because they were afraid.
When we have complete confidence
in our amazing God, Jehovah,
when we have put our full confidence
in the ransom sacrifice
of his Son, Jesus Christ,
we can do
what the apostle Paul says here
in Philippians chapter 1.
Will you read it with me?
At Philippians 1:28,
Paul says:
“And in no way being frightened
“by your opponents.
“This very thing
is a proof of destruction for them,
“but of salvation for you;
and this is from God.”
You see, brothers,
that confidence in Jehovah
and in the ransom sacrifice
of Christ can set us free,
so that we are not afraid
of our opponents.
But another thing that can help us
to overcome the fear of persecution
is realizing something very important,
and that is that Jehovah will allow
our enemies to go only so far.
Now, you remember the text
in 1 Corinthians chapter 10.
Now, let’s read this,
1 Corinthians 10:13.
The apostle Paul says:
“No temptation has come upon you
except what is common to men.
“But God is faithful,
“and he will not let you be tempted
“beyond what you can bear,
“but along with the temptation
“he will also make the way out
so that you may be able to endure it.”
That’s a promise from our God, Jehovah.
He will only allow our enemies to go so far.
In a well-known illustration from a book
that was written in the 1600’s,
it shows a path
that leads off to the final goal,
and on either side of the path,
there are lions.
The caption to the illustration says:
“The lions were chained,
but he didn’t see the chains.”
Now, what’s the point?
You see,
we may encounter lions along our path
on our journey to the new world.
But what do we need to remember?
Every one of those lions is chained.
And so we must look,
not at the lions, brothers,
but at the chains.
And as we concentrate
on the fact that Jehovah loves us,
that he loves his people,
and that he will never allow
Satan or his agents to do anything
that will permanently harm us,
our fear of our persecutors
begins to dwindle away.
When you see the lion,
remember, don’t stare at the lion.
Stare at the chain.
So then, brothers,
I come back to the question,
What then do we have to fear?
Well, the Bible tells us.
It’s here in Psalm 111
—Psalm 111:10.
It says: “The fear of Jehovah
is the beginning of wisdom.
“All those observing his orders
show good insight.
His praise endures forever.”
Well, that’s what we do have to fear.
We have to have a wholesome fear
of our wonderful God, Jehovah.
That wholesome fear of displeasing
the Almighty God of the universe
is our compass.
It shows us the way;
it tells us what we need to do.
No matter how much opposition
may come upon us,
no matter what form
that opposition may take,
if we are God-fearing men and women,
we will know exactly what we need to do.
Do you agree?
Now, brothers, this is not theory.
Our brothers and sisters around the world
are living examples of the truths
that we have just discussed.
Please watch the following video
that contains heartfelt comments
from persecuted brothers
and sisters in Russia,
and see why we have
no reason to fear persecution.
I was horrified when several masked officers
broke down two doors
and burst into the home
where the meeting was being held.
Everything happened at once
—loud sounds, noise, the order:
“Everyone sit on the floor!”
I was overcome with fear
when they put me in handcuffs,
placed me in the police van,
and took me to jail.
I was afraid because I didn’t know
how long I would be there
and what was awaiting me.
When I was being interrogated,
I was afraid that I might be unfaithful
to Jehovah and let my brothers down.
After being detained, I was mostly afraid
about what I would face in prison
—whom I would encounter, how to act,
how others would treat me—the unknown.
When one of the officers began
to describe how bad life is behind bars,
I imagined that behind
the officer stood an angel
just like the one who
supported Daniel in the illustration.
This helped me to calm down
and not to panic or be afraid.
That’s how Jehovah supported me.
At the first court appearance,
when I was brought out,
the brothers’ feelings impelled them
to show support somehow,
and they began applauding.
How that encouraged me
that they were with me!
Fervent and sincere prayers to Jehovah
helped me to cope with these fears.
Isaiah 30:15 gave me much support.
I realized that tranquility and trust
in Jehovah are now the most important things.
Understanding this made things
much easier for me.
We took the elevator down
to the first floor, the doors opened,
and there stood a large crowd
of our brothers and sisters
—and they all began clapping.
When I saw that, my emotions just welled up,
and I got a lump in my throat.
I felt as if I had wings;
I felt the “great cloud of witnesses.”
I prayed to Jehovah
for calmness, courage, and wisdom
and that he help me
not to bring reproach on his holy name.
Almost immediately, “the peace of God”
came over me, and I was calm.
The unpleasant sensations did not go away,
but I was no longer afraid.
While overcoming our fear, my wife and I
tried to go out in service every day.
When you don’t concentrate on yourself
but focus on helping others, fear disappears.
Something that helped me
to cope with my fears
is hope,
looking at the situation
through Jehovah’s eyes,
seeing what will happen next,
that this is not the end of the situation,
but only a difficult phase
through which you can pass.
I was helped to cope
with my fear by the words of the song:
“Take one day at a time;
“leave tomorrow until tomorrow;
peace is what I find.”
I understood that it was important
to solve problems as they came up
and not to be troubled
by what might never happen.
Fear is interesting;
that is, in principle, fear can be
inside a person, and if someone
is afraid, that is not shameful.
But the question is,
Can you overcome this fear?
Can you get the fear under your control?
Can you overcome this surge of negativity?
And when my heart persuaded me to get scared,
then I started to pray.
I prayed to Jehovah to give me courage
and not be afraid of anyone or anything.
I still say to myself,
‘Feliks, do not fear anybody
or anything except Jehovah!’
Dear brothers and sisters,
I really appreciate your support.
I’m very happy for all your letters,
for all your thoughts, for all your prayers.
I really appreciate it a lot.
I try to do my best,
and I try to serve Jehovah
in the best way that I can.
I will do that forever!
Brothers and sisters,
we know that persecution
is coming to us too.
May we trust in Jehovah
and overcome any fear
that we have of our opposers.
May we be confident
that any lions on our path are chained.
Look at the chains, not the lions.
And may we be ever guided
by our wholesome fear of Jehovah God.
Are you determined to fear nothing
except our wonderful God, Jehovah?
Then I ask you,
What do we have to fear?
Thank you for answering
this question about fear so eloquently.
Now we are looking forward to the discussion
by Brother Jackson on the interesting theme
“Are You Completely Sober?”
I guess so, looking at the time.
Are you completely sober?
I know what you’re thinking: ‘Really?
‘Seriously?
‘The answer is obvious, isn’t it?
‘We’ve been in this Assembly Hall for hours,
and there’s no opportunity to drink.’
So the answer to the question
seems rather obvious, doesn’t it?
But before you dismiss
this question completely,
could there be
some other meaning to this question,
a spiritual meaning?
The answer, of course, is yes.
Because when we look at the Greek text
upon which the Christian Greek Scriptures
were translated from,
we notice that literally
the term “to be sober”
occurs a number of times.
And yet, the Christian Greek Scriptures
of the New World Translation
do not actually use the words “to be sober.”
Let’s take an example.
Please turn with me, if you will,
to 1 Peter 1:13.
Now, if you have a device,
you can also quickly look
at the Kingdom Interlinear
if you wish to verify this.
But 1 Peter 1:13
(and just the beginning of this verse),
it says:
“So brace up your minds for activity;
keep your senses completely.”
The Greek expression here could be translated
as “being sober perfectly.”
But notice that we have
the expression translated
as “keep your senses completely.”
So that raises the interesting question,
Why didn’t
the New World Bible Translation Committee
say “to be sober”
or “to be completely sober”?
Well, the answer to that question
goes back to your initial reaction
when you heard the title of this talk.
Let’s be honest, when you heard
“Are You Completely Sober?”
what did you think of immediately?
Drinking alcohol or avoiding it.
But the majority of times
that this expression
occurs in the Christian Greek Scriptures,
it does not specifically refer
to avoiding alcohol
or becoming intoxicated with alcohol.
Rather, it has a larger figurative meaning.
So for us to follow
the admonition “to be sober,”
we need to know, really,
what the Bible means by that expression.
What is included in that?
So, what we’re going to briefly do
is look at four different ways
that the New World Translation
has covered this expression.
And by looking
at the different ways in English
that this has been translated,
we’ll see what really is involved
with this expression “to be sober.”
So let’s start.
If you turn with me, please,
to 1 Timothy chapter 3—
And immediately we remember
that 1 Timothy chapter 3
is talking about the qualifications
for overseers, and also it mentions
what sisters should do.
Now, in verse 2 and verse 11
(we won’t read it but glancing at it),
in Greek,
the word “to be sober” literally is there,
and you can see it
in the Kingdom Interlinear.
But how is it translated?
We don’t see the word “sober,” do we?
The expression there is
to be “moderate in habits.”
Now, why did the brothers
translate it this way?
Because although it could refer
to avoiding being intoxicated,
it has this wider meaning
of having good sense
when it comes to things
like conduct and speech
or the choice of entertainment or recreation.
It means not going to foolish extremes
or being erratic in our thinking
or unbalanced in our opinions.
So all of that is involved
in this figurative meaning
of the expression
to be “moderate in habits.”
Let’s take an example
by looking at another verse
in the Bible as to what is involved
in not being extreme.
Let’s turn to 1 Corinthians this time
—1 Corinthians 7:31.
Now, this doesn’t use
the term in Greek “to be sober,”
but it gives us further information
as to what’s involved
with being moderate in habits.
So verse 31 says:
“Those making use of the world
as those not using it to the full.”
Now, what does that mean?
Well, maybe we could use
this illustration to highlight it.
Imagine a hungry person
who wants to pick fruit from a tree.
Now, a person who’s not unbalanced
and doesn’t go to extremes perhaps would be
happy just to get enough fruit
to satisfy his hunger
or maybe to get a few extra pieces of fruit
so that he could take some home.
But a person who was to ‘use it to the full’
is that type of person
who after they’ve collected everything
they can get (more than they could ever use),
they see the one piece
of fruit right up at the top
and they have to have it,
even if it involves a certain risk.
So when the apostle Paul
said under inspiration
that we
‘shouldn’t use the world to the full,’
symbolically,
we could say, it’s just like this
—not trying to get
everything  out of this world.
Now, what sort of symbolic fruit
might we be tempted with?
Well, there are so many opportunities today
for education, recreation, entertainment,
travel, vacations, employment, and business.
Are we truly sober
when it comes to those things,
or are we like the person
who is trying to grab every opportunity
and use the world to the full?
Well, let’s look at a second example
of this Greek word being used
—1 Peter 4:7.
First Peter 4:7 says:
“But the end of all things
has drawn close.
“Therefore, be sound in mind,
and be vigilant.”
Now, notice the footnote says,
“Or ‘alert; awake.’”
But if you look at the Kingdom Interlinear,
it says: “Be you sober.”
So in this case,
the brothers translated
the literal term in Greek, “sober,”
to be “vigilant,” or “alert” and “awake.”
With regard to what?
With regard to our prayers.
It’s interesting that the apostle Peter
was inspired to say these words.
No doubt he remembered the time
when he wasn’t
‘vigilant with regard to prayers,’
when Jesus said “keep praying” constantly
in the garden of Gethsemane.
And, of course,
Peter would have remembered what resulted
because of that lack
of being sober in a spiritual sense.
So, what about us?
Are we vigilant with regard to prayers?
Do we pray to Jehovah constantly,
whenever we have an opportunity
right through the day?
Or do we only just pray
when we wake up in the morning,
when we eat,
and before we go to bed at night?
Well, for us
to ‘be vigilant with regard to prayers,’
if we constantly have Jehovah in our minds,
then we can truly say that we are,
in a symbolic sense, sober.
Now, a third example
—1 Corinthians chapter 15.
Of course,
all of us remember very clearly
the words in verse 33 about bad associations,
but this verse is verse 34
in the same context.
And how does it start?
It says: “Come to your senses
in a righteous way.”
Again, if we look at the literal rendering
of the Greek, it says:
“Sober you up.”
Now, what is this talking about?
Well, the study note of our Bible
(and of course, you can only get this
in the electronic form at the moment),
it says: “Come to your senses:
“Paul here uses a Greek word
“that literally means ‘to sober up.’
“Because some of the Corinthian Christians
“gave ear to apostate teachings,
“such as the denial of the resurrection,
“they were in a spiritual stupor of sorts,
“confused and disoriented as if drunk.
“Paul thus urges them to wake up,
“to shake off their confusion
“by getting a clear understanding
of the teaching of the resurrection.
“They needed to do so before their stupor
led them to spiritual sickness
and even death.”
So do we see why the brothers
translated it this way?
“Come to your senses” is not just talking
about drinking wine or beer,
but it’s talking
about avoiding bad associates
and those who give wrong ideas.
So could it be that we may be affected
by the opinions of some,
maybe even within the congregation,
who say,
“Is the end really so close?”
or “Is what the world offers
really that bad?”
Or if we were to be tempted to believe
every account or report on the Internet
with regard to those taking
the lead in the organization,
do we just quickly believe those things?
Or worse still, do we search the Internet
looking for juicy stories
about other Jehovah’s Witnesses?
We need to remember
that Satan is “the father of the lie.”
He’s an expert at lying,
and he makes sure there are
plenty of lies for us to come across.
But if we are sober spiritually,
this means we won’t get fooled
or tricked by false stories.
Now, the fourth and final example
we want to share with you
is in 1 Thessalonians
—1 Thessalonians 5:6.
And here again in the Greek text,
we see the word “sober,”
if it’s literally translated into English.
Verse 6 says: “So, then,
“let us not sleep on as the rest do,
“but let us stay awake
“and [notice, this is the expression]
keep our senses.”
So, what is the context of this verse?
It’s talking
about ‘Jehovah’s day coming as a thief.’
It’s talking about those saying
“Peace and security!”
So in this sense,
to “be sober” means
we know the time we’re living in.
We’re not only spiritually awake,
but we’re alert.
Think of this illustration:
There could be a guard,
and that guard is totally awake,
but he’s watching
the tournament on the television
—maybe it’s football,
something he’s excited about.
He’s not alert to the dangers
that are lurking.
So in a similar way,
we need to be totally awake spiritually
and alert to what is happening
and to the dangers that present themselves,
such as getting involved
with the political issues
that we see in the world today.
To do so would make us part of the world.
Yes, we have to focus on God’s Kingdom
as the only true solution.
That’s what it means to be sober.
So we’ve seen
those four aspects of this literal word
when it’s translated
into English as “being sober.”
But why is that so important?
Brothers and sisters,
as it’s been already presented
on this program,
we know challenging times
are in front of us.
Yes, we need to be completely sober
when we face those challenges.
This year is a special year;
it marks 100 years
since the appointment
of “the faithful and discreet slave.”
That slave, when we look back
over the 100 years,
has remained awake, spiritually speaking,
and alert and has kept on reminding us
of the need to do that.
Now, it’s true.
Some might say: “Well, yes.
“But at times,
we look back over 100 years,
“and there were times they got
excited about a certain year or time,
and the end didn’t come at that time.”
But just imagine if you had a watchdog
and that dog barks
in the middle of the night
and you get up and there’s nothing there,
do you shoot the dog?
It only proves that the dog
is doing what you want it to do.
So in a similar way,
realize the faithful slave,
yes, in their enthusiasm,
sometimes we have said things
that maybe disappointed others.
But remember,
the role of “the faithful and discreet slave”
is to feed us and to keep us
awake spiritually and keep us alert.
And thinking about it,
when that day comes
when Jesus brings destruction
on this wicked system of things,
where do you want to be?
on a beach drinking a martini?
climbing a symbolic tree
to get the last bit of fruit from this world?
Or do you want to be
busy in Jehovah’s service,
whether it’s building and preaching
and all the things we need to do?
We know the answer.
Yes, but to do that,
we have to remain sober spiritually.
And one final point,
if we look in the Insight  volume
under the heading “Soberness,”
there’s a very interesting point,
because Peter and Paul
used this expression in Greek.
And the Insight  volume
makes this very interesting comment.
It says: “In keeping his senses,
“Timothy was to realize that Paul
would not be on the scene much longer.”
Then it says about Peter:
‘Peter likewise knew
that he and his fellow apostles
would not be on hand much longer.’
Then it goes on to say:
“Knowing the seriousness of the times,
“with growing persecution from the world,
“they should be
sound in mind, watchful, vigilant,
“and should not neglect serious prayer,
to obtain the strength
they would need for endurance.”
Yes, the faithful slave has been serving us
with spiritual food for 100 years.
But, friends, remember,
the faithful slave will not always be here.
Soon will come the time
when the remaining ones of the anointed
will be taken to have their reward.
Of course,
Jehovah will continue to care for us.
He always has a provision
in place to care for us.
But what is the important thing?
What is it that the faithful slave
wants to convey to us?
Just the same as Paul and Peter
wanted to convey
to those to whom they wrote,
we want to convey to you
the importance of each one of us
being moderate in habits,
vigilant with regard to prayers,
keeping our senses,
not being distracted by false stories,
and being alert to the time
in which we’re living.
So we leave you with that question,
Are you sober?
Are you completely  sober?
Well, we certainly appreciate
this sobering talk.
You will now be interested
to hear what Brother Kenneth Cook
has to say on the topic
“Will You Care for It?”
Brother Cook, please.
We care for the things
that are important to us, don’t we?
And there are many of such things.
For example,
we care for our families,
we care for our friends,
we care for our ministry,
and above all,
we care for our worship of Jehovah.
And we do this faithfully to the very end.
When others need us,
we’re there for them, as we’ve seen today.
During times
of natural disasters, civil unrest,
and severe opposition to our work,
we are there for one another.
In addition to all of that,
our love must also, though,
be great enough to care for those
whom we try to reach in our public ministry.
In this, Jesus set the example for us.
We can feel
his caring attitude in what he said
at Matthew 9:36-38.
So please follow along at Matthew 9:36.
It says:
“On seeing the crowds,
“he felt pity for them,
“because they were
skinned and thrown about
“like sheep without a shepherd.
“Then he said to his disciples:
“‘Yes, the harvest is great,
but the workers are few.
“‘Therefore, beg the Master of the harvest
to send out workers into his harvest.’”
Jesus felt pity for the people, didn’t he?
What does pity mean in this case?
The pity mentioned here
stems from heartfelt love.
He loved the people.
We love people.
It’s a tender feeling toward persons
in a state of need or suffering.
Like Jesus, our love for others
must include genuine care for them
—even pity for them—
so that we’re moved to help them,
hoping that they respond to God’s Word
and will desire to do Jehovah’s will.
And we must do this
because caring for others
is an important part
of following the Christ, right?
In a few minutes,
we will look at how we can remain focused
on compassionately carrying out our ministry
and helping people
to dedicate their lives to God.
And this will include revealing
what our yeartext is for 2020.
So as Brother Lett said earlier,
“Stay tuned.”
Before we get to that, though,
we’ll draw out
some Bible principles from long ago
that will help us today
in caring for the people
that we must yet reach
in this important ministry, or work.
Since ancient times,
Jehovah has taught his people
how to care for others.
In fact, the Israelites
were told to show consideration
even for the animals under their care.
For instance,
when they were about to leave Egypt,
Jehovah gave them this command
at Exodus 12:5, 6.
Please follow along.
Now, here is the setting:
Jehovah gives instructions
about selecting the Passover sacrifice.
Verse 3 tells us that the Israelites
were to select the sheep
on the tenth of the month.
With this in mind,
notice what verse 5 states:
“Your sheep should be
a sound, one-year-old male.
“You may choose
from the young rams or from the goats.
“You must care for it
“until the 14th day of this month,
“and the whole congregation
of the assembly of Israel
must slaughter it at twilight.”
Why was it important for them
to not only select the sheep
but to “care for it until the 14th”?
To answer that question,
let’s draw out two principles
that we will then apply to our ministry
—and they do apply.
First, we know that the sacrificial sheep
needed to remain unblemished
to be acceptable to Jehovah.
Verse 5 said: “Your sheep should be
a sound, one-year-old male.”
If an Israelite selected a sound sheep
but then neglected it
and the sheep was injured in some way,
that sheep would no longer be
acceptable to Jehovah for sacrifice.
The principle:
Keep the sacrifice acceptable.
Don’t neglect it
just because the end is close,
and we can apply
that principle to our ministry.
Now, principle number two:
We can also be certain
that a measure of compassion
was involved in what Jehovah told them there.
In this case,
the sacrificial sheep was no less important
just because its time,
so to speak, was short.
See, as we’ll see in this discussion,
this too can apply to our ministry.
And we’re wise to remember these principles.
Fittingly, it is Jehovah
who sets the example for us
in showing compassion
and caring for what is important
to the very end.
Foremost in this
is how Jehovah cared for Jesus
right up to the end of his earthly ministry.
For instance,
Jehovah showed his support for Jesus
by answering Jesus’ prayers.
At one point, Jesus even said:
“Father, I thank you that you have heard me.”
Also, Jehovah voiced his support for Jesus.
At his baptism,
Jesus heard Jehovah speak from heaven,
stating:
“This is my Son, the beloved,
whom I have approved.”
Imagine how that encouraged him!
And then later, as Jesus was in agony
during the hours before his death,
an angel of God comforted Jesus,
and no doubt that angel
was a friend whom Jesus knew well.
Yes, from the beginning to the very end,
Jehovah cared for Jesus,
the sacrificial “Lamb of God.”
We benefit when we apply such principles
to what we have been given to do today.
For instance, the time is short, yes.
Yet, our public ministry
is no less important now
just because the end is close.
In fact, it’s even more important
that we continue caring for this ministry
as the end approaches.
We must care for this “sacrifice of praise”
to our heavenly Father right up to the end
—that is, right up to the time
when Jehovah makes it clear
that this part of our service to him
has come to an end.
Until that time,
what should be the focus
of our public ministry?
Jesus stated what it should be
at Matthew 28:18-20,
so please go to those verses.
Now, starting at Matthew 28:18,
it says:
“Jesus approached
and spoke to them, saying:
“‘All authority has been given me
in heaven and on the earth.
“‘Go, therefore, and make disciples
of people of all the nations,
“‘baptizing them in the name of the Father
“‘and of the Son and of the holy spirit,
“‘teaching them to observe
all the things I have commanded you.
“‘And look!
I am with you all the days
until the conclusion
of the system of things.’”
So now,
with these words of Jesus in mind,
what should be
the focus of our public ministry?
Well, the focus must be
to ‘make disciples of Christ
‘among people of all the nations,
teaching them and baptizing them,’
as Jesus stated.
Notice that Jesus’ statement
was more than just a command.
He didn’t start off saying:
“I command you! Go!”—right?
Rather, Jesus said:
“All authority has been given me . . .
Go, therefore.”
Jesus’ true disciples
would see beyond the command
embedded in those words
and go forth with conviction.
Why?
Because they would know
that Jesus was empowered, authorized,
to oversee this great work
that they were now commissioned to do.
He would be with them,
and he is with us today.
We’re absolutely confident of that fact.
In view of that,
how can we help our Bible students
so that even more of them
become baptized disciples,
as Jesus there directed?
This is important to consider because,
while many get baptized each year,
our yearly baptism figures have remained
at about the same level for some time.
Now, are these good figures?
Yes, they are.
Absolutely!
But what can we do
to help even more people
take this vital step
before the end comes?
To answer that question,
let’s briefly consider
four ways to reach the heart.
There’s much that we can do,
but we’ll just consider four ways here.
We do it through what we
emphasize about Jehovah,
what we teach our students about prayer,
how we help them get to meetings,
and how we help them handle problems.
Let’s consider that first way:
We reach the heart
through what we emphasize about Jehovah.
Our goal is to help our students see
that Jehovah cares for them.
He cares about them.
He loves them deeply.
As we use our publications
(such as the Teach Us  book)
with our students,
we should prepare well
and highlight the Scriptural answers
to questions such as:
Does God care about us?
How does God feel when people suffer?
Is it possible to be Jehovah’s friend?
Discuss the answers,
draw out the meaning that brings us joy
and identify the principles
that improve our life,
and help the student
to grow ever closer to Jehovah.
Now the second way:
We reach the heart through what we
teach our students about prayer.
Show him or her how to pray properly,
with meaning and from the heart,
as we pray with them at each study session.
Explain that in our private prayers
we can really open up to Jehovah
and express feelings that we
might not share with other humans.
We can also ask for God’s help
to love only what he loves.
Why can we do this with confidence?
Because Jehovah cares for us,
and we should make that very clear
as we teach our Bible students.
Next, the third way:
We reach the heart through how we
help our students get to meetings.
Invite your Bible student
to attend meetings as soon as possible.
What a student sees at our meetings
may touch his heart
and help him to progress.
Very early on, show the video
What Happens at a Kingdom Hall?
Then warmly invite him to attend with you;
appeal to him.
Also, offer transportation if it is needed.
I really appreciated getting a ride
to the first meeting that I attended,
and I still remember it.
Finally, the fourth way:
We reach the heart through how we
help our students handle problems,
including problems that may develop
if someone offends him or her.
This is all part of reaching the heart
and preparing and helping them.
Our Bible students
need to experience Jehovah’s love
as they benefit
from applying Bible principles.
See, this helps them
to know Jehovah better.
To help them,
show your students how to use tools
such as the JW Library® app,
the Research Guide for Jehovah’s Witnesses,
and jw.org®.
When our students are trained
to search for answers before baptism,
they will be better prepared
to handle problems
and get along with others.
When we do these things
for our Bible students,
we show that we are really caring
for what Jehovah has entrusted to us.
Both Jehovah and his Son desire
that we help as many people
to the point of dedication and baptism
while there’s still time.
To succeed,
don’t spend time
conducting an unproductive study.
Rather, focus on “those who [are]
rightly disposed for everlasting life,”
and care for them
with Jehovah’s blessing on your efforts.
So, then, with all of this in mind,
what is our yeartext for 2020?
It is taken from Matthew 28:19:
“Go, therefore, and make disciples . . . ,
baptizing them.”
Now, for those of you who listened
to Alexa earlier in the program
or read your daily text for today,
you know that this is also
the Scripture text for today,
October 5, 2019.
That’s just a coincidence.
Don’t expect it next year.
Now, with that text in mind,
keep putting your heart into your ministry
and into helping people,
and be certain to take care of this ministry
with those principles we considered
to the very end.
Thank you very much,
Brother Cook, for your presentation.
Looking back on the program
that we were able to enjoy,
we certainly felt encouraged
by being reminded
that we have no human leader
but that it is Jesus who is our Leader.
Remember what it says at Matthew 23:10:
“Neither be called leaders,
for your Leader is one, the Christ.”
We enjoyed also listening
to Brother Stephen Lett,
who emphasized that our relief ministry
is overseen and directed by Jehovah.
I’m sure that you also
enjoyed the four videos.
The first one was entitled
‘The Good Hand of Our God Is Upon Us . . .
Let Us Get Up and Build.’
The next video provided a historical look
at property acquisitions,
followed by another video related
to the new construction project
that is being planned.
The fourth video was
about the new application
for processing applications,
followed by a presentation
on a new way to access
jw.org® audio files.
After that, we enjoyed
the Scriptural discussion,
“An Attack Coming From the North,”
presented by Brother David Splane
of the Governing Body.
And Brother Samuel Herd next encouraged us
to study the Bible with a Study Bible.
And how we appreciate the Study Bible!
After singing a song together
and listening to greetings
from brothers in other places and countries,
Brother Anthony Morris reminded us
that we have work to do.
As indicated in the news media,
there are increasing problems in the world.
In certain areas, we can also see
increasing hostility against God’s people.
Brother Mark Sanderson of the Governing Body
showed that we do not have to be fearful
because the Almighty is on our side.
Next, we heard the talk
by Brother Geoffrey Jackson,
“Are You Completely Sober?”
We are if we keep our senses.
And finally, Brother Kenneth Cook
of the Governing Body raised the question
“Will You Care for It?”
Brother Cook reviewed
how Jehovah cared for Jesus,
the sacrificial Lamb of God,
until the very end of his life on earth.
Likewise, in harmony
with the 2020 yeartext
that’s taken from Matthew 28:19,
he highlighted how
we must care for our ministry
and our “sacrifice of praise”
until the very end.
This includes our efforts to help
‘those who are rightly disposed’
to dedicate their life to Jehovah
and to get baptized.
Well, we have had
an encouraging time together, haven’t we?
Well, we enjoyed the various videos
and also the video presentations,
and we all benefited
from the Scriptural talks
delivered by members of the Governing Body.
And then we also appreciate the discussion
on the yeartext for the coming year:
“Go, therefore, and make disciples . . . ,
baptizing them.”