A newspaper in Japan
once quoted a Catholic priest.
He said, ‘The God of the Old Testament,
‘Yahweh,
‘is a God of anger,
and I can’t feel close to him.’
And then he added,
‘But he developed and transformed
‘into what is the God of the New Testament,
that is, the God of love whom Jesus taught.’
Have you ever heard that?
A lot of people still think like this,
as if God has a split personality.
They are uncomfortable
when they read in the Bible
that God gets angry sometimes.
Why is that?
Well, it may be for one of two reasons.
First, there are outspoken critics
in this world
who constantly try to discredit Jehovah.
A prominent biologist, for example,
made headlines a few years ago.
He said in his book:
“The God of the Old Testament
is arguably the most unpleasant character
in all fiction.”
I stopped the quote there
because it gets much worse.
How blasphemous a viewpoint that is!
The more often people hear
statements like this,
the more they tend to believe them.
There’s a second reason, though,
why some struggle with God’s anger.
They have suffered in abusive relationships,
and now they’re sensitive
to any perceived abuse.
Take Carolyn for example, she said:
“When my drunken father
used to explode in anger,
“his appearance changed.
He became like a wolf
baring its teeth before attacking.”
She said, “I lived this nightmare every day.”
Well, abuse like this can scar people
for a long time.
So how can we help sincere persons
get past their fears about God’s anger
and draw closer to Jehovah?
Well, let’s address the critics first
and then see how we can reassure those
who may be feeling insecure.
First, let’s make one thing clear:
Jehovah does not have multiple personalities.
When Jesus was on earth, he advocated
the powerful truth that Jehovah is one.
When a Jewish scribe asked him
what was the greatest of all commandments,
what did he say?
Let’s read Mark 12:29, 30
and see what his reply was in his own words.
He answered by quoting today’s text
—Mark 12:29, 30.
“Jesus answered: ‘The first is,
“‘“Hear, O Israel, Jehovah our God
is one Jehovah,
“‘“and you must love Jehovah your God
“‘“with your whole heart
and with your whole soul
and with your whole mind
and with your whole strength.”’”
So for Jesus, loving Jehovah for who he is
(not for who we want him to be),
is really the most important decision
any of us could make.
Now, the pagan nations had all sorts of gods
for different purposes.
And they would worship different aspects
of even the same God in different localities,
like the god Baal, for example.
And something similar happened
in other religions.
Say, for example, the Catholic Church
with its different manifestations
of the worship of Mary.
But things were very different in Israel.
They learned that there was
only one God, Jehovah,
who was responsible for everything.
And each time they read Deuteronomy 6:4,
they were reminded
that God had one personality.
So why does a God of love
get angry sometimes?
Well, the answer is quite simple.
When rebels challenged Jehovah’s sovereignty,
he had to defend his name and standards.
Rebellion did make him angry and rightly so,
but Jehovah’s anger is always under control
and guided by right principles.
As a Father, he had to protect his household.
Respect for his own name
and his love for his children
compelled him to act.
At the same time,
Jehovah is “slow to anger
and abundant in loving-kindness.”
His fundamental mood is not anger, but joy.
And Jesus said that “God loved
the world so much
that he gave his only-begotten Son.”
Jehovah has been, is, and always will be
a God of unchangeable love.
First John 4:8 says: “God is love.”
It identifies who he is.
But Jesus also said that God gave his Son
in order that “everyone
exercising faith in him
“might not be destroyed
but have everlasting life.”
Did you notice that Jesus said
those not exercising faith will be destroyed?
So Jehovah’s personality didn’t mellow
over the years,
as if it needed mellowing.
It didn’t transform
from one personality to another.
His severity today against the wicked
is no less
nor his love any greater
than it was in the past.
Jehovah does not change.
We can illustrate it like this, perhaps:
Criminals may know that a police officer
is an arm of the law.
His children may see him
as a loving father that he is.
And his close friends may value him
for his good sense of humor.
Now, the police officer,
the father, and the friend
are all the same person.
In each situation, a different aspect
of his personality stands out.
And it’s the same with Jehovah.
In harmony with his name,
“He Causes to Become”
or becomes whatever he needs to
in every situation
in order to fulfill his purpose,
especially his purpose
toward those who love him.
So if we want to get closer to Jehovah,
we have to accept the full range
of his beautiful, multifaceted,
and unchanging personality.
For those who love God,
we don’t fear his anger.
We learn to trust him
because he’s always kind
and tender toward us.
Why can we say that?
Well, open your Bibles with me
to Jeremiah 29:11,
and notice why we can be sure
that Jehovah always wants the best for us
as he did for his servants in the past.
In his own words:
“‘For I well know the thoughts
that I am thinking toward you,’
“declares Jehovah,
“‘thoughts of peace, and not of calamity,
to give you a future and a hope.’”
Because Jehovah loves us,
because he is always
in full control of himself
and circumstances around him,
and because Jesus
has already died for our sins,
we can always feel safe with Jehovah.
We do not ever need to fear approaching him.
Very soon now, as Zechariah 14:9 predicts,
Jehovah must become “King over all the earth.
“In that day [the prophet said]
“Jehovah will [prove to] be one,
and his name one.”
Everyone in heaven and on earth
will agree at that time
that Jehovah our God
is the Universal Sovereign,
and you and I will gladly join our voices
with that happy chorus.
What a beautiful prospect that is!