The text today is taken
from The Watchtower of 2016, January,
and the theme
“Be Compelled
by God’s ‘Indescribable Free Gift.’”
Well, this Memorial season
really does move us
to contemplate what Jehovah has done for us,
and we should be compelled.
The Insight volume has
a very interesting article
on this matter of forgiveness.
And in one of the statements it mentions
that “the Hebrew verb sa·lachʹ
“[for] (forgive)
is used only with regard
to [Jehovah’s] pardoning a sinner.”
It’s never used in connection
with a human forgiving a human.
So the extent of
and reasons for Jehovah’s forgiveness
really are unmatchable.
So, what should we be compelled to do?
Well, let’s reflect
on the illustration that Jesus gave
in Matthew chapter 18,
and if you turn there
you’ll recall that in verse 21
Peter had asked:
‘Lord, how many times am I to forgive
‘my brother if he sins against me?
Up to seven times?’
Now, what was wrong with that question?
Well, Peter had been influenced
by a hard-hearted spirit
that was prevalent in those days,
and in some instances even today.
Well, what do we mean?
Well, Peter measured forgiveness,
and that was common among the Pharisees.
Jesus went on to say what in verse 22?
We know it very well:
“I say to you,
not up to seven times,
but up to 77 times.”
And then, in connection
with divine forgiveness he
—Jesus—
responds in a way
that helps us to see the contrast
in the human understanding
of forgiveness and God’s.
Notice what he says in verse 23:
“That is why the Kingdom of the heavens
“may be likened
to a king who wanted
to settle accounts with his slaves.”
Now notice,
the king wanted to settle accounts.
It wasn’t the slaves.
The slaves had built up a debt with the king,
and justice called for the king
to handle matters
—balance the books, as it were.
But then, he found one slave
“who owed him 10,000 talents”
—40 million dollars.
That’s a lot of money.
Jehovah
—if we think about that illustration—
is telling us something.
He has given those
that are his slaves
—us—
a lot of leeway.
He has forgiven us
thousands of times,
so often that we are not aware,
really, of the many sins
we commit against Jehovah.
Now, going back to the illustration,
verse 26.
This slave begs
because he can’t afford to pay,
and he says to the master:
‘Be patient with me,
and I’ll pay everything I owe you.’
Well, how in the world could he do that?
He was a slave.
How could he pay back 40 million dollars?
And the master knew that there
was no way he could pay this back.
Well now, putting the illustration
in today’s terms,
the average yearly wage
for the United States
—I googled this—
in 2014
was almost 52,000 dollars.
That’s just averaging out everybody.
There’s a lot of people
who don’t make that much,
and many who make more than that,
but the average was 52,000 dollars.
Now, if the 10,000 talents
equaled 40 million dollars,
it would take a man 770 years
to pay off that debt
if he gave everything that he made
to pay off the debt.
So the master knew,
‘This slave, he can’t—
he can’t pay me.’
So verse 27 says:
“Moved with pity at this,
the master of that slave
let him off and canceled his debt.”
Oh, boy, what a relief that would be.
But the slave
should have recognized something.
He could never be
in the same position as the master.
He didn’t have the resources.
Nor could anyone possibly owe him
what he owed the master.
Now, if he had captured the spirit
of forgiveness shown to him,
there would hardly be any debt owed to him
that he couldn’t tolerate or even forget.
But in verse 28, look at his attitude:
“That slave went out
and found one of his fellow slaves,
[on the same plane as him]
who owed him 100 denarii [70 dollars].”
Now notice,
he “went out and found” that slave.
So rather than looking to overlook
the debts of those who were indebted to him,
he was looking for those who owed him.
Now, we’re going to read
verses 29, 30, 32, 33, and 35.
Notice:
“So his fellow slave fell down
“and began to beg him, saying,
“‘Be patient with me,
and I will pay you back.’
However, he was not willing.”
Now, let’s stop there.
Is it possible that this slave
that owed him could pay him back?
Yes, it was possible he could work it out
within his resources
—70 dollars.
But then, what was the reaction?
The account says:
“He went and had him thrown into prison
until he could pay back what he owed.”
Boy, how petty.
Verse 32: “Then [the] master
summoned him and said to him:
“‘Wicked slave, I canceled
all that debt for you
“‘when you pleaded with me
“‘[that debt that you
could never have paid off].
“‘Should you not also have shown mercy
to your fellow slave
“‘[that slave who possibly
could have paid it off the same]
as I showed mercy to you?’”
And then the clincher,
verse 35, Jesus’ point:
“My heavenly Father will also deal with you
“[that’s me, and that’s you]
“in the same way
if each of you
does not forgive your brother.”
Not by rote,
not by formula,
but ‘from our heart.’
Now the king, as we said,
forgave the debt of 40 million dollars.
That slave was unwilling
to forgive his fellow slave
for the amount of 70 dollars.
Jehovah is a big Forgiver,
and we thank him for that.
Last evening helped us to see how big.
Really, grasping the depth
of our indebtedness to Jehovah
and the depth of his forgiveness
should compel us to constantly work
at having a forgiving spirit.
The Insight volume says that in the Bible
“the Hebrew word na·saʼʹ
“may denote the pardon, or forgiveness,
extended by God or by humans.”
But as we stated originally,
“sa·lachʹ
“is used exclusively
[for] God’s forgiveness,
the act by which [a] sinner
is restored to divine favor.”
Now remember, our forgiveness
can’t begin to match Jehovah’s.
So there’s nothing that any human
can do to us that matches what we
—born in sin, alienated from God,
inclined to do wrong—
have done to offend Jehovah.
And yet
—as we discussed yesterday,
last evening, and we’re reminded of—
God recommends his own love to us,
and that “while we were yet sinners”
he had his Son die for us.
I’d like to quote to you
The Watchtower of October 15, 1999,
page 13
—October 15, 1999.
The article is “Forgive From Your Heart.”
It says this:
“You should see in God’s willingness
to forgive a pattern
“as to how you ought to treat other humans.
“Paul focused on this, writing:
“‘Become kind to one another,
tenderly compassionate, freely forgiving.’”
Not like an accountant keeping track,
but “freely forgiving one another
just as God also by Christ
freely forgave you.”
Then The Watchtower says this:
“Do you see the link?
“Jehovah God forgave you, [that’s me]
“so
—Paul forcefully reasons—
“you need to imitate [God] Him
and be ‘tenderly compassionate,
freely forgiving’ of others.”
And then The Watchtower asked
some penetrating questions.
It said: “Ask yourself,
‘Am I [really] doing that?
“‘If it is not [in] my nature,
am I working in that direction,
really striving to imitate God
in being forgiving?’”
Now, we might say:
‘Well, I’m forgiving.
I forgive a lot of people.’
Proof?
Proverbs 17:9:
“Whoever forgives a transgression seeks love,
but the one who keeps harping
on a matter separates close friends.”
If we keep talking about
what somebody has done to us,
we haven’t forgiven in the heart.
Jehovah doesn’t do that.
So forgiving others for personal offenses,
regardless of the number of times involved,
is a Christian requirement.
God’s forgiveness is not extended
toward those who refuse to forgive.
Remember what Jesus said:
“Forgive us our debts,
as we also have forgiven our debtors.”
And what a beautiful God we have.
His action and that of his Son compels us
to be freely forgiving.