The matter of dress and grooming
is a deeply personal matter.
It’s something that elicits
all sorts of emotions.
But let me just ask at this point,
What are you thinking about?
Maybe you’re thinking,
‘Why does he have this hat on his head?’
Some are thinking,
‘This must be a very defining moment
in Brother Jackson’s lifetime.’
Others are thinking:
‘Is this a new precedent?
We’ve never done that before.’
Well, let me take it off.
That was an object lesson
to point out how distracting
our dress and grooming can be.
Yes, it can distract
from the message that we bear.
Instead of thinking about what someone
is conveying in the message,
if our dress and grooming
is just out of the ordinary
or something that is shocking,
then it certainly can take away
from the glory to Jehovah
and also the message that we bear.
But when we go around the world,
we see a large variety of dress and grooming
used by our brothers and sisters.
Without showing you photos,
you might remember
many of the Watchtower photographs
where our brothers are witnessing.
Some don’t have a tie;
others don’t have a jacket.
In Fiji, of course,
men wear what might be referred to
as a kilt, or a sulu.
So there’s a large variety of dresses
and costumes and outfits that are acceptable.
And we probably noticed, too,
some of the Governing Body members,
when they’ve released Bibles
or have been at conventions,
they have donned some of the local attire.
So it’s not as if Jehovah’s organization
is so strict and inflexible
that we all have to dress
exactly the same way.
It’s true, there are various circumstances
that God’s people face.
In some countries,
there’s such a variety of items
that we can use for dress and grooming.
In other countries,
there really aren’t as many things
that our brothers can use.
I know my wife and I were very touched
a number of years ago
when we attended a regional convention.
As I was waiting to give the last talk,
sitting behind the platform,
I noticed the brothers and sisters
who were in the Watchtower Study
were giving comments.
And it really touched my heart
when I saw sisters come off of the platform
and then give their shoes and their jewelry
to other sisters who were
about to go on the same platform.
You see, they didn’t have much;
they shared what they had.
They didn’t have a lot of choice.
But sometimes we know
that some of you dear sisters, particularly,
may go into a department store
and it may look like you have a huge variety
of things that you can choose from.
But when you start looking,
sometimes you may feel
like those sisters
at that particular convention
—that there really isn’t a lot
that you can use as a Christian.
So, what can help us?
Well, the encouraging thing is
that wherever you go in the world
where the brothers have ties or jackets
or whatever they have,
there’s one thing in common:
Jehovah’s people try to be neat,
clean, and presentable.
And from the Governing Body’s viewpoint,
of course, you know
we’re not trying to make all sorts of rules
—rigid rules—
with regard to this.
So, what can help us to help our brothers
and sisters to have the right viewpoint
—the viewpoint that brings glory to Jehovah?
Well, I thought
we might think of five Scriptural principles.
Now, there are many other
Scriptural principles we could look at,
but these are five principles
that perhaps could help us.
So, first of all, let’s take our Bibles
and turn to 1 Timothy 2:9,
and we are going to have this on the screen
with the highlighted portions.
“Likewise, the women
should adorn themselves
“in appropriate [and then notice
the footnote says “respectable”] dress,
“with modesty and soundness of mind
“[and again look at the footnote,
“good judgment; sensibleness”],
“not with styles of hair braiding and gold
or pearls or very expensive clothing.”
So, what principle do we get here,
no matter where we live in the world?
Well, certainly,
we wouldn’t want any clothing
that’s showy or bizarre
or provocative or that’s revealing
or too extreme with regard to fads.
Again, the principle of the hat
—if we’re doing something
or wearing something that,
really, is so different
from what is expected, what happens?
Well, perhaps at the very least,
it distracts from the message,
but it could be
a lot worse than that, couldn’t it?
It could give the wrong impression
with regard to our morals and so forth.
Now, a second scripture we can look at
is at 2 Corinthians 6:3.
“In no way are we giving
any cause for stumbling,
so that no fault
may be found with our ministry.”
Notice the comment here,
“no way” or “any cause.”
So whatever selections we make
with regard to dress and grooming,
we certainly would want to make sure
that in no way at all
could this cause some stumbling
on the part of those
not only outside the congregation
when we’re presenting the message
but also within the congregation.
If we were to wear something
that could be provocative,
perhaps it would arouse
in some wrong desires.
So having that in mind
gives us a good principle
with regard to selection
of dress and grooming.
Now, a third principle
is found in the book of Numbers 15:39.
And we might say
that this is in the context
of the Israelite nation
when Jehovah did give them
some strict laws
with regard to dress and grooming
—laws that made sure the Israelites
would be different
from the nations around them.
So let’s read Numbers 15:39:
“You must have this fringed edge
so that you will see it
and remember all the commandments
of Jehovah and observe them.”
And notice this point:
“You must not follow
your own hearts and eyes,
which are leading you
to spiritual prostitution.”
Now, that’s a very interesting principle,
isn’t it?
We’re not for one minute suggesting
that we have to have these fringed edges
on our garments today.
But what’s the thought?
Jehovah was telling them
that when you’re selecting what you wear,
don’t just follow your hearts and eyes.
In other words, we shouldn’t feel:
‘Well, I really like this.
This is just nice.
‘It suits me.
It reflects the colors of my skin,’
or whatever other feelings we may have.
But, rather, there are a lot more factors
to take into consideration.
No doubt,
there were some back in Israelite times
that didn’t like a fringe
on the edge of their garments,
but having in mind what Jehovah wanted
helped them to see what they needed to do.
So the principle
is a good principle for us today
—to ask such questions as:
Will this raise eyebrows?
Will it lower the standards that I have?
Does it fit?
Is it the appropriate dress for my age?
Those are important questions
that all of us need to think about.
Well, a fourth principle is found
at 1 Corinthians 10:23, 24.
And again, it’s one of the principles
perhaps we would have thought
of when we were thinking about this subject.
“All things are lawful,
“but not all things are advantageous.
“but not all things build up.
“Let each one keep seeking,
not his own advantage,
but that of the other person.”
So again, what type of questions
would we need to ask?
Well, perhaps this selection we’ve made
is not so bad
that we’re going to have
someone come and talk to us about it.
But is it upbuilding?
Does it represent Jehovah in a fine manner
(and we could say)
not only at times of worship,
when we are in the Kingdom Hall
or when we’re witnessing,
but also when we’re relaxing?
Would someone be shocked to find out
that we’re one of Jehovah’s Witnesses
when we’re on vacation
because of the way we’re dressed?
Well, those are interesting questions,
aren’t they?
And the final scripture
that perhaps gives us a little direction
is at Philippians 3:17.
Here Paul says:
“Unitedly become imitators of me, brothers,
“and keep your eye on those
who are walking in a way that is
in harmony
with the example we set for you.”
Now, what’s the thought
behind that principle?
Well, if we have questions in our mind
with regard to dress and grooming,
it’s good for us to look at those
who are mature in the congregation.
Yes, what do they wear?
What standards have been set
within the congregation as a whole?
And that will give us some idea
as to what type of clothing we should wear.
So, brothers and sisters,
particularly the Bethel family,
we commend you
for the dress and grooming that you display.
We know that it does bring honor to Jehovah.
But let’s always keep in mind
these basic principles.
Yes, without making
a whole lot of rigid laws,
let’s always do things to Jehovah’s glory.