Welcome to this month’s edition
of JW Broadcasting.
Here are just a few highlights
that we have in store for you.
Do you feel that you’ve missed
past opportunities
to do more for Jehovah?
Or do you feel that your age
or present circumstances
keep you from reaching out?
We’ll see how one couple learned
that there may be doors of activity available
to those with a willing spirit.
Have you ever received an assignment
that you felt was overwhelming?
Brother and Sister Halme,
serving in West Africa,
will share what helped them
accept such an assignment
and remain spiritually strong
through difficult times.
And if you’re a regular pioneer,
what role do you have
in strengthening the congregation?
You’ll find this dramatization
very insightful.
Our focus is on our ministry
in this May 2018 edition
of JW Broadcasting!
To set the stage
for the experiences in our program,
I’d like to talk to you
for a few minutes on the theme
“Invigorate Your Ministry—How?”
You dear brothers and sisters are having
a regular share in the preaching work,
and just think of the results.
Each year,
about two billion hours
are spent in the ministry.
Millions of Bible studies are conducted,
and those being baptized
number into the hundreds of thousands.
If you are a Kingdom publisher,
you have had a share
in those thrilling statistics.
But there’s a potential danger.
With so much to do in our life
—not just in the ministry
but also with secular work,
family responsibilities,
for some, even health issues—
we can get into a rut.
It’s not always easy to detect at first,
because in this age of technology
we always feel busy.
But what consumes our day?
Watch this one-minute video,
and try to detect what’s going on
in the life of one brother.
His life is in a rut.
Try to figure out why.
Would you say
that this brother’s life is in a rut?
Oh, he’s active all day
—he always has something to do.
But it’s as if his mind
has been kidnapped by his devices.
Have you ever had
the experience of reading an e-mail
while someone
is trying to tell you something?
It can be embarrassing
when you realize
that they’ve asked you a question,
and they’re waiting for an answer,
but you have no idea what they asked.
It’s embarrassing, right?
But what if the person
who is trying to speak to you is Jehovah?
Even though we aren’t doing anything wrong,
our daily routine
can occupy our attention so much
that we are not able to hear
the refreshing words of Jehovah.
That can happen to any one of us.
Even our spiritual activity
can get into a rut.
One Christian sister described it this way:
“I would go out in service,
“go to meetings, study, pray
“—but I did it all on automatic control,
never feeling anything.”
Have you ever felt that way?
Do you see
all the happy servants of Jehovah
whose experiences
appear on JW Broadcasting,
and you say to yourself:
‘Why can’t I find that joy?
Why is my ministry in a rut?’
Perhaps you feel
like a remote-control train
that goes around and around on a track,
working the same territory,
with the same partner,
saying the same thing at each door.
Of course, there’s nothing wrong
with being in a good routine.
But being in a rut can sap our energy
and take the joy out of our service.
We could even come to view
our ministry as boring.
Of course, we feel invigorated
when we get good results:
We meet an interested person
when going from door to door
—we’re invigorated!
An inactive person approaches the cart
and wants to get in touch
with the local congregation
—we’re even more invigorated!
We start a Bible study
—we’re on top of the world!
I’m sure you’ll agree,
all those outcomes
are good reasons for joy.
The problem is
that we’re not always in control
of getting those outcomes.
In real life,
we may spend an entire morning
in the door-to-door work
without meeting an interested person.
We may spend months
making return visits
without starting a study.
And once again,
our ministry can get into a rut.
Now, don’t misunderstand.
It’s not that we’re doing anything wrong,
but we’re not getting
the full joy out of doing what’s right.
Of course, Satan would love it
if our service to Jehovah
were to fall into a rut.
He would love it if we lost our joy.
If we lose our joy, we lose hope,
we lose strength,
and we might even begin
to feel like giving up.
The point is this, brothers and sisters:
If you feel that your ministry
has fallen into a rut,
don’t be discouraged and don’t give up.
There are ways
that we can invigorate our ministry
and serve Jehovah with renewed joy.
To illustrate that:
Maybe you’ve had
the frustrating experience
of locking yourself
out of your house or apartment.
Of course, with a key,
opening the door is simple.
A locked door
might seem like an obstacle,
but it isn’t if you have the key.
And the same is true
with invigorating our ministry.
If we’ve fallen into a rut
and if we’ve lost
that feeling of joy in our service,
there are a number of keys
that can help us unlock the door.
Let’s look at one.
Open your Bible
to 1 Corinthians 16:8, 9.
Now, in these verses,
the apostle Paul was presented
with a key of opportunity,
and he used it to open a door.
First Corinthians 16:8, 9 says:
“But I am remaining in Ephesus
“until the Festival of Pentecost,
“because a large door that leads to activity
has been opened to me.”
Here, the apostle Paul found a key,
and it didn’t require
moving to another location.
In this case,
the key was to stay where he was
and to take full advantage
of an opportunity right before him.
Sometimes, the key
to getting out of a rut in our ministry
is to take advantage of opportunities
we have right where we are.
For example,
have you considered auxiliary pioneering
or regular pioneering?
What about learning a foreign language
with the goal of helping
a nearby group or congregation?
Opening one door often leads
to other doors of opportunity.
For example,
a brother named Jacob wrote this:
“When I was seven,
many of my classmates were Vietnamese.
“I wanted to tell them about Jehovah,
“so after a while
I made plans to learn their language.
“For the most part,
“I learned by comparing
the English and Vietnamese editions
“of The Watchtower.
“I also made friends in a nearby
Vietnamese-language congregation.
“When I was 18, I started pioneering.
“Later, I attended
the Bible School for Single Brothers.
“This helped me
with my present pioneer assignment,
“where I am the only elder
in a Vietnamese-language group.
“Many Vietnamese people are amazed
that I have learned their language.
“They invite me in,
and often I can study the Bible with them.
Some have progressed to baptism.”
The point is,
our ministry is what we make it.
If we allow ourselves to remain in a rut,
it will be boring.
If we use our keys
and if we take advantage
of opportunities that present themselves,
we will invigorate our ministry
and give it new meaning.
This doesn’t always involve
putting in more time in the ministry.
It could mean that we
simply ‘make the best use of our time’
as Ephesians 5:16 says.
In fact, there’s a saying:
“Don’t work harder; work smarter.”
The key to working smarter
could be as simple
as switching things up a bit.
For example:
Could we work with different publishers
instead of the same one all the time?
Could we try a different approach
to our presentation,
perhaps making better use
of the Bible or our videos?
Could we engage
in other aspects of the ministry,
such as cart witnessing
or phone witnessing?
Could we use our time
more effectively to reach people
when they’re most likely to be home?
Here’s something else
we could do to unlock a door
and invigorate our ministry.
Open your Bible to Acts 16:9, 10.
Now, here the apostle Paul found
a unique way to unlock
a door to greater joy.
Acts 16:9, 10 says:
“And during the night
a vision appeared to Paul
“—a Macedonian man
was standing there urging him and saying:
“‘Step over into Macedonia and help us.’
“As soon as he had seen the vision,
“we tried to go into Macedonia,
“drawing the conclusion
that God had summoned us
to declare the good news to them.”
Notice, Paul didn’t think of all the reasons
he couldn’t step into Macedonia.
No, he took action
as soon as he was presented
with the opportunity.
Paul unlocked the door
to invigorate his ministry.
Sometimes we think
that only those who are young
can reach out to pioneer
or to serve where the need is greater.
But that’s not always the case.
You parents may be able to unlock
a door of opportunity for yourselves,
and think of the example
you set for your children when you do so.
That’s what a mother named Tara discovered:
“I started pioneering
when my youngest daughter
was in elementary school,” she says.
“It was important to me
“that my children see me serving Jehovah
to the best of my ability
as I encouraged them to reach out.”
Tara’s husband, Anthony,
saw the effect
that his wife’s pioneering had
and, in time,
he too joined the ranks.
This is what he said:
“When Tara became a pioneer,
“it made an immediate impact
“on daughters number one and number two,
“and they became pioneers.
“When I became a pioneer,
“daughters number three
and number four followed.
“I wish I had pursued
full-time service sooner,
as it made a huge impact
on the spirituality of the family.”
I can relate to this experience
because of the good example of my parents.
My mother was baptized in Canada
in 1940 when she was 16.
Jehovah’s Witnesses
had just been banned in Canada.
Her father had already died,
and her mother was opposed at that time.
The brothers had very little money,
but they encouraged
my mother to pursue spiritual goals.
With that encouragement,
she started pioneering in 1942
while the ban was still on in Canada.
In 1947, she was invited
to become a special pioneer
in the province of Quebec.
At that time,
special pioneers were required
to spend 200 hours
each month in the ministry.
With basically no money
and no family support,
she accepted that assignment.
This picture was taken
when she and her pioneer partner
were boarding the train to Quebec.
Whenever I see this picture,
it reminds me
of the intrepid spirit that my mother had
—not being afraid
to take on a challenging assignment,
but putting complete trust in Jehovah.
That spirit encourages me even to this day.
My father has that same spirit.
In the summer of 1976,
when I was 11 years old,
a new arrangement was announced
at our district convention
—auxiliary pioneering.
You could be an auxiliary pioneer
if you could devote 60 hours
in one month to the ministry.
The month of October 1976
had five weekends.
My father encouraged
our whole congregation
to try auxiliary pioneering that month.
So many brothers and sisters, including me,
decided to get a taste of pioneering.
It was a wonderful experience
that I will never forget.
Parents, your good example
will help your children
to have a living ministry
of their own that they will love.
Brothers and sisters,
if you find yourself in a rut,
there is no reason to stay there.
We’ve discussed several ways
to reinvigorate our ministry,
and with Jehovah’s help
we will be successful.
Now let’s meet a few brothers and sisters
who’ve expanded
and invigorated their ministry.
We’re sure you’ll appreciate their stories.
Our first experience comes from Brazil,
in South America.
Cristiano and Joana Souza
found the key to invigorating their ministry
in a congregation letter
encouraging individuals
to apply for the School
for Kingdom Evangelizers.
What new blessings
did they experience by reaching out?
We had our own house,
a certain amount of comfort.
My husband had a stable job,
and I was doing a lot where we were.
I had Bible studies.
I was already a regular pioneer,
so I thought I was doing enough.
It was fine to stay there.
We’d often see the younger ones
going to Bethel,
going to serve as special pioneers.
And once we reached our 40’s,
I thought that since we’re getting older,
we won’t be able to reach out
and do more for Jehovah.
But after a letter
was read to the congregations,
well, that was really
the starting point for us to see
that we could do more for Jehovah.
When I heard that there was
a school for couples up to 65 years old,
I said, “Cristiano, it’s now or never.”
So immediately at the first convention
that held a meeting for interested couples,
we attended the meeting
and realized that out of the requirements
there was one
that my husband didn’t meet yet,
which was two years as a regular pioneer.
So I thought, ‘Why not?’
After the convention,
I applied to be a regular pioneer.
So we made plans to attend the school.
But we didn’t want to stay there
waiting to be accepted,
as there were no guarantees of being accepted
in the same year in which we applied.
We sold our house.
And two weeks later,
we had sold all the furniture.
So we made arrangements
to serve where the need was greater.
We took only what was necessary in our car.
But “what is necessary” is always too much.
When you get to the territory, you realize
you didn’t even need everything you took.
We were really excited because we knew
the brothers were expecting us.
There was a gas station
that belonged to a brother,
and when we arrived,
the whole congregation
was waiting for us there
to welcome us.
Nine people!
And that had a great impact on us,
because you could see
the expression on their faces;
it was as if they were asking for help.
They helped us a lot.
I can honestly say
that they helped us more
than we helped them.
Now they would be able
to have regular meetings
—a public talk every week.
You know, we were in São Paulo
and we had all the meetings.
But in these remote areas, they need
spiritual food from Jehovah so much.
But there needs to be people
willing to go and help.
Then one day,
we had a wonderful surprise.
A brother called me and said,
“Cristiano, have you checked your e-mails?”
We’d received a letter
inviting us to the school.
The school really is a gift from Jehovah.
I’ve encouraged others that I know
to attend the school
because you really feel
how Jehovah cares for his organization.
And a small thing we can do
is simply give our best,
and the school helps us do just that
—find out what is our best.
We were assigned
to a congregation called Itiruçu.
The brothers are very loving,
and we’re really happy in our assignment.
I do miss my house.
It’s nice to have your own house
and not to have to worry about paying rent.
I miss my hairdresser.
But nothing compares
to the blessings and the joy
that comes from serving
where there’s a need.
This joy helps us to combat
any homesickness we feel
and stops us from developing
any desire to go back home.
In the big city,
everything’s very rushed.
I would only see my wife
when I got home from work.
I’d be tired, and then also
have to care for congregational matters.
So there wasn’t much time
for us to be together.
Now it’s completely different.
We have much more time
—during the ministry,
in the congregation,
being together at home.
So for us as a family,
it has been very positive, very good.
We’re not tired.
We’re not old in the sense—
No we’re not.
—of saying that we’ve got no more to give.
We really believe we can do more for Jehovah.
And we want to do more for Jehovah.
The school is proof
that he wants us to do more.
We want to use our life to the full
to serve Jehovah wherever he sends us.
We are willing to go.
We feel it’s the only way
to say a big “thank you”
to Jehovah
for everything he’s done for us
—the territory, school,
the brothers, and Bible students.
What better way to thank Jehovah.
Do you feel the way
that Brother and Sister Souza felt
—that you’ve missed the chance
to do more for Jehovah?
They learned there were
doors of opportunity accessible to them
if they were willing to reach out.
Their choice to make themselves available
resulted in rich blessings.
But did you notice
when those blessings started?
Before the school,
they chose to serve
where the need was greater.
This had a profound effect on them,
deepening their appreciation
for spiritual provisions.
If you desire to enliven your ministry
by means of theocratic education,
consider ways you can prepare
your heart before you attend.
The Souzas’ example proves
that even the road
to expanding our ministry
can be deeply satisfying.
When we’re faced
with challenging assignments,
reliance on Jehovah is of utmost importance.
In what ways can we show that reliance?
I have the pleasure of introducing you
to a friend of mine,
Shane Brady, who is presently serving
along with his wife, Iolanda,
at the branch in Finland.
Brother Shane Brady and I
previously worked together
at the Canada branch.
Shane has been involved
in legally defending our brothers
for the past 22 years in many countries,
including Armenia, Kazakhstan,
and Kyrgyzstan.
Shane, it’s good to see you.
How are you doing?
I’m doing very well.
It’s great to see you too, Mark.
Shane, we want to ask you,
What have been some of the challenges
that you’ve faced
in accepting these assignments
in various countries in the world?
Well, there certainly have been
a few challenges.
One is frequent travel.
Another is language;
each country that we assist
has its own language.
Some court cases are very stressful,
and at times, we’ve faced firsthand
the hatred of our opposers.
Yes. And you know, Shane,
in spite of all that,
you and your wife have always been willing
to go on these assignments.
We appreciate your spirit so much.
Is there an experience
that you can share with us
that would give us a taste
of the kinds of situations
that you’ve had to deal with
in these countries?
Well, there have been many experiences.
But one experience comes to mind.
A few months ago,
there was a special pioneer,
and a case was started against him.
And if the decision was negative,
it could have had very serious consequences
for our work in that country.
So we did our best
to present a strong defense.
But as the trial progressed,
things didn’t seem to be going so well.
But on the last day of the trial,
everything changed.
We presented a motion,
and we asked the judge
to terminate the case against the brother.
Personally, I didn’t think
it would actually work.
But one older brother who we’ve worked with
over the years always told us,
“We need to give Jehovah something to bless.”
And so we did, and the results
were quite unexpected.
When we made the motion, the judge turned
to the prosecutor and asked,
“Well, what’s your opinion?”
And to our surprise,
the prosecutor agreed with our request,
and he even went beyond what we asked.
He said to the judge
that the government official
that started the case
against our brother should be punished.
Well, the judge agreed;
the case was terminated.
When we were walking out of the courtroom,
I looked at the other brothers with me
and we all said the same thing,
“What happened?”
It was obvious
—Jehovah had intervened.
That’s wonderful, Shane.
I wish we had more time
to hear many more experiences.
But could you just share
at least one more with us?
Sure.
In another land where our work
is not recognized,
on the night of the Memorial,
a number of the brothers were arrested
for so-called illegal religious activity.
They were all convicted at trial.
So arrangements were made
to appeal each of those cases,
and they were heard
before a different appeal court judge.
What at first seemed quite negative,
the loss at trial,
turned out to be an amazing result.
Let me give you just one example.
In one of the appeals,
as we were presenting the appeal,
not long into the case,
the appeal court judge stopped us,
and he began to ask us
many questions about the Bible
and about what Jehovah’s Witnesses believe.
So for quite some time,
we answered these Biblical questions,
and then the case continued.
And then after some minutes,
the judge stopped us again.
And this time the judge said,
“I remember reading in the Bible”—
The judge said this,
“I remember reading in the Bible
“that Jesus said:
‘If they have persecuted me,
they will persecute you also.’”
So we said to the judge:
“Yes, indeed. Jesus said that.”
The judge asked,
“Do you think that’s the reason why
Jehovah’s Witnesses
are having problems in this region?”
Well, what could we say
but agree with the judge.
But that wasn’t the end of it.
As the case continued a few minutes more,
the judge stopped us again.
And this time the judge said:
“You know, I’m not sure if Jesus said this.
“It’s in the Bible where he said:
“‘Where there are two or three
gathered together,
there I am in your midst.’”
And we assured the judge,
“Indeed, those are Jesus’ words.”
The judge looked out at this old courtroom,
which was filled
with our brothers and sisters, and he said,
“Well, Jesus must be in our midst today.”
We felt like breaking into applause.
At the end of the court hearing,
the judge ruled in our favor
and acquitted the brother,
and the judges in all of the other cases
also acquitted our brothers.
It was just a thrilling experience!
Oh, that’s wonderful;
that’s wonderful, Shane.
Thank you so much
for sharing those experiences.
You know, despite the challenges
that you’ve had to face,
how do you feel about the way
you and Iolanda have benefited
from being involved in accepting
these challenging assignments
in various parts of the world?
Well, we have benefited
in so many ways, Mark.
Our relationship with Jehovah has deepened.
Certainly, our trust in Jehovah
has been strengthened.
And we’ve experienced firsthand the love
of the amazing worldwide brotherhood.
Could I just share one experience about that?
Please, please do.
Two years ago, we were involved in a case
where police had raided
a congregation meeting in one country.
They had brutally beaten the brothers
and threatened the sisters.
It was just terrible!
Some weeks later in the court case
that started against the brothers
(that the police brought
against the brothers),
during that court case,
the police repeatedly tried
to arrest me and another brother
I was working with.
Over two days they were trying to arrest us.
Even in the courthouse,
they tried to detain and arrest us.
And all through this, my wife, Iolanda,
was watching what was happening.
But do you know what was so remarkable?
It was that despite the brutal treatment
our brothers and sisters
had endured just a few weeks earlier
at the hands
of these very same police officers,
those dear brothers and sisters
came to our aid.
They were like a wall
of protection around us,
and they would not leave our side
until the ordeal was done.
It was love in action.
So to answer your question,
we have benefited in so many ways.
We don’t regret for a moment
accepting this thrilling assignment.
Well, thank you so much, Shane.
Please give our love to Iolanda as well.
We appreciate the tremendous work
that you’re accomplishing,
and may Jehovah’s spirit
continue to be with you.
It’s our privilege.
We look forward to continuing
to work with you, Mark.
Well, now,
what if getting yourself out of a rut
takes longer than expected?
We’re going to meet a couple from Italy
who had the goal to participate
in a special preaching campaign.
These campaigns
can be a life-changing experience
for the publishers involved,
pushing them, sometimes,
far out of their comfort zone.
However, the Di Giacintos
faced trying circumstances
that prevented them from participating,
but they did not stop knocking
on this door of opportunity.
We live in a beautiful,
quiet town in central Italy,
between the sea and the mountains.
We have many friends,
some of whom are good cooks.
We have been serving for some years
in a Romanian-language congregation,
and we preach to people who have moved
to Italy to seek a better life.
When we heard the announcement
about the special campaign,
we looked at each other
and said, “Let’s go!”
‘A large door of activity’
was opening up to us.
But there was a problem—my job.
I would need a month’s leave of absence,
and that would be difficult.
We prayed, and we did research.
And during family worship,
we decided that in order to participate,
I would ask for a one-month leave from work.
But Jehovah had something else in mind
that would create
the right circumstances for us.
When I arrived at work the next day,
I found an unexpected situation.
Because of the failing economy,
my boss gave me and some other employees
a letter of dismissal.
I was not at all worried.
I trusted in Jehovah,
and I knew that this new situation
would allow me
to participate in the campaign.
Participating in this campaign
is a dream come true.
We wanted to participate in 2013,
but unfortunately things in life
do not always go as we would like.
We received some truly shocking news.
My father had been diagnosed
with pancreatic cancer.
Emotionally, it was not easy.
The tranquillity
we had dreamed and hoped for
was almost gone.
The only thing that could help me
at that moment was
the hope for what Jehovah promises us.
In addition to my father’s death,
I began to experience panic attacks.
I was afraid of something that didn’t exist
—afraid of not being able to move on.
It’s the kind of emotion
that leaves a lump in your throat,
and you can’t even breathe.
I realized that only Jehovah
could help me fill the void that I felt.
After a family worship,
Fabio and I decided to turn in
our regular pioneer applications.
I felt Jehovah at my side,
embracing and supporting me.
In the end, they turned out to be
the three most beautiful years of our lives,
which also allowed us
to participate in this beautiful campaign.
In Romania, there are
many isolated territories
that local brothers cannot work
because of the great distances to be covered.
It is really exciting to reach many people
by traveling on dirt roads
that are often muddy.
The people are generous,
hospitable, and genuine.
They almost always invite us into their homes
and are willing to talk to us.
Talking to people who do not know Jehovah
and who are still very much interested
in doctrinal topics is really exciting.
Experiencing firsthand
a culture different from ours,
seeing people who live a more simple life,
and trying to understand their needs
is an experience that we will take with us.
And it will help us
to preach more effectively
in our assigned
congregation’s territory in Italy.
Now we are stronger than when we left home.
This experience has made us
love the ministry even more.
We look forward to returning
to our home territory with renewed zeal.
We are certain that Jehovah will guide us
to further service opportunities
in order to help others know
his wonderful purposes.
What blessings did this couple experience
by staying focused on their goal?
It brought them the joy of full-time service.
Not even the threat of unemployment
caused them to waver
in their determination to participate.
After the campaign,
they returned to their home territory
with a renewed energy and zeal.
When we stay focused on Jehovah,
even in the most trying of circumstances,
it will strengthen our resolve
to serve him faithfully.
Juuso and Pauliina Halme,
a couple from Finland,
now serving in Sierra Leone,
in West Africa,
were invited to accept an assignment
that seemed overwhelming.
What happened when some
of their worst fears came true?
How did Jehovah provide
“the power beyond what is normal”
to help them to endure?
Worrying doesn’t help us.
There is no need, really,
to worry about what could happen.
Even if it happens, let Jehovah show
how he can handle the situation.
He can actually do it in ways
you could never expect.
We are Juuso and Pauliina Halme.
We loved our assignment
in the Finland branch.
We had wonderful friends.
Our families, they were very close.
We had time to be with them often.
In 2014, we got the Yearbook
and that had an account of Sierra Leone.
And I was reading that account,
and I remember saying
a couple of times to Pauliina,
“This would be a tough place.”
After coming back from Gilead,
I couldn’t believe it;
we got a letter saying
that we had been reassigned
to Sierra Leone branch.
And it was a huge change for us.
Then what we did
is we Googled Sierra Leone
and what we saw was only about a civil war
that took place years ago.
An Ebola outbreak
was starting in West Africa.
Some of our relatives
were worried about that.
That was our impression,
first impression, about the country.
We were terrified, and we couldn’t sleep.
We just prayed the whole night.
And really, with the reassignment,
our greatest fear was my father.
He had been terminally ill
for about two years,
and we knew that at some point
it would get worse.
He would need more help
and also Juuso’s mother.
So were we able to travel back to Finland?
It’s so expensive,
and we didn’t have savings.
Although we had all those fears,
after praying about it a lot,
we just realized
that we could not say no.
And we realized
that this assignment was from Jehovah.
Let’s go there.
Let’s get to work.
Let’s give our best to it.
Then actually in three months,
our greatest fear came true.
It really happened
that Juuso’s mom
called us and she told us
that Juuso’s father’s situation had changed.
So we immediately started to check flights.
And then the next call was
that he had passed away.
We were able to get flights, fly back home,
support my mother,
and help with the funeral.
We were so happy
when we finally got back to Sierra Leone.
And now we thought that we could focus
on our assignment and on our work at Bethel.
Then one day, we got another
Skype call from my father.
And then he told us
that he was diagnosed
with an extremely aggressive cancer,
and he’s in hospital now,
and he asked us
to come back to Finland for a visit.
We had a beautiful ten days
together with my father.
Then, finally, he passed away.
Yeah, that was really
the lowest point in our life.
That came out of the blue;
we were not expecting it.
We had two widows to take care of.
So we were really wondering
if we could continue
in our assignment in Sierra Leone.
At that time,
one of our favorite scriptures was
Isaiah 30:15
that “your strength will be
in keeping calm and showing trust.”
And when we poured our hearts
to Jehovah in prayer,
we could see so well how Jehovah
helped us to stay calm
and have peace.
And we got some good advice here
from mature brothers
not to make any quick decisions.
So we put our trust in Jehovah,
and we could just see
that it was Jehovah’s will that we continue
in our assignment in Sierra Leone.
The fact is that, really,
the blessings always
surpass any of the challenges.
And we have come to love
our assignment in Sierra Leone.
Our brothers and sisters,
they are so faithful in Sierra Leone
despite their problems and challenges.
They give beautiful examples for us.
Being in a country where there is a lot
of potential, a lot of work, . . .
. . . you can have as many Bible studies
as you can conduct,
so it’s just a preaching paradise.
Going through these experiences,
we are so happy that Jehovah
is the Writer of our story.
And, for sure,
there’s a happy end.
If he wants to take you there, go there;
see what Jehovah
has in mind for you.
And then you can really
“taste and see that Jehovah is good.”
Despite heartbreaking challenges,
the Halmes saw Jehovah’s loving support
and they did not give up!
When we extend ourselves for Jehovah,
we can be confident
that he will help us in good times
and in difficult times.
We learn that we are safe
with Jehovah, come what may.
What quality do you need
to serve in a foreign land,
like Brother and Sister Di Giacinto,
or to face the fear of the unknown,
like Brother and Sister Halme?
We need courage.
As was announced last year,
courage is
this year’s regional convention theme.
The drama presentation
will focus on a Bible character
that needed great courage
to accomplish his ministry.
It’s our pleasure
to present a preview of the drama
The Story of Jonah
—A Lesson in Courage and Mercy.
Papa says you are a prophet.
I was a prophet.
I tried to run away from Jehovah.
But when has Jehovah ever asked a prophet
to go to a foreign land
to preach judgment against it?
What about the people?
They worship gods of war.
What do you think they’re like?
So, what will you do now?
You need to go back inside, Joanna.
No! We can talk to Father!
Joanna!
I can’t go to Nineveh.
I just can’t do it.
You’re Jehovah’s prophet.
Not anymore.
Go home, Joanna.
O Jehovah,
out of the depths of the Grave,
I cry to you for help.
What will become of me?
No doubt you eagerly anticipate
this year’s regional convention program
held around the world starting this month.
Many of the segments on our program thus far
have featured some aspect
of preaching in a foreign land.
If current circumstances
don’t permit you to serve in this capacity,
be assured that there’s much you can do
in your home territory
to revive your ministry.
For example—
Out of the over 100,000 publishers
in South Korea,
there are more than
40,000 zealous regular pioneers.
What efforts have they made
to reach more people
in frequently worked territory?
Let’s find out.
I started pioneering
less than a year after I got baptized,
so I was eager to sharpen
my preaching skills.
I really wanted to share my hope with others.
But it’s so hard to meet people
at their homes during the day.
And even if we do meet them,
it’s not easy to start a conversation.
Our congregation organized
convenience store witnessing
from 7:00 a.m. to 9:00 a.m.,
so I thought this might be
a good way to reach people
and have meaningful conversations.
But the thing is that I’m not
a morning person,
so getting up early was not easy.
So I had to make some adjustments.
I tried not to make plans
or to stay up late the night before.
The sample presentations
from our meetings were also very helpful.
In the past, I hardly got the chance
to open the Bible while I was preaching,
but now I have a few Bible studies.
Even the time we spend traveling
from one convenience store to the next
is very uplifting spiritually
because we use that time
to share our preaching skills
and build each other up.
Having a regular share
in convenience store witnessing
has allowed me to be
more productive in the ministry.
I feel like I’m progressing spiritually
and becoming a better minister
of the good news.
On weekdays, I work to support my family.
So I would usually go out in field service
on the weekends.
But it wasn’t easy
to find people at their homes
because they usually make plans and go out.
And you know,
it’s hard to get excited
about the preaching work
when you’re not meeting many people.
I wanted to set
a good example for my family,
but I found it a real challenge
to maintain my zeal for the ministry.
So I began to regularly participate
in evening witnessing
on Mondays, Tuesdays, and Fridays.
I usually get off work around 5:00 p.m.
After a long day at work,
it’s not always easy to get dressed
to go out in the field ministry.
But I kept up with my return visits
and had some really encouraging experiences.
A young man I had been visiting
accepted a Bible study,
and he’s making fine progress.
My children are able to see
how much joy I get from the ministry,
and so now they too
are able to give a bold witness
in their own words,
even in the face of opposition.
I am very proud of my children.
Training and teaching them how to make
effective return visits and Bible studies
brings me great joy.
We serve in a small rural town
where many leave home
early in the morning to work in the field,
and they return late at night.
So it’s not easy
to find people at home during the daytime.
And even if we do find them at their doors,
it’s not easy to develop
a meaningful Bible-based conversation,
let alone make return visits
and conduct Bible studies with them.
After returning home
from preaching at night,
I would ask myself,
‘Did I have a meaningful share
in the ministry today?’
It’s a small rural town.
So many people are concerned
about what their neighbors
would think if they talked with us.
So even those who were interested
in learning more about the Bible
were reluctant to have
Bible discussions with us.
It was really unfortunate.
We tried to figure out
the right time to call on people,
and we found out
that many householders are more relaxed
and willing to talk about the Bible
if we visit them
around nine or ten o’clock in the evening.
I gave much thought
on how I could help my Bible students
have a regular intake of spiritual food.
One of my students
worked from 9 a.m. to 10 p.m.,
so I asked her if we could arrange
to study early in the morning.
She agreed.
I often tell my Bible students,
‘Just call me whenever you have
a little time to talk.’
When I get those calls,
no matter what time it is,
it’s time to rush out that door.
There was one elderly lady
who was in her early 80’s
who had attended church all her life.
To accommodate her needs,
I visited her
around nine or ten o’clock in the evening
for our Bible studies.
I would come home
feeling tired and hungry,
but the satisfaction of knowing
that I’ve helped her learn
more about the truth
enables me to maintain my joy.
Now I am able to conduct
about 12 Bible studies.
I try to “become all things
to people of all sorts”
in order to look after their needs.
And it brings me great satisfaction and joy
to see my studies make progress
because that’s really how Jehovah wants us
to be carrying out our ministry.
You might feel that you’ve worked
every corner of your home territory.
But just like a literal fisherman
adapts to the time when the fish are biting,
we need to work when people can be found.
Cast your nets into productive waters!
Our sister arranged her schedule
to call on her Bible student
at nine or ten in the evening.
Of course, we want to use good judgment
to call at times that are both practical
and safe for our territory.
But by being adaptable in when, where,
or how we preach the good news,
we may yield good results like those
of our fellow Witnesses in South Korea.
This will help us to have
a meaningful share in the all-important work
of finding those who
are “rightly disposed for everlasting life.”
Regular pioneers work in a powerful way
to help their brothers and sisters
get the most out of their ministry.
But does that mean
that they’re impervious to being in a rut,
as mentioned earlier?
In the following dramatization,
see how one pioneer sister comes to realize
the need to adjust her approach
to the field ministry.
It was really nice of Maria
to invite me in service.
But I already have plans with Sarah.
We have similar service schedules,
and we really enjoy working together.
I try to get most of my time
during the week, . . .
Anyone made plans to work together?
. . . though I do meet with the group
sometimes on Saturday.
Sister Martin,
can you work with Rachel today?
Thanks, everyone.
Anyone made plans to work together?
OK.
Joanna, you can work with Sarah.
Anyone made plans to work together?
Sarah, do you want to go with me
to a Bible study?
Could I work with Alisha?
Uh-huh.
OK, let’s work together.
Joanna, could you two work together, please?
Um, I’d love to.
But I’ve just arranged to work with Sarah.
I’m so sorry.
Uh-huh.
No problem.
Maria, could you work with this sister?
While doing my Bible reading that night,
I was really affected
by the words found
at 2 Corinthians 6:12, 13:
“You are restricted
in your own tender affections . . .
Open your hearts wide.”
It struck me that some in the congregation
missed out on a beautiful blessing
by drawing away from the apostle Paul.
I realized I was limiting my joy as well
by not working with more in the ministry.
I was going through the motions
of pioneering,
but I was stuck in the same routine.
How are you, Maria?
Good. And you?
Let me ask you something.
Could you join me on a Bible study Saturday?
Oh, I’d love that! Uh-huh.
That’s great.
So later we’ll make the arrangements. OK?
The meeting is starting.
We’d like to invite everyone
to take your seats
because our meeting is about to begin.
My student liked Maria and Isabelle so much.
I really learned a lot from them.
I started going out regularly
on the weekends . . .
Anyone made plans to work together?
. . . and working with different ones
in the ministry.
And I learned more about Sister Martin
after one day in the ministry
than I had in years
of seeing her at meetings.
Sarah and I still enjoy working together.
But I’ve found that by working
with a variety of friends,
my own joy has increased.
I’m so glad I ‘opened my heart wide.’
Joanna came to realize
that her privilege of full-time service
was more than just hours and a schedule.
By working with a variety
of sisters in the ministry
and supporting her field service group,
she could strengthen and encourage others.
It was within her power to help.
But with what result?
It rejuvenated her ministry!
We truly appreciate
the love and sacrifice of our pioneers.
Have you been inspired
to make a change in your ministry?
Whether big or small,
at home or abroad,
we can find the satisfaction that comes
from reinvigorating our ministry.
That’s the theme featured
in the music video entitled
I’m Making a Change.
Been thinking it over—
Each day it seems
My serving Jehovah
Falls into the same routine.
The things that I’m doing now
I’ve always done.
So it’s clear that I need to break out—
Out of my comfort zone.
Now I’m making a change starting from today.
I’m turning a page, yes, I’m on my way.
Jehovah, I see what I need to do.
I’m changing direction and trusting in you.
It’s gonna take courage,
But now I see
How changing my thinking
Renews and refreshes me.
I’m trying some new things,
and I’m energized.
There were doors that were opening wide,
But I never realized.
So I’m making a change, and I’m on my way.
I’m turning a page each and ev’ry day.
Jehovah, I see what I need to do.
I’m changing direction and trusting in you.
Back then, I remember when
It seemed it wouldn’t happen.
Some days, well, I have to say,
I didn’t know why.
But now I can see just how
My boldness led to blessings.
I’m sure there’ll be many more
As time goes rolling by.
Now I’m turning a page each and ev’ry day.
I’m making some changes along the way.
Jehovah, I saw what I had to do,
And you gave me your blessing
for trusting in you.
So I’m making a change starting from today.
I’m turning a page, yes, I’m on my way.
Jehovah, I see what I need to do.
I’m changing direction.
So I’m making a change, and I’m on my way.
I’m turning a page each and ev’ry day.
Jehovah, I see what I need to do.
I’m changing direction
and trusting in you—
Trusting in you.
The Governing Body deeply appreciates
the work of each Kingdom publisher.
You dear brothers and sisters
are having a regular share
in the preaching work,
and we commend you for that.
You can be sure
that “God is not unrighteous
so as to forget your work
and the love you showed for his name,”
as the Bible says at Hebrews 6:10.
Just knowing that can help us
to take a fresh look at our ministry
and can invigorate us
to participate to the fullest extent.
To conclude,
we bring you greetings
from Bosnia and Herzegovina.
This mountainous region has a rich history
as a traditional meeting place
between eastern and western cultures;
it dates from the Middle Ages.
Because of the diverse religious beliefs
within the country,
the 1,160 publishers
must adapt their preaching methods
to appeal to the hearts of those who listen.
This is the city of Mostar,
which sits on the Neretva River.
The Neretva River
flows for nearly 230 kilometers,
or almost 143 miles.
Mostar was a former front line
during the wars of the 1990’s,
and many buildings still bear the marks
of the intense fighting that took place.
Likewise, the aftermath
left many people in this region
with emotional and mental scars.
Our brothers and sisters are working hard
to bring the hope of something good
to those in need.
In the 1930’s,
a pioneer brother named Alfred Tuček
spearheaded the preaching work
in the city of Mostar.
He was actually one of the first
in the former Yugoslavia to pioneer.
Today, the congregation in Mostar
has about 60 publishers,
including nine pioneers
and four field missionaries.
They bring their warm love and greetings
to all of us around the world!
This is JW Broadcasting
from the world headquarters
of Jehovah’s Witnesses.