The theme selected
for my comments this month
is “Punctuality—A Godly Quality.”
You might remember the opening paragraph
in a 1990 Watchtower article
on the subject of punctuality.
It said that an elder’s closest friends
jokingly called him Armageddon.
Why?
They replied: “We know he’s coming,
but only God knows when!”
The elder had a problem with punctuality.
Punctuality has nothing
in common with procrastination.
To procrastinate means
“to intentionally put off
the doing of something
that should be done.”
The saying,
“Tomorrow is the busiest day of the year”
reflects the human tendency
to procrastinate.
How appropriate then
is the inspired encouragement
concerning the present
—today.
Galatians 6:10 says:
“As long as we have the opportunity,
let us work what is good toward all.”
“As long as we have the opportunity”
does not sound like procrastination to me.
No, the Bible encourages just the opposite
—punctuality.
Punctuality refers to the characteristic
of being prompt in keeping appointments.
Punctuality is a godly quality.
In fact, Matthew 6:33
prioritizes our pursuit of Kingdom interests.
It says:
“Keep on, then, seeking first
the Kingdom and his righteousness,
and all these other things
will be added to you.”
It said to ‘seek the Kingdom first,’
not second, not third or fourth
—first.
When we put the Kingdom first in our life,
we do not put it off
in favor of some trivial pursuit.
If it is time for a Christian meeting,
we are there well before it starts.
Perhaps you have heard some say:
“At least I made it to the meeting.
Better late than never!”
But the godly way is:
“Better never late!”
Jehovah is a punctual God.
He sets the example for us.
When Jehovah decided to destroy
the ungodly world in a deluge,
he said to Noah at Genesis 6:14:
“Make for yourself an ark.”
Then, at Genesis 7:4,
Jehovah told Noah
to enter into the ark and informed him:
“For in just seven days,
I will make it rain on the earth
for 40 days and 40 nights.”
What happened?
A “better late than never” attitude?
No, that is not acceptable to Jehovah.
Instead, Genesis 7:10 says:
“And seven days later
the floodwaters came upon the earth.”
Right on time.
Punctuality is a godly quality.
By means of a prophecy in Daniel chapter 9,
Jehovah indicated
hundreds of years in advance
when Jesus would fulfill
his role as Messiah and Savior.
When did Jesus present
himself for that role?
“Better late than never?”
No, precisely on time in 29 C.E.,
Jesus was anointed as Christ.
In fact, Romans 5:6 says:
“Christ died for ungodly men
at the appointed time.”
Jehovah is punctual.
What about in our time?
The Bible tells us to keep in expectation
of Jehovah’s future day of judgment.
When will it happen?
Well, to us it may seem that it has delayed.
But what do we know about Jehovah?
He is punctual.
And so it is that Habakkuk 2:3 tells us:
“For the vision
is yet for its appointed time,
“and it is rushing toward its end,
“and it will not lie.
“Even if it should delay,
keep in expectation of it!
“For it will without fail come true.
It will not be late!”
Punctuality is Jehovah’s way.
Unlike the elder cited earlier,
this Armageddon will be on time.
The apostle Paul in 1 Corinthians chapter 14
was specifically discussing what happens
at Christian gatherings.
In verse 26, he said:
“When you come together, . . .
Let all things take place for building up.”
Then, at 1 Corinthians 14:40,
he concludes by saying:
“But let all things take place decently
and by arrangement.”
Look at the words again.
When speaking about Christian meetings,
he said:
‘Let things take place decently.’
In Greek,
it literally means “well-behavedly.”
Paul also used a Greek word
translated here “by arrangement.”
The literal meaning of the Greek word
is “according to order.”
If we are to be well-behaved,
according to order at our meetings,
what would be one aspect of that?
Being punctual
—on time—
for the start of the meeting.
While the lack of punctuality
affects all cultures
to one degree or another,
it is true that some cultures
are more punctual
than others as a whole.
A missionary reported
that in one town where he served,
his wife would be
the only person in the audience
when he announced the opening song
at the beginning of the meeting.
But when he announced the closing song,
70 people would be there.
On the other hand,
in a Western European country,
about a thousand people were asked:
“If you were invited
to dinner at 7:00 p.m.,
“should you arrive
five or ten minutes early,
or five or ten minutes late,
or exactly on time?”
The majority responded
that “courtesy requires
scrupulous respect for the host
and arriving at the exact minute.”
Each culture would likely think
that the other is extreme.
However, being punctual is more
than a matter of regional preference.
It is a godly quality
that true Christians of every culture
want to cultivate.
Punctuality must become a habit
—a way of life.
It is similar to some countries
that do not have
a habit of good hygiene, or cleanliness.
That may be true,
but it is expected that Jehovah’s people
in those lands will excel
in good hygiene and clean habits.
In the same way,
no matter what our background,
culture, or upbringing,
it is expected
that we as imitators of our God
will develop
the godly habit of being punctual.
What helps us to be punctual?
The Bible encourages advance planning.
Proverbs 21:5 says:
“The plans of the diligent
surely lead to success,
but all who are hasty
surely head for poverty.”
So being punctual is not just a matter
of hastily fulfilling
an obligation or an appointment.
It involves thinking in advance
about our responsibilities.
Yes, planning to be prepared for them
and to be prompt in carrying them out.
Well, what are some activities
that we would want
to be punctual in fulfilling?
It can be the everyday things in life,
such as arriving at work
or at school on time;
being punctual for appointments,
such as a visit to the doctor or dentist;
arriving at the designated time
when invited to another’s home for a meal.
What is our habit like
when it comes to these areas of life?
Even more important is punctuality
when attending
our Christian meetings and assemblies.
This means being present
before the opening song and prayer.
The apostle Paul quoted from Psalm 22
when he wrote Hebrews 2:12.
Of Jesus he said:
“I will declare your name to my brothers;
in the midst of the congregation
I will praise you with song.”
If that was true of Jesus,
it is a great incentive
for us to participate
in singing the first song
with our congregation.
And the opening prayer
is important for us.
In ancient times,
Jehovah called the temple
his “house of prayer.”
It’s true that the opening prayer
requests Jehovah’s guidance
and holy spirit on the program,
however, it also prepares
our minds and hearts
to receive the information to be considered.
Of course, there may be times when one
is unavoidably late in arriving at a meeting.
Public transportation may be delayed
or our car may break down.
That’s understandable on occasion.
But what is our habit?
In the past,
it was suggested that we consider
arriving 15 or 20 minutes
before a meeting started.
One brother with six siblings
said his father made a goal
of being at the Kingdom Hall
20 minutes before the program began.
That certainly took advance planning.
His father’s byline
for meeting attendance was:
“If you’re 5 minutes early,
then your 15 minutes late.”
In most cases, the whole family arrived
20 minutes before the meeting
for wholesome association.
Another opportunity for punctuality
is arriving on time
for a meeting for service.
This is challenging for some.
However, with a little advanced planning,
we can be successful.
Punctuality is particularly important
since the actual meeting
is only about ten minutes long.
If we’re late,
not only is it disruptive
but it could force
the one taking the lead
to redo the arrangements
made for the group.
And speaking of our ministry,
what is an opportunity
to be punctual every month?
Yes, you guessed it,
turning in our field service report
at the end of the month.
Do you have a way
of reminding yourself of this?
In some lands,
it is almost as if it is a custom
for the start
of a wedding talk to be delayed.
Often this is because
of mistakenly gauging how much time
the bride needs
to get dressed and made up
for her grand appearance.
However,
being considerate of those invited
should move those involved
to allow extra time
to complete the task of preparation.
A 1990 Watchtower
commented on being punctual
in starting a wedding.
The very next sentence stated:
“You may like to have your egg boiled
for just so many minutes.”
I am not sure exactly how
that applies to a wedding,
but I think we get the point,
don’t we?
We should have calculated
the timing in advance
so that the ceremony begins on time.
Do we have yet another example
of being punctual,
not procrastinating?
How about when there is a difference
between you and a fellow believer
or a family member?
Of course, if it is simply a minor issue
because of imperfection,
often the best thing to do
is forgive and forget.
But if it was more serious
or we cannot simply let it go,
what should we do?
We need to settle the matter
and restore the peace.
When should we take this step?
Do not procrastinate.
If we do,
the problem may fester and get worse.
What kind of a priority
did Jesus establish
for restoring peace
between fellow believers?
At Matthew 5:23, 24,
note his clear indication of punctuality:
“If, then, you are bringing
your gift to the altar
“and there you remember
that your brother has something against you,
“leave your gift there in front
of the altar, and go away.
“First make your peace with your brother,
and then come back and offer your gift.”
Did you pick up on the timing
that Jesus recommended for reconciliation?
He said:
“[First] First make your peace
with your brother.”
It is a high priority
and should be treated as such.
But remember
the scripture we shared earlier,
Proverbs 21:5?
This principle should be implemented.
The last part of the verse
warns us not to be “hasty.”
Hasty is not synonymous with punctuality.
Instead,
the first part of the verse indicates
we should prepare or plan the visit first.
Then follow through without procrastinating.
It said this approach will “lead to success.”
What is the success we are seeking?
Jesus did not say to justify our position
or to point out the flaw
in the other person’s words or actions.
No, he said you would be successful
if you
“make your peace with your brother.”
Punctuality is a godly quality
that we should strive to cultivate.
Another aspect of punctuality
is ending an assignment on time.
In the interest of punctuality,
let’s move on
to the next segment of our program.