Welcome to JW Broadcasting!
In this month’s program,
we’ll meet a brother who preaches
in the Indian Sign Language field.
What can we learn from his view
of the challenges he faces
in his assignment?
Jehovah’s sheep
belong to him.
This dramatization
shows a special way
that Jehovah uses shepherds
in the congregation
to care for his flock.
And have you witnessed
the life-changing moment
when someone
first learns God’s name?
We’ll see the results of this sister’s
lifelong search to know the true God.
This and much more is ahead
on the June 2016 edition
of JW Broadcasting!
Jehovah’s people have always considered
the studying of his Word
to be an essential part of life.
God’s Law to Israel commanded
that the king “must read from [the Law]
all the days of his life, so that he
may learn to fear Jehovah his God.”
In the Mayan territories
of Yucatán, Mexico,
our brothers are helping people
learn to read God’s Word for themselves.
People’s lives change when they
can finally read the Bible on their own
and more readily ‘learn
to fear Jehovah their God.’
One out of every six people on earth
doesn’t know how to read.
Jehovah’s Witnesses
around the world
have organized literacy classes
to help such ones.
I don’t like to read.
I used to sleep at the meetings.
In our territory,
most people speak the Mayan language,
but very few can read it.
On occasion I would give a talk,
and when I would
cite a scripture,
most of the audience would look it up.
But then I would see
a blank stare on their faces
because they
couldn’t read the text.
I was moved
to learn how to read
because I wanted to learn about Jehovah
and study his Word, the Bible.
So a sister came
to my house to teach me.
Literacy classes are often conducted
on an individual level.
After a person has had their Bible study,
they can spend some time
to practice reading skills.
But when
the local elders notice
that there are many
that can benefit from this training,
they can schedule
a larger class
at the Kingdom Hall.
The study material used
for this purpose is the brochure
Apply Yourself to Reading and Writing.
It’s available in 30 languages
in the Central America branch territory.
Other study materials can be used
as well, as long as they help
the development of the students
enrolled in the class.
And we use a board
on which we write,
for instance, words
that are difficult to pronounce.
This helps in the reading
of complicated words.
There are some who are,
well, very quick learners.
On the other hand,
others go word by word.
But as they practice,
they start getting the hang of it.
I’m good at masonry work,
but learning to read
is not easy.
Reading at his age
is a big challenge.
You need to understand
that each student learns differently.
With some,
you need to be very patient.
The first word
I learned to write was Jehovah.
“It’s like this,” I tell him.
He says, “It’s ‘cause
you’re not being patient with me!”
Having a sense of humor
is a big help in the learning process,
so as not to focus
on errors and mistakes.
Since 1946, when records
began being taken in Mexico,
more than 152,000 people
have learned to read and write,
thanks to these training efforts.
The Secretary of Public Education
in the State of Mexico
has recognized the work and the great help
these literacy classes
have been to the local citizens.
The skills they learn
help in their day-to-day life,
but also it helps them
to learn more about Jehovah
and to be able to teach others.
I used to have to memorize
everything I was going to say,
but now I can read
short scriptures to people
directly from the Bible.
As the students progress
in the class, they demonstrate
the words found
at 1 Timothy 4:15,
which says in part
“so that your advancement
may be plainly seen by all people.”
And these benefits
are plainly seen in the students.
My husband was an alcoholic,
he smoked,
and he used bad language.
But he made big changes
in his life,
and we see that this training
has been a big help.
We really see
these great blessings.
Reading helped me
to get baptized.
Helping other people
to improve their reading skills
makes me feel very happy.
I feel great because I see
on their face the joy they get
from reading and understanding
the information.
Well, I’ve benefited so much.
For instance,
now we read the Bible
together as a family.
It makes me very happy.
We’re more united as a family.
Our children
respect my husband more,
like the father he is.
Now I’m a ministerial servant.
When I go preaching
door to door,
some people say,
“I don’t know how to read.”
But then I tell them,
“I didn’t know either,
but I learned about Jehovah.
And you can too!”
If I learned to read,
anybody can.
Our theme for this month
is “Consider, Incite, and Encourage
One Another All the More So.”
JW Broadcasting
—why do we enjoy it so much?
Many of you have expressed
how the monthly broadcast draws you closer
to our brothers and sisters
and to Jehovah’s organization.
If you’re homebound or isolated,
you especially treasure these programs.
And yet, while we appreciate
the advances in technology
that have made all of this possible,
we know that your sincere desire
is to be present
with your brothers and sisters in person
at our congregation meetings.
Jehovah’s Witnesses
around the world share this feeling.
In northern Finland, for example,
winters are especially cold,
even by Finnish standards.
At times, temperatures plummet
to minus 50 degrees Celsius,
or minus 58 degrees Fahrenheit!
Under those conditions,
it’s very difficult to drive,
much less walk long distances.
Still, the brothers love
to gather together.
How do they manage it?
In one small village, there is a brother
who lives near the Kingdom Hall
and has a warm garage.
On meeting nights, he uses his car
to bring each family
in the congregation to the hall.
Then he parks in his garage and runs
the short distance back to the Kingdom Hall.
When the meeting is over, he returns
all the friends safely to their homes.
In the Bible,
gatherings for pure worship
were occasions for personal association
with fellow believers.
Such association required travel
to a designated place.
This involved work,
sacrifice, even risk.
Consider what is stated
at Exodus 34:24.
This verse has to do with the command
that every Israelite male
should gather three times a year
for the festivals in Jerusalem.
What would that mean
in practical terms?
Wouldn’t the nation
be left vulnerable to attack
if no men were left
to guard the land?
And if word spread
among the surrounding nations
that practically everyone
congregated in Jerusalem
three times a year,
like clockwork, year after year,
wouldn’t it be just a matter of time
before some invading army
would come
and pillage an Israelite city?
At Exodus 34:24,
we find
Jehovah’s remarkable answer:
“For I will drive the nations
away from before you,
and I will enlarge your territory,
and nobody will desire,”
yes, even desire, “your land
“while you are going up to see
the face of Jehovah your God
three times a year.”
Jehovah kept that promise.
It’s a historical fact
that from 1513 B.C.E.
all the way down to 66 C.E.
no foreign nation ever came
to invade Israelite territory
during those three annual festivals.
Jehovah placed high value
on having his people
gather together
in the same space.
In the Christian era,
the apostle Paul wrote
at 1 Corinthians 14:23
about ‘the whole congregation
coming together to one place.’
Now, although modern broadcasting
technology didn’t exist in those days,
there were other viable methods
of communicating, such as writing letters,
that didn’t require people to be physically
present in the same location.
Still, the apostle John,
though a capable writer,
preferred face-to-face interchange
with fellow Christians
as he expressed
at 2 John 12.
Or consider what is stated
at Job 1:6:
“Now the day came
when the sons of the true God
entered to take their station
before Jehovah.”
Job 2:1 speaks
of another such day.
Just imagine!
Here Jehovah himself,
though having all conceivable methods
of communication at his disposal,
set specific days
for his spirit creatures in heaven
to assemble
in his immediate presence.
Clearly, the Scriptures encourage
regular personal association
with fellow servants of God.
Virtual attendance through modern
communication technology has value,
and we’re happy to use it,
but it’s no substitute for being together.
And why not?
Because of what association
with the congregation achieves.
It’s not just that we receive nutritious
and varied spiritual food.
Meetings inform us,
but so does JW Broadcasting.
Meetings encourage us,
Fellow Christians who offer comments
and sing from the heart build us up,
and yet we can hear that also
on JW Broadcasting.
It’s when we’re together
—all together in one place—
that others can hear us
and draw encouragement
from our heartfelt convictions,
our smile, our handshake.
Meetings give us opportunities
to show our brothers and sisters
that we esteem them
as worthy of our time,
attention, and concern.
That is why we go and visit our brothers
who are homebound or isolated
because we want to show them
that we love them.
Moreover, in a special way,
our meetings bring us
under the influence of holy spirit.
At Revelation 2:7,
the glorified Jesus said:
“Let the one
who has an ear hear
what the spirit says
to the congregations.”
We need that spirit
to help us resist temptation,
to embolden and equip us
for the ministry,
and to enable us
to make sound decisions.
Still, there’s a reason
to attend meetings
that’s even more important
than the pleasant company,
the peaceful atmosphere,
the genuine refreshment,
the sense of belonging,
the opportunities to give,
or even the fact that meetings
are a means by which
we receive
Jehovah’s holy spirit.
The key reason
why we gather together
is stated at Psalm 26:12:
“My foot is standing
on level ground;
in the great congregation,
I will praise Jehovah.”
Yes, the principal reason
why we gather together in person
is to give Jehovah what he deserves
—praise, glory, yes, worship.
Our meeting attendance
shows Jehovah
that we want to draw close
to him and his Son.
In his abundant love, Jehovah invites
many more to serve him and keep living.
Because he lives eternally,
Jehovah can nurture
those relationships forever.
The Adversary can offer
no such hope of endless life,
so he promotes selfishness,
pride, and other negative traits
that isolate people from one another,
even when they are in the same room,
engaged in the same activities.
In contrast, our great God
is drawing his people
closer to himself,
to his Son,
and to one another
so that we “may all be one,”
as Jesus prayed
as recorded at John 17:21.
And it’s not just the act
of converging
on the same location
that unites us either.
Lots of people coexist in the same space
when they go to a market,
attend a sporting event,
or use public transportation.
Crowding of itself
does not equate with unity.
What makes the true
Christian congregation different?
Notice how Hebrews chapter 10,
verses 24 and 25
answers this question.
Now here we find
the divinely inspired standard
for all our gatherings:
“And let us
consider one another so as to incite
“to love and fine works,
not forsaking our meeting together,
“as some have the custom,
but encouraging one another,
“and all the more so as you see
the day drawing near.”
Now, what does it mean
to “consider one another”?
What does it mean
“to incite to love and fine works”?
And in what way might we
‘encourage one another’?
The verb “consider”
could also be rendered
“be concerned about;
pay attention to.”
So when
we “consider one another,”
we show interest
that goes far beyond a brief greeting.
And when we pay careful attention
to one another, we’re better prepared
to incite, that is, to motivate one another,
to stir one another to action.
And how might we do this?
Not by making comparisons
or shaming our brothers,
for that would hardly be
“encouraging one another,”
we endeavor to lift one another’s hearts
when we’re together.
And when we do this
to the best of our ability,
then we can be confident
that Jehovah’s spirit will do the rest,
and that our brothers
will feel strengthened.
It’s evident, then,
that true worship
means participation;
it requires a response.
Another noteworthy example of this
is the encouragement we both give
and receive when we sing together
with our brothers and sisters.
In ancient Israel,
at times they had a chorus,
such as the one described
in Nehemiah chapter 12
that we talked about
in our midweek meeting back in February.
Much of Israel’s group singing
was antiphonal,
that is, some of the singers
prompted others to respond.
For instance, Psalm 106
which begins and ends with the words
“Praise Jah!” or “Hallelujah!”
encouraged the people
to say in response: “Amen!”
Psalm 136 was written
to allow for different choruses
to answer one another.
Now just imagine
responding choruses
singing these alternating lines:
“Give thanks to Jehovah, for he is good;
“his loyal love endures forever.
“Give thanks to the God of gods,
“for his loyal love endures forever.
“Give thanks to the Lord of lords,
for his loyal love endures forever.”
And on it went for 26 verses!
To this day,
singing demonstrates
our heartfelt response
to the goodness of Jehovah.
What a joy it is to sing
in company with others who are moved
to pour out the depths
of their feelings to Jehovah!
And now at our Kingdom Halls,
we’re accompanied by orchestral renderings
of many of our songs
—another reason to sing out
at our midweek
and weekend meetings.
And speaking of the midweek meeting,
how are you enjoying the new format?
More of the program is devoted
to delving into the Bible itself.
Time spent on preparing us
for our public ministry
focuses more than ever
on situations we face in field service.
And the meetings move along
at a satisfying pace.
Yes, JW Broadcasting
is a wonderful blessing,
a powerful means to talk to
and fortify our brothers
around the world
—simultaneously.
Still, nothing can replace
the experience
of worshipping Jehovah
in concert
with our fellow servants of God
at congregation meetings.
When a meeting concludes
and we lift our heads
after the final prayer,
we find ourselves surrounded
by others who love Jehovah
and support his sovereignty.
These important benefits
are detailed
in the April 2016
study article
“Why Should We Meet
Together for Worship?”
This month, we’re studying
that article worldwide.
Later, in October,
we begin a special campaign
to invite the public
to our meetings.
If you do not yet regularly associate
with Jehovah’s Witnesses
or if you travel away
from your congregation, use jw.org
to find a meeting you can attend.
Click: “About Us,” “Meetings,”
and “Find a Location Near You”
or simply scroll to the bottom
of any jw.org page
and click “Attend Our Meetings.”
At our meetings,
you’ll experience what it means
to consider, incite, and ‘encourage
one another all the more so
as we see
the day drawing near.’
We’ve discussed
vital ways we benefit
when we come together
for worship at Christian meetings.
What many notice
when they first attend meetings
of Jehovah’s Witnesses
is that they hear
God’s name, Jehovah.
In this life story,
Soten Yoeun relates the impact
that learning God’s name
had on her
after surviving
the killing fields of Cambodia.
On the killing fields
in Cambodia,
I prayed to God,
but I didn’t know his name.
When I was a very young girl,
they separated our family
and they put me
to work in the rice field
from five in the morning
till nine in the evening.
When you see
some other children that get killed,
you really desperately cry
for help inside.
You always think
that you are next.
But in my heart I always believed
that there had to be a true God
somewhere, somehow
that can help me get through this.
One year later,
my family decided to escape Cambodia.
We walk close to six
or seven months to Thailand.
And I have 20 brothers and sisters
—only 4 of us survived.
I have a blind aunt that holds
on my shoulder all the time.
But one day, we got caught.
As they start shooting,
I push my aunt down to the ground
and try to pretend
that we are dead.
And when I get up,
I had no idea
where my parent was.
We spent
many months in the jungle.
As I try to survive,
I eat whatever I can find,
and I also help my auntie to survive.
One day when I go
out to look for food,
I walked so far away
I couldn’t find my way back.
I start crying really hard
underneath a tree
and look up to the sky
and pray to the true God.
I was raised as a child
to pray to Buddhas.
But on this night
when I start praying,
I specifically said
that I’m not praying
to Buddha
—I’m praying
to the true God.
And I say,
“True God,
if you are really here,
“please help me
“because I am really scared
and I’m hungry
and I’m cold.”
After I pray, I just fall to sleep
under the big tree.
Eventually, I make it
into the refugee camp in Thailand,
and I was reunited
with my family.
We lived in the refugee camp
in Thailand
for about ten years
before we come to United States.
My searching for the true God,
it didn’t stop there.
We tried to go
to different churches,
but we
didn’t understand anything.
One day when I come home
from school,
I met this gentlemen
named Herold,
and he asked if he can talk
to me about God.
I agree because I saw he have a Bible;
he must be a good man.
When he talked to me,
I tried to pay attention so hard,
but I still didn’t understand
what he was saying.
And he went very slow.
And then he said, “Your name?”
I said, “My name Soten.”
And then he said, “Your name, Soten;
my name is Herold.
God’s name, Jehovah.”
I never thought
that God had name.
And ever since that day on,
I never forget Jehovah’s name.
It’s superglued in my heart.
He gave me his phone number.
He say he gonna ask his wife
to stop by someday,
but then I move away
from where I lived.
Even though I didn’t do
the truth at that time,
I always pray to Jehovah.
After I learned God’s name,
I went back to the church.
The priest would start out
with “heavenly Father”
but leave out Jehovah’s name.
So I raised my hand.
I asked him, “Sir,
“when you pray “heavenly Father,”
why don’t you say
“‘heavenly Father, Jehovah’?
Why you not using God’s name?”
And then he told me that God
does not force me to be here,
so I’m welcomed to leave
or stay if I want.
So because I realized
that they don’t use
Jehovah’s name,
I left and never returned.
And after many years,
I tried to call Herold,
but no one
picked up the phone.
So I leave a message.
I was hoping
that they remembered me.
Two weeks later,
Herold comes to my door,
but at the time, I was working at night
and asleep during the day.
But Herold never give up;
he come back.
And I keep on praying
to Jehovah,
asking for someone
to knock on my door.
And finally, one day
I open the door,
and when I saw him,
I almost couldn’t talk.
I was teared up.
I was so happy to see him
because this is the man
who introduced me to Jehovah’s name.
Eventually, I start
to study with a sister,
and she helped me
grow spiritually.
To know that you have
a heavenly Father
that cares about you
—that was
the best feeling on earth.
It makes me want to know more about him
—want to learn more about him.
I would ask questions:
“Did he like this?
Did he like that?”
And then when I go
to the Kingdom Hall,
I hear Jehovah’s name
so many times.
I feel, that’s it!
I found my place.
I got baptized in 2013.
My blind aunt that I help her
survive through the jungle,
she’s still living until today.
And now that I can get a chance
to talk to her about Jehovah,
that was a blessing.
And I can’t stress enough
how wonderful
and big privilege
that I receive from Jehovah
—just to know
who he is and to learn
that there is true God.
He have a name,
and his name is Jehovah.
Sister Yoeun
still carries painful memories
from what she and her family suffered
because of man’s ruthless wars.
But she now has hope
for the future
and the comfort of knowing
her heavenly Father, Jehovah
—something we
all share with her.
Sister Yoeun has the added joy
of worshipping the true God
together with her husband
and young daughter.
When we’re at our meetings,
we help the congregation
to stay close together,
part of the “one flock”
that follows the “one shepherd.”
In the following dramatization,
note the way in which one young man
receives Jehovah’s love
through faithful undershepherds.
I always loved music.
I got my first guitar
when I was 15,
and since then it’s been my way
of expressing myself.
When they asked,
“Dave, do you want
to join the band?”
I didn’t have to think twice.
Making music,
that’s all that really mattered to me.
I thought being a musician
would make me happy.
So that is the path
I followed.
Only it is not
what I thought it to be.
I work here
during the day to pay the bills.
I thought my life
would turn out better.
But something was missing.
Instead of being happy,
I just felt lost.
Man, I’m distracted!
They are friendly
and look happy.
He gave me a tract and said:
“Many people are searching
for true happiness.
Maybe you
are one of them.”
This could help.
I quickly wrote down my address
and asked whether they would mind
passing by after I finished my shift.
I was searching all right.
Actually, the answers
were in front of me all along.
How come I only get it now?
You see,
I was baptized.
But I never gave
the truth a chance.
Roy did come as promised.
I told him,
“I’m a baptized brother.”
He really listened to me.
Then he shared Psalm 100:3:
“Know that Jehovah is God.
“He is the one who made us,
and we belong to him.
We are his people
and the sheep of his pasture.”
In the Bible,
Jehovah is likened to a shepherd.
He knows
every single one of his sheep,
and he knows
when one goes missing.
A lost sheep is not a lost cause;
it still belongs to him.
And Jehovah
doesn’t spare any efforts
in searching for it
until he finds it.
I was like one of those lost sheep.
But I still belonged
to Jehovah,
and he has never
forgotten about me.
Roy promised
we would keep in touch
and invited me
to the Sunday meeting.
Man, I was nervous
that morning.
I wanted to look my best.
Roy and Matthew
were waiting for me,
giving me a warm welcome
—something I’ll never forget.
How I missed this!
This is indeed
Jehovah’s congregation.
This is where I belong.
The truth has never
been so clear to me.
How I enjoy the close company
of my brothers and sisters!
What I enjoy most
is helping others
to find our loving Father,
Jehovah.
With Jehovah’s help,
I will never be lost again.
The November 2015 broadcast stressed
that there is no better place to be
than in Jehovah’s protective arms.
Those who have drifted away from Jehovah
were then, and are still now,
warmly encouraged
to act without delay.
As we saw depicted,
Jehovah provides shepherds
who care for his sheep
and lovingly guide them
back into his organization.
When the preaching work
was getting started
in such countries
as South Korea,
Jehovah often used missionaries
to help strengthen our brothers.
In an archived interview,
Brother Chong-il Park
describes the effect
this had on his sacred service
and how it prepared him
for the trials he would face.
From 1939 on,
our brothers
didn’t have any contact
with Jehovah’s organization,
and they thought
that no organization existed.
Then, in 1948,
a brother
read from a newspaper
about the activity
of Watchtower Society.
And it surprised the brothers.
So brothers wrote the Society,
and the Society
was so happy
hearing from Korean brothers,
and they answered
with many booklets
in Korean.
There were
two different reactions.
Some brothers was excited
about preaching work.
Yet,
another group questioned:
“Is that true organization
of Jehovah?”
First missionary group
—Brother and Sister Steele—
arrived on August 9, 1949.
All the questions
were answered
by Brother Steele,
and then
right away
brothers were preaching
in unity.
I began pioneering
in January 1950.
And then in March 1950,
six more missionaries
arrived from Gilead School.
We had only one congregation
in Seoul.
And the missionaries
were busy for many Bible studies.
So many interested persons
coming to the meetings.
The public talk was arranged
in school auditorium
—first time.
And there were
over 360 people attended,
whereas the publishers was
about 60.
The same day,
Korean War broke out,
and the missionaries
had to leave
on 27th of June
to Japan.
And then our brothers
had to take refuge
to southern part
of Korea.
I was hiding
in the country.
Then few days later,
the secret police
from Communist found us.
We explained to him
as a Christian
we cannot participate in the war,
so we had
to hide ourselves.
And then he says: “Well,
I do not know much about religion,
“so I better take
one of my friends
“who knows about religion.
“So I will
come back tomorrow.
Don’t leave from here.”
So, then,
we waited until next day,
and he came with another.
So I started preaching
from the Bible
about why
this war broke out
and the many problems
in the world
and so on,
because the fulfillment
of Jesus’ prophecy
in Matthew 24.
And then they say,
“Well, thank you very much
for your preaching.”
And then say, “Goodbye.”
Then two days later,
the latter one came
with another friend
so that we could preach to them.
During three months
they were staying in Seoul,
and, in fact,
they protected us.
I was picked
by South Korean army
to serve the back support
of the military
in front line to carry arms
to the soldiers,
which I could not accept,
so I refused it.
And then
I was beaten.
And then one day
this company has to move
to another place.
I hide myself
in behind the ceiling
so that they don’t notice
when they leave the place.
And the next morning
when I came down,
there was nothing left.
I walked on one street,
toward one direction,
and then I found a sign
that said
“International Bible Students Association.”
So I stayed with the brothers
for six months.
Brother Steele
came back from Japan
by himself to take care
of the brothers.
In 1952, Brother Steele
recommended me
to Gilead School.
So that I was invited
in 22nd class.
So I took the steps
to get the passport.
And then the government find out
that I didn’t serve in military.
They gave me draft notice
instead of passport.
So I had to stand
for the neutrality
instead of going to Gilead School,
which made me to be confined
in military prison
for two years.
Then 1958, I was enrolled
in Gilead School in 32nd class.
I really appreciate
that great Gilead School training.
Since my job in the branch,
especially in translation work
—and translation work
involves much deep knowledge—
the Gilead training
has certainly helped
in translation work.
The real appreciation
about the truth
and the organization,
the brothers’ qualities,
the humbleness and meekness,
certainly it helped me
to follow the examples
to apply
in the full-time service.
Did you note what Brother Park
said he appreciated most
even after enduring persecution
and prison for his faith?
It was the Christlike qualities
of his brothers
and the training he received
from Jehovah’s organization
—another example of the benefits
that result from our meeting together.
If you’d like to find more ways
to imitate Brother Park’s faith,
you can read his life story
beginning on page 12
of the December 2008 issue
of Awake!
Like many older ones
before them,
younger brothers and sisters
are taking on challenging assignments
that bring them
rich spiritual rewards.
We go next to India to hear
from Brother Francis Rodrigues.
He’s using his training
from the School for Kingdom Evangelizers
to teach people
in the Indian Sign Language field.
Brother Rodrigues searches for those
rightly disposed for everlasting life
wherever he can find them
despite the obstacles.
And you may have noted
that his joy comes from directing people
to the congregation to be part
of our true spiritual brotherhood.
That example is repeated millions
of times over through the diligent efforts
of publishers and pioneers
around the world.
Why not examine your ministry
to find ways to help
yet more people to build
a good relationship with Jehovah?
As we’ve seen
just in this program,
examples of faith
come in a variety of forms.
In the April 2016 program,
we saw the first two installments
in the series
“Viewpoints on the Origin of Life.”
We’ll now enjoy two more examples of those
whose backgrounds in scientific study
enabled them to cultivate
strong faith in the Creator.
My name
is Rocío Picado Herrero.
I studied chemistry
at the University of Salamanca, in Spain.
I specialize in organic chemistry.
This field focuses
on the study of the carbon atom
and all the compounds
that are derived from this atom.
I believed that life
came about through evolution.
I remember seeing a picture
in a natural science book
that depicted the embryos
of different vertebrates,
and in the early stages of development,
the similarities were outstanding.
But when I started studying
at the university,
I began studying
in detail the process
on which
the evolution theory is based.
To my surprise,
I discovered that these processes
were not proven facts.
As a chemist, I’m fascinated
by the distribution
of atoms within a molecule.
In living creatures,
the 20 amino acids
that are vital
for the synthesis of life,
the basic proteins
required for life,
interestingly,
are all levorotatory or left-handed.
So when a ray
of polarized light arrives,
these amino acids
divert the light toward the left.
There is no explanation for this
because the logical thing would be
that if this were a random process,
half would be right-handed
and the other half
would be left-handed.
I asked myself, ‘How could evolution
produce compounds that are levorotatory
and precisely the ones
essential for life?’
In the end, I had to conclude
that there must be a force,
a Designer, a Creator of life
and of the elements
and the amino acids
required for life.
Even though
I had a religious upbringing,
my ideas were not clear
as to who God was.
I merely viewed him
as a Supreme Being
before whom
we would be held accountable.
The Bible
is not a science textbook.
Its purpose is not to describe
the universe we live in
or the laws
that regulate our universe.
But when it does mention science,
and when it discusses scientific matters,
it does so with great accuracy.
And undoubtedly the greatest benefit
is that it allows me to enjoy
a personal relationship
with the Creator of the universe
—a universe that fascinates me
from a scientific perspective.
My name is Davey Loos.
I studied biochemistry
at the University of Leuven in Belgium,
and after that time
I did a PhD in the same area.
When I was a young child,
I believed in the Bible.
But growing up,
I kind of lost my interest in it.
When you go to university
and you study life sciences
or biochemistry, for example,
you get introduced into the idea
of the origin of life very quickly
and also into the principle
of evolution.
The professors
who taught these courses,
they were really scientists
with long careers,
and they were well-established scientists,
and we had a lot of respect for them.
So there was just no way to really question
the principle of evolution.
In 1999, there was a war
in Europe—in Kosovo—
and I remember reading
in the Bible as a child
about the future events
that would take place,
and I started wondering whether the war
in Kosovo was one of those events.
So that lead me
to pick up the Bible again.
At the time, I felt that I had to reexamine
my beliefs about the origin of life
and also about the principle
of evolution.
Based on the theory of evolution,
we would expect to see
an abundance of transitional forms
to be present in the fossil record.
But when we do look at the fossil evidence,
we just don’t see that.
We see that the major species
come into existence
at specific times,
and their form and structure
is still exactly the same
as their form
and structure today.
It was actually Darwin himself
who wrote in his book
that the biggest objection
that could be brought against this theory
would be the fact
that the fossil record
does not show an abundance
of transitional forms.
And that’s what really happens
if you look at the set of data
—the fossil record seems to prove
the opposite of evolution.
As a biochemist,
I had the opportunity to learn about
and study
many different biomolecules.
And I observed
that pretty much every biomolecule
is really a complex molecule.
We can look at them
as nanoscale molecular motors
or machines that are performing
very complex and specific tasks.
For me, the complexity that we see in nature
and the complexity in those molecules
points to the fact
that there really is a Creator.
Did you see common ground
that could help you
in your next discussion
with someone who believes in evolution?
When Sister Picado Herrero’s
chemistry research
showed evidence of design,
she called to mind her view of God
from her religious upbringing.
The person you meet
who believes in evolution
might also have unanswered questions
about God from their upbringing,
and they may respond
to the simple evidences
of a Creator
that you present.
Brother Loos
was moved by world events
to pick up the Bible
and reexamine his beliefs.
Everyone we meet,
even firm believers in evolution,
are affected by world conditions
and may listen to our message of hope.
So when someone says
that he believes in evolution,
don’t be quick to assume
that he’ll reject the good news.
Really, our ministry
and other aspects of life often improve
when we slow down,
take our time,
and as our music video admonishes:
“Don’t Run Fast.”
You can walk, but please don’t run.
It’s hard to do when you’re having fun.
But there’s a reason we don’t race;
When you’re with the friends,
It’s not the time or place.
Don’t run so fast.
Take your time and make things last.
Learn to love the things you do.
Just don’t run fast.
You’ve got things you have to do,
People to serve, who depend on you.
But don’t forget why you’re here;
Learn to love the friends;
Let them know you care.
Don’t run so fast.
Take your time and make things last.
Learn to love the things you do.
Just don’t run fast.
You can run to someone’s door.
Is there someone home?
Well, you’re not real sure.
But look around and see everyone,
People walking by. Can you talk to one?
Don’t run so fast.
Take your time and make things last.
Learn to love the things you do.
Just don’t run fast.
Oh. Just don’t run fast!
Of course, we shouldn’t run
at all in the Kingdom Hall.
But in a figurative sense,
this counsel, not to run fast,
applies to more
than just our young ones.
As we saw, even when we’re busy
with important theocratic work,
we can still take the time
to consider, incite,
and encourage our brothers.
And rather than rushing
through our field service,
we want to imitate
Jesus’ focus on finding people
and reaching hearts.
Jehovah reaches our hearts
in ever so many ways,
such as when we attend
our spiritual gatherings.
By now, some of you
have already attended
the 2016 “Remain Loyal to Jehovah!”
regional convention.
But millions of us still have
an exciting three days ahead
with 47 well-prepared talks,
18 songs that we’ll
sing to Jehovah,
and more than 50 audio
and video presentations,
including 2 feature-length dramas.
All of these program parts
have been prepared to help us
remain loyal to God
despite serious challenges.
For instance,
how can we maintain our loyalty
when under stress or temptation?
What did Jehovah
personally teach Job
that can strengthen
our loyalty?
And why does the Bible say
that Jehovah’s loyal love
is more precious than life itself?
To find out more
of what you can expect,
review the full convention program,
which can be downloaded
from jw.org.
You won’t want to miss any part
of the “Remain Loyal to Jehovah!”
convention program!
As we close,
we bring you greetings
from the Las Perlas-Ngäbere
congregation in Panama.
The Volcán region
is the highest point in the country,
enjoying a cool climate
for growing coffee
and a variety of vegetables.
The busy harvest work
from October to December
brings large numbers
of Ngäbere-speaking people
to the area.
Their kind nature gives our brothers
excellent opportunities
to teach them
about God’s Kingdom.
Local brothers and sisters
provide regular support
to the Ngäbere Remote Translation Office.
And some are making the effort
to learn the language to assist
in the congregation’s spiritual harvest.
We send them
our warm Christian love
and greetings in return and pray for them
to continue in their zealous spirit.
We thank you and hope
you’ve enjoyed our program.
This is JW Broadcasting
from Brooklyn, New York!