It is interesting that Peter gives counsel
about cultivating humility.
Let’s turn the clock back
and learn why the quality of humility
was indelibly etched
in the mind and heart of Peter.
Let’s open our Bibles to Luke chapter 22.
In Luke chapter 22,
we’ll find Jesus getting ready
for that final Passover in 33 C.E.
And in Luke 22, starting in verse 8,
it is Thursday afternoon, Nisan 13,
and what happens?
Verse 8: “Jesus sent Peter [there he is]
“and John, saying: ‘Go and get
the Passover ready for us to eat.’”
‘Get it ready, Peter and John.’
Verse 9: “They said to him:
‘Where do you want us to get it ready?’”
They understood the instructions: Get it ready.
Jesus said to go into Jerusalem,
and you’ll find the man
with the earthenware jar.
Verse 12: “And that man
“will show you
a large, furnished upper room.
Get it ready there.”
Verse 13: “So they left
and found it just as he had told them,
and they prepared for the Passover.”
Get it ready; prepare the Passover.
What would that include?
Bread, wine, oil for the lamps,
lamb, a towel, a basin, water.
Basin and water
—they knew
how important washing feet was.
They witnessed when
Jesus reproved Simon the Pharisee
with the statement: Simon,
“you gave me no water for my feet.”
‘Simon, you gave me no water.
You missed the mark on this one.’
So as they stared
at that basin and water,
as they prepared
and got the room ready,
did they look at each other
and wonder:
‘Who’s going to wash the feet?
Who’s going to do it?’
They had a golden opportunity
to apply all the things that Jesus
had been teaching them
for three and a half years on humility.
This was the time.
After three and a half years,
conduct yourself as a lesser one.
Don’t lord it over others.
You want to serve others and not be served.
This was it; this was the time.
They could have showed Jesus
that they got the point; they got it.
They had time to think about it
and time to pray about it.
It was Thursday afternoon,
but now we progress
and let’s see what happens.
Let’s now progress
to the evening, and it’s Nisan 14.
Let’s pick up the account in John chapter 13.
They got the room ready,
they followed the instructions,
and now let’s go to John 13
and get John’s vantage point from this.
He was there;
he was with Peter getting it ready.
So now it’s 98 C.E.,
and John is writing this information.
He had time to reflect
and to think about this for years,
and now look what he says in verse 3:
“So Jesus,
“knowing that the Father
had given all things into his hands
and that he came from God
and was going to God.”
Knowing these things
—he understood that.
He sat back and said:
‘Jesus knew who he was; he knew all things.
‘He had the full understanding of his dignity.
‘He knew that he
had been entrusted with all things.
‘He knew.
‘He knew he was the second greatest
personage in the universe.
‘He knew he was
“the firstborn of all creation.”
‘He knew he had
shared with his Father in creating all things.
He had knowledge of all this
—knowing all these things.’
John sits back; he writes this.
And then knowing this,
verse 4 is the contrast:
‘He got up from the evening meal
and laid aside his outer garments.
‘Taking a towel,
he wraps it around his waist.
‘After that, he puts the water
into the basin
‘and starts to wash
the feet of the disciples
and dry them off with the towel
that was wrapped around him.’
Knowing who He was,
John said He did this.
But not only does John reflect
on who Jesus was,
no, he reflects on why Jesus did it.
Why did he do it?
That’s what John was interested in,
and we get that answer back in verse 1,
where John says why:
‘Because he loved his own
that were in the world;
he loved them to the end.’
John said He “loved them to the end.”
What does that mean?
He wanted to instill in them qualities
that would help them conquer the world,
qualities that would strengthen
the Christian congregation,
qualities such as unselfish love
and humility.
He loved them to the end.
He never gave up on them.
They had their weaknesses,
but he did not give up.
Now, for Peter, some 30 years later,
he’s thinking about humility.
John, some 60 years later,
after the lesson Jesus taught
about humility,
it’s echoing loud and clear
in his mind and heart.
However, the fact remains
that neither of them
had the humility at the time
to apply what Jesus
had been teaching them
for three and a half years.
Now, after John finished his writing, he sat back;
he was under inspiration;
he finished that writing.
Did he sit back,
reread what he just wrote,
and perhaps say to himself:
‘I wish I could have written
‘that after Jesus washed the feet
of one or two of his disciples,
‘I got up and washed the feet
‘of the rest of my brothers?
‘I took that towel, and I imitated the Christ?
Or, Peter and I got up?’
But the point is, they didn’t.
What can we learn?
Don’t allow valuable lessons
that Jesus teaches us
to echo in our minds and hearts
only after we missed
the opportunity to apply them.
So in a practical setting
for us serving here at Bethel:
‘Even though I know
I have the seniority
‘—I have full knowledge of my seniority—
‘will I get up and fight the attitude
of entitlement?
‘I know I have
authority entrusted to me as the overseer;
‘I am the overseer;
I know that. I have full knowledge of that.
‘Fine, will I get up
‘and roll my sleeves back
and do the grunt work?
‘Or do I just find pleasure
in giving orders?
‘I know I have
a wonderful privilege of service;
‘I know that; others know it too.
Fine, but will I get up to train others?’
Brother Jackson reminded us of this
at the last Gilead graduation
when he said to treasure your privileges,
but don’t hoard them.
That means we have to get up.
It takes humility
to train others to take our place.
‘As a brother or a sister,
‘I know I have more experience
than the other person in my job.
‘I know I have the experience; I know that.
‘I have more experience than my workmate.
‘Fine, but will I get up in all humility
‘and share information that I have
‘with others to make their job easier?
Or will I hold the knowledge I have hostage?’
If we get up in all humility
and do these things,
then we can say that Jesus’ humble act,
as recorded here in John 13,
has made a lasting
and indelible impression
not only on Peter and John
but on me.