Jesus said that the identifying mark
of true Christians would be
their love for one another.
This was especially evident
at our 2019 “Love Never Fails”!
International Conventions.
I never expected
the welcome that we received.
There were over 200 brothers in the airport.
For me, it’s like I’m in Paradise already
because of the love I feel here.
Wherever I turn, there’s love.
As I walked around the corner,
the reception of the friends,
the way they embraced me,
was something
that I could not have expected.
No one could’ve even described it to me.
Mexico has a lot of different cultures.
But here in this stadium,
we are one people united by love,
serving Jehovah.
That’s unique, it’s wonderful,
and it’s all thanks to love.
It doesn’t matter where we come from
or what language we speak.
The language here is love.
Our love of neighbor motivated us
to share in a global preaching campaign.
Foreign delegates
worked shoulder to shoulder
with hosts from the local city
to invite millions of people
from around the world
to one of the 24 international conventions.
This gave our brothers and sisters
from different parts of the globe
an opportunity to get to know each other,
united by the common goal of spreading
the good news to everyone they met.
I worked in field service with a sister
who used to study the Bible
with a Brazilian woman.
The sister had prayed to send
a Brazilian sister to accompany her.
When we visited the woman together,
she could see the love we have between us
and the efforts we made to come so far
to attend the convention here in Denmark.
Over a million people attended
the international conventions
in many different languages.
Both foreign and local delegates
as well as newly interested ones
were able to learn firsthand
how love never fails.
“Clothe yourselves with love,
for it is a perfect bond of union.”
First, love identifies us.
Humility
—that’s love in action.
Loyal love is a beautiful aspect
of Jehovah’s personality.
Well, Jesus made it simple, didn’t he?
He said: ‘Look for the love.
Look for the love,
and you’ll find the right religion.’
Christian love has power.
It can reach hearts in ways
that the spoken word cannot.
But, really,
what other group of persons on earth
are interested in discussing
love that doesn’t fail?
When someone sees us,
they should see a loving individual.
When they see any one of us
who are servants of Jehovah,
then they should see love.
In addition to spending time in the ministry,
activities were planned
so that delegates could get to know
their brothers better.
This gave delegates the opportunity
to learn about the culture
and our spiritual heritage
in the host country.
In some cities,
they visited exhibits and locations
where previously our faith
and love had been tested.
For example, delegates in Berlin
had the opportunity to visit
Sachsenhausen concentration camp
where many of our brothers were imprisoned
during World War II.
I thought it was especially amazing,
despite the circumstances
those brothers and sisters faced,
that even their persecutors
had to recognize
the true identifying mark of Christianity
—of love.
This visit showed the faithful endurance
our brothers and sisters
demonstrated under vicious persecution
and the love they had for Jehovah
–a fitting example of love that never fails.
Adolf Hitler wanted to exterminate
Jehovah’s Witnesses;
he called them a brood.
But instead,
Jehovah’s Witnesses are still here,
proving that Christian love never fails.
Another example of faith and endurance
was seen in Seoul, Korea.
Since 1953,
young Korean brothers had been imprisoned
for refusing military service.
Altogether,
over 19,000 brothers
who refused to compromise their faith
spent nearly 37,000 years in prison.
Delegates were able to visit
a neutrality exhibition to learn more
about the strong faith and unwavering courage
these young brothers displayed.
On February 28, 2019,
the last of our imprisoned brothers
was released.
Because I received
a not-guilty verdict just two weeks ago,
I was able to attend
this international convention.
I am so grateful to Jehovah.
My son receiving this acquittal
enabled him to attend this convention.
We never imagined this would be possible.
What a joy it was
for these brothers to attend
this historic international convention
alongside their families
and thousands of foreign delegates!
Just being able to sit
next to my son for the convention
completely fills my heart.
Despite an ongoing economic crisis,
many delegates from Venezuela
were able to attend
the international convention
in Sao Paulo, Brazil.
Coming from Venezuela,
it’s difficult to earn
a living or save money.
We had to sell our electronic devices
and work long hours to be here.
But these sacrifices
will always be worth it.
The love we show to our brothers is possible
because of the love Jehovah shows us.
An expression of his love to us
comes in the form of his Word, the Bible.
In Copenhagen, Denmark,
delegates from Iceland
were delighted to receive a special gift.
We are happy to announce the release
of the Icelandic New World Translation
of the Christian Greek Scriptures.
Additionally,
at several 2019 international conventions,
our brothers received
the revised New World Translation
in the language of their heart.
I can really feel the love from Jehovah.
He’s given us this wonderful gift
because he wants us to know
that the words in this book
are from him.
The conventions also gave
thousands the opportunity
to express their love for Jehovah
by symbolizing their dedication to him
through baptism.
The love among our brothers
was evident to onlookers as well.
The police directing traffic
had less work than they normally do.
The atmosphere was so contagious
that they started greeting
foreign and local delegates.
They were so happy.
They said:
“This country does not need more police.
What it needs is more Jehovah’s Witnesses!”
Our 2019 international conventions
have given us
an opportunity to demonstrate
how Jehovah’s love
motivates us to love.
Well, as we approach
the end of this system of things,
we’re going to need love
more than ever before.
Of course,
we need loyalty;
of course,
we need endurance;
and, of course,
we’re going to sing that song of courage.
But remember what else we want
—Jehovah’s loyal love!
May we be determined
to imitate Him in letting
our love never ever fail,
all to Jehovah’s glory.