Jehovah has warned us that we’re living
in “critical times hard to deal with.”
And Jesus foretold that in the last days
there would be great “earthquakes
in one place after another”
and other “fearful sights.”
Many of us either have or will be affected
by some form of natural disaster.
If this happens, how can we be prepared?
First,
we can prepare spiritually by maintaining
a close relationship with Jehovah.
He is “the God of all comfort,”
and he can comfort us
in times of tribulation.
How does he do this?
We do not expect divine intervention.
But if we pray during times of distress,
his powerful holy spirit
can bring Bible passages
back to mind to comfort us.
Second,
we can take practical steps,
perhaps preparing an emergency kit.
Our kit could contain
the following items if possible:
first-aid supplies,
bottled water,
and nonperishable food.
Also, we shouldn’t forget
to update the elders
with our latest contact information.
If we don’t do so,
valuable time could be lost in a disaster.
Additionally,
during a Family Worship evening,
our family could review
the types of disasters that might happen
and what could be done in each situation
—such as where we meet,
how we contact the elders, and so forth.
And third,
we can help others
when they’re experiencing a disaster,
knowing they’d do the same for us.
How can we do this?
By offering prayers in their behalf,
by volunteering to assist
with disaster relief efforts,
and by contributing donations
to the worldwide work.
No, we can’t avoid all natural disasters.
But if we prepare spiritually,
practically,
and help others currently affected,
we can take comfort in knowing
that in Jehovah’s eyes
we are prepared.
That was great, practical advice
for all of us to take to heart.
But there are some things
we can do to help our local congregation.
Let’s turn briefly
to interview Brother Bram Siegel,
who’s with
the Coordinators’ Committee Office.
Bram, how can all of us cooperate
with the congregation arrangement
when a disaster hits?
Immediately after a disaster occurs,
each field service group overseer
will contact everyone in his group
to make sure that all are accounted for
and to see if anyone needs assistance.
So each of us
should make sure to give the elders
our up-to-date contact information.
That way they can reach us
when something happens.
That’s a very important reminder
—good point!
But what if my area
was not hit by the disaster
but an adjacent town or city was?
Can I just travel there on my own to help,
or what should I do?
We really appreciate
the beautiful spirit the brotherhood shows
when it comes to providing disaster relief.
Really, the best time
to make yourself available to help
is right now,
before a disaster occurs.
Just ask your local elders
for an application.
Later, when there’s a need
to provide disaster relief,
the branch office will know
that you’re willing and ready to assist.
Thank you very much, Bram,
for those important reminders.
Thank you.