James 4:7:
“Oppose the Devil, and he will flee from you”
is indeed powerful encouragement.
By these reassuring words,
Jehovah reminds us of the potential we have.
Why can we say so?
Because Jehovah
would never expect us to do something
that is beyond our abilities.
And even if we ourselves
in certain situations might feel
we do not have the strength anymore,
we know Jehovah will empower us.
Now,
when was the last time
that you opposed the Devil?
We all understand
the general concept of James 4:7,
and yet it might be a challenge
to get specific when it comes
to applying it on a personal level.
We are not having conversations
directly with the Devil
as Jesus did
when he was tempted three times.
And we know that the Devil
might not cause all of our problems,
but we also know
that he is sure to use them for his purpose.
Therefore, let us try
to analyze two examples, two areas,
where we oppose the Devil
and experience that he flees from us.
First of all, let’s talk about our health.
Now, health problems are something
most of us
have to deal with in one way or another.
Sadly, some of us even have to deal
with serious issues or disabilities.
So, now, what does this
have to do with opposing the Devil?
One of the subtle attacks of the Devil
is that he tries to use
our proper concern for our health
in order to shift
our focus away from spiritual things.
He wants to make use
of us being overly distracted.
He would like us
to become consumed
with matters of health to the extent
that they take first place in our life,
or he would like us to go to extremes
in striving to maintain our health.
But he has no success.
One of the reasons for this
we find in Luke chapter 12.
I’d like to invite you to open
with me to Luke chapter 12,
and we would like to read verse 25.
Here Jesus asked a good question.
He says:
“Who of you by being anxious
can add a cubit to his life span?”
So while we take good care of our health
in line with Jesus’ words found at Luke 5:31,
we are not becoming unduly anxious
over things we cannot control.
At the convention,
I talked to one of the attendants,
a brother in his 30’s.
At first, it was just normal small talk
till later in the conversation
he revealed to me that he was actually
supposed to be at the hospital.
The doctors had told him
that he would not survive
the next five months.
Would he now be fully absorbed
in finding some treatment
and forgetting all of his spiritual routine?
No.
Our brother persisted
in getting some medicine
to be able to attend the convention.
He wanted to serve as an attendant.
He wanted to care for others.
And so strengthened by the program,
he was ready to go back
to the hospital the next day.
We are not sacrificing our spirituality.
We maintain our spiritual balance,
and despite our challenges,
we are caring for others.
In this way, we oppose the Devil
—and some of us on a daily basis.
Now let’s look at this second example.
Another area where we successfully
oppose the Devil is our attitude.
We all know that attitude
makes a big difference in life.
For example,
a positive or a negative attitude
can influence
how we deal with certain situations
and how other people react to us.
The same is true with a complaining
or a grateful attitude.
If we had a bad attitude,
nothing would seem right,
even when from an objective point of view,
life is just good.
It would be like
putting a dirty towel
on a nice piece of decoration in our room.
So, what does this
have to do with opposing the Devil?
A negative attitude can be used by Satan.
It can accumulate in our heart
and overpower our ability to decide wisely.
We might lose our joy in Jehovah’s service.
It also can weaken
our resolve to resist wrongdoing.
So do we see how the Devil
would be able to benefit from it?
Of course, as Christ’s followers,
we avoid a negative
or a complaining attitude,
although this is not always easy.
And maybe we feel down
because we are sometimes not content
with what we’re able to accomplish.
Are we, for example, disappointed at times
that we did not reach a goal
that we set for ourselves?
Maybe we were encouraged
to spend more time in the ministry,
and then things just did not turn out
the way we planned them.
And then we are sitting
in a congregation meeting,
and we are listening
to the nice experiences of others.
How do we feel?
Are we discouraged?
That can be dangerous.
Let’s turn to Proverbs chapter 24 together.
Let’s read together Proverbs 24:10
because here this danger
that can be utilized by Satan is identified.
Here we read at Proverbs 24:10:
“If you become discouraged
in the day of distress
“[that’s what we’re talking about],
your strength will be meager.”
Prolonged negative feelings
can rob us of our strength,
making us feel weak and vulnerable.
Satan knows this well.
It is difficult enough
if our heart is plagued
with such feelings
of unworthiness or worthlessness.
However, when Satan
attempts to exploit such feelings,
it makes this situation
even more burdensome.
So as we maintain
a balanced view of ourselves
or, as the apostle Paul
calls it at Romans 12:3,
as we maintain “a sound mind,”
we oppose the Devil.
As we remind ourselves
that Jehovah just expects 100 percent
—our personal 100 percent,
today’s 100 percent,
not the 100 percent of somebody else,
not the 100 percent
of what we were able to do years ago
—and as we keep
this balanced view of ourselves,
we are not doing the Devil’s work.
So when was the last time
that you opposed the Devil?
We just discussed
two subtle forms of his attacks.
Probably we are all
opposing the Devil on a daily basis.
We do not allow ourselves
to be unduly anxious about health matters,
and we work hard
in maintaining a good attitude.
The fact
that we are here together today
is proof that we all oppose the Devil
and that we experience that he flees from us.