Well, today’s text
is a partial quote
of Hebrews 13:7.
Why don’t we read the entire verse,
and then we’ll discuss its importance
to those to whom Paul was writing
but also to us today?
That’s Hebrews 13:7:
“Remember those who are taking
“the lead among you,
“who have spoken the word of God to you,
“and as you contemplate
how their conduct turns out,
imitate their faith.”
Now, to whom was Paul writing?
Well, to the Hebrew or Jewish Christians
who belonged
to the congregation in Jerusalem.
Was it important for them
to pay attention to those taking the lead?
Well, consider,
Paul wrote this around 61 C.E.,
so that was about five years before Jerusalem
was surrounded by Roman armies
and then later destroyed.
Now, who were taking the lead
in the Jerusalem congregation at that time?
The May 15, 1997, Watchtower,
pages 16 and 17,
explains that it appears
that the governing body,
composed of the remaining members
of the apostles and older men,
was likely very active in Jerusalem
right up until 66 C.E.
So surely they would be
among ‘those taking the lead’
to whom Paul referred.
Now, what things
could the brothers remember
about the faith and the conduct
of the apostles and older men?
Certainly, they could remember the words
and the example of the apostle Peter.
Though Peter was arrested and beaten,
he, along with the rest of the apostles,
told the authorities:
“We must obey God as ruler rather than men.”
And Peter remained active
for the rest of his life,
encouraging the brothers.
They could remember the loyalty
and the courage of the apostle James,
who Herod Agrippa I
put to death by the sword in 44 C.E.
Remembering the loyalty
and the courage of these brothers
would have been a benefit
to the brothers in the congregation,
especially as the end
of the Jewish system drew near.
Well, now,
how can we apply Paul’s exhortation today?
As the Watchtower  comments mention,
one way is to remember
and imitate the example
of our faithful members
of the Governing Body.
And just as members
of the Jerusalem congregation,
we at Bethel
have an extraordinary privilege
and a unique opportunity to see the faith
and observe the conduct
of our brothers on the Governing Body.
And today, by means of JW Broadcasting®,
our brothers around the world
actually see members of the Governing Body,
they hear them speak the Word of God to them,
and they can observe their conduct.
And also we have the life stories
of former members of the Governing Body
who faithfully served Jehovah for decades
until they received their heavenly reward.
Let’s just remember four of them
and what they told us
about ‘how their conduct turned out.’
The first is T. J. Sullivan.
Now, Brother Sullivan
faithfully served on the Governing Body
until his death in 1974.
In his life story
in The Watchtower  of August 15, 1965,
Brother Sullivan related
what happened at Madison Square Garden
in June of 1939.
Brother Rutherford was giving a talk
when a demon-controlled mob
tried to break up that meeting.
A number of brothers were falsely arrested.
Listen to his comments:
“Brother Rutherford insisted on going
“to the police station immediately . . .
“I was privileged to drive
along with him on that occasion.
“Driving through
from the Madison Square Garden
“to the police station,
“we saw demonstrated
the mad fury of the mob
“and the restraining power of our God
“to preserve his people.
“At the police station we had to struggle
through the mob to get in.”
So after assisting the brothers
and on leaving the police station,
Brother Sullivan added:
“On our leaving,
the same demonic mob was still outside.
“They tried to force their way
into the car and bar its progress.
“It was necessary for some of us
to ride on the running boards
to keep the crowds
from tearing the doors open.”
What courage!
What boldness
Brothers Rutherford and Sullivan displayed!
Will we need to display
such courage in the days ahead?
Well, now, let’s remember
Brother George Gangas,
another former member
of the Governing Body.
His life story appeared
in the October 15, 1966, Watchtower.
Have you ever felt inadequate
for assignments you were given?
Brother Gangas related what happened
when he gave his first six-minute talk.
He was gripped with fear
and could hardly finish.
But he never quit.
He also set a wonderful example
in his love for the meetings.
He prayed to God
to not permit him to miss any meetings,
and for 45 years up to that point,
he had not.
He said:
“To me, meeting with the brothers
“is one of life’s greatest pleasures
“and a source of encouragement.
“I love to be at the Kingdom Hall
among the first,
“and leave among the last,
if possible.
“I feel an inward joy
when talking with God’s people.
“When I am among them
I feel at home with my family,
in a spiritual paradise.”
Brother Gangas
finished his earthly course
in 1994 at 98 years old.
Next, we remember
Brother Karl Klein.
He related that on one occasion,
Brother Rutherford gave him a blunt reproof.
The next time he saw Karl,
he cheerily said, “Hello, Karl.”
But because of still feeling hurt,
Karl just muttered a greeting.
Brother Rutherford continued:
“Karl, watch out! The Devil’s after you!”
Embarrassed, he replied,
“Oh, there’s nothing, Brother Rutherford.”
But he knew better
and repeated his warning:
“That’s all right.
Just watch out. The Devil’s after you.”
Yes, we should remember
these words of Brother Klein
because they are Bible-based.
Never do we want
to “allow place for the Devil”
by harboring resentment.
In January 2001 at the age of 95,
Karl Klein
faithfully completed his earthly course.
Next, we remember Brother Dan Sydlik.
Brother Sydlik’s life story appeared
in the June 1, 1985, Watchtower.
We were always encouraged
when Brother Sydlik
would start his morning worship
with a hearty, “It’s good to be alive
to serve the true and loving God, Jehovah.”
His story reveals
why Brother Sydlik loved life,
loved God’s people, loved Jehovah.
He wrote:
“Throughout life’s experiences, . . .
there has been the ever-sustaining power
of God’s friendship.”
He added:
“Even at this moment,
“sheer joy overwhelms me
“when I read
the psalmist’s words [in Psalm 33]:
“‘Happy the nation
that has Jehovah for its God,
“‘the people that he chose as his estate!
“‘. . . Let your friendship
be over us, Jehovah,
as we rest our expectations on you.’”
Brother Sydlik
finished his earthly course in April 2006
after having served at Bethel
for nearly 60 years.
Yes, brothers, we do well to remember
both the current and former members
of the Governing Body.
As was the case with the Jewish Christians
to whom Paul wrote,
we too are approaching
the end of a system of things.
And so we need to imitate the faith
of our brothers who take the lead among us.
And that will help us endure to the end,
whether that end is the end of our life now
or the end of this wicked system of things.