This wasn’t the first health scare with Mum.
And my brother and sister
were always quick to help out.
But this time was different.
She’d be here for at least another week
and then more long-term care.
We just weren’t prepared for that.
I should have accepted
more help when the friends offered.
I just didn’t want to be a burden.
Janice understood,
and she was wondering
how this might affect her Bethel service.
Terrance wished he lived closer
so he could do more.
We decided to pray, sleep on it,
and regroup after doing some research.
I shared the example of Joseph in Genesis 45,
where he told his father:
“You must dwell in the land of Goshen,
where you will be near me . . .
I will supply you with food.”
He didn’t let a long distance
get in his way of caring for Jacob.
He took practical steps
and made his care a priority.
Janice and Terrance too found great articles
offering solutions
such as asking for periodic help,
making more time to communicate with Mum,
or even getting a part-time nurse.
We weren’t prepared
for her situation to change so suddenly,
but Jehovah is guiding us
through each new challenge.
And with his help, we’re honoring Mum,
making her care our continual priority.
In this dramatization, we saw one way
that a family decided
to care for an aging parent.
Of course, situations will differ
from one family to the next.
Each must make a prayerful decision
based on their circumstances.