Our text, Ecclesiastes 7:8,
says in its entirety:
‘Better is the end of a matter
than the beginning.’
But then it adds:
‘Better to be patient
than to show a haughty spirit.’
Well, if we’re patient,
sometimes a very grim-looking circumstance
becomes much better in the end
than we could have ever imagined
at the beginning.
Well, do we have a Bible example
where this principle
actually plays out that way?
First Kings chapter 20, please
—1 Kings 20.
King Ben-hadad of Syria
and 32 other kings
are fighting against Israel.
So the beginning
is not looking very good for Israel.
In fact, if you look at verse 7,
1 Kings 20:7,
it says that “the king of Israel
called all the elders of the land and said:
“‘Take note, please,
and see that this man [Ben-hadad]
“‘is bent on bringing calamity,
“‘for he demanded my wives,
my sons, my silver, and my gold,
and I did not refuse him.’”
Well, pretty bleak-looking circumstances.
But then after another interchange
between the two kings,
it’s obvious that Ben-hadad
was haughty.
In verse 10, you can almost see him
swaggering when he says:
“So may the gods do to me and add to it
“if there is enough dust in Samaria
to give each of the people
following me a handful!”
Well, again,
the beginning looks grim.
But then Ahab, in response,
he basically uses
the principle of our text for today.
In verse 11:
“The king of Israel answered:
“‘Tell him, “The one who puts on his armor
[you see, in the beginning]
“‘“should not boast about himself
like one who takes it off
[in the end].”’”
Well, the end of the matter
proved much better for Israel.
Verse 21 says that the king of Israel
“inflicted a great defeat on the Syrians.”
Better was the end of the matter
than its beginning.
Well, do we have another example
where it states it very similarly?
Yes, Judges
—Judges 15.
This is one of the accounts
about Samson,
and Samson wreaked havoc.
He wreaked destruction
upon the Philistines.
So much so
that they are now coming
to Judah in all-out revenge.
Well, the men of Judah realized this,
and they’re worried
about being slaughtered.
So they caught up with Samson
and handed him
over to the Philistines.
In 15:13
the situation appears grim
for Samson at first.
Thirteen says in the last sentence:
“They bound him with two new ropes
and brought him up from the crag.”
Well, the haughty Philistines were thrilled
to have him bound
and just handed over to them.
In fact, in verse 14 it says:
“When he came to Lehi,
the Philistines shouted triumphantly
at meeting him.”
They couldn’t wait
to get their hands on him.
Well, how did the situation for Samson
prove better in the end
than at the beginning?
Well, the verse says
that “Jehovah’s spirit empowered him”
and the fetters
just “melted off his hands.”
And then in 15 and 16,
Samson finds the jawbone of a donkey
and he struck down
a thousand Philistines.
For Samson, the end of the matter
was better than the beginning.
Well, how about Job?
Job 42
—Job 42.
We’re all familiar with how Job’s tests
in the beginning were so trialsome
—one tragic circumstance after another—
and then he was humiliated
with verbal abuse
from his false comforters.
It can’t get much worse than that.
But because
of his endurance and patience,
how did it turn out in the end?
Well, verse 12 sounds very much
like our text for today.
Job 42:12, it says:
“So Jehovah blessed
the last part of Job’s life
more than the beginning.”
Well, how has this scripture,
Ecclesiastes 7:8,
been treated in our literature?
How has it been applied?
A couple of examples:
A 1998 Watchtower applied it
to parents counseling their children.
Now, for some during their teen years,
they go through a phase in life
and their attitude
is very frustrating to the parent.
In fact, during the teen years,
sometimes a parent will think,
‘There’s no hope for this child.’
But if they’re patient,
what often results?
Oh, we’ve read countless experiences
in our magazines
and heard them on JW Broadcasting
of a wayward teen
who is now an adult
faithfully serving Jehovah.
Better was the end of the matter
than its beginning.
A 1994 Watchtower applied this
to one who feels
that he’s being overlooked
for privileges.
Well, instead of manifesting
a prideful spirit,
how much better to wait patiently.
In time, when that privilege
comes our way,
the end of the matter
is much better than at first.
Some years ago,
an older brother
who had been serving as an elder
moved to a new congregation.
Well, the elders in the new congregation
did not reappoint him right away.
A couple of years went by,
and he was appointed
as a ministerial servant,
not an elder.
Well, a couple more years went by,
and the former elder
is now doing a slow burn inside.
And it manifested itself
in his comments,
even being critical of some
of the decisions of the elders.
Well, please find
Philippians 2 with me.
One of the elders on that body
spoke to the brother,
and he explained
that with his current disturbed attitude,
it was very unlikely the body of elders
would welcome him aboard.
He explained that his attitude
was rooted in his view of position.
And the elder used Philippians 2:5-9.
Now, verse 5 counsels that we’re to have
the “mental attitude” of Jesus.
Well, what was Jesus’ attitude
about position?
Verse 6
—it’s talking about position—
it says that Jesus did not try
to seize Jehovah’s position.
And verse 7,
just the opposite of going up the ladder,
Jesus was willing
to go down the ladder
to assume a lower position
—become a human.
And then verse 8 says:
“More than that, when he came as a man,
he humbled himself
and became obedient to the point of death,
yes, death on a torture stake.”
And then the bottom line,
in verse 9:
“For this very reason.”
For what reason?
Because of Jesus’ humble attitude
in accepting a lesser assignment
to do Jehovah’s further will.
And what was the result?
The verse continues:
“For this very reason,
God exalted him to a superior position
and . . . gave him [a] name . . .
above every other name.”
Well, the elder
asked the brother if he thought
that he was manifesting
the “mental attitude” of Jesus,
and that brother said, “No.”
He said, “I’m too caught up
in the position of being an elder.”
So the elder asked him,
“Well, what are you going to do?”
The older brother said,
“I need to reach out
for the office of overseer all over again
and stop sulking about my position.”
Well, what was the result?
For years he had not been reappointed
as an elder.
Six months after that conversation,
the body of elders
unanimously recommended
he be appointed as an elder.
Why?
Ecclesiastes 7:8:
“Better to be patient than . . .
haughty in spirit.”
Well, that older brother,
he died some years later,
happily serving as an elder.
Better was the end of the matter
than its beginning.
Another application of the verse:
In the beginning,
in the rebellion in Eden,
it looked very bleak
for the human family.
But Jehovah had an arrangement
to rectify matters,
Jesus cooperated,
and what does that result in
for you and me if we remain faithful?
No question about it
—our reward at the end of this system
will be better than at the first!