Big projects require thousands of volunteers
over a period of several years.
On our program thus far,
we have also considered disaster relief work
and branch renovation projects.
All of these initiatives require
that volunteers fill out an application
to be used in these capacities.
And there are so many avenues of service
that require the submittal of an application.
With that thought in mind,
please carefully watch
the next video entitled
A New Application
for Processing Applications.
Have you ever submitted
an application to expand your ministry?
Since the early 1900’s,
our organization has used paper applications
for many forms of service
and faithful workers have responded.
This growth is in fulfillment
of Jesus’ words at Matthew 9:37:
“The harvest is great.”
And the needs are greater than ever before.
Can more workers make themselves available?
Can applying for different avenues
of service be simplified?
We are pleased to announce
online applications on jw.org®!
Publishers will be able to apply online
to expand their ministry!
Elders will review
and approve applications online.
When needed, circuit overseers will review
Your willing spirit
to expand your theocratic service
supports the need
for more workers in many ways.
Jehovah inspired King David to write:
“Your people
will offer themselves willingly.”
And Jehovah’s people
have always wholeheartedly responded.
We hope this new online tool
will help you support the Kingdom
in whatever way you can,
all to Jehovah’s praise.
As you noted,
this provision will be available
for those applying
for various privileges of service
beginning January 2020.
Technology continues to make advancements.
Is there a way to harness such advances
for the benefit of Jehovah’s people?
Brother Clive Martin,
who oversees
the MEPS Department at Warwick,
will discuss a new way
to access jw.org® audio files.
Please, Brother Martin.
We just love the rich supply
of spiritual food on our website and app.
However, some have asked
if there’s an easier way to find
and listen
to the audio publications and programs.
This would be particularly helpful
for many of our dear publishers
who have limited vision
and who depend on these audio programs.
With this in mind,
we’re happy to introduce
jw.org® for Amazon Alexa
and the Google Voice Assistant.
You may have bought
one of these voice assistants
to listen to music,
check the news and the weather,
or perhaps to control your home appliances.
Now you can use it to listen
to the content that we need
for our regular spiritual routine.
Let’s try it out.
“Alexa, read the daily text from jw.org.”
Reading the daily text.
Saturday, October 5:
“Make disciples of people
of all the nations, baptizing them.”
“Alexa, play the Bible reading
for this week from jw.org.”
Playing this week’s Bible reading.
The letter of James.
Chapter 1.
For Google devices,
the command is just a little different.
Let’s ask for a specific chapter.
“Hey, Google,
ask jw.org to play Matthew 24.”
Playing the Bible
starting at Matthew chapter 24.
Chapter 24:
“Now as Jesus was departing from . . . ”
Are you learning another language?
Here’s a feature that can help.
“Alexa,
play the Watchtower  study
in Russian from jw.org.”
Playing this week’s
Watchtower  study article in Russian.
Just remember, though,
that your newfound friend
does have some limitations.
“Alexa, what do you think
of that new point in The Watchtower?”
I don’t have an opinion on that.
And that’s probably just as well.
Would you like to listen
to the audio track of the monthly broadcast?
“Hey, Google,
ask jw.org to play the broadcast.”
Playing JW Broadcasting®, September 2019.
Hello, everyone.
We’re so happy to have you
with us for this month’s broadcast.
You can also ask for the broadcast
for a specific month or year.
Now, how about some theocratic music?
“Alexa, play original songs from jw.org.”
Playing original songs.
You can also listen to our collection
of Kingdom songs in the same way.
Or if you want to practice
a specific song for the meeting,
“Hey, Google, ask jw.org to play song 57.”
Playing 57,
“Preaching to All Sorts of People.”
These features will be available
within the next few days.
So look on jw.org
this coming week for instructions
on how to enable these features
for your Alexa or Google device.
We thank Jehovah and his organization
that they make it
ever easier for us to benefit
from our rich library of spiritual content.
We now look forward
to Scriptural talks to be presented
by various members of the Governing Body.
First, please give your attention
to Brother David Splane.
His subject is intriguing:
“An Attack Coming From the North.”
Alexa!
Where are you when I need you?
Well, an attack coming from the north—
What are we talking about?
Are we talking
about the attack of Gog of Magog?
No.
We’re talking about an attack
by a plague of locusts
coming from the north.
And we can read
about that plague in Joel chapter 2.
I’d like you to follow
and leave your Bibles open, please,
at Joel because we’re going to be considering
a few verses in this prophecy.
This is Joel 2:7-9
—an attack by a plague,
a swarm, of locusts.
Joel 2:7:
“They charge like warriors,
“they scale a wall like soldiers,
“each keeps to his own course,
“and they do not swerve from their paths.
“They do not shove one another;
“each man advances in his course.
“If the weapons cause some to fall,
the others do not break ranks.
“Into the city they rush,
on the wall they run.
“Onto the houses they climb,
through the windows they enter like a thief.”
Now, I think you can see
that we’re not talking about insects here.
Notice in verse 8:
“Each man  advances in his course.”
So we’re talking about people
who are likened to locusts,
who have the characteristics of locusts.
And the question is,
Are these good people,
or are they bad people?
Well, for many years,
including in the April 15, 2009, Watchtower,
our understanding was
that these were good people.
In fact, these were Jehovah’s people.
These were Jehovah’s Witnesses
who were preaching
the good news of the Kingdom.
And the idea was that they
were just like locusts because,
first of all,
you couldn’t stop them from preaching
and they would go to any length
to keep preaching the good news
—probably not go
into people’s windows like thieves,
but otherwise, they’d stop short of that.
But they would do other things.
Preaching the good news
—it didn’t matter what wall of opposition
was erected against them;
they would scale that wall
and keep preaching.
And if we were to confine ourselves
to a reading of just these three verses,
we could make a case for that explanation.
But now, prophecy is best understood
when we consider it in context.
And if you look
at the context of Joel chapter 2,
you are forced to come
to a different conclusion.
Now let’s consider
a couple of reasons why this is so.
Now, we talk about context,
so let’s look at verse 20
in the same chapter,
Joel chapter 2.
And here in verse 20,
we’re talking about the locusts
that come from the north,
and we’re going to see
how Jehovah views these locusts.
Are these good people,
or are they bad people?
Verse 20:
“I will drive the northerner
far away from you;
“I will disperse him
to a dry and desolate wasteland,
with his vanguard toward the eastern sea.”
Well, Jehovah is talking
about the locusts here,
and he says he’s going
to drive them away.
If these were Kingdom publishers
who are declaring the good news,
why would Jehovah want to drive them away?
And then how does Jehovah view these locusts?
Look at the last part of verse 20:
“The foul smell from him will ascend,
the stench from him will keep ascending.”
That’s not good.
So it’s looking like these locusts
are not good people.
What is Jehovah talking about here?
Pest control.
He doesn’t like the locusts.
Now look at verse 25.
Jehovah says:
“And I will make compensation
to you for the years
“that the swarming locust,
the unwinged locust,
“the voracious locust,
and the devouring locust have eaten,
my great army that I sent among you.”
Well, now, if the locusts
were ministers of the Kingdom,
why would Jehovah say
that he had to “make compensation”
for the damage that the locusts have done?
The locusts,
if they were Kingdom publishers,
would just be helping people
to save their lives.
So why would Jehovah call that damage?
Why would he say
they would have to “make compensation”?
Now, that’s one aspect of this
that we considered.
But there’s another one,
and that is the sequence of events.
Look at verse 28,
and we’ll read
just the first part of verse 28.
And keep in mind, at this point,
Jehovah has driven the locusts away.
They have done all the damage they could.
They have devastated the land.
They have destroyed all of the vegetation,
and now Jehovah God has driven
“the northerner,” the locust, away.
And so, what does he say in verse 28?
“After that
“[after the locusts
have been driven away]
I will pour out my spirit
on every sort of flesh.”
Now let’s think about that.
If the locusts were really carrying out
the preaching work
and they don’t get the holy spirit
until after they finish the preaching work,
does that mean
that we’ve been preaching all this time
without the help
of Jehovah’s powerful holy spirit?
I’m sure you’ll all agree,
we couldn’t possibly keep preaching
without the help
of Jehovah’s powerful holy spirit.
So it’s obvious that we have
some thinking to do about this prophecy.
Now, someone might bring up
Revelation chapter 9,
because in Revelation chapter 9,
we read of locusts with “human faces”
and what “seemed to be crowns of gold”
on their heads,
and they torment the wicked.
And someone will say,
“Well, don’t those locusts represent
Jehovah’s anointed servants
and their preaching work?”
And the answer is yes.
And it’s true
that there are some similarities
between Revelation chapter 9
and Joel chapter 2,
but there are
significant differences as well.
For example, in Joel’s prophecy,
the locusts come from the north,
they devastate the vegetation,
and they’re driven away.
But what about Revelation?
Well, those locusts come out of an abyss,
and “they [are] told
not to harm the vegetation,”
and they stay on until their work is done.
So there are similarities,
but there are also differences.
What are we saying?
We are saying that the locusts in Revelation
are not the same as the locusts in Joel.
Now, it’s not unusual for a symbol
to mean one thing in one Bible book
and something quite different in another
—Revelation 5:5, Jesus,
“the Lion of the tribe of Judah”;
1 Peter 5:8, Satan the Devil,
“a roaring lion”
—same symbol but quite different meanings.
Well, now,
if the locusts are bad people,
if they are not Jehovah’s faithful servants,
we have to look for a different explanation.
What could it be?
It’s a simple one.
Joel is predicting a military attack.
Jehovah will use Babylonian soldiers
who are just like locusts
—“my great army,” he calls them—
to bring his people into captivity.
And the army is called “the northerner”
because the Babylonians will come up
and invade Israel from the north.
And when we read Joel 2:8, 9
with the idea of Babylonian soldiers,
it all makes sense.
Let’s just read those verses again,
verse 8 and verse 9:
“They do not shove one another;
“each man advances in his course.
“If the weapons cause some to fall,
the others do not break ranks.
“Into the city they rush,
on the wall they run.
Onto the houses they climb,
through the windows they enter like a thief.”
Can you picture the scene?
There are soldiers everywhere.
No one can escape
the sword of the Babylonians.
And this concords
with what the prophet Isaiah wrote.
He was looking into the future,
and he was looking at this event
and the outcome of this event.
And he says:
“All who were found were taken prisoner,
even though they had fled far away.”
Now, the prophet Jeremiah
foretold something similar
at Jeremiah 16:16.
Let’s read that; then we’ll go back to Joel.
Jeremiah 16:16:
“‘Here I am sending
for many fishermen,’
“declares Jehovah,
‘and they will fish for them.
“‘After that I will send
for many hunters,
“‘and they will hunt them down
“‘on every mountain and every hill
and out of the clefts of the crags.’”
Now, we used to think
that the hunters and fishers
were hunting and fishing
for righthearted ones
in sort of a marking work, I guess,
where they were looking
for righthearted ones.
But now, the revised New World Translation
helps us to get
the right understanding of this.
Did you notice what it says?
“They will hunt them down.”
It’s the wicked who are being hunted,
not the righthearted ones.
And just to confirm that, look at verse 17:
“For my eyes are on everything they do.
“They have not been hidden from before me,
nor has their error
been hidden from my eyes.”
And then in verse 18, he says he is going
to ‘repay the full amount of their error.’
So these are not righthearted ones.
These are people
who might try to hide in the forest.
They’ll be hunted down.
If they go out and try to hide in the sea,
they’ll be fished out of the water.
They will not get away
from the Babylonian soldiers.
But now Joel has some good news for us,
and we want some good news after this,
don’t we?
And the news is restoration.
And Joel is saying that at some point
an ample supply of spiritual food
is going to become available for the people.
Let’s go back to Joel
and this time
read entirely verses 28 and 29.
Joel 2
—Joel 2:28, 29:
“After that
“[so the Babylonians
have done what they were going to do]
“I will pour out my spirit
on every sort of flesh,
“and your sons
and your daughters will prophesy,
“your old men will dream dreams,
and your young men will see visions.
“And even on my male slaves
and female slaves
I will pour out my spirit in those days.”
Well, when was the prophecy fulfilled?
After that, certainly.
The apostle Peter tells us
that it was first fulfilled
at Pentecost 33 C.E.
Jehovah poured out his spirit,
and at the end of that day,
there were 3,000 publishers of the Kingdom.
And did Jehovah bless their zealous activity?
He certainly did,
because by the end of the century,
thousands had become obedient to the word.
How many thousands?
We don’t know.
The Bible doesn’t say.
But we do know that it would have to be
a lot less than 144,000
because the search for Kingdom heirs
was going on in the first century,
and it wasn’t nearly complete
by the end of the first century.
Yet, the zealous activity of those 3,000
who began preaching the good news,
that zealous activity,
was blessed by Jehovah God,
and thousands became obedient to the word.
Well, now, can we see
a little bit of a parallel here?
The year 1919.
In 1919,
according to official records,
there were fewer than 6,000 publishers
of the good news.
But has Jehovah blessed the efforts
of those 6,000 publishers?
By the end of the century,
he certainly had shown that he’d blessed
the efforts of the brothers.
Do you know that every year
since 1983,
more than 144,000
have been baptized each year?
And our brothers today
don’t have the gifts of the spirit.
So, what does this indicate?
It indicates that Jehovah has made
a mighty outpouring of his spirit
in these last days.
It’s a marvelous thing to behold.
Now, when you think of it,
we sort of had our explanation
backward in the past.
Because in the past,
the idea was that the spirit
was poured out in 1919
and then the locusts went to work,
because the locusts were Jehovah’s people.
But that’s not what the Bible says, is it?
The Bible says
that the locusts finish their work,
and after that, the spirit is poured out.
Well, today, thousands upon thousands
are getting baptized,
and we can expect that more
are going to get baptized in the future,
with the new instructions we’ve received:
Concentrate more on conversations;
concentrate more on starting Bible studies.
And with those instructions in mind,
no doubt we’re going to have
a tremendous increase in baptisms.
But now, here’s a little word of caution:
By all means, have conversations;
by all means, read the Bible to people;
by all means, offer Bible studies.
But don’t forget to offer literature.
If you say,
“I deliberately didn’t offer
one piece of literature all month,”
you’re not bragging.
What do we print it for?
And, brothers, let’s be realistic about it:
You have a lovely conversation with someone,
and then you don’t find the person
for another three weeks.
Leave the person some literature
that he can read
so that he can further his interest.
Well, we might think
of this explanation and say:
“Well, that’s obvious.
This explanation is obvious.
Why didn’t we see it before?”
And the answer is, yes, it’s obvious
when Jehovah’s time for us
to understand it comes along.
But before Jehovah’s time
for us to understand it comes along,
it isn’t always so obvious.
So we always look to Jehovah God
for clarification in matters.
Now, what has changed?
It’s true that in a few lands (but not many)
Jehovah’s people do seem to be everywhere,
as numerous as locusts,
and it’s true
that in every land we won’t allow
any wall of opposition
to prevent us from doing our work;
but we’re just not doing it
in fulfillment of Joel chapter 2
and Jeremiah chapter 16.
So let’s continue having a zealous share
in proclaiming the life-giving message
that God has given us,
confident that he won’t drive us away.
He will sustain us until the work is done.
Well, it was certainly
very encouraging and interesting.
Thank you, Brother Splane.
Now Brother Herd
has something to share with us.
His title is
“Study the Bible With the Study Bible.”
Who is the most important
person that you know?
Well, as dedicated Witnesses of Jehovah,
I’m sure you would say, “Jehovah.”
Well, who is the second
most important person that you know?
I asked my wife that once,
and she said, “You.”
And then she said, “I’m just joking.”
No, it’s Jesus Christ, and we all know that.
But, now, how important is it for us to know
not just Jehovah but also his Son?
Well, let’s look at something in the Bible.
Open your Bibles, if you please,
to John 17:3,
one of the most familiar scriptures
that we learn when we come into the truth,
John 17:3:
“This means everlasting life,
their coming to know you,
the only true God,
and the one whom you sent, Jesus Christ.”
Well, now, let’s think about it.
It means our salvation
—doesn’t it?—
to come to know Jehovah God
and his Son, Jesus.
Come to know them
—it means everlasting life.
Our salvation rests on our knowledge
of Jehovah God and his Son, Jesus.
It means our life.
But “coming to know,” what does this mean?
Could it be what
the study note on this verse says?
“The verb is used in the present tense
to express continuous action.”
Absolutely!
That’s the correct answer.
So coming to know Jehovah
or someone else is an ongoing process.
We have to become
acquainted with that person.
Now, if I should ask you,
How many of you know me?
Raise your hands, please.
Get them down because you
don’t really know me.
Oh, in a sense,
you were right in raising your hand.
You know who I am;
you know the position I have.
You’ve got my name, you’ve heard me
give some talks, and so forth.
So you have some knowledge of me,
but there are so many things
about me that you don’t know.
And if you did know these things,
it wouldn’t help you.
But, now, coming to know Jehovah
is altogether different.
Coming to know Jesus is altogether different.
The more we know about them, why, then
the better we have a relationship with them.
And we’re going to benefit
from that knowledge in ever so many ways.
So we want to come to know Jehovah.
No matter how long we’ve been in the truth
(and some of you
have been there for decades),
we must keep working
at coming to know Jehovah God
and his Son, Jesus.
But the question is,
How can we come to know
Jehovah better and better?
Well, we can learn much through creation.
We look around us,
and it draws us ever closer to Jehovah.
When we see the animal creation,
as we have earlier today
(the zebra and various birds
and other animals),
we think of Jehovah and his great wisdom
and the blessings
that he has showered upon us
as a result of the creation around us.
And how many of us enjoy going
to the beautiful parks a certain time of year
and enjoying all the creation
—the greenery, the flowers, the trees?
My, there’s just no end to it!
And whenever we see fish
that we’ve never seen before
(and there are so many fish
that are so new to us),
their beauty—
It all speaks of Jehovah
as the Creator, does it not?
And we marvel at these wonderful things.
But here’s another way that we benefit:
It’s through his Word.
It’s through the Bible that we’re able
to know the name of our God—Jehovah.
We’re able to appreciate
what that name stands for,
and we’re drawn ever closer
to him as a result of that knowledge.
We’re able to have
the knowledge of his purpose.
We know that he’s not responsible
for all the wickedness
that goes on in the earth around us.
That’s not of his making,
but yet people in the world feel that it is.
If someone dies, they blame God:
“Why did he take that beautiful little girl?
“She was only two years old.
Why did he do a thing like that?”
Well, they have no knowledge,
but you have knowledge.
When a person dies whom they love,
people in the world have no idea
about the resurrection.
They feel that two things can happen.
Many of them feel this way (not all),
that two things can happen
—either they go to heaven
and become a flower in His garden
up there in some kind of a way
or else they go somewhere else
where they are tormented
day and night forever and ever.
Now, what about God’s Son?
How can we come to know
him better and better.
Well, let’s watch the following video,
How Can We Come to Know
the Son of God Better and Better?,
seven minutes.
He was neither rich nor powerful
from the world’s point of view.
He did not even have a home
that he could call his own.
Yet, his teachings
have changed the course of history.
They have helped millions to gain
something more important
than material wealth.
The man is Jesus Christ, the Son of God.
Jehovah wants us to know his Son,
to love his Son, to be like his Son.
To help us know his Son,
Jehovah lovingly reserved
a portion of his Word, the four Gospels
—Matthew, Mark, Luke, and John—
and the book of Acts.
These Bible books
have helped true Christians to find
the happiest, most meaningful life possible.
The Gospels portray a man
of tender and deep feelings.
They show the wide range
of Jesus’ personality:
compassion for a leper,
indignation at self-righteous
religious leaders,
deep sadness
over the nation that rejected him.
In the Gospels,
we learn of the many miracles
Jesus performed,
from healing the sick to raising the dead.
Those miracles changed people’s lives,
yet Jesus was not known
as Healer or a miracle worker.
Instead, he was called the Teacher.
And what a teacher he was!
Think of the wise sayings
of Jesus that have become
part of everyday speech
thousands of years after he uttered them.
The Gospels give
a fourfold historical account
of the life and ministry of Jesus.
Matthew, an apostle, evidently wrote
his Gospel for the Jews.
Over 40 percent of its content is unique.
Matthew gives us a far more extensive account
of the Sermon on the Mount.
In this profound sermon,
Jesus does not just tell us
the course of wisdom.
He does much more.
He shows us by explaining,
reasoning, and offering proof.
How we marvel at the simplicity, clarity,
and unparalleled wisdom
in the teachings of Jesus!
Mark’s vigorous, fast-moving account
was seemingly written for non-Jewish readers.
It mentions 19 miracles of Jesus,
including the only account
of the deaf man whose hearing Jesus restored.
Considerately, Jesus takes
the man away from the crowd
and heals him in a private place.
How reassuring to learn
that Jesus uses his power
in such a considerate and thoughtful way!
Luke, the beloved physician,
wrote for both Jews and non-Jews.
Some 60 percent of this Gospel is unique,
including the account of the resurrection
of the only child of the widow of Nain.
Jesus is “moved with pity” for this widow.
After resurrecting her son,
Jesus gives him to his mother.
Death has torn the family apart,
but Jesus makes them a family again.
How beautifully this account reveals
a very tender side of the Son of God!
John, the apostle who
was especially close to Jesus,
wrote his Gospel last.
Some 90 percent contains information
not found in the other three Gospels.
Only John mentions
the resurrection of Lazarus.
In this touching account,
Jesus openly sheds tears.
How comforting it is to know that Jesus
has such deep empathy!
Together, the four Gospels
paint a detailed portrait of Jesus.
The Bible book of Acts
also helps us to come to know Jesus.
Written by the physician Luke,
Acts is a continuation
of the Gospel of Luke.
In the opening chapter,
we learn of Jesus’ final words
to his disciples before ascending to heaven.
The resurrected Jesus leaves
no doubt as to what he expects his disciples,
including us, to do.
They are to be witnesses of him
“to the most distant part of the earth.”
The Bible book of Acts helps us to understand
what being a follower of Jesus is all about.
How can we benefit fully
from the four Gospels and the book of Acts?
We must do more than just read them.
We must slow down and take the time
to study them carefully
and meditate on them deeply.
We need to bring the accounts
to life by doing research,
observing details,
comparing parallel accounts,
and using our imagination
to see, hear, and feel the action.
Over the years, our organization
has published a number of books
designed to help us to dig deeply.
At the annual meeting in 2015,
the Governing Body announced
that a new online
Study Bible  would be released.
How can the Study Bible
help us come to know Jesus better?
Within the four Gospels alone,
there are about 2,300 study notes.
Added to that, the image gallery,
maps, and introduction videos
bring the Bible accounts to life.
There’s no question about it.
Our organization
has given us the help we need
to dig deeper into the Gospels
and the book of Acts
and to reflect appreciatively on them.
As a result, we come to know
the Son of God better and better.
We agree with the sentiment
of the apostle Peter,
who said of Jesus:
“Though you never saw him, you love him.”
Have you benefited from using
the online Study Bible?
I’m sure you will agree
that it is a great tool to help us
come to know God’s Son better and better.
But what if accessing the information online
is not easy for you as an individual?
Let’s face it, not everyone has easy access
to the Internet
or finds it easy to navigate online.
Well, the Governing Body
is pleased to announce
the release of a printed version
of the Study Bible
containing the five Bible books
we just discussed in the video
—Matthew through Acts.
Why are we releasing
a printed version of the Study Bible?
Well, many prefer
a printed medium such as a book,
especially for doing
deeper reading and making notes.
It’s easier to slow down
and absorb the information at hand.
And many of us find it easier
when we use a printed and bound book
for our study periods.
Have you ever gone back
and found something you read in a book
because you recall
that it was either at the top
or bottom of a page
or on the left- or on the right-hand side
of a two-page spread?
Would you like to see
what this new publication looks like?
Well, let’s watch the next video.
What are some of the features
of the printed Study Bible
that make it an effective tool for studying
the four Gospels and the book of Acts?
Let’s see.
Each Bible book has
an introduction with noteworthy facts,
study notes about the title,
and an overview of the book.
Subheadings within the sacred text help you
to locate specific accounts more easily.
Wide margins offer
ample space for note-taking.
Study notes are found below the scriptures.
The image gallery
contains 153 illustrations and photographs
from the books of Matthew through Acts.
The map gallery helps you to combine
specific events with locations.
The glossary gives definitions
of Biblical and non-Biblical words
that are used in the main text
or in the study notes.
Would you like to read
the entire Bible in one year?
Then use the Bible reading schedule
to keep track of your progress.
This Study Bible
is designed to help you study more deeply
and bring Bible accounts to life.
Take, for instance,
the account of the widow in the temple.
Verse 41 says that
Jesus “sat down
with the treasury chests in view.”
Hmm.
What does the study note
say about treasury chests?
That’s interesting:
‘According to rabbinical sources,
there were 13 treasury chests’ for collecting
the contributions
of those entering the temple.
And these chests were
“apparently located in the area
called the Court of the Women.”
I wonder where that was in the temple.
Hmm.
The study note directs us to Appendix B11.
Wow, look at those
four giant golden lampstands!
‘The facade surrounding the front doors
may have been plated with gold.’
Impressive!
The “light from the rising sun
would have been reflected
with dazzling brilliance.”
Let me go back to the account.
Verse 42 says: “Now a poor widow came
and dropped in two small coins
of very little value.”
What does the parallel account say?
Luke’s account calls her “a needy widow.”
The study note says:
“Needy . . . may denote a person
“who lacks the basic necessities of life
or someone for whom life
is a great struggle.”
Might the widow have felt that her small gift
was too insignificant to matter?
I’ve felt that way before.
Jesus showed that the widow
and her contribution
were valuable to Jehovah.
“This poor widow
put in more than all the others . . .
She . . . put in everything she had.”
She gave her best.
When I give Jehovah my best,
no matter how much it is,
it is precious to him.
Clearly, the Study Bible
is designed to help us study
the Bible more deeply.
May this printed edition
of Matthew through Acts
help you to come to know Jesus Christ,
the Son of God, better and better.
Remember that Jehovah set aside
a significant portion of his Word
for us to become acquainted
with his Son, Jesus
—our Ransomer, our Leader
and, of course, our King.
Jehovah wants us to know his Son.
He wants us to love his Son
and to put faith in his Son.
So by all means,
let’s—each and every
one of us—use this new Bible
to make progress
in coming to know the Son of God.
And as you do,
you will also be coming to know better
the One whom Jesus perfectly imitated,
our loving heavenly Father, Jehovah.
Thank you very much, Brother Herd.
We appreciate what we heard from you.
And what a blessing
the Study Bible  has proven to be
for those who have it
available in their language.