Before I started pioneering,
I was really nervous that I wouldn’t be able
to get my time in every month.
It was a bit hard when I started pioneering
because I didn’t have a car.
My boss,
he didn’t give me part-time work.
I found it really hard
to balance schoolwork
and pioneering
at the same time.
My biggest struggle was fear of man,
so that really hindered me
because I wasn’t very good
at talking to people.
Having a good routine was a struggle.
My brother and I are
the only ones in the truth.
My family didn’t understand
why we wanted to go preaching.
I didn’t think
that I’d make a good pioneer.
I’ve had Type 1 diabetes
since I was five.
So I was always worried
about whether or not
I could balance that health condition
with pioneering.
The challenges
don’t seem that big now,
but back at that time
they were a really big deal.
But the coolest thing
was how Jehovah helped me.
Prayer to Jehovah
helped me overcome my fears.
My family was
a massive help from Jehovah.
Because my dad was the one
who first encouraged me to pioneer,
when I did start pioneering,
he promised that I would have
the full support of my family.
When I spoke to brothers and sisters
who spent their youth
in the full-time service
that really helped me
because it was really encouraging,
and it really motivated me
to want to make my own memories
and my own experiences
in the full-time service.
So there were
practical things I could do.
I didn’t have a car;
I just walked or I caught the bus.
I had to work out
what my priorities were first.
So I had to find out how many hours
would I have to go witnessing every week.
So then I just sat down
and I looked at every day
and planned out which days
I could go witnessing,
which days I had to go to school,
and also allocated time
so that I could do my homework and study.
Having a schedule
was really good
because I could see it
all out in front of me,
and I could see
that the hour requirement
was actually attainable,
so that made it a lot less daunting.
I first set short-term goals of pioneering
in the special months of activity.
Then I was able
to begin continuous auxiliary,
and then eventually
I started regular pioneering.
One of the best things I did
to prepare myself for pioneering
was to auxiliary pioneer beforehand.
It really set me up
to be able to overcome
any challenges
that I faced while I was pioneering.
I thought about Malachi 3:10.
I knew I trusted in Jehovah,
but this was my chance
to test him out.
I prayed,
put my trust in Jehovah,
and put my application in.
After my form
was in for pioneering,
a brother, with time,
a brother called me and offered me work.
I had unemployment
for three months,
which wasn’t a good time.
But during that time,
I had Jehovah as my main focus.
And so he supported me,
and he didn’t let me down.
Asking brothers and sisters to come
and work with me,
maybe on days that I knew
that I wouldn’t get as much support,
really helped.
That helped me to organize
my hours a little bit more,
and also I’d get to know
my brothers and sisters more as well.
One of the greatest joys of pioneering
has been to pioneer with Mum.
And we had the privilege of going
to the pioneer school together,
which was really special.
Psalm 16:8 reminds me
that Jehovah is right beside me.
When I’m preaching,
it’s like Jehovah is holding my hand.
So with full-time service,
I love making Jehovah happy.
With everything that he has given me,
I’m finally able to give something back.
Looking back
—pioneering—
it was the best decision
I’ve ever made.
It’s opened up
so many different avenues
of service to Jehovah,
and it helped me also
to have that real desire
to want to stay
in full-time service.
Helping someone
on the road to everlasting life,
it’s the best feeling ever;
and it’s really irreplaceable.
The only thing I can say,
“As a young person, start pioneering!”