Welcome to JW Broadcasting.
In this month’s program,
we will feature the study methods
that are used in Gilead School.
For a moment, let’s imagine ourselves
starting our day as a Gilead student.
See you later.
See you, Nathan.
Morning.
Have a good day in class.
Thank you.
Welcome.
How are you?
Good morning.
Hello, Nathan.
Lyubomyr.
Nice to see you.
How are you?
Good.
I am good.
Good to see you.
How was your night?
It was good.
A long night of studying,
but it was worth it.
I’m really looking forward
to the lesson this morning.
You know, I agree with you.
I feel the same.
The information we have been studying
is really touching my heart.
I know what you mean.
I feel like I’ve become
more of a spiritual person,
and my relationship with Jehovah
has become so much stronger.
Good morning everyone.
Very good to see you all here this morning.
What are the study methods
that are helping the students grow
in their relationship with Jehovah?
And more importantly,
how can we apply these methods
in our own personal study?
We’ll find the answers and more.
Here are some
of the highlights of what’s ahead.
These brothers and sisters describe
how they approach their personal Bible study.
They’re from different parts of the world,
but they share
many common study techniques.
What questions do they ask
as they read and meditate on the Bible?
How does their deep study take them
beyond the basics of Bible understanding?
Young ones,
are you digging deep into God’s Word now?
How can this help you
make the truth your own?
And can you succeed even without the support
of those spiritually close to you?
This sister’s experience will show us
the benefits of searching the Bible
as if for hidden treasures.
Can you be ready to make
a wise choice in matters of conscience?
Do study habits affect
how well-prepared and well-trained
your conscience is
for an unexpected situation?
We’ll see how
the sister in this dramatization
answers these questions.
This is JW Broadcasting for July 2018.
We begin with an archived interview
of Brother Allan Boyle.
Among his many assignments,
Brother Boyle spent 37 years
in the Art Department
at world headquarters.
The beautiful and accurate illustrations
produced there enhance our study,
helping us to visualize
and meditate on what we are reading.
An assignment
to create these pictures is exciting,
but it requires
that a person have spiritual qualities.
Artists collaborate
and must humbly listen
to each other’s comments.
They must apply direction
from “the faithful and discreet slave”
to prepare artwork
that we can take in as spiritual food.
As you’ll hear Brother Boyle describe,
a person must be
an avid student of the Bible.
Listen to Brother Boyle’s story,
and note what he said was needed
for him to do his assignment well.
I was born in 1933.
I got to the age of 18,
and one suppertime
my mother
had invited the company servant,
as they were called back then,
to come for supper.
He asked me
what I was going to do with my life.
I said to him,
“Well, I’m going to pioneer.”
So three weeks later,
at the convention in London,
I got baptized and then
went pioneering six months after that.
I was 21 when I was in the circuit work,
and that was a wonderful experience.
And in those days,
of course, you didn’t have a car.
I used to have a motorbike.
And I’d go around
on the motorbike with my briefcase
and my typewriter
and my clothes in the other case on the back.
Yeah, that was very exciting.
I was invited to go to Gilead,
and that was wonderfully exciting.
We had 103 in the class.
Little did I know at the time
that I would be sent
as a missionary to Ireland.
My friend had been invited to go down
to London Bethel to do the artwork there.
I’d always wanted to be in Bethel.
I thought, ‘Well, why don’t I just
call him up and congratulate him?’
So that’s what I did,
and he told me that he decided not to go.
So he said: “If you’re
still interested, why don’t you go?
You know, call them up and let them know.”
So that’s what I did.
The next morning, I called up London Bethel,
and within a week I was
in London Bethel doing the graphics work
for the magazines, you know.
It was a wonderful, thrilling experience.
I was in London Bethel for a couple of years,
in 1977 to 1979,
and then Brother Barry invited me
to come over to Brooklyn Bethel.
You know that you’re doing
something that’s going to be beneficial
and helpful to other people,
even to people in different
languages, in different cultures.
A little painting that you do
is going to help them
to get a memory of something significant.
One of the most beautiful things
about working in the Art Department
and doing paintings
is that it makes you do research.
You have to investigate.
Is this the right time of the day?
Is it night? Is it day?
What did the sky look like?
What was it like
before the Flood when Noah built the ark?
How did he paint underneath the ark?
How did he waterproof it?
Because that’s
the most important part, isn’t it?
He used bitumen.
OK, how did he get underneath the ark?
Maybe he put it on stilts.
You have to come up
with all these little questions in your mind.
To do the research was very rewarding.
This is a little model of a boat,
and underneath the deck they used to keep
a ballast sack of 110 pounds (50 kg) of sand.
It says in the Scriptures
that Jesus was asleep on “a pillow.”
Apparently, this was
the ballast sack that he was asleep on.
And actually,
in the Kingdom Interlinear translation,
it doesn’t say
that he was asleep on “a pillow”;
it says he was asleep on “the pillow.”
So apparently,
back 2,000 years ago in that area,
everybody knew what “the pillow” was.
I remember meeting
a brother once who’d been to Siberia,
and he’d taken a snapshot
of somebody’s kitchen in Siberia.
And to my amazement, on the wall
—pinned with drawing pins on the wall—
was one of the pages of the publications
that we produced here at Brooklyn.
And so, remarkably,
it’s wonderful to feel
that whatever we do here
—if it’s support work,
if it’s the painting,
and, of course, we need
a lot of support work for the paintings—
all of what we do here
has an effect upon the brothers and sisters
out there in the world, wherever it might be.
And you really feel
that your time is well spent.
You’re adorning the Word of truth.
You’re helping other people
to be taught something from the Bible,
which is going to be to their benefit.
It’s been very rewarding and thrilling
to be in Jehovah’s service,
and I’ve really enjoyed it.
Allan Boyle finished
his earthly course in 2016.
Those in the Art Department
who worked with him
remember his enthusiasm
and his thorough attention to detail.
What Allan brought to his assignment
was rooted
in his own personal study of the Bible.
He found it rewarding to do the research
needed to illustrate Bible scenes.
Today, the Writing Department supplies
a team of researchers to assist the artists.
But did you recall
what Allan said helped his research?
He asked questions
about the scenes he was painting!
These same kinds of questions
are part of the study methods
Gilead students learn in class.
And these are the same methods
that we’ll learn about in this program.
How would you feel
if you received an invitation
to attend the next class of Gilead School?
For many, it has been
a lifelong dream to attend Gilead.
The course helps students
keep “a tight grip on the word of life.”
For others, the idea of five months
of intense study seems intimidating.
We know we need to study,
but we may find
it a challenge to get the most
out of the time we spend
reading God’s Word.
In this program, we will discuss
why study is so important,
what it means to study something,
and how you can get more
from your study sessions.
Since most cannot attend Gilead,
we will demonstrate
the method used in Gilead School.
First, why is study so important?
Only by study can we
keep “a tight grip on the word of life.”
When the apostle Paul penned these words,
he was imprisoned and nearing the end
of his action-packed life.
He had been the “apostle to the nations”
and had spent his best years
taking the Word of God
to the then-known world.
As he reflected on the fruits of his labors,
he wrote a letter to his friends
in the congregation in Philippi in Macedonia.
Inspired by holy spirit, he wrote words
that would aid his brothers
to gain the prize of eternal life.
These words are found
at Philippians 2:15, 16.
Let’s read them:
“So that you may come to be
blameless and innocent,
“children of God
without a blemish in the midst
“of a crooked and twisted generation,
“among whom you are shining
as illuminators in the world,
keeping a tight grip on the word of life.”
Imagine the joy Paul felt
when he was reunited
in the heavenly resurrection
with those who listened to his admonition
to keep “a tight grip on the word of life”!
Whether we have
the heavenly or earthly hope,
Paul’s words can help us gain
the prize of eternal life.
They imprint on our hearts and minds
a basic exhortation
that will lead us through these last days
and into our everlasting reward.
The question is, Will we remain
‘blameless and without blemish
in the midst of this crooked
and twisted generation’ of our day?
Will we rejoice with other faithful servants
of God in the new world?
We can and we will
if we take to heart Paul’s counsel
to keep “a tight grip on the word of life.”
Next, what does it mean to study?
Stop and contemplate this word picture
for keeping a tight grip.
Imagine a hiker who has slipped near a ledge.
But before falling over the cliff,
he grabs hold of a tree branch.
How tight do you think
his grip will be on that branch?
This is not a halfhearted effort.
Likewise, keeping a tight grip
on the word of life
is not just a mechanical routine,
nor is it a casual habit.
It requires strenuous effort.
It involves actively living
by the truths in God’s Word.
To do this, we must understand
more than what God
expressly commands and condemns.
We must be able to identify principles,
or life lessons, contained in the Bible.
Once identified, we must understand
how to match these valuable truths
to specific situations in our lives.
Then we must allow these principles
to influence our decisions
and guide our reaction
to trials and temptations.
Ask yourself,
‘How strong is my grip
on the word of life?’
To answer that,
let’s consider
the fundamentals of Bible study.
This is not about old methods or new methods,
nor is it about what device you are using.
This discussion transcends devices.
Study requires active thinking.
In a world of increasing distractions,
this is becoming an even greater challenge.
We’ve often received instant information
that enables us to quickly recite facts,
but this is not the same as active thinking.
Through active thinking,
we draw meaningful conclusions in our hearts.
We are certainly grateful
for all the study tools we’ve been given.
We should use these to the full.
At the same time, we need to be careful
that these tools do not cause us
to develop mental laziness.
Devices can help us to access information,
but they can’t think for us.
We must work hard if we are
to develop new patterns of thinking.
For example, if we study
The Watchtower on a device,
we can use the hyperlink feature
to read the Scriptures.
With a simple touch,
we quickly find and read the verse.
That is good!
If you regularly do this,
you get a grip on the word of life.
But would you like to get
a tight grip on the word of life?
To get a tight grip requires more effort
than a swipe of a finger
and then swiftly moving on.
You need to slow down
and analyze the material.
Only then will the information you study
become imprinted on your mind and heart,
leaving a clear and distinct impression.
How, then, can I get more out of my study?
Let’s demonstrate a method
taught during Gilead School.
It involves the use of six questions.
The following poem, written
by English journalist Rudyard Kipling,
can help guide better thinking:
“I keep six honest serving-men
“(They taught me all I knew);
“Their names are What and Why
“and When and How
and Where and Who.”
When studying God’s Word,
ask yourself these questions
and then do research in our publications
to get the facts
and discern the spiritual lessons.
To illustrate how to do this,
let’s open our Bibles to Genesis chapter 49
and look at verses 22 through 25.
First, we ask the when and where.
Now, with some research,
we learn that Jacob
spoke these words near the end of his life.
He was in Egypt,
but what he described
takes us back to Canaan some 40 years
when his son Joseph was a young man.
Now we have
a clearer picture of these verses.
So now, let’s read and analyze verse 22:
“Joseph is the offshoot of a fruitful tree,
a fruitful tree by a spring,
whose branches extend over the wall.”
“The offshoot of a fruitful tree.”
Who is the “fruitful tree”?
It is Joseph’s father, Jacob.
How was he fruitful?
He bore many children.
Joseph’s “branches extend over the wall.”
As Jacob’s offshoot,
Joseph is singled out
for a special blessing
superior to that of his brothers.
Why?
Joseph proved he had
the qualities needed for leadership.
However, of even greater value
than his abilities
was his being a spiritual man.
Let’s read verse 23:
“But the archers kept harassing him
and shot at him and kept harboring
animosity against him.”
“The archers kept harassing him.”
Who are “the archers”?
Joseph’s half brothers.
How?
They shot figuratively at Joseph
—arrows of envy and hatred
and jealousy were used to attack him.
Now, eventually,
his brothers sold him into slavery.
Now let’s read verse 24:
“And yet his bow remained in place,
“and his hands stayed strong and agile.
“This was from the hands
of the powerful one of Jacob,
from the shepherd, the stone of Israel.”
“His bow remained in place.”
How?
Despite the repeated attacks,
Joseph repaid animosity with kindness.
Joseph endured this ill-treatment
and did not weaken in his devotion to God.
Now we ask, How?
How is it that Joseph
kept a spiritual outlook
despite the harassment and animosity?
Let’s read verse 25:
“He [Joseph] is from the God of your father,
“and he will help you,
and he is with the Almighty,
“and he will bless you with the blessings
of the heavens above,
“with the blessings of the deep below,
with the blessings of the breasts and womb.”
“He is with the Almighty.”
Joseph had Jehovah’s help.
The Almighty was by his side through it all.
We’ve used our questions
to get the facts of the account,
but we’re not done.
Now let’s use them
to take our study to a spiritual plane.
Next, let’s ask a what question.
What does this account
teach us about Jehovah?
Jehovah never abandons his loyal servants.
Even in the depths of prison,
Joseph was not alone.
Jehovah found ways to bless Joseph.
Now make the connection
to Jehovah’s people today,
including yourself.
Jehovah will never abandon us.
Rather, he shows loyal love
to all those who serve him whole-souled.
Would Jehovah let Joseph
remain in prison indefinitely?
No.
At the appointed time, relief came.
Joseph was raised from a prisoner in chains
to the second most powerful man in Egypt
—from prison to palace in one day.
Make the connection to us.
Our trials are temporary.
Jehovah will soon bring relief,
even in unexpected or surprising ways.
Meanwhile, we are never alone;
Jehovah is with us.
Again, let’s ask the question, How?
How does the account
contribute to the Bible’s theme?
Joseph suffered, but his suffering led
to the survival of Abraham’s offspring,
leading to the Messiah.
Joseph’s account
is not just a riveting story.
It directly contributed
to the development of Jehovah’s purpose.
Think about this:
In spite of the poor conduct of his brothers,
Joseph forgave them and took the initiative
to improve their relationship with him.
Joseph’s attitude
was a reflection of Jehovah’s attitude.
With their family reunited,
Jehovah also forgave Joseph’s brothers
and took the initiative
in restoring their relationship with Himself.
In fact, Jehovah gave Joseph’s brother Judah
the honor of being
an ancestor of the Messiah.
What are the lessons in this account?
Let’s highlight just one.
Genesis 49:23:
“But the archers kept harassing him
and shot at him and kept harboring
animosity against him.”
Arrows of animosity were fired at Joseph.
Recall Joseph’s response in verse 24?
“And yet his bow remained in place,
and his hands stayed strong and agile.”
In other words, he did not return fire.
His bow remained in place.
Reflect on the last time
you were wronged by someone.
How did we react to what we experienced?
Did we seek to vindicate ourselves
or insist on our rights?
Did we fire arrows of animosity in return,
or did we show mercy and loyal love?
Did our reaction reveal
that God’s spirit was operative on us?
Like Joseph, we know
we will have Jehovah’s approval
even if we are wronged or experience trials
that make us feel like we are in prison.
Reflective questions like these
enable us to make the account our own.
It becomes part of us,
part of our way of thinking,
our way of acting.
This nourishes our relationship with Jehovah.
This type of study rewards us
not simply with a collection of facts
that impress us today
and are forgotten tomorrow.
Rather, it leaves us
with core principles that we remember,
that influence our decisions,
and that guide our lives.
We tighten our grip on the word of life.
Let’s review the fundamentals of study.
Again, this is not
about old methods or new methods
or about what device you are using.
This discussion transcends devices.
It’s about basic methods of Bible study.
We can liken these three phases of study
to gathering, sifting, and baking grain.
Gathering is when we read the Bible.
We don’t run through the field
grabbing just handfuls of grain;
we systematically harvest the field.
Sifting is when we sort out what we gathered,
answering who, what, where,
when, why, and how to get the facts.
Baking is when we think
—“turning up the heat” in our mind and heart—
something no one else can do for you.
The questions we ask
can take our study to a spiritual plane.
Most importantly,
what does this teach me about Jehovah?
How does it contribute to the Bible’s theme?
And the bottom line:
What is the lesson for me?
Jehovah gave us a mind
that is begging to learn.
It is a gift with the capacity
to cultivate thinking ability.
When we make the effort
to unearth gems from God’s Word,
we find that study
is rewarding and delightful.
More importantly, our study skills enable us
to keep a tight grip on the word of life.
A tight grip on God’s Word
will make our life better now
and give us the opportunity
to continue learning
about our heavenly Father for all eternity.
Joseph’s account
was an excellent example for us
to demonstrate
the fundamentals of Bible study.
During our discussion,
we used pictures
to help bring the account to life.
As we learned
from Brother Boyle’s interview,
pictures and illustrations
give us an accurate image
to use in our meditation.
And if there’s a video,
we have yet another way
to imagine ourselves in the account.
So we’re excited
to introduce this month’s music video
depicting the trials
and blessings that Joseph experienced.
It reminds us that, like Joseph,
when we have Jehovah,
we are never alone.
Abandoned and betrayed,
Forsaken and alone,
Despair my one companion,
My heart within me like a stone
With no one here for me,
No kindly word of care,
Who’ll offer consolation?
My heavy burden, who can share?
I’m not alone;
I never was.
I’ll never be,
And all because
Jehovah knows;
Jehovah sees.
He hears my prayer;
He’s here with me.
Whatever comes my way,
I’m never alone.
Whatever I may lose
By sticking close to you,
No matter who may fail me,
I know you’ll never be untrue.
You’re close to me, O God,
And never far away.
My faith, my hope, reliance​—
I know you never will betray.
I’m not alone;
I never was.
I’ll never be,
And all because
Jehovah knows;
Jehovah sees.
He hears my prayer;
He’s here with me.
Whatever comes my way,
I’m never alone.
I never was.
I’ll never be,
And all because
Jehovah knows;
Jehovah sees.
He hears my prayer;
He’s here with me.
Whatever comes my way,
I’m never alone.
Have you ever felt as Joseph did?
There were times when Joseph’s life
was not turning out as he had hoped.
He no doubt wondered
if he’d ever be set free from prison
or if he’d ever see his father again
or his younger brother, Benjamin.
But Joseph knew that his God, Jehovah,
never lost sight of him.
This surely helped him endure.
We could be in a painful situation
that seems to drag on endlessly.
But when we study
a Bible account like Joseph’s
—asking the six questions—
we can fully understand
and apply the lessons in our life.
Then we can build the same faith that he had
—that we too are never alone.
Let’s now listen to brothers and sisters
who are using
the study methods we’ve discussed.
Some learned them in Gilead School,
others from Gilead graduates,
or good examples
in their families and congregations.
They’ve also applied what they learned
from our publications
about good study habits.
See if any of the ways they study
could help you keep
“a tight grip” on God’s Word.
The more you study,
the more you understand Jehovah.
The more you understand Jehovah,
the more you love him.
Jehovah clearly tells us:
“My thoughts are not your thoughts.”
So if we want to understand
Jehovah’s thinking better,
we need to dig deep in our study,
and then we share those thoughts with others.
Personal study is like fuel
that keeps you going.
Personally, I’m not a good student,
but I really learned how to study the Bible.
The Bible came alive during Gilead.
Self-discipline is involved
—very much.
I overcome the tiredness aspect
of Bible study by not doing it
at a time of day
when I know I’m going to be tired.
I can be tired for other things later on
—but not for that.
Each session of my Bible study
begins with a prayer,
“Please help me recognize
it is counsel for me,
and then give me the strength
to work on it.”
I have a color-coded system,
so I know what certain things stand for.
I have a particular color
for Jehovah’s good hand in people’s lives;
I have another color for warning examples;
I have another for fine examples to imitate.
You have to get behind the information,
not just focus on one verse or one chapter.
See who’s involved, the time,
the conditions, how many people are there,
and then you’ll get
the true meaning of the verse.
John 1:1,
who is “the Word”?
We can go to verse 18.
“Begotten” meant
he had a beginning,
a time when he started
—when he began—
in heaven with his Father.
That’s where he was.
Philippians 4:6, 7 is a scripture
that I’ve read many times over.
“The peace of God that excels all thought.”
OK, how do you get that?
It’s from having
a good relationship with Jehovah.
How is it that God’s peace
‘guards your heart’?
“By means of Christ Jesus” our Lord.
And I said: “Why by Jesus?
“Because Jesus paid the ransom;
that ransom is what makes possible
a relationship with Jehovah.”
So it almost goes full circle.
I attended a School for Congregation Elders
that had Gilead graduates as instructors.
One of the methods is to analyze
a certain Bible account
from different perspectives.
We can’t see
the whole picture from one angle.
I share my research results
with Bible students,
and that helps them
to know Jehovah better,
and it helps them to see
that what they’re studying
is of practical value.
I had studied up on Jacob;
he wrestled all night
with an angel.
And I wanted to share it
with some of my friends.
One of the brothers
that happened to sit around
when this discussion was going on
came back to me, and he said to me:
“I had concluded my arrangements
“to quit full-time service.
“But after listening to that discussion,
I’ve decided that I’m no longer stopping.”
And that was
such a wonderful moment for me.
I thanked Jehovah.
When I learned that I
was going to become a mom,
I said, “Jehovah, if this little one
could love you,
then I’ll get to keep him forever.”
And I began to teach everything
I was learning to him.
So it’s a matter
of keeping my faith strong,
and there’s no shortcut.
Every session of study
that is properly done with good meditation
adds a new pillar
to the strength of our faith.
I look forward to those times
when I can, you know,
run upstairs by myself
and just shut everything off,
and it’s just me and Jehovah.
Life today is very unpredictable,
but I’ve come to see that as long as I
keep a tight grip on God’s Word,
nothing can “separate [me] from God’s love.”
The joy these brothers and sisters get
from their personal study
is clearly heard in their expressions.
Recall what they said:
“The more you understand Jehovah,
the more you love him.”
“Study is like fuel that keeps you going.”
And “I can shut everything off,
and it’s just me and Jehovah.”
We also heard them ask the six questions:
who, what, where, when, why, and how.
They also used tools for research
and note-taking that works for them.
Is there something you saw
or that we discussed
that you’d like to add
to your study routine?
If so, try it out.
Young ones, it’s true
that the more you understand Jehovah,
the more you love him.
And what a blessing you have
if your family worships Jehovah with you
and teaches you how to draw close to him.
But some young ones
have had to build their faith
without their family’s support.
Listen to the experience of Ersi Royer
from the United States.
What spiritual decision did she face
at just 14 years old?
And what did she do
that illustrates the value
of deep personal study?
Growing up,
it wasn’t the typical,
“My mom is a pioneer, my dad is an elder,
and we’re doing great in the congregation.”
My family life wasn’t the best,
so why would I want to do this religion
that nobody is happy
in our family with?
And I think that can make you feel
very alone or odd
or awkward or secluded.
And at that time,
I was graduating eighth grade.
There were dances;
friends were hanging out, going to parties.
And I remember thinking:
‘Wow, these look like really nice kids.
Why aren’t I doing that?’
I hadn’t really delved into the Bible enough
to answer questions
that I really needed to know.
I went in prayer to Jehovah and said:
“I’m so sorry, but today I’m not a Witness.
I’m going to try to prove
everything that I’ve been taught is wrong.”
I asked him that if he’s real,
to help me understand.
So I went in my room
and shut the door.
I got every book off the shelf.
I started off organized,
but by the end of the evening,
I had books
all over the place with pages open.
The more I kept reading about Jehovah,
the more the next topic would take me
to then connect the scriptures.
Jesus is linked to Jehovah;
the angels are linked to Jehovah;
the resurrection is linked to Jehovah.
So you can’t believe in one thing
and not everything else
if you really want to know the truth.
And so that’s what did it for me,
especially the scripture in Psalms
when it said
that ‘you saw even the embryo of me.’
And it was an emotional scripture for me
because I thought:
‘Wow,
‘my parents aren’t doing great
in the truth right now.
‘But Jehovah found a way to find me,
‘and he knew what I could be.
‘Now I have my answer.
I don’t have an excuse.
‘Jehovah gave me enough knowledge
that now I’m responsible.
I now need to act on that
and show my love in return for him.’
Within a week, I found another sister
in the hall that was really helpful
in me getting out
in service quite often.
I don’t think to this day she ever knew
how much I appreciated that.
Although things were declining
in our family spiritually,
I was able to get baptized.
As I progressed spiritually,
I could see that I did not have
the support of my family,
but I had to trust that Jehovah
would help me through it.
And at least by the time I got home,
if there was an issue,
I had the strength of the meeting
and the brothers and sisters
and joy that they
couldn’t take away from me.
I remember I came home one day
with some friends.
It was a nice day
—encouraging, upbuilding.
We pulled into our driveway;
they dropped me off
and said good-bye.
My parents were really upset
when they came and met me at the door.
They couldn’t fully understand
why I was making my decisions
the way I was
to serve Jehovah more fully.
We just could not agree
on where my relationship
with Jehovah was going.
And at that point,
I left with the clothes on my back.
In a matter of a few minutes,
my life forever changed.
I had a spiritual aunt that took me in,
helped me gather myself together,
and literally fed me, clothed me,
helped me spiritually.
And so then, my support became Jehovah
and the congregation.
I remember that a sister told me years ago,
“Be who you needed when you were young.”
And so when I look at those little ones,
I look at myself and say,
‘How could I have benefited
from someone taking the time for me
when I was that age?’
I’ve always tried remembering the young ones
—because that’s just part of who I am—
and making sure that they know
that they’re not alone.
If there is a young one out there
who isn’t sure
if this is the truth or not,
I would like them to know
that Jehovah knows
who they are,
and he’s finding a way
for them to know him.
Jehovah is real,
he knows them by name,
he wants them to live,
and he’s fighting for them.
How amazing that young Ersi chose
to spend an entire day studying
—proving to herself
that Jehovah knew her and loved her.
But this was no onetime study marathon.
From there, she worked to develop
the study habits she needed
to endure, grow,
and become a spiritual person.
She pioneered for several years,
and now serves at Bethel
with her husband, Jeff.
In my conversation with Ersi,
she expressed her love for her family
and the hope that someday in the future
she’ll be reunited with them spiritually.
There’s no situation in life
that cannot be handled better than by seeking
Jehovah’s guidance in the Bible.
That’s certainly true
in matters of conscience.
In these situations,
Jehovah does not tell us
what to do with a command,
but his Word gives us the principles
we use to train our conscience.
In this dramatization,
Emma has to make a difficult decision.
How is her conscience involved,
and what steps
does she take to make her decision?
Every day we make choices
that can affect
our relationship with Jehovah.
When there’s a clear Scriptural command,
the right choice may seem easy.
But what if there’s not?
How can we be sure
we’re making a wise decision?
An invitation to our niece’s wedding arrived.
Thomas was excited about it.
I was excited too.
But the ceremony
was being held at a local church.
I wondered if it would still be OK
for me to attend.
Even though Thomas wasn’t yet willing
to accept a Bible study,
he gradually softened over the years
since I came into the truth.
I knew he understood why
I would never enter a church for worship,
but what about attending a wedding?
Jehovah approves of weddings.
That afternoon,
I went to help Amy plan a menu
for the pioneer school lunch coming up.
She noticed I was a bit distracted,
so I told her my concerns about the wedding.
But you’re not thinking of going, are you?
Amy sure had a strong opinion on the matter,
but I didn’t feel
she really understood my situation.
Although I appreciated her concern,
I felt like she was judging me.
The next day, I decided
to visit Charlotte and Allan
and ask their advice.
Like me, Charlotte had come into the truth
many years before Allan,
so they really understood my situation.
Is Amy right?
Would it be wrong to attend the wedding?
What would you do if you were me?
Charlotte explained that in situations
where there’s no specific Bible command,
it becomes a matter of conscience.
And what one person’s conscience allows
may be different from another.
The important thing
is that we make decisions
that leave us with a good conscience.
But how do I do that?
Dear Emma, it’s really a matter of training.
Allan showed me the scripture
at Hebrews 5:14,
where the apostle Paul wrote:
“Solid food belongs to mature people,
“to those who through use
“have their powers of discernment trained
to distinguish both right and wrong.”
But Paul didn’t just write those words;
he lived them.
He carefully studied
the principles in God’s Word.
And as a result,
he was able to make decisions
that left him with a good conscience.
So even when there’s no stated law
on a matter,
we can always find a Bible principle
that can give us insight into God’s thinking.
So I made it a matter of prayer,
and then I got to work.
I researched articles
in the Watch Tower Publications Index
and the Research Guide.
I found a really good thought
in chapter 2 of the “God’s Love” book.
I also read about others
who faced similar situations
and what Bible principles they found helpful.
Then I meditated on all these.
As I kept studying,
I was able to bring my conscience
in harmony with Jehovah’s spirit,
not just with my heart.
I realized that having
a Bible-trained conscience
doesn’t mean everyone
will always think exactly alike
—and that’s OK.
But if we train our conscience
by applying Bible principles,
it will guide us along in life,
so that each of us
can remain in God’s love.
What did our sister, Emma,
do that we can imitate?
When she realized
that she needed more information,
she got to work!
She studied in order
to train her conscience
and to make a decision
that left her conscience clean.
We can do the same
when a conscience matter comes up.
But we can do more.
We can prepare in advance,
train our conscience on matters
that do not have clear Bible commands,
and study Bible principles
that teach our conscience
the rules it should work with.
Then, when we need it, it’s ready.
We can trust it and make decisions
in harmony with a Bible-trained conscience.
We urge you brothers and sisters:
Keep “a tight grip on the word of life.”
That’s what our program has been about.
We learned why
it’s essential to stay close to God
and to receive his gift of everlasting life.
But what’s more,
we learned practical ways to do it
using tried and true methods
of personal Bible study.
We may not have
an opportunity to attend Gilead
or another theocratic school,
but Jehovah shows all of us
how to benefit from his written Word.
What an expression of God’s love!
To prepare this month’s program,
our team spent time
with the Theocratic Schools Department
at the world headquarters facility
in Patterson, New York.
This has been the home
for Gilead School since 1995.
And since arriving here,
47 classes have graduated.
Gilead School began
with its first class in 1943,
and since then,
close to 9,000 students have been trained.
When students come to class each day,
the writings and models on display
put their mind on spiritual things
as they get ready to study God’s Word.
Isaiah 11:9 says:
“The earth will certainly be filled
with the knowledge of Jehovah
as the waters cover the sea.”
Our worldwide brotherhood
works in harmony with that prophecy.
It’s fitting then that here in the classroom,
lectures cover every part of the Bible,
exploring background information
to get the sense of the account.
. . . probably still got bruises.
And Paul is telling them, very honestly,
‘we have to enter through many tribulations.’
Can you imagine, you’re sitting there
and you’re looking at this man
bruised and cut,
and he’s saying,
‘We (you and I)
have to go through many tribulations.’
Students participate freely,
drawing lessons that they can use
in their life and assignments.
It impresses me to see
that the Christian congregation in our time
follows exactly
the pattern that was used back then.
Studying in the Theocratic Schools’ library
is a cherished part of their day.
In a quiet, relaxed setting,
they associate figuratively
with “the faithful and discreet slave,”
searching and taking in the spiritual food
that nourishes
and strengthens their relationship
with their heavenly Father, Jehovah.
Students benefit from the hard work
of the school instructors.
Under the direction
of the Teaching Committee
of the Governing Body,
they manage the curriculum
for Gilead and other schools
that are taught here and in the field.
Through their diligent efforts
and Jehovah’s blessing,
the Theocratic Schools staff
count it a privilege
to serve their brothers
and the Governing Body.
We send you
our sincere Christian love and greetings.
Thank you for joining us this month.
This is JW Broadcasting
from the world headquarters
of Jehovah’s Witnesses.