Welcome to another edition
of JW Broadcasting.
Here are this month’s highlights:
What is it like to engage
in the special metropolitan witnessing work
in the bustling United States city
of San Francisco?
We’ll hear encouraging experiences
from brothers and sisters
who preach
in this diverse language field.
Can young ones
serve Jehovah successfully
even if their family’s
spiritual activity stops?
We’ll hear from a sister who tells
what kept her love for Jehovah growing
throughout her family’s
busy show business career.
In our Preparing for Marriage series,
we’ll learn how those who are dating
can get to know
“the secret person of the heart”
before making
a solemn lifelong commitment.
And we’ll discuss
the beautiful quality of loyalty,
including an interview with a couple
who has served Jehovah loyally
for over 60 years.
All this is ahead
on JW Broadcasting for August 2016.
This month’s theme is taken
from David’s poetic song to Jehovah
at Psalm 18:25, which states:
“With someone loyal you act in loyalty.”
The Hebrew term “act in loyalty”
reminds us
of God’s loyal love
—that is love motivated
by commitment,
integrity, loyalty,
and deep attachment.
So loyalty is more
than just a feeling;
it is active;
it’s rooted in love.
How comforting it is
to know that Jehovah
lovingly attaches himself
to those who are loyal to him!
But what motivated David
to write the words
at Psalm 18:25?
The superscription reveals
that it was composed
after “Jehovah rescued him
from the hand of all his enemies
and from the hand of Saul.”
Think of the great joy
and relief he must have felt
after experiencing firsthand
Jehovah’s loyal love
and mighty saving acts.
However, throughout his life,
David experienced
disloyalty at its worst:
from his king, Saul;
from his wife Michal;
from his trusted counselor Ahithophel;
and from his son Absalom.
He felt the deep hurt of betrayal
by those he trusted and loved most.
Loyalty is a choice.
What do we find when we look back
at David’s life?
David chose to stay loyal to God.
From a humble shepherd boy
caring for his sheep
to a valiant king
caring for the nation,
he proved
to be someone loyal,
a man agreeable
to Jehovah’s heart.
But it can be a real test
to maintain loyalty to God
when we face injustices.
Imagine the desperate situation
that David and his mighty warriors
experienced when they
were fugitives,
forced to hide in the wilderness,
often low on provisions.
They saw firsthand
King Saul’s jealous rage.
But what choice did David make
when urged by his men
to seize the opportunity
to take Saul’s life?
Notice what David told his men
at 1 Samuel 24:6:
“It is unthinkable
from Jehovah’s standpoint
“that I should do
such a thing to my lord,
“the anointed of Jehovah,
by lifting my hand against him,
for he is the anointed of Jehovah.”
David knew that if he remained loyal,
Jehovah would remain loyal to him
—He would show him loyal love.
He humbly put aside
his personal feelings
and viewed matters
from Jehovah’s perspective.
He chose to wait patiently
for Jehovah to “act in loyalty.”
We’ll soon be facing
life-changing events foretold in the Bible
that will test our loyalty
to Jehovah and his organization.
So now is the time
to strengthen our loyalty!
As we do, we can be sure
that Jehovah knows our circumstances
—perhaps injustices
we have experienced—
and will reward our loyal service.
So ask yourself, ‘What loyal actions
will motivate Jehovah to be loyal to me?’
Let’s consider three areas.
First, we can be loyal
to Jehovah by defending him.
But Jehovah is
the Sovereign of the universe.
How can we come to his defense?
We can learn how
from the fine example of Elihu!
In the book of Job,
Elihu listened patiently as Job
and his three false comforters spoke.
Notice Elihu’s reaction
at Job 32:2, 3:
“His anger blazed against Job
“for trying to prove himself
right rather than God.
“He was also very angry
with Job’s three companions
“because they could not find an answer
but had declared God wicked.”
A fire of righteous indignation
was burning inside young Elihu.
In Job 36:2, 3,
he loyally comes
to Jehovah’s defense saying:
“Be patient with me
a little longer while I explain,
“for I still have words
to speak on God’s behalf.
“I will speak comprehensively
about what I know,
and I will ascribe
righteousness to my Maker.”
Elihu courageously proved loyal
by praising,
and, yes, defending God.
Why do we need to come
to Jehovah’s defense today?
Because our loving heavenly Father
is blasphemed in so many ways.
False religions claim
that he’s part of a Trinity
and that he torments people
eternally in burning hell.
Others say that he
does not exist or if he does,
he doesn’t really care about us.
We know that such lies
come from Satan the Devil.
We demonstrate our loyalty
by speaking in defense of Jehovah,
thereby proving
Satan the liar that he is.
We boldly and zealously proclaim
that he does exist
as the almighty God;
and that he is
wise, just, and loving,
and that he will soon
bring an end to all evil
and reward his loyal ones
with eternal life.
Jehovah could make
the stones cry out in defense,
yet he honors his loyal Witnesses
—you and me—
with this fine privilege.
Second, we can be loyal
to Jehovah by being loyal
to “the faithful and discreet slave,”
the Governing Body.
Jehovah and Jesus are using
“the faithful and discreet slave”
to feed us spiritually,
so we owe our loyalty to that slave.
But some may say,
‘Isn’t the Governing Body
made up of imperfect men?’
Yes, it is.
The last perfect person to walk
the earth was Jesus himself.
There is no perfect person
or organization on the globe.
But as a long-time faithful brother
used to say,
“This is the best imperfect organization
on earth.”
Jesus didn’t say
the slave would be infallible.
He said it would be
faithful and discreet.
The way we listen to
and obey the faithful slave
has a direct bearing on the strength
of our friendship with God.
In fact, it means our very life.
But what if the Governing Body
serves some spiritual food
that is not to our liking?
Or what if we do not fully understand
or agree with a clarification of a belief?
On one occasion, Jesus’ followers,
including the apostle Peter,
were confronted
with a new teaching.
How did most react?
Notice John 6:60, it states:
“When they heard this,
many of his disciples said:
‘This speech is shocking;
who can listen to it?’”
The result?
Continuing in verse 66:
“Because of this,
many of his disciples
went off to the things behind
and would no longer walk with him.”
But how did Peter respond
when Jesus asked them,
‘Are you too stumbled?’
At John 6:68, we read:
“Simon Peter answered him:
‘Lord, whom shall we go away to?
You have sayings of everlasting life.’”
What loyalty!
Peter’s loyalty
was based on solid evidence
that Jesus was the Messiah.
His loyalty
was evidence of his faith.
That is the kind of loyalty
we want to imitate today.
There are times we must wait on
Jehovah to clarify matters.
In the meantime,
may we prove ourselves loyal like Peter
and follow closely
the lead of the faithful slave,
who closely follow
in the footsteps of their Master, Jesus.
At times, though, we receive
counsel that touches us personally.
For instance, on JW Broadcasting
we’ve received loving reminders
from members of the Governing Body
to be forgiving,
to honor Jehovah
with our valuable things,
and to remain spiritually alert.
Through The Watchtower
and at Christian meetings,
we’re reminded to be careful
about our dress and grooming,
to choose good associates
and wholesome entertainment,
and to remain morally clean.
Are we quick to respond
and make needed adjustments
or do we find ourselves wanting
to defend our personal rights?
A situation
in the apostle Paul’s life
tested his loyalty
to theocratic direction.
It’s found in Acts chapter 21.
As you recall,
Paul arrived in Jerusalem in 56 C.E.
after a very successful missionary tour.
You can imagine his excitement
as he related in detail
“the things God did among
the nations through his ministry.”
After hearing
Paul’s extraordinary account,
the older men revealed to Paul
a problem in Judea
that involved him personally.
Read what they said
at Acts 21:21:
“But they [the Jewish believers]
have heard it rumored about you
“that you have been teaching
all the Jews
“among the nations
an apostasy from Moses,
“telling them
not to circumcise their children
or to follow the customary practices.”
Well, perhaps Paul thought,
‘Me, an apostate?
‘Really?
How can they say such a thing?
‘I just finished
my third missionary tour,
and look how
Jehovah blessed the work!’
Nevertheless, the older men
gave Paul very clear direction
at Acts 21:23, 24
that he likely did not anticipate,
and there it reads:
“So do what we tell you:
“We have four men who have put
themselves under a vow.
“Take these men with you
and cleanse yourself
“ceremonially together with them
and take care of their expenses,
“so that they may have
their heads shaved.
“Then everyone will know
that there is nothing
“to the rumors
they were told about you,
but that you are walking orderly
and you are also keeping the Law.”
Was this the time
for Paul to question
their decision
or demand his rights?
He could have reasoned:
‘Didn’t you read my letter
to the Galatians,
‘where it says the Law was nailed
to the torture stake with Jesus?
‘I did nothing wrong!
‘Why do I have to put on
this pretense
just because a few
are overly sensitive?’
No.
He humbly did
as they requested,
although it
nearly cost him his life.
Yes, it meant swallowing his pride,
but Paul knew
there were bigger issues
involved than his personal rights.
He was considerate
of the consciences of others.
But more importantly,
he showed his loyalty to Jehovah
and to the governing body.
Do we see
the bigger issue in our life?
Let us be determined
to be humble,
flexible,
and obedient like Paul,
and thereby
prove ourselves faithful
to “the faithful and discreet slave.”
Third, we can be loyal to Jehovah
by being loyal to the elders.
We’ve discussed loyalty to Jehovah himself
and to the faithful slave,
but what about direction
we receive
from the elders
in our congregation?
We listen
to our elders give talks
and comments
at the meetings each week,
we work with them
in the ministry,
and we associate
with them.
This regular contact
gives us more opportunities
to see their imperfections
and flaws.
We could begin to focus
on their weaknesses,
weakening our trust
in God’s arrangement.
For example, if you zoom in
on any of our pictures
in our magazines,
all you’ll see are colored spots or pixels.
But when you zoom out,
you see a beautiful photo or painting.
Similarly, when looking at our elders,
don’t zoom in on their imperfections
—the spots of ink—
rather, see the big picture.
Why, then, is it so important
to strengthen our loyalty
to our hard-working, loving shepherds?
Because these “gifts in men”
are an expression
of Jehovah’s loyal love
as they loyally lead, feed,
and protect
his precious sheep.
As the great tribulation nears,
our survival will depend
on our readiness
to respond to their direction,
as they follow
the Governing Body’s direction.
Our loyalty is not to men,
but to Jehovah’s arrangement
made up of imperfect,
but loyal men.
That is a lesson
that Korah, Dathan,
and Abiram refused to learn.
In this clip from the video
Respect Jehovah’s Authority,
listen to Korah’s defiant attitude
toward Moses
as taken
from Numbers chapter 16.
There’s Moses.
That is enough of you
because the whole assembly
are all of them holy
and Jehovah is in their midst.
Why, then, should you lift yourselves up
above the congregation of Jehovah?
Korah and the others
made great pretenses of loyalty to God,
but completely ignored the fact
that Jehovah directly appointed
Moses and Aaron.
Who, then, were
they really murmuring against?
Notice Numbers 26:9:
“This Dathan and Abiram
were chosen ones of the assembly
“who fought against Moses
and Aaron along with Korah’s group
when they fought against Jehovah.”
While focusing on the man Moses
and his imperfections,
they did not really see that it was Jehovah
who was directing the nation.
They were actually fighting
against Jehovah.
Their disloyalty to God’s appointed men
cost them their lives.
But Korah’s sons
made a different choice.
In this next clip, notice an attitude
far different from their father’s.
My father and his companions
actually rebelled
against Jehovah’s authority.
Their envy, pride,
and ambition led to rebellion,
and in the end they brought
dishonor upon themselves.
My father sought glory,
but his glory was short-lived.
I’m glad, though, that my brothers
and I took the right side of the issue.
It must have been hard though.
Yes, it was.
But that helps us to understand
how important it is
that we do not allow
friendships or family
to take priority
over our relationship with Jehovah
and our obedience to him.
That’s what Father
has always told me.
Mmm, yes.
Ultimately, successful direction
for us humans
comes from Jehovah.
We should completely trust
in his choices of appointed ones.
You see, respect for those
whom Jehovah has appointed
shows respect
for Jehovah’s authority.
The loyalty displayed by Korah’s sons
moved Jehovah to act
in loyalty by sparing their lives.
What fine examples
for us to imitate!
May we never find ourselves
fighting against Jehovah
by murmuring
or complaining against those
who he has appointed
to lead his people today.
To see more
of the good and the bad examples
of loyalty
among the Israelites,
we encourage you to watch the entire
Respect Jehovah’s Authority video
on JW Broadcasting.
In review, how can we show
our loyalty to Jehovah?
First, by coming to his defense
as his Witnesses.
Second, by maintaining our loyal support
of “the faithful and discreet slave.”
And third, by loyally following direction
from the appointed elders.
As you imitate faithful examples
like the sons of Korah,
like David, Peter, and Paul,
you will prove to be someone
Jehovah views as loyal
—worthy of receiving
his acts of loyalty forever.
Our second point on loyalty
shows us ways we can follow
the faithful and discreet slave’s direction.
But have you ever wondered how
the Governing Body arrives
at important decisions?
In this Bethel morning worship,
Brother David Splane
answers that very question.
“Well, there’ve been so many changes.
It’s hard to keep up.”
We hear that a lot.
And it’s true.
So the question is,
How do these changes come about?
Does the Governing Body get together
on a Wednesday morning and say,
“Well, what will we change
this week?
Let’s throw the brotherhood
off guard a little bit.”
That would not be
faithful or discreet.
The fact is that,
although changes may seem
to be announced one after another,
the decision to put
the changes into effect
is often years in the making.
Now, one of the first big changes
that the current Governing Body
had to grapple with
had to do with this,
Is it feasible
to have a Branch Committee serving
in the United States?
Now, for years the thought was
that we really couldn’t have
a Branch Committee
functioning in the United States
because the States was host
to the Governing Body
and the world headquarters.
So this was going to be
a big decision,
and it wasn’t taken overnight.
A lot of consultation
with mature,
experienced brothers was necessary.
But finally the decision was made,
and we believe that decision
has had Jehovah’s rich blessing.
We’re proud
of our hard-working Branch Committee,
and we’re happy
to have their support.
We need their support.
Now let’s consider
a couple of other examples.
Beginning in the first week
of January 2009,
the School, Service Meeting,
and the Congregation Book Study
were merged.
Now that decision
was almost ten years
in the making.
As far back as 1999,
it was being discussed.
Well, then, why wasn’t the decision
made ten years earlier?
Because the Governing Body
wanted to be sure.
Will the brothers
have what they need?
Will they have
all of the spiritual food they need
if we merge the meetings?
Now then one Wednesday
—I think it was
about three-thirty in the afternoon—
we’d had a long meeting.
We received two letters
from large branches.
And one of the branches said
that they had many large congregations
with seven or eight book studies,
but with only one elder
and one ministerial servant.
So the elder might conduct
five book studies,
and the ministerial servant
might conduct three,
and then they had all of the parts
on the meetings to prepare.
So all they were doing with their time
was conducting book studies
and preparing parts
for the meetings.
It was hard!
And then the same week we received
a letter from another branch,
and they explained why the attendance
at the book study was so low.
They explained that the publishers
loved the meetings
—all of the meetings—
including the book study.
But they’re very poor,
and they couldn’t afford the bus fare
to attend two midweek meetings;
they had to choose.
And if they attended
the School and Service Meeting,
they could get almost two hours
of spiritual direction,
whereas with the book study,
they would get one.
So most of the time
it was the School
and Service Meeting
that won out.
Well, those two letters
put a real face
on the situation,
and it helped us
to make the decision.
Now, in 2008,
a public edition
and a study edition
of The Watchtower
began to be published.
That decision was
a long time coming.
We discussed the possibility off and on,
but we always said,
“Let’s not be hasty;
let’s wait a little bit.
Let’s see what Jehovah wants.”
The main thing was,
What would Jehovah want?
And how would we know?
We decided to make
a sort of fleece test.
And so in 2006,
we began publishing
one Awake! a month,
but we kept publishing
two Watchtowers.
So that would be three magazines
per month, instead of four.
And the rationale was,
“We’ll try it for a year,
“and if at the end of a year
“our magazine placements
have plummeted,
“we’ll know that Jehovah
is not backing this arrangement.
We can go back to producing
two Awakes! a year.”
Well, what was the result?
At the end of the year,
we were placing
as many magazines at three per month
as we had been placing
at four per month the year before.
So that indicated to us
that Jehovah
was backing the arrangement.
And how many
of us have appreciated
having a study edition
of The Watchtower
that speaks directly
to the brotherhood
and then a public edition
of The Watchtower
that can be tailored
a little bit more
to the needs of the public.
Now, before making
any decision
that affects
the Kingdom work,
the Governing Body
has to carefully consider
the spiritual implications.
As an example,
in 2008,
the decision was made to reduce
the length of public talks
from 45 minutes
to 30 minutes.
Well you say, ‘How could
that decision possibly affect
the spirituality
of the brotherhood?’
And if you’re serving
in an urban congregation with many elders
and nearby there are other
urban congregations with many elders,
perhaps you’d have difficulty
in understanding the reasoning.
But the Governing Body
has to look at the whole picture.
Thousands of our brothers
have served where the need is great,
and they’ve learned
a foreign language.
And in many, many
of these congregations
the learners are the elders.
Some of the learners
have told us
that for every minute
of a public talk,
it has required one hour
of preparation.
So can you imagine:
45-minute public talk
—45 hours for some of them?
So the reduction in the length
of the public talks has actually meant
that these congregations
could have more public talks.
That’s not all.
There are thousands of elders
who are serving
in isolated congregations
that may be 100 miles or more
from the next congregation.
So in one congregation
you have one elder,
and then 100 miles away you have
another congregation with one elder.
How many public talks
were those brothers getting
when there were
45-minute public talks?
The 15-minute reduction
made a difference.
So if we take a narrow view
and think only about our own situation
and our own congregation,
well, we can have difficulty
in understanding
why certain decisions are made.
Now the same principles
apply to clarifications in our beliefs.
The Governing Body loves
to get together and discuss the Bible.
And when those Bibles
come out on the table
and when the brothers
bring their research in
and they’re starting to search
the Scriptures and analyze the Scriptures,
you see the happy smiles
on their faces.
The brothers love
discussing spiritual things.
But the clarifications
are often a long time
in coming into print.
Why?
Because the clarification
on one scripture
can have
a domino effect on others.
The clarification
on one scripture
can have ramifications
on other prophecies,
so we have to be absolutely sure
that everything fits.
So to reiterate,
although certain changes
may be announced one after another,
these decisions
are thought out very carefully.
And here’s
an interesting side point:
The older members
of the Governing Body
—Brother Jaracz, Brother Barr—
were just as interested
in making the adjustments
as the younger members were.
They were very progressive.
What an insight into the faithful
and discreet slave’s loving concern!
Did you hear things
the Governing Body does
that would further motivate you
to support and follow their direction?
Perhaps it’s how
they consulted experienced brothers;
or that they consider our brothers’
varying circumstances worldwide;
or, most importantly,
how they patiently and prayerfully seek
to know Jehovah’s will
and look for his blessing on a decision.
Millions of our brothers
and sisters around the world
can recount
the blessings they’ve gained
by remaining loyal
to Jehovah and his organization.
And we’re privileged to have
two such examples here with us today:
Brother and Sister
William and Sandra Malenfant.
Brother Malenfant is a helper
to the Teaching Committee,
and Sister Malenfant’s current assignment
is in the Service Department.
And we’re looking forward to hearing
about their rich spiritual history.
So, Bill and Sandra,
we’re so happy
that we could have you
here in the studio with us,
and we do look forward
to learning more about you.
Maybe we would like
to go back.
How did you get
on the road that has led you
to so many years of faithful,
loyal service to Jehovah?
It was back in 1954.
My mother had contact on and off
with the Witnesses for years.
I was about 20 years old,
and she was invited
to a public talk
at the Oakland Central Congregation
in California.
She asked me,
“Would you accompany me?”
And I said: “Yeah.
Sure, I’ll be happy to go.”
Well, I recognized a young man
I knew from high school at the meeting,
and he approached me after
and told me I needed a Bible study.
I really didn’t want a Bible study,
but he insisted,
and so I said,
“Well, you can come by.”
Would you believe it?
I started a Bible study
in the “Let God Be True” book.
Four months later,
I was baptized.
It was exactly what I was looking for,
but I didn’t realize it.
Good choice.
Thank you.
And, Sandra, your start on the road
to a career serving Jehovah?
Before I was born, my parents
started on this search for the truth.
It happened because they
had lost a little girl in death,
and they went from church to church
looking for some kind of comfort.
And, of course, the clergy
had no comfort for them.
They just said, “Well, God wanted
another angel in heaven.”
And that angered my father.
He thought: ‘No.
‘If God wants another angel,
he can make one.
He wouldn’t take my little girl!’
So it just happened
that one evening
they were listening to the radio
—long before TV, of course—
and they heard
a Jehovah’s Witness give a talk.
And the title of that talk was
“Where Are the Dead?”
Imagine!
He gave all the Scriptural proof
about the condition of the dead
and the hope for the resurrection.
And my father immediately said,
“This is the truth!”
So they wrote
to the radio station;
got a copy
of the booklet of the talk;
and then, also,
they started receiving
the subscription
to The Watchtower.
But it wasn’t until I was born
and three years old
that the Witnesses
finally made contact with us.
So, what motivated you
to make a choice
to get into the full-time service
and give your life to Jehovah?
Well, what motivated me
was when I attended
a convention, also in ’56.
I got baptized in ’54.
But in ’56, I went to a district convention
in Albany, California,
and there was a pioneer booth.
So I approached the booth,
and an older sister there looked at me
and said:
“You’re young and strong.
Why aren’t you a pioneer?”
I felt, ‘Well, yes.
Why not?’
So I started
pioneering in 1956.
That’s what motivated me.
And I was—
Really, I look back at that;
it was one of the best decisions
I made in my life.
Sandra, how about you?
Motivated to get
into full-time service.
Well, for pioneer service, you know,
it was—it was like a given.
Young people were
just encouraged to pioneer.
And most of the young people
were doing that.
You know, after a year or two, maybe they
would get married and start a family.
But those years in pioneering
—starting out their life that way—
gave them a wonderful basis
for loyal service the rest of their life.
Beautiful.
So you were pioneering.
How did your paths
eventually meet?
It was at a circuit assembly
in Oakland, California, 1956.
Very interesting things
took place.
I had the job
of dismantling the stage.
And I was carrying
this large piece of plywood off the stage,
and I ran right into Sandra
and knocked her flat!
Well, I took advantage
of the opportunity.
I thought, ‘Well, that’s not
the best way to introduce yourself.’
But I said, “By the way,
would you like to accompany me
to a get-together
some of the friends are having?”
Very good, Bill.
Well, yes,
and I followed through on it.
We had a lot
of association,
and after a number of months,
we got married.
And both of us
were pioneering
—very happy in our ministry
serving Jehovah.
You really swept her off her feet.
Literally.
I fell for him.
Very good.
So, shortly after you were married,
I understand
that you received some direction.
Yes, the circuit overseer
visited our congregation.
We were only married about a month,
I think, when he came through.
And he told us that the organization
was looking for pioneers
who’d be willing to serve
as special pioneers and go wherever,
where the need was great
in the United States particularly.
So we told him:
“Sure. We’d be delighted to do it.”
And four months
after our marriage,
we received an assignment
as special pioneers to Decorah, Iowa.
Now, that was
a very interesting place
because there were
only eight publishers in the congregation.
But we arrived
and started with the meetings there
at the Kingdom Hall.
And the Kingdom Hall was up
above Hunt’s Variety Store
in downtown Decorah,
and we lived in a room behind it.
Well, you know,
you’re on your own like that
—not a lot of brothers around—
so you look
for encouragement and company.
And we would travel down
to Strawberry Point, Iowa,
to where
Charles and Shirley Sinutko lived
in a log cabin
—one-room log cabin.
And we’d go visit with them in order
to have some mutual encouragement.
It’s a nice picture of you
in that log cabin too
as you were
special pioneering.
So you’re busy
in that work.
What special invitation
did you receive?
Well, we received
the invitation to attend Gilead
—the 34th class of Gilead School—
and that was a wonderful thing
after two and half years of pioneering,
special pioneering in Iowa.
And we were assigned
to Lebanon,
but we were unable to enter Lebanon
because we couldn’t get the visa.
So, then, the organization
asked us,
“Well, will you take
an assignment to Morocco?”
We were ready to go anywhere.
So that’s how we took
a boat from New York City
—five days across the Atlantic—
to Casablanca.
Very nice.
Well, what was it like to be
in the missionary service in Morocco?
It was very interesting.
We really enjoyed it.
But, you know, we only spoke English.
So in Morocco,
we had to learn French.
And the first month
of our missionary service in Morocco,
for 30 days we studied
the language 11 hours a day.
Well, that could get pretty tiring
for 11 hours a day,
so we’d go to the French movies
and count that as language time.
And then, we were moved
to Tangier.
And there was
a Spanish congregation in Tangier,
so we had to learn
the Spanish language too.
But that was
really a rich blessing
for the two of us
to be exposed to that culture
and to have
that privilege of serving there.
So after four years, I understand
that you came back to visit your family.
What events
were challenging thereafter?
I think Sandra can relate that.
Well, it was
usually permitted
that after you were
in your assignment four years,
then you were allowed
to come home
and at least have a vacation
and visit your family.
But we got back.
We visited our family,
and while there,
I had a medical examination and found out
that I had a serious health problem.
Of course, we didn’t have
the funds to cover that.
So Bill wrote to the Society,
and we made arrangements.
They said,
“Well, just take care of your situation,
and let us know when you’re free.”
So he got a job
to take care
of our medical needs
as well as living conditions.
But you know,
we just felt like we were failures.
Jehovah knew
we were discouraged.
He knew we felt
distraught about this.
So he knew just what we needed,
and he gave it to us.
As I got to feeling better
and we got more free
in our use of time,
we started pioneering.
And Jehovah blessed
our ministry just incredibly.
There were times,
in this supposedly “unproductive territory”
that we had up to 25 people
attending the meetings.
Many of them got baptized,
and they’re our fast friends to this day.
That’s incredible!
So Jehovah knows what you need,
and he provides it.
That is beautiful!
What temptation
did you have to resist
when you came back
and were going through these difficulties?
Well, I think it’s
a temptation that confronts
a lot of brothers and sisters
who return because of health reasons,
and some just end up settling down
because of their circumstances.
But the temptation there was:
‘Well, you’re home.
‘You’ve already done your service
in Morocco for a number of years.
‘You’ve been
in the full-time ministry.
Just settle down now.
Buy a house.’
But really,
that wasn’t our desire.
So as soon as Sandra
got on her feet
and was feeling well enough,
we got pioneering.
And then I wrote headquarters,
and I said: ‘Here we are.
‘We’re ready to take on whatever.
What would you like us to do?’
Good example.
Thank you.
So you made yourself
available to the organization.
Where did they send you next?
A wonderful assignment.
We were sent
as special pioneers to Washington D.C.,
to help start
a Spanish congregation.
And that was indeed
a very rich blessing.
We were there
a year and a half
until that little congregation
was solid and was formed.
And then we received
another blessing.
We were appointed
to the circuit work.
So I had the Spanish circuit in Florida
from Key West to Orlando
—one circuit in the whole state.
Then we came to New York City
—lived in the Bronx.
I had a circuit, and we did
district work in the Spanish field.
Then, to Texas
—to what they call the Valley of Texas,
the Rio Grande Valley—
for a couple of years in the circuit.
Then the district in Spanish
from Houston, Texas,
to Yuba City, California.
And we loved
every minute of it.
Well, that’s definitely
the traveling work.
Then 1977 rolls around
and you receive another invitation.
Yes, indeed!
We were doing
preconvention work
in the L.A. area
at the Leimert Assembly Hall,
and we received a letter
inviting us to come to Bethel.
That was a very, very special privilege:
to be invited to Bethel.
I went into the Service Department,
because at that time they
invited a number of traveling overseers
to come in and work
in the Service Department,
and Sandra went
into housekeeping.
And we were both
delighted to come to Bethel.
Well, sort of.
I really loved the ministry;
I loved, especially,
the district work
—being with
the circuit overseer and his wife
every week
and out in service.
So I wasn’t too anxious
for this Bethel thing.
But, you know.
Jehovah, again, knows what you need.
We came here, and we
started adjusting to Bethel life.
And it really proved out
to be a real blessing
because we got
the close association
with so many
other loyal Witnesses of Jehovah.
Well, I’m sure you
have many more experiences
to let us know about,
but we appreciate you sharing those.
The Governing Body
has made significant adjustments
in the work that is taking place
at Bethel and the field,
and it has affected
many long-time faithful brothers
—loyal brothers
in the traveling work,
overseers in the congregation,
overseers at Bethel.
Bill, what do you think
about some of these changes
that the Governing Body
has made recently?
I think they’re
very wise decisions.
They know what is needed;
they appreciate the older men
who have served for years.
We know that the older brothers
in circuit work, district work,
wherever, they’re “worthy of double honor”
because of the way
they’ve given
of themselves to the work.
But we have to recognize, too,
there comes a time
when we want the younger men
to come along,
to accept responsibility.
And, really,
when we were young,
we received responsibilities
with very little background and training.
Now we’ve got all these schools
for Kingdom Evangelizers
and the Kingdom Ministry School.
So many opportunities
for younger ones to be trained.
And so I think
it’s a wonderful arrangement.
Many thousands of young men
are doing so well,
ready to accept responsibility.
It’s a blessing
for the entire organization.
Well, thank you for sharing that.
That’ll benefit many brothers.
So we look
at this couple before us,
and we see some who have made
wise choices along the way.
So we look back at over 60 years
of faithful, loyal service.
As you look back at decisions
you made in life, any regrets?
Oh, absolutely none!
We consider that whatever
we have given up or done
it’s been our gift to Jehovah.
You know, when I was a little girl,
I remember I used to go out on our farm
and, especially when there
was a full moon, I used to pray to Jehovah.
And I’d say,
“Just let me use up my life in your service.”
You know, he’s answered
that prayer because my life,
the majority of it, is used up
and he’s let me do it in his service.
Beautiful.
Bill, how do you view sacrifices
that you have made along the way?
Well, as you know, a sacrifice
can be something
you give up to serve God, perhaps.
Or a sacrifice can be
what you give to Jehovah,
like David said in Psalm 54.
“I will sacrifice to you willingly.”
And that’s how I view sacrifice.
We’re happy to give of ourselves
to Jehovah God—to serve him.
And I want to add, too, Sandra has been
a wonderful partner with me
—willing to go anywhere,
put up with all kinds
of circumstances and difficulties.
A scripture that I—
There are a number
of good Scriptures,
obviously, that we all love.
But one in particular
that stays in my mind
is Romans 14:7,8:
‘We live, we live to Jehovah.
‘We die, we die to Jehovah.
So whether we live or we die,
we belong to Jehovah.’
And we’ve made that decision,
not just because he’s the Creator.
We’ve made the decision
to give ourselves to Jehovah God.
So, absolutely,
we’ve had the best life possible.
We have no regrets at all
about what we’ve done with our life,
giving Jehovah the first place.
Bill and Sandra,
it’s been a real privilege
to hear more about you, and I know
there are more stories to tell.
How can you boil down 60-plus years
of loyal service to Jehovah?
But you have given us great insights.
Thank you for sharing those gems with us.
Like the Malenfants, many loyal Witnesses
were not taught the truth
from the Bible from birth to adulthood.
For some young ones,
seeds of truth are planted along the way
but can lay dormant
for years due to family circumstances.
Sister Cory Wells explains
how her family’s special talent
almost kept her
from riding on the road to life.
The first rodeo I performed in front
of an audience, I was eight years old.
We were considered
one of the top two acts in rodeo.
My strength lay in my fearlessness.
Even though there was
a certain amount of excitement
—it was fun to travel,
to be together as a family—
it was empty.
Trick riding is like gymnastics
on the back of a running horse.
We’ve had horses all of our lives.
My father specialized in training horses.
He used to send us to the mountains,
riding all day long.
And then we’d come home
in the evening,
and we would start trick riding.
The way we learned was by a book.
We looked at stick pictures
that showed how it should be done,
and so it was trial and error.
At the same time that we were learning,
our horses were learning.
The horse that I rode
just let me do anything.
My horse’s name was Sweet Lips.
I was eight when I got him,
and I named him myself.
He was like my best friend.
My parents were very active
in the rodeo as competitors.
My mom was barrel racing;
my father was
a saddle bronc rider.
I grew up as
one of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
but when I was very young,
maybe six or seven,
my father stopped
serving Jehovah.
To be honest with you,
when they announced that
at the Kingdom Hall,
it really didn’t have
much meaning to me at the time.
I didn’t know what it meant.
And I could see people crying,
and so I cried.
But I didn’t really understand it.
Really, from that point, our family
was not active as Jehovah’s Witnesses.
I grew up on the road,
traveling rodeo to rodeo
—from coast to coast
and from the south to the north—
as far as the roads go.
The four of us rode initially
—Connie; Kelly; myself;
and my brother, Jim.
Our family traveled together.
That meant a lot to me.
What separated us
from the others at the time
was the high speed
that we did it at and also
the difficulty with the tricks
that we chose to do.
People were very excited.
They would hire us back
at the same place year after year.
Throughout all that time,
we did not miss one Memorial.
We were always there.
There was something in us.
We didn’t know it
when we were little,
but my parents
had succeeded
in planting
the truth in our hearts.
My link to the truth
was my grandmother.
I can remember going
to the ranch and visiting her.
She was very busy, but one thing
that really sticks in my mind
is she always studied
—every day.
She read her Bible.
Her magazines were studied.
And I think it just put a seed in there
that later on started to grow.
I just felt like
I needed direction.
It’s like a line
was drawn in the sand.
Take one path or the other.
And so, ironically,
the first book
that I picked up
to read was the Bible.
One of the scriptures
that probably
meant the most to me
was Proverbs 3:5,6:
“Trust in Jehovah
with all your heart
“and do not lean upon
your own understanding.
“In all your ways
take notice of him,
and he himself
will make your paths straight.”
I used to think
about those words
and what I would have to do
to live up to them.
Although we traveled
with the rodeo
about ten months
out of the year,
we did go
to the district convention,
and the Live Forever book
came out.
And there just came a time
when I knew
I—I needed to make changes.
A sister started
studying with me,
and as I started reading
the Bible for myself and studying,
then Jehovah became real.
All it took was one or two people,
and the whole family followed.
My father too returned to the truth.
Trick riding was our family business.
It was our livelihood,
but we had decided that we were done.
We were going to stop.
With that decision would come
giving up everything we knew.
I think—I think the most difficult thing
for me to do was to sell the horse
—you just, you just get
such a close bond with them
when you’re putting
your life in their hands like that—
but I was willing to do that.
I just—
I knew what I wanted to do;
I did it.
I got baptized
in October of ʼ85.
Our last performance
was in February of ʼ86.
We just finished out
our contracts.
I started pioneering
in September of ʼ86,
and I’ve never stopped.
I also married a man
who loves Jehovah.
We’ve had
the privilege of working
on international construction projects.
We went to Mexico.
We went to Venezuela.
My father is an elder.
My mom is pioneering.
In fact, all of my siblings
have been able
to regular pioneer
at some point in their lives.
We’re presently in the circuit work.
Serving Jehovah together
is such a blessing.
Everything that we do
every day is for Jehovah.
That’s what I wanted to do
when I made this decision.
If I would have taken
that other path when I was young,
I may not be alive today.
What I did was dangerous.
Even fame and fortune in the world
—there’s nothing there.
I wanted “the real life.”
I wanted to serve Jehovah.
I have no regrets.
If I could change anything
when it comes
to my service to Jehovah,
I would change nothing!
I would just do it better.
It took courage for Cory and her family
to choose loyalty to Jehovah
over an exciting rodeo career.
Jehovah will always help us
when we’re prayerfully deciding
how an activity or a career we love
affects our dedication to him.
Can the time it demands,
or even the danger involved,
take us away
from whole-souled service?
Our loyalty
to Jehovah is expressed
in how we follow Bible principles
when making
any important decision in life.
Few decisions are as important
as whom we choose to marry.
Part 1
of our Preparing for Marriage series
appeared in the May 2016 program.
In that dramatization,
a sister realizes she is
too young for a romantic relationship
and that cultivating
Christian qualities now
would help her later
when she’s ready for marriage.
Part 2 in the series next depicts
how a dating couple
can successfully know
“the secret person of the heart”
so that each can find
a marriage mate
who is loyal to them
and to Jehovah.
Meeting Ji-min
was completely unexpected.
I wasn’t looking for a girlfriend,
but as we talked,
everything just clicked.
The only problem is the distance.
I flew out to see her once,
but most of the time,
all we can do
is communicate online.
How can I be sure
she’s the one?
I decided the best decision
was to ask my father.
He knew the relationship
was becoming more serious,
and he appreciated my concerns.
He said:
“The same things are important,
“whether the person is next door
“or a world away.
“Most people simply focus on
“appearance or social standing,
“but for a truly successful relationship,
what matters is spirituality.”
Now I had already talked
with Ji-min’s elders,
and they said she was
a wonderful pioneer.
Dad said: “That’s good,
but it takes more than that.
It takes time to get to know
‘the secret person of the heart.’”
But how do you get to know
“the secret person of the heart”?
He said: “First, pray.
“Ask Jehovah
to help you see Ji-min
“as she truly is,
“both her good qualities
“and ones
that may need improvement.
“Also,
when you are able to visit,
“observe her actions.
“How does she treat her friends,
her parents,
“ones in the congregation?
“That’s a good indication of how
she’ll treat you someday.
But it’s not just about her.”
He had me read Ephesians 5:25:
“Husbands, continue loving your wives,
“just as the Christ
also loved the congregation
and gave himself up for it.”
He asked,
“Are you ready to be
that kind of husband?”
He thought I was
but that the only person
that truly knows is me.
We’ve been able to save up
and make a number
of visits since then,
taking the time to discover
what we both are spiritually.
And while we know we’re not perfect,
if we keep our focus on Jehovah,
we can be perfect for each other.
Did you notice the ways
they learned more about each other
before deciding to marry?
Despite the distance,
they regularly discussed
spiritual matters,
arranged for visits
chaperoned by trusted adults,
and worshipped together
at meetings and in the ministry
—all good ways
to prepare for marriage.
The beautiful scene depicting the couple
in the metropolitan witnessing work
is a reminder of how effective
this form of witnessing has become.
We received a report
from San Francisco, California,
in the United States,
where publishers have been engaged
in special metropolitan witnessing
since 2013.
It’s helping our brothers
reach multiple language groups,
start Bible studies,
and make disciples.
When I’m rolling the carts down
to get ready for the work,
I can feel people’s eyes on me
and it makes me feel proud
that I’m representing Jehovah
even before I get to the location.
We have a chance
to use our Bibles very regularly.
We talk to honesthearted people
who are interested
in really learning
what the Bible teaches.
Jehovah is reaching people
in those hard-to-reach areas
where it could mean their life
to even talk about things
such as the Bible.
When you’re part
of the metropolitan work,
you get to welcome people
being drawn by Jehovah.
We see thousands of people
every day who walk by our carts.
While we’re placing literature
in up to 40 different languages each week,
what’s really exciting is to see
how many conversations we’re starting
and how many Bible studies
we’re initiating.
We’re visible to a lot of people
in the community,
especially those who were inactive
or maybe were raised around the truth.
Jehovah has arranged
to have his people
put right in the center
of everything,
and we’re able to meet people
from all over the world.
I’ve met people from Peru, South Africa,
Japan, Germany, England.
France, Italy,
Cameroon, Congo.
Beaucoup!
In Shona, a greeting
would be something like . . .
. . . , which means
“Would you like to study the Bible?”
. . . , which means “Would you like
to study the Bible?” in sign language.
So when I asked her if she had seen
the sign-language Bible,
she shook her head no,
and I showed her Acts 17:27.
And as soon as it was done,
she started signing, “I understood that!”
And then she said,
“Didn’t you say this was a free app?”
So, right then,
she started downloading it on her phone.
We had a gentleman come up
and wanted to . . .
First, he said, “debate,”
and then he said, “just discuss.”
But as he was talking with us,
he had to catch his train
but he missed three trains
because he wanted to continue
the conversation and speak with us.
It’s a really good experience
because we just get to talk to people
and let them see
a different side of us.
It’s not necessarily about whether
we placed a book with him or not.
And in the end, he turned
to my husband and I
and said, “You know, you’re
really good ambassadors.”
We start Bible studies
here every day,
and these studies
are conducted globally.
I met Alfredo in 2014,
right before the Memorial.
He approached the cart.
He had a rough life.
He was doing a lot of bad things,
and so he felt
that he couldn’t overcome them.
So I told him that no matter
how big his problems are,
they’re not too big
for Jehovah,
and so I encouraged him
to start studying the Bible again.
“Come, now,
and let us set matters straight
between us,” says Jehovah.
“Though your sins are like scarlet,
they will be made as white as snow.”
When Jehovah forgives you,
he forgives you completely.
I got baptized,
and in the same month,
I started auxiliary pioneering.
It is such a privilege to be
one of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
with brothers
all around the world.
If anybody is hesitant
to take part
in the special metropolitan
witnessing work,
maybe you’re worried
about finances, time,
or you’re just afraid
that it’s something different
and you won’t know
what to do,
please don’t let
any of those things stop you.
It’s from Jehovah.
Grab hold of it tight,
and don’t let go!
Each month,
the brothers and sisters
in San Francisco’s
metropolitan witnessing
distribute
over 5,000 publications
and start an average
of 185 Bible studies.
After some initial concern
from local authorities
over having literature carts
at the Golden Gate Bridge,
authorities have expressed appreciation
for our brothers being there
with the Bible’s message of hope.
It’s been requested
that we always have on hand
the April 2014 Awake!
with the cover title
“Why Go On?
—Three Reasons to Keep Living.”
One afternoon an officer
approached a cart and said,
“Well, your magazine worked!”
The police had just helped
a young woman
who was thinking
of jumping from the bridge.
When they reached her,
she had the Awake! issue in her hand
and had decided not to jump.
Life in this system
can be difficult for everyone,
but our witnessing work
comforts people
and teaches them to know
and thank their Creator for life.
And the longer we know Jehovah
as his Witnesses,
the more reasons we find
to thank him for his acts of loyalty.
We’re even moved to sing
our appreciation to Jehovah,
like in this music video entitled
“Our Thanks Go to You.”
When I cannot find
Any peace of mind,
You will listen.
My thanks go to you.
When troubles arise,
Whatever the size,
For your answers,
Our thanks go to you.
We need not be anxious over anything.
You’ll guard our hearts and our thoughts
If we continue having trust in you to
Give us peace of mind
When life is unkind.
For our welfare,
Our thanks go to you.
All the loyal
find you loyal too.
For your care,
all our thanks go to you.
We saw the family in our music video
facing economic pressure
and our dear older couple enduring
the stress of failing health.
But as Philippians 4:6 encourages,
they let their “petitions
be made known to God.”
You and I can do the same
for any problem that causes us anxiety.
We should not only supplicate Jehovah
to give us his holy spirit
so that we can endure
but also thank him,
fully assured
that “he will not abandon his loyal ones.”
We’d again like to thank
Brother and Sister Malenfant
for being here with us.
With almost 60 years
of full-time service,
the Malenfants have so much
they can share,
so we’re pleased to announce
that an extended version
of their interview
will be released later this month
on JW Broadcasting.
Finally in our program,
we have a special behind-the-scenes visit
with the orchestra
that records
our beautiful theocratic music.
In December 2015,
75 musicians gathered
from 16 countries
for a five-day session at our studio
in Patterson, New York.
A team of 15 technicians
joined them to record 22 pieces.
Among several songs
we sing at our meetings
was the stirring arrangement
of song 147,
“A Special Possession,”
that we sang at this year’s Memorial.
The orchestra took time
from their busy session
to send you
their Christian love and greetings.
And we thank them
and the Governing Body
for the music we have
to joyfully praise our God, Jehovah.
We’re happy to have been together
with you for this month’s program.
From Brooklyn, New York,
this is JW Broadcasting.