The theme for our program this month is
“Treasure Jehovah’s Reminders.”
And it’s based on Psalm 19:7,
where we’re told:
“The reminder of Jehovah is trustworthy,
making the inexperienced one wise.”
In the original language,
the word here translated as “reminder”
comes from a root word meaning
“to go over again, to repeat.”
Reminders have always been
an essential part of Jehovah’s teaching.
In ancient Israel,
God’s people continually received
commandments,
regulations, and reminders.
In fact, Jehovah tells us
that he sent
his prophets “again and again”
to repeatedly remind his people
of their responsibilities.
The apostle Peter
felt the need to give reminders
even to those
who were “well-established in the truth.”
Notice how he describes this
at 2 Peter 1:12, 13:
“For this reason I intend always
“to remind you of these things,
“although you know them
and are well-established
“in the truth that is present in you.
“But I consider it right,
“as long as I am in this tabernacle,
to stir you with reminders.”
In verse 15,
he goes on to give the reason
why he felt the need
to give the brothers reminders.
He says:
“I will always do my utmost
so that after my departure,
you may be able to recall
these things for yourselves.”
So Peter was determined
to help the brothers and sisters
in his day to remember, or recall,
the teachings they had already learned.
It shouldn’t come as a surprise, then,
if today a lot of our teaching
involves reminders.
It follows the pattern set
by Jehovah in ancient Israel
and with the first-century Christians.
But why do we need reminders?
Let’s consider three reasons.
First, let’s look at Psalm 103:2.
There it says:
“Let me praise Jehovah;
may I never forget all that he has done.”
Why, then, do we need reminders?
Simply put, because we forget.
If we had perfect memories,
we wouldn’t need so many reminders.
Even in everyday life,
many of us use little notes
to remind ourselves
of what we need to do.
And who of us
hasn’t seen the need
for a list of reminders
when going shopping,
only to realize when we returned
that we forgot to get one
of the important items
we needed to purchase?
If reminders are important
in everyday life,
how much more so in matters
that involve our relationship
with Jehovah.
Let’s read Luke 10:39, 40.
Speaking of Martha, we are told:
“She also had a sister called Mary,
“who sat down at the feet of the Lord
“and kept listening to what he was saying.
“Martha, on the other hand,
was distracted
with attending to many duties.”
What was Martha’s problem?
She was distracted.
So the second reason
why we need reminders
is that, like Martha,
at times we too become distracted.
Although we may already know
a vital fact,
that fact might get put
into the back of our mind,
figuratively speaking,
because other matters
are demanding our attention.
Satan is the great Distracter.
He tries to turn our attention away
from the true issues of our day.
People in general have become
more and more distracted
by entertainment
and other nonessential matters.
No wonder that Satan
has succeeded in misleading so many.
They don’t even realize
what has happened.
Reason number three
is alluded to
at Matthew 24:45:
“Who really
is the faithful and discreet slave
“whom his master appointed
over his domestics,
to give them their food
at the proper time?”
Notice that the spiritual food
is given to us “at the proper time.”
Our circumstances in life
are continually changing.
How often do we hear,
“That was just what I needed?”
We’ve all experienced that,
haven’t we?
So, what are three of the reasons
why we need reminders?
One,
because we tend to forget things.
Two,
we often become distracted.
Three,
our changed circumstances
may require a reminder
of something we already knew
but didn’t fully need at that time.
So that brings us to the next question:
What will help us to remember?
It’s interesting to note
that Jehovah has used many ways
to remind his people
of what they should do.
At Numbers 10:10, we’re told
that the various festivals
were given as reminders,
especially the celebration
of the Passover.
That means
that every time the Israelites
prepared and celebrated
one of these festivals,
they were reminded
of important matters,
such as how Jehovah
provides for his people
and how he has saved them
in the past.
Something similar happens today
at the commemoration
of the Lord’s Evening Meal.
Not only do we hear
the reminders from God’s Word
but the act of passing
the bread and wine
also serves as an action
that reminds us
of what Jesus did in our behalf.
But what do we need to do
in order for those reminders
to have a beneficial impact
on our lives?
Notice what Psalm 119:99 says.
It tells us:
“I have more insight than all my teachers,
because I ponder over your reminders.”
Yes, we need to ponder
over these reminders.
That means not just
listening to or reading them,
but it involves thinking deeply
about them—
meditating on their value.
Just to listen or read  without meditating
is like looking through the lens
of a movie camera
without pressing the record button.
We see things and hear things,
but nothing is recorded.
So we need
to meditate, visualize,
and review these reminders.
This will help us
to remember what we learn.
But, figuratively speaking,
there is something else
that we can do
to press the record button.
That means we don’t have to wait
for someone else
to give us a reminder.
We can make our own reminder.
How can we do so?
The answer to that question
is highlighted
in Jehovah’s instructions to Moses
as found at Exodus 17:14:
“Jehovah now said to Moses:
“‘Write this as a memorial
“‘[or the footnote says: “reminder”]
in the book and repeat it to Joshua.’”
What’s the point?
Write down new things
we want to remember.
Some brothers use a notebook,
or exercise book,
to write down a list of interesting points
that they want to remember.
Then they look through the book
from time to time
to remind themselves of those points.
Many of us do this with our notes
from conventions and assemblies.
Of course, to do that successfully,
you need to remember
where you put the notebook.
Additionally,
we have to be careful
that we don’t write down
every little fact.
Otherwise, we may become overwhelmed
with all the information.
We can make
these notes either on paper
or electronically using computers
or electronic devices.
Whatever system we use,
let’s make lists of things
that we want to remember.
Many brothers have found it good
to have two separate lists.
One list could be subjects
—perhaps points that we want to use
in the ministry or in our own lives.
Another, scriptures
—explanations that clarify
the meaning of certain verses.
With regard to notes on scriptures,
let’s ask a very important question:
Do you have a study Bible?
What is a study Bible?
Perhaps it’s a separate Bible
to the one you take in the ministry.
It’s a Bible for you to write in
so that you’re reminded
of things that you’ve learned.
These are some of the things
we can do with a study Bible:
Highlight or underline some words or verses.
That will make it easier to find them again.
But remember not to make
too many highlights or marks;
otherwise, nothing will stand out.
Write a summary of points and scriptures
you want to remember
on the blank pages in the front
or the back of your Bible.
Write notes in the margin
—that’s what Gilead students often do.
Of course, you need
the right type of pen or pencil
that won’t bleed through
to the other side of the page.
What type of things
could you write in the margin?
Perhaps new points
that you learn while reading magazines
or attending meetings and assemblies.
If you learn a new point, ask yourself,
‘What verse is being explained?’
And then write a brief comment
in the margin next to that verse.
Let’s take an example.
Perhaps you are reading
the Sermon on the Mount
and you get to Matthew 7:24-27.
That’s the illustration
about the two men who built houses
—one on sand and the other on rock.
As you research this
in Watchtower Library
or the Research Guide,
you come across the article
“Are You Building on Sand or on Rock?”
in the November 1, 2008, Watchtower.
What points could you write in the margin
to help you remember the explanation?
Well, perhaps you could write:
Sand equals build on the surface.
Rock equals dig down deep.
Digging equals doing and applying.
You might even put Luke 6:46-48 there.
Now, if you still have room
and your writing is small,
you could add something like this:
Not hearers only, but doers.
Both houses in same location,
same tests, foundations different.
Now every time
you read those verses,
you will be reminded
of what they mean.
Perhaps like me,
you’ve had several study Bibles
over the years.
I think back to the first one I used.
It was like this big green Bible.
Then, later that was replaced
by another Bible
—this black covered Bible.
And then, further still,
we had another Bible
—the Reference Bible.
And, of course,
now for most of us,
we have the large-print Bible.
This does, however,
highlight a challenge
we might experience.
It can be frustrating
when a new edition
of the Bible comes out.
How do you transfer all your study notes
over to the new Bible?
Additionally, our beloved study Bible
may wear out
or, worse still, be lost, stolen, burned,
ruined, run over, blown away.
So that’s the advantage
of using an electronic list;
it doesn’t matter
what type of file you use.
It can be updated very easily,
and you can even make copies
—not like the printed copy
that already has
the old idea written in the margin.
Even now in English,
we have the books
of Matthew, Mark, and Luke
in our electronic study Bible
on jw.org and WOL.
Later in the program,
we have some exciting news
about how JW Library
will help us in this regard.
But I’ll leave that for later.
Really, having a study Bible
is not only helpful
but it also makes our personal study
far more interesting.
How so?
Every time we read
or study a publication,
we’ll find ourselves
searching for new points
that we can write
in our study Bible.
This way, we’ll be doing
what the psalmist expressed
at Psalm 119:111:
‘We will take Jehovah’s reminders
‘as our permanent possession
(or heritage),
for his reminders
are the joy of our hearts!’