While meditating on the text this morning,
I was reminded of an experience
I had many years ago as a missionary.
At the time,
I was studying with a young man
who was training to be a pastor
in his church.
This man had got to the point
where he started to attend all our meetings
while at the same time
still attending his church gatherings.
The church, obviously,
was very disturbed
about the fact that he was coming
to the meetings of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
and their headquarters
sent in a missionary from overseas
to try and rectify the situation.
The young man told me what happened.
He said the missionary asked him,
“What is it that impresses you
about Jehovah’s Witnesses?”
He said, “Well, one of the things is
that they do the preaching work.”
The missionary replied,
“Well, our church can do that too.”
So the next time they had a service,
the missionary conducted the service
and with great zeal and enthusiasm
demanded that everyone in the church
take part in the preaching work.
He announced the time that they
would have the group to go preaching.
The young man told me
quite a number of people came along.
But there was just one thing missing,
you guessed it, the missionary.
He felt that it was enough
just to encourage everybody else
to do it without engaging in it himself.
How different was the example
of Jesus and of our hard-working elders
who do take the lead
with regard to the preaching work.
Now let’s take our Bibles
and turn to a very interesting scripture
in Hebrews 13:7, 17.
Now, I’d like to highlight the beauty
of the New World Translation
in these two verses.
You see at the beginning of verse 7:
“Remember those
who are taking the lead among you.”
And then verse 17:
“Be obedient to those
who are taking the lead among you.”
If you look at other Bibles,
whether new or old,
most of them say “your leaders.”
Now, obviously,
the New World Translation Committee
had in mind Jesus’ comments with regard
to no one being a leader among us,
and although it’s a different
word in the Greek text,
still in English we can’t help
but be sensitive to that matter.
And so this accurate translation
of saying “taking the lead”
really summarizes, doesn’t it,
what the role is of an elder.
We’re not leaders,
but we set the right example.
Now, this accurate translation
is also portrayed
in the words of our Lord Jesus Christ
as recorded in Luke chapter 22,
and you’ll be interested to note
that this is part of the revision
of the New World Translation text.
Luke 22:26,
it now portrays accurately
the fact that both expressions in Hebrew
and this one here are the same word.
So, Luke 22:26,
it says:
“You, though, are not to be that way.
But let the one who is the greatest
among you become as the youngest.”
And then notice:
“and the one taking the lead,”
now this is the same expression
as in the Hebrews,
“as the one ministering.”
So, obviously,
to take the lead means to do the work,
to be a minister,
to be a servant, to serve others.
This also reminds me,
many years ago,
when I worked with the translation team
in the Pacific nation of Samoa.
At that point, we were trying to select
an accurate expression
to convey this thought of “taking the lead.”
And there were two words eventually
that the brothers
were trying to select between,
or choose between.
One was the word ta’ita’i
and the other ta’imua.
Now, you don’t have
to remember those words,
but as a foreigner,
I didn’t really understand
the subtleties between
the difference of the two words.
So I asked the brothers,
“How can you explain to me
what these two words mean?”
So one of the brothers was very eloquent.
He said: “Well, just imagine
a procession, a parade.
“So a ta’ita’i is the old man who sits
“on the side of the road
barking out the orders:
“‘You should do it this way;
you should do it that way.’
“The ta’imua, on the other hand,
is the one right in the front of the parade
taking the lead
and everyone’s following him.”
Which word do you think we selected?
Doesn’t that summarize nicely just exactly
what’s involved with being an elder?
It’s not a matter of sitting
on the sidelines barking out orders
but getting involved,
setting the right example,
and then others following.
And this is in harmony
with one Greek lexicon
that describes
this expression this way, it says,
“The concept of leading can be expressed
“by showing how to do something,
“demonstrating how we ought to do it,
and going ahead showing the way.”
Of course, on the other hand,
some religions even view
the expression “elder” as a title.
You’ve probably heard of them
introducing themselves,
“Good morning, I’m Elder Jackson.”
Well, of course,
none of us would want to view
being an elder as a title
in the sense of a position
that lords it over others.
And with that in mind,
another subtlety to the revision
is seen in 1 Timothy chapter 3,
so please turn there with me,
1 Timothy 3:1.
These are well-known words
—particularly when brothers are considering
the qualifications for elders—
but you may or may not have seen
the subtleties of the change
here in this revision.
It says now:
“This statement is trustworthy:
“If a man is reaching out to be an overseer,
he is desirous of a fine work.”
Do you remember before
the original New World Translation said:
‘If someone is reaching out
for the office of being an overseer?’
And that reflected
and no doubt was influenced
by the King James
and many of the older translations
that translated it that way.
But when we look at the rest of the verse,
we see that it’s not the office,
or the position,
of being an overseer
that someone reaches out for;
rather, it’s the work.
Yes, the hard work that needs
to be done by an overseer.
An overseer recognizes
that he needs to work hard
at setting the right example,
and then others will follow
—rather than just telling
everyone what they should do.
So when we look at these subtleties
in the New World Translation,
it only helps us to appreciate
it even more, doesn’t it?
So with this in mind,
what does our text this morning
help us to keep in mind?
Well, as elders, what do we need to do?
Not sit on the sidelines
barking out orders but, rather,
to take the lead,
be in the forefront, do the work,
and then others will follow our example,
just as we follow the example of Jesus.