In your ministry, have you ever met someone
who strongly believes that we are still
under the Ten Commandments?
Now, that can happen at times
because many people
—especially in the southern parts
of this country—
feel very strongly
about the Ten Commandments.
There are even legal battles going on
as to whether monuments
displaying the Ten Commandments
can be displayed
on government property.
And, of course, many people feel
that the Ten Commandments
are basically what was used
for the Constitution
and for the laws of many countries.
So at one point, perhaps,
a person might say to us,
‘Do you believe that we are still
under the Ten Commandments?’
Perhaps you may diplomatically answer,
‘Well, I believe we are under the principles
of the Ten Commandments
and the law of love
—the law of the Christ.’
But a person may push
the point and say,
‘But do you believe the Ten Commandments
are binding today?’
Well, when we give them
an explanation from the Scriptures,
perhaps they may feel disappointed
and maybe they realize
that there’s a verse in the Bible
that they feel supports their belief.
So let’s take our Bibles
and turn to Matthew chapter five,
the Sermon on the Mount,
from which our text
is taken this morning.
And perhaps they may point
to verses 17 and 18.
Now that reads:
“Do not think I came to destroy
the Law or the Prophets.
“I came, not to destroy, but to fulfill.
“Truly I say to you that sooner
would heaven and earth pass away
“than for one stroke of a letter
to pass away from the Law
until all things take place.”
Now, this person,
in presenting their explanation,
may show that they believe
this expression “fulfilled”
means “established permanently.”
And even some Bible commentaries
say that this involves total commitment.
Well, how would you answer
the person at that stage?
How can we help them?
Perhaps you might take them
through a series of scriptures,
such as Romans 10:4
where it says:
“Christ is the end of the Law.”
You might read Galatians 4:4,5
where it says,
‘those under the law were released.’
Or Ephesians 2:15 where it speaks
of the Law being “abolished.”
But if you’ve done that,
perhaps you’ve had
the same experience that I have
—that a person may agree
with those scriptures but say:
‘That’s not referring
to the Ten Commandments.
‘That’s referring to all the other laws
in the Mosaic Law arrangement.
But the Ten Commandments
remain forever.’
Well, how can you help someone
to reason on that matter?
Well, let’s look back again
at Matthew chapter 5,
and we notice there
in verses 17 and 18,
it mentions that Jesus came
“not to destroy, but to fulfill.”
And we could ask the person
how they understand the word “fulfill”
—what they feel that means.
And perhaps they might say,
‘Established permanently.’
Well, then we could point out
that Jesus then continues to talk
about various aspects of the Law.
If we look at verse 21,
what do we notice?
“You heard that it was said
to those of ancient times:
‘You must not murder.’”
So, yes, this is one
of the Ten Commandments.
Interestingly, the study Bible has a note
on this verse that says
this phrase,
“You heard that is was said:
“. . . can refer both to things stated
in the inspired Hebrew Scriptures
and to teachings of Jewish tradition.”
Now, we’ll see this as we go on.
If we go to verse 23,
what does it talk about here?
“If, then, you are bringing
your gift to the altar
and there you remember your brother
has something against you.”
This is not part
of the Ten Commandments, is it?
It’s talking about the arrangements
for sacrifices.
Then, if we look at verse 27:
“You heard that it was said:
‘You must not commit adultery.’”
Well, again we have
the Ten Commandments.
But if we look at verse 31,
Jesus here says:
“Moreover, it was said:
‘Whoever divorces his wife,
let him give her
a certificate of divorce.’”
That’s not one
of the Ten Commandments, is it?
Reading on further in verse 33,
it says:
“Again you heard that it was said
to those of ancient times:
‘You must not swear without performing.’”
Again, not one
of the Ten Commandments.
Verse 38:
“You heard that it was said:
‘Eye for eye and tooth for tooth.’”
Again, not one
of the Ten Commandments.
And then we come to the scripture
we’ve been considering this morning
in verse 43:
“You heard that it was said:
‘You must love your neighbor
and hate your enemy.’”
Now, when we consider this
—we look at the study Bible notes
on this verse—
it makes this comment
about “hate your enemy.”
It says: “The Mosaic Law
contained no such command.
“Some Jewish rabbis believed
that the command to love their neighbor
implied that they should hate their enemy.”
So this wasn’t really part
of the Law that Moses gave.
But what do we see from this?
Well, if a person argues very strongly
that the word “fulfilled,”
when Jesus is talking about the Law,
applies to the Ten Commandments only
—we look down here—
Jesus when he’s talking about the Law,
doesn’t just talk
about the Ten Commandments, does he?
He talks about all these things,
including even the oral tradition.
So if a person were to believe
that Jesus’ words, when saying “fulfilled,”
refer to absolutely establishing
something permanently,
would also feel
—or have to feel—
that he’s referring to this law
of “eye for eye, tooth for tooth”
when, in fact, he showed
something better than that, didn’t he?
And the same too
with the scripture for today’s text.
So, what do we see here?
Well, we can’t make
that comment about Jesus’ words.
So, what does it mean
when it says,
‘to fulfill and not to destroy’?
Perhaps a simple illustration
would help us.
If someone signs
a contract as a builder
to build a home
for someone else,
what does it mean
to destroy the contract?
Well, perhaps it means ripping it up,
burning it, getting rid of it
—certainly not building the house.
But on the other hand,
what does it mean
to fulfill the contract
to build the house?
Well, it means
that the person builds the house.
But once the house is built,
then the contract
is completed, or fulfilled.
This person isn’t under obligation
to continue over and over again
to keep building the same house.
So perhaps an illustration
such as that
may help someone
of humble heart
to see that when Jesus said
he “came, not to destroy,
but to fulfill,”
that he wasn’t there
to eradicate the Law.
In Galatians 4, it mentions
he was ‘born under Law.’
So he had to fulfill, or complete,
or do what the Law stated.
But, of course, the other scriptures
help us when they tell us
that the Law was completed,
that the Christ
was the end to the Law.
Now, perhaps a person
might still find this
a little difficult to comprehend.
One final scripture we could share with them
is in the book of Romans,
Romans 7:6, 7.
Romans 7:6, 7,
verse 6 says:
“But now we have been released
from the Law,
“because we have died
to that which restrained us,
“in order that we might be slaves
in a new sense by the spirit
and not in the old sense
by the written code.”
Now, if we pause there,
perhaps the person might jump in and say:
‘Ah, yes. That’s the Law
that doesn’t include the Ten Commandments.
Those are all the other laws,
but the Ten Commandments remain forever.’
Well, then we ask them,
‘Just let’s read on, verse 7,
what does it say?’
“What, then, are we to say?
“Is the Law sin?
“Certainly not!
“Really, I would not have come
to know sin
“had it not been for the Law.
For example, . . .”
Now, what example
is Paul going to use?
It says: “For example,
I would not have known covetousness
if the Law had not said:
‘You must not covet.’”
So, obviously, the apostle Paul
and our Lord Jesus Christ
did not separate the Law
into two parts
—the Ten Commandments
and the other laws.
So we can see clearly from here
that we have a good answer
to give persons
when they adamantly state
that the Ten Commandments
are still binding.
Hopefully, we can go on then
to help them to see
that Jesus was teaching us
the principles behind the laws
and that “the law of the Christ”
involves loving Jehovah
and loving our neighbors,
and then following
what direction Jehovah has given us.
So you may think
this is quite a complicated subject
to discuss early in the morning.
But next time
when someone does ask you,
“Do you believe
the Ten Commandments are binding?”
hopefully, you’ll remember
these comments.