Welcome to JW Broadcasting®.
This is my friend and cohost, Izak Marais.
Izak, what’s in store
for this month’s program?
Thank you, Brother Lösch.
This month we’ll examine the many ways
Jehovah assures us that he is with us.
Our music video for this month shows how,
from the moment
that we start to take steps
toward dedication and baptism,
Jehovah draws close to us.
Jehovah is also with us in the ministry.
In this report, we’ll see how he blessed
a special preaching effort in Europe.
And Jehovah is with us
as we meet challenges of daily life,
as our Sister Reeta and her children learned.
That sounds exciting!
Let’s get started.
This is the November 2019 edition
of JW Broadcasting.
Millions have benefited
from the animated series
Become Jehovah’s Friend
and many other Bible-based videos.
Have you enjoyed
getting to know Caleb and Sophia?
When you’ve watched a video,
perhaps you’ve wondered:
‘How does the Governing Body know
that the video will turn out exactly right?
How can they see and hear
the video before it exists?’
Let’s go behind the scenes
and see how this works.
Animated videos,
like those in the series
Become Jehovah’s Friend,
have been helping young ones
draw closer to their heavenly Father
for several years now.
Look, Mom, I’m rejoicing in the hope!
Wee!
But did you know
that what you see on the screen
might last just a few short minutes
but it may involve weeks of work
by a virtual army of volunteers?
With so much time and expense
involved in making an animated video,
a lot of careful planning
is required to avoid waste
and to keep
the process running smoothly.
Let’s take a look at how the effective use
of preproduction tools
help all of these brothers and sisters
work together to take a video
from initial concept to final production.
Under the direction of the Teaching Committee
of the Governing Body,
the work begins
long before the artists even get started.
They provide direction
on the theme that needs to be taught.
Members of the animation team collaborate
to develop the featured characters
as well as plot structure,
and they work closely
with writers and storyboard artists
to develop the approved idea
into a story line.
Once a complete script is ready,
the whole team
gathers together for a table read.
This is the first time the team
hears the whole script being read aloud.
Dialogue is meant to be heard.
So when we read it aloud at the table read,
we pick up on things
we didn’t see in the written script.
We’re able to tighten the story
and make it as clear as possible.
The script is reviewed
by the research team for accuracy.
Then it’s revised, polished, and submitted
to the Teaching Committee for approval.
With an approved script in hand,
the director then works with an artist
to start turning words into pictures
—visualizing each scene on a storyboard.
First come the rough boards,
showing what will be included in each shot.
When it comes to the animation world, really,
everything you see on screen
has to be designed and created
—the characters,
the furniture,
the props, the environment
are all created by a designer.
The storyboard really helps us
figure out exactly what we need to create
so that we’re not creating
too much or too little.
Once approved by the director,
the storyboard artist
cleans up each of the boards.
Preliminary recordings of dialogue, music,
and sound effects are added.
These are then used by the director
and compositor to create an animatic.
An animatic
is a rough draft of the entire video.
The animatic is very important for us.
That way the director
and, more importantly, the Teaching Committee
can see the entire video
before we are actually making it.
And with that they can review it
and give us the proper direction.
The finished animatic is submitted
to the Teaching Committee for review.
Based on direction from the committee,
the team makes sure
that the teaching points come across clearly
and that the finished product
is true to the spirit
and intent
of the approved concept for the video.
Finally, using the approved
animatic as a blueprint,
full production begins.
Really, everything in animation
can be very time-consuming.
An animator working full-time here at Bethel
may be able to produce
four to six seconds of animation in one week,
and that doesn’t even include other aspects
that are very important, such as modeling,
rigging, lighting,
compositing, and many others.
From the examples shown here,
you can see
just how closely the final version
of the video Make Jehovah Happy
follows the animatic.
Preproduction tools
such as storyboards and animatics
do more than save
the organization time and money.
They enable the Teaching Committee
to carefully evaluate
every project along the way
from the initial approved concept
to the final product
in order to keep providing videos
that help all of us
honor our Friend, Jehovah.
Isn’t it amazing to see all the work
that goes into our videos?
Jehovah provides for his people
just what they need at the right time.
Truly, he is with his people.
Brother Lösch,
I know you have some thoughts on this.
I’d like to talk
about a very common expression
in the Bible.
The expression is:
“I am with you.”
Thirteen times it’s attributed
to a statement from Jehovah.
Three times it’s something that Jesus said
to one or more of his disciples.
Of course, there are dozens of other times
that the same sentiment
is expressed using similar wording.
Few things in the world
equal the joy humans experience
than the birth of a child.
As children grow up,
they are sometimes exposed to situations
that tend to cause nervousness
or even fear.
So a parent may occasionally feel compelled
to reassure a child:
“Have no fear; I am with you.”
Jehovah loves his servants
as if they were his children.
Likewise, at John 13:1,
Jesus’ feelings for his disciples
are well expressed.
There it says:
“Jesus, having loved his own
who were in the world,
loved them to the end.”
So when we face fears,
trials, or causes for anxiety,
both our heavenly Father and his Son, Jesus,
reassuringly say, “I am with you.”
Think of the righteous man Noah.
Genesis 6:9 says
that “Noah walked with the true God.”
There’s no doubt that Jehovah was with Noah.
He preserved him
and his family through the Flood.
Afterward,
Jehovah further proved he was with Noah.
In Genesis chapter 9, Jehovah said:
‘I am now establishing my covenant with you:
‘Never again will all flesh be destroyed
by the waters of a flood.’
Jehovah could have made that determination
and promised himself
that he wouldn’t do that again,
but instead, he reached out to Noah
and reassured him that he was with him
by making the rainbow covenant
with Noah and his offspring.
Using similar terminology,
Jehovah indicated
that he was with Abraham,
Isaac, Jacob, Joseph,
Moses, Joshua, and Gideon.
They were all individuals
whom Jehovah was pleased with,
so he reassured them that he was with them.
How about for a group of people?
Is Jehovah moved to feel the same way
toward a large crowd
of his servants collectively?
Please find with me Exodus 6:6, 7.
The whole nation of Israel
was experiencing severe trials
and suffering as slaves in Egypt.
Notice Jehovah’s reassurance
to the vast number of people.
Verses 6 and 7 state:
“Therefore, say to the Israelites:
“‘I am Jehovah,
“‘and I will bring you out
from under the burdens of the Egyptians
“‘and rescue you from their slavery,
“‘and I will reclaim you
with an outstretched arm
“‘and with great judgments.
“‘And I will take you in as my people,
and I will be your God,
“‘and you will certainly know
that I am Jehovah your God
who is bringing you out
from under the burdens of Egypt.’”
If that great, mixed group of people
would follow his leadings,
he said he’d ‘take them in’
and he ‘would be their God.’
What was he saying?
He was reassuring them:
“I will be with you,”
and he was.
For forty years in the wilderness,
he was with them
—feeding them, providing water for them,
ensuring that their clothes
and sandals would not wear out,
protecting them
from poisonous snakes, and so forth.
And later, when entering the land of promise,
he protected them during enemy warfare.
Jehovah promised to be with and to support
the kings of Israel
as long as they heeded
his commandments and direction.
King Solomon was told:
“Jehovah [your] God . . .
will not desert you or abandon you,
but he will be with you.”
King Asa was informed:
“Jehovah is with you
as long as you remain with him.”
When faced with overwhelming enemy forces,
King Jehoshaphat was told:
“Tomorrow go out against them,
and Jehovah will be with you.”
Jehovah also proved to be
with the many prophets
that he sent out in his name.
Just one example is Jeremiah.
Imagine if you had Jeremiah’s assignment.
Suppose you had been directed to deliver
a scathing denunciation and judgment
against wicked kings,
corrupt priests, and false prophets.
How would you feel?
underqualified?
Would you feel like a little child
challenging a whole group of evil grown-ups?
Notice how Jeremiah felt
as he expressed himself
at Jeremiah 1:6:
“But I said: ‘Alas, O Sovereign Lord Jehovah!
I do not know how to speak,
for I am just a boy.’”
What were Jehovah’s reassuring words
in reply?
Jeremiah 1:8, 9:
“‘Do not be afraid
“‘because of their appearance,
for “I am with you to save you,”
“declares Jehovah.’
“Then Jehovah stretched out his hand
and touched my mouth.
“And Jehovah said to me:
‘I have put my words in your mouth.’”
If Jehovah put the words
that you were to say “in your mouth,”
you’d no longer feel
like a little child, would you?
We don’t think of Jeremiah
as being an incredible superman;
he was a human like us.
It’s of interest that though Jeremiah
lived in another time and place,
he faced situations similar to those we face.
We interact with different types of people
in our daily life,
at work, and at school.
Some of them can be intimidating.
And like Jeremiah,
Jehovah has commissioned us
to go to strangers and preach.
We share the good news of the Kingdom.
Some are interested;
others are just plain apathetic.
But at times, we may come
across someone who is angry
and may even be threatening.
This is the time to remember Jeremiah.
Though initially timid,
he courageously faced
the challenge of an intimidating response.
How did he rally to the occasion?
It was because Jehovah had reassured him:
“I am with you.”
He said:
“I have put my words in your mouth.”
Does Jehovah do something similar for us?
Yes.
Long after Jeremiah
and the other faithful ones
who are recorded
in the Hebrew Scriptures came and went,
Jehovah has proved to be
with true Christians,
both past and present.
Find with me John chapter 8.
Think of Jesus.
It’s true he was a perfect man,
but did Jehovah leave him all alone?
At John 8:16,
what did Jesus himself say?
“And yet even if I do judge,
my judgment is truthful,
“because I am not alone,
but the Father who sent me is with me.”
We might be thinking
of that intimidating person in the ministry.
Even if you are facing the person
without a fellow Witness standing beside you,
are you really all alone?
Jesus knew that at the most stressful
and emotionally draining time
during his human life,
his disciples would leave him all alone.
But was he really alone?
Let’s read the inspired account
at John 16:32.
Again, these are Jesus’ own words:
“Look! The hour is coming,
indeed, it has come,
“when each one of you
will be scattered to his own house
“and you will leave me alone.
“But I am not alone,
because the Father is with me.”
Jesus was not alone
during his most anxious moments.
Jehovah was with him.
If you think you are alone
standing at the door
of an irritated householder,
think again.
Jehovah is with you.
You have more with you
than if you had your whole congregation
standing in the person’s front yard.
Well, why did Jesus share
this precious insight with us?
Look at the next verse.
Jesus explains his reason
for saying what he did.
John 16:33:
“I have said these things to you
“so that by means of me you may have peace.
“In the world you will have tribulation,
“but take courage!
I have conquered the world.”
We thank Jesus for addressing
our fears and concerns when giving a witness.
Instead of trembling with fear,
he shared his confidence in Jehovah’s support
so that we “may have peace.”
He acknowledged
that we would face tribulation,
but he said
that we could look at his example
and have courage
to deal with the tribulation.
Why?
Jesus said in verse 32
that it was
because ‘the Father was with him.’
Do you recall that Jehovah told Jeremiah:
“I have put my words in your mouth?”
Can Jehovah do the same for us
when we are opposed by unbelievers?
The Christian Greek Scriptures
answer with a resounding yes!
Please follow along with the reading
of the book of Mark chapter 13,
and please notice
that the setting Jesus describes
is in the ministry,
preaching the good news.
Maybe you’ve had a good morning in service,
but then you take one more door.
The person is irate
and even calls the police.
What should you do?
What will you say when the police arrive?
You don’t have to be overly concerned.
Why not?
Because similar to Jeremiah,
Jehovah will, in effect,
put His words in your mouth.
Mark 13:10, 11 says:
“Also, in all the nations,
the good news has to be preached first.
“And when they are taking you
to hand you over,
“do not be anxious beforehand
about what to say;
“but whatever is given you
in that hour, say this,
“for you are not the ones speaking,
but the holy spirit is.”
By this, do we mean that Jehovah
will miraculously put words
in your mouth for you to say?
Not necessarily.
Did you notice verse 11 said
that “the holy spirit” is the one speaking?
You’ve been taught the basis
for your faith from the Scriptures,
and you know the reason
that you teach the Bible’s message.
That’s all stored in your mind.
So, what’s the holy spirit’s role
when we are in an intimidating situation
when sharing the good news?
Jehovah is with you.
He uses his holy spirit
to bring to the surface
some of those precious gems
that might be buried in your mind.
You may be amazed at what you remember
when put under pressure by the authorities
or even by outright opposers.
In this way, Jehovah is with you.
Add to the fact that Jesus is with you
in the disciple-making work.
Let’s be reminded
of this very encouraging thought
at Matthew 28:19, 20.
Jesus was discussing our commission
to preach, teach, and make disciples.
And how does he conclude
the Bible book of Matthew?
Let’s read Matthew 28:19, 20:
“Go, therefore, and make disciples
of people of all the nations,
“baptizing them in the name of the Father
“and of the Son and of the holy spirit,
“teaching them to observe
all the things I have commanded you.
“And look!
I am with you all the days
until the conclusion
of the system of things.”
Jesus said that he is with us now
when we are making disciples
and teaching people the truth.
And he promises
he’ll support us in this important work
until the end
of this wicked system of things.
As prophesied, during this time
of the conclusion of the system,
we are being persecuted
in different areas of the world.
As the Scriptures show,
Satan and his angels
are “misleading the entire inhabited earth.”
Recently, Jehovah’s people
have been persecuted in Russia.
But will the persecution
succeed in eliminating
true worship in that area of the world?
No!
Why not?
It’s because Jehovah is with them.
He and Jesus promised: “I am with you.”
Russia did not learn from the past.
It will prove to be the same for them
as it was for Nazi Germany under Hitler.
Hitler thought his regime
could eradicate
true worship and God’s people
from areas under their control.
But they made a big mistake.
While it is true
that they murdered some 2,000 brothers,
in the end, their scheme ended up in failure.
Why?
Because God was with us, not with them.
“God with us”
—those words have decorated national emblems
and even the uniforms of soldiers of Prussia
and the Czarist Russian Empire.
These words were also
on the belts of German troops
when they marched into Belgium
in the year 1914 of our Common Era.
But they had it wrong!
The Sovereign Lord Jehovah
was with us, not with them.
He’s with all of us now.
He’ll be with us during Armageddon.
He’ll be with us after Armageddon.
He’ll be with us at the end
of the Thousand Year Reign of Christ.
He’ll be with mankind
at the end of 100,000 years.
He’ll be with humans
at the end of 100 million years
and at the end of 100 million years
times 100 million years.
Jehovah will be with mankind forever,
and so will Jesus!
They are both on record as saying:
“I am with you”!
Thank you very much, Brother Lösch.
Today, Jehovah is with his people everywhere.
We’re going to see examples of this next.
First is the experience
of Adam and Nancy Solomon.
When they came into the truth,
they faced bitter opposition
from their families.
Notice how Jehovah was with them
during this stressful time.
My family are Hungarian Jews.
Most of them were killed
in concentration camps.
That’s something
that the Holocaust took from me
—it took the concept of family.
I needed explanations.
I needed to know why my family was murdered.
It made me really search
at a very young age to see
if there was a real religion out there.
It was just a secular thing to be Jewish;
it was a cultural thing.
A friend of mine came up to me and said:
“I have to tell you something.
“I got this book
from one of Jehovah’s Witnesses.
It is the most beautiful book
I have ever read.”
I said, “Oh, I’ll read it.”
And it couldn’t have been a week later
that I got a knock on my door, and there were
two young women at the door
who started to talk to me about the Bible.
Once I started having a study
on a regular basis with Carolyn,
I enjoyed it more and more.
One day my father was home.
He just screamed at them
and basically threw them out of the house.
It just progressed after that.
There was just no peace at any time
and a lot of tears.
And I just couldn’t understand
why they weren’t even asking me:
“Well, what is it
that you like about this religion?
“Who are these people?
Let us talk to—”
No, nothing.
It was very, very hard.
Shortly after my baptism,
my mother came up to me, and she said:
“Your father and I are going out for the day.
You better not be here when we get home.”
I was 17 years old.
I didn’t know where I was going to go.
I didn’t know what I was going to do.
But I trusted in Jehovah.
And I picked up the phone,
and I called my Carolyn.
In what seemed like minutes,
there were brothers and sisters at the house.
They were putting my things into this truck
and bringing it over to Carolyn’s house.
And she said, “You can live with me.”
Before I was baptized,
I would drive back and forth
to school with a friend of mine.
Little by little,
I was telling him what I was learning.
He said: “You know,
I want to meet these people.
I have some questions.”
I had questions.
I asked them:
“Why do we die?,
Why do we grow old?,”
and so forth and so on.
And they went right to the Bible,
and when I left the house after that,
I said, “This is the truth!”
Growing up in my house,
going to church every Sunday
was something that you had to do.
But when I became a teenager,
then religion became less in my life,
and basketball became more.
Being a young man, you’d watch sports
and you’d see
that sports players made a lot of money.
My teachers would tell my parents:
“He’s going to be a good basketball player.
“Take care of him.
“He could be worth, you know,
several hundred thousand dollars
by the time he graduates.”
I received over 125 scholarships.
Now you’re talking about a free education
just because you can play basketball.
So I realized, you know,
at an early age that playing
professional basketball could mean a lot,
not only for me but for my family.
So as far as God was concerned,
I had a little interest in God
(like I would ask my mom questions),
but it wasn’t until Nancy
brought me to the Witnesses
that really something just kicked in.
I was studying,
and my mom was downstairs in the basement.
I heard her crying,
and I said, “What’s wrong?”
And she said, “I know you’re going to become
one of those Jehovah’s Witnesses.”
So realizing in my mind
that I’m not going to become
a basketball player
but that I’m going to become
one of Jehovah’s Witnesses
because that’s more important
—that affected me many, many times.
When others found out
that I was going to become
one of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
people shied away.
People try to use you when they think
you can give them something
or you’re going to be somebody big.
By going the direction
of serving Jehovah completely,
you lost all the worldly people
that you thought were your friends.
And so that was
in one summer that I started
the study with Brother Crespo,
and in six months, I was baptized.
And then we decided to get married.
The scripture that says
that ‘even if my own father
and my mother would abandon me,’
that even ‘Jehovah would take me in,’
—it proved to be true in so many ways.
Once you become one of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
you’re part of a family
that will do anything for you.
We’ve had adversity over the years,
but Jehovah never said
everything was going to be perfect.
What he says is
that when you face these problems,
you will not face them alone.
And Jehovah has never let us down
when it comes to that.
When their families
and friends abandoned them,
did you notice how Jehovah
continued to be with Adam and Nancy?
Their spiritual family
immediately stepped in to support them.
I appreciated what Nancy said:
‘Jehovah never said
everything will be perfect.
‘He said that when you face problems,
you will not face them alone.’
She and Adam never felt alone.
Often, we ask Jehovah
to be with us when we need something
—a spiritual need or a material need.
But as we’ll see in this next experience,
even before we know that we have a need,
Jehovah already knows what we need.
My name is Reeta.
My son is Jackson,
and my daughter is Sherina.
It’s just the three of us.
I have been working
on a tea estate as a tea picker.
One day, I prayed to God very hard.
I said,
“Please help me to learn about the Bible.”
Within two days,
Jehovah’s Witnesses came
and knocked on my door,
and I agreed to study the Bible.
I couldn’t believe it.
I only prayed yesterday,
asking God to help me to study the Bible.
Our meetings begin at 4:45 p.m.,
but we have to get ready by 12 o’clock
to attend the meetings.
So we prepare our bags
on Wednesday night.
I carry two big bags
on my shoulders
and walk for three
and a half kilometers (2 mi)
to get to the meetings on time.
We love seeing our brothers.
That’s why we always
go to the meetings early.
I have been pioneering now
for a year and six months.
There is no greater happiness
than what comes from pioneering.
This is a onetime opportunity.
That is why we decided that we should
give the best that we can to Jehovah.
Now I am so happy to be serving this way.
One time, I was not paid at all.
I didn’t even have a rupee.
On that day, my children and I ate well.
But after eating,
we were very worried
about what we were going
to do the following day.
So that night,
I said a prayer with the kids
and we read the Bible.
Jesus said,
‘Don’t worry about tomorrow.’
So I trusted that somehow
Jehovah would give us what we needed.
It was 10:30 at night.
I was fast asleep, and the phone rang.
Usually no one calls this late,
so I wondered,
‘Who could be calling me this late?’
I picked up the phone,
and it was a brother on the line.
He said, “Sister,
go to your bookshelf
and take the Greatest Man book.”
Then he asked me to turn to a page.
When I turned to that page,
there were 10,000 rupees (about $55, U.S.)
between those pages.
We could not believe our eyes.
It was exactly what we needed
for that month’s expenses.
A few days earlier,
he and his wife had visited us
and secretly left the money
in the book before leaving.
So I thanked Jehovah in prayer with the kids.
Jehovah already knew exactly what we needed
even before we realized it.
Honestly, every night I open the doors,
go outside, and look up at the night sky.
When I look up, I see many stars.
I daily meditate about his wisdom,
his power,
what amazing things he is able to do.
This earth, this universe
—how amazingly well he cares for them!
He takes care of the smallest thing.
I completely rely on Jehovah,
and then I remember
that Jehovah has the ability
to help us with his holy spirit.
He’s such a loving Father.
He’s always holding our hand tight,
and no one can separate us from him.
If anyone tries, they will fail.
He’s so generous with his love.
He’s so affectionate with us.
No one can take away
the love Jehovah has for us.
Did you notice from Reeta’s experience
that Jehovah is with us in several ways?
Reeta really appreciates
congregation meetings.
They love being with their brothers.
How about you?
Do you value the meetings
and the encouraging association
you find there?
Reeta takes time to meditate
on the wonders of creation,
and she does more than marvel
at what she sees.
She notices
how Jehovah’s love and care for her
is evident in all his works.
She knows that Jehovah
has the power to create anything,
and he wants to use his power in her behalf.
It’s no surprise that Reeta is keenly aware
of Jehovah’s constant support
in her pioneer ministry.
Jehovah proves to be with us in the ministry,
whether we’re preaching
in our local community
or sharing in a special campaign.
Let’s go to Europe
and watch a report about a special campaign.
As with Reeta’s experience,
see if you can identify
how Jehovah was with the many thousands
who volunteered for this campaign.
In the Central Europe branch territory,
a special campaign was organized.
Actually, the School
for Branch Committee Members and Their Wives
triggered an evaluation of how much territory
in the countries we oversee
is not really covered thoroughly.
So we asked our circuit overseers
to recommend to us which sections
of the congregation’s territory
could be listed
as so-called “unassigned territory.”
All in all, we received
over 11,000 territories
from the congregations,
with approximately 3 million inhabitants.
So because of this grand scale,
there was suddenly the idea,
‘Why not organize
a special preaching campaign
‘to cover all these territories
on one single weekend?’
This was really exciting.
And after getting
the Branch Committee’s approval,
the Service Department
started to organize it.
To be honest, at first,
we were not really sure
how the publishers
would react to such a campaign.
But we fully trusted in Jehovah,
and the response was stunning.
Over 20,000 publishers participated
and were assigned
to all these territories throughout Germany.
The campaign took place
on one weekend in May 2017
and was especially successful
in metropolitan areas,
as in Berlin, Hamburg, and Düsseldorf.
At one door, a man just arrived.
He wanted to open his shop
where he sells Arabian specialties.
We were able to show him a video in Arabic.
Then he gave us his address and phone number.
He also agreed
to have someone visit him again.
Yes, it’s really a privilege
to join in such a campaign
and to see that every human
is precious to Jehovah,
no matter where they live
or where they come from.
Because of the need
and the fantastic response in 2017,
it was decided to repeat
such a campaign in May 2018.
And this time it was expanded to Switzerland,
Austria, Luxembourg, and Liechtenstein.
And now imagine,
over 32,000 publishers participated,
which is actually over 60 percent more
than in May 2017.
This was really faith-strengthening.
And, again, a lot
of wonderful experiences were reported.
It’s incredible.
No matter where you are in Berlin,
you can see small groups
of brothers everywhere.
That was really great.
In the ministry we met a woman,
and she told us
that she had just prayed for a Bible study.
We are now more than ever convinced
that Jehovah leads all this work
through his angels.
Today, Sunday, we had a nice experience.
A woman called us from behind.
She had actually already passed us,
but she had the feeling
she had to go back again
—she told us later.
After she had invited us to her home,
we exchanged our contact information
and we also filled in
the online contact form.
Had we been in the territory
just one minute later,
we would never have made the contact.
This must have been guided by the angels.
Yesterday morning while in the ministry,
a young man ran after us
and asked us what we were doing.
We explained it to him.
He asked us why there is still
so much evil in the world, then.
In the afternoon,
we were able to call on him again.
We could start a Bible study right away
and arrange a return visit,
which we will make today.
Being together
with the friends is just so great.
You’re out and about with a large group.
You meet up again regularly
to change partners and to relate experiences.
It’s just great.
Thousands of videos were shown,
and a lot of Bible studies were started.
And what is very interesting
is that a lot of publishers
felt motivated
to expand their ministry after the campaign.
For sure,
these preaching campaigns truly prove
that Jehovah and Jesus
are directing the preaching work.
And the angels are helping us
in reaching out to all people.
Yes, we really have a lot of reasons
to be Jehovah’s happy people.
Jehovah truly proved to be
with all who volunteered
to share in this campaign.
How else could the good news
reach three million people
in such a well-organized way?
We’d like to thank
the more than 32,000 brothers and sisters
who shared in this special work.
As Brother Lösch noted in his talk,
Jehovah is with us in the ministry.
There’s no doubt he is directing
the global preaching work
through Jesus and his angels.
Did you notice how many people were contacted
soon after they prayed for a Bible study
or for a question to be answered?
Isn’t that interesting?
When we’re together
with a large group of Jehovah’s people
in the ministry
and at our meetings and assemblies,
we really feel Jehovah’s blessing, don’t we?
But what if we’re isolated?
What if we’re facing persecution?
This is what Alphonse Takla
experienced some years ago in Egypt.
Let’s see how Jehovah proved to be with him.
All was dark;
everything was pitch-black dark.
Egypt was at war with Israel,
and they were arresting the brothers,
charging us of practicing illegal activities
as a banned organization.
On that night, we were being transferred
to the concentration camp.
We couldn’t see much.
“What’s going on there?
What’s this place look like? Where is it?”
The officer got two soldiers to escort us
to our cell where the brothers were.
We knew that when people
are taken to the concentration camp,
they spend years
and some of them never return back.
When I was, you know, a teenager,
I liked the characters in the Bible,
like Abraham,
Daniel,
Moses.
I thought that they were
champions of true worship.
At some stage, I felt jealous of them.
They had this huge relationship with God,
so I’d like to be part of that.
I continued to read the Bible
to get closer to God.
I knew that Jehovah would look after me;
he would not abandon his servant.
So we tried to encourage them:
“Brothers, keep in mind
that we’re here because we worship Jehovah.”
We sat together to discuss, you know,
what we were going to do
to keep spiritually strong.
So we thought that we needed to pray.
We picked out a scripture every day,
like a daily text,
and then after that, recited scriptures.
One would handle
a talk from the memory of heart
and then an open discussion
of Bible questions.
At that stage,
we didn’t have a Bible with us.
The officers wanted us to renounce our faith,
so they told me to lay on the ground,
and there they started to beat me.
The whole camp was around,
and one of the prisoners fainted.
I started to pray to Jehovah:
“Jehovah, help me to be able to endure that!”
It was very severe pain.
And I felt his help
because after a few beatings,
my body felt numb.
I didn’t feel much more pain.
One of the prisoners said to me,
“If I get out of here alive,
“I’ll tell my children
that in the concentration camp,
“I saw the Christians that reminded me
of the first-century Christians
—that they were happy even to die
without renouncing their faith.”
One of the officers
—this nasty one
that used to beat us very, very severely—
came one day and said,
“We need two of you to come out
and write a report about what you believe.”
So we thought about it:
‘Is it wise to do that?
Or maybe they will use it against us.’
You know, we prayed to Jehovah
for help to make a decision here,
to guide us on what to do.
So in the end, we reached a point that,
well, we may get out; we may not.
So we might as well give them a witness.
I told the officer, “We need a Bible.”
And he said, “What for?”
I said to him, “Because we need
to quote from the Bible in this report.”
So he said,
“OK, do you have a Bible in the storeroom?”
I said, “Yes, I have a Bible.”
He said, “OK, go and get your Bible.”
I went to my bag and picked up the Bible.
So he picked up the Bible from my hand,
opened it randomly, and started to read.
“Numbers.”
He looked at me.
“Who wrote this book?”
I said to him, “Moses.”
“You’re a liar!” at the top of his voice.
So I kept quiet,
and he closed the book again
and opened it again.
“You’re a liar!”
again at the top of his voice.
I was racing in my mind
where it is written in the Bible
that Jehovah told Moses to write any of this.
He shut the book again,
and for a third time,
opened it again,
and he started to read in a loud voice.
So the officer looked at me
with a big surprise on his face.
After we wrote the report,
I asked him,
“Can we keep the Bible, please?”
He said, “OK, keep the Bible.”
For three months, nearly every day,
the officers came in and beat us
and expected us to compromise.
We never did that.
All I can say is that it was Jehovah’s hand.
Jehovah was helping us to endure
—to continue to do his will
by not compromising
because we belong to him
and we rely on him.
God will not abandon his servant.
Why was Alphonse thrown into prison?
It wasn’t because he refused to say
a simple greeting
to the president of his country.
No, that phrase was a political slogan.
Like many Jehovah’s Witnesses,
Alphonse was persecuted for his neutrality.
What helped Alphonse to be loyal?
He prayed.
He prayed to maintain
a strong spiritual routine,
he prayed when he had to make a decision,
and he prayed for help
to endure brutal treatment.
Like Alphonse,
do you depend on the power of prayer?
Alphonse and, earlier, Reeta
likened their relationship
with Jehovah to holding His hand.
Reeta said,
‘Jehovah holds our hand tight.’
Alphonse said, “All I can say
is that it was Jehovah’s hand.”
What a beautiful image!
That’s how close we can be to Jehovah.
This month’s music video reminds us of that.
Jehovah is always willing to hold our hand.
It’s entitled Jehovah’s Always by Our Side.
At times, I felt scared inside,
Only looking for a place to hide.
The world made me feel different.
Now I hold my head up high.
He said he’d be my confidence,
That he’d come to my defense.
His love I can’t deny,
’Cause he gave me
Courage when I was feeling weak,
Courage when I could not speak,
Courage in my darkest night,
Courage to stand up tall,
Courage to face it all,
Courage to trust him with my life.
Jehovah’s always by my side.
He walks with me
To help me see
His ways are always right.
He’ll take my hand,
Help me understand
It’s worth the sacrifice.
You are not alone.
Even far away from home,
He’ll be your guide.
He will pick you up
Even when you think you’ve had enough
And make you strong and wise,
’Cause he’ll give you
Courage when you are feeling weak,
Courage when you cannot speak,
Courage in your darkest nights,
Courage to stand up tall,
Courage to face it all,
Courage to trust him with your life.
Jehovah’s always by our side—
Always, always.
Jehovah’s always by our side.
He walks with you and me
To help us see
His ways are always right.
Jehovah’s always by our side.
He’ll take our hand,
Help us understand
It’s worth the sacrifice.
He gave me
Courage when I was feeling weak,
Courage when I could not speak,
Courage in my darkest night,
Courage to stand up tall,
Courage to face it all,
Courage to trust him with my life.
Jehovah’s always by our side—
Always, always.
Jehovah’s always by our side.
What a beautiful song!
For many months on JW Broadcasting,
we’ve enjoyed a series
of video dramatizations
about applying Bible principles in our lives.
We have learned
that we can enjoy happier lives today
and live in a way that pleases God
when we apply
Jehovah’s principles and standards.
Applying God’s principles
also gives us a wonderful hope.
As our concluding video in this series shows,
focusing on our future hope
helps us to build the faith
to withstand trials we face today.
See if you remember these scenes.
Getting baptized
was the most important decision I ever made.
But it took some time to realize that
that was just the start of my Christian life.
Sometimes it was hard to show courage.
Why don’t you people get involved
and make a real difference for once?
And it was hard for my son too.
No thanks.
I’m a Jehovah’s Witness,
and I don’t celebrate birthdays.
What?
Hum?
That’s rude.
Come on, sign it!
I really liked Lucas,
and he was very sick.
I really wanted to sign his birthday card,
but Dad helped me to see
how Jehovah felt about it,
and that helped me be brave.
I still didn’t sign the card,
but I’m going to do something else for Lucas.
My parents had always set
a good example for me.
But after I moved
to serve where the need was greater,
it seemed like my parents were growing apart.
Are you both doing OK?
Because you don’t look OK.
Of course, we’re OK.
OK? We’re doing wonderful, right?
Yeah, we’re doing good.
Everything is good.
I was really worried.
Later, they told me that what helped them
was their love for Jehovah.
They meditated on the example
of Abraham and Sarah,
who showed honor to each other
by listening and by caring.
That example really helped my parents.
And since then,
I’ve seen how it can help
in any relationship.
I’m a long way from home,
but showing love to others
—it helps me to stay happy in my assignment.
When our doctor told us that our baby
would likely be born with severe problems
and could even die,
it was more than I could bear.
And because my husband
was not one of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
I needed God’s help more than ever
to calm my heart and help me explain
why I could never have an abortion.
And even though it took me years
before I would agree to a Bible study
and even more years before I made
enough changes to qualify for baptism,
the life we have now
—serving Jehovah together—
nothing could make me happier.
Nothing could make us happier.
Happiness really does come
from serving Jehovah,
but serving him faithfully
definitely takes courage.
It was so hard for me
to turn down that girl at school.
And I felt so guilty
for how involved I’d gotten with her.
My uncle used the Bible
to help me get back on track
and to remind me
of two other very important things:
that Jehovah was proud of me
and that I was not alone.
James 1:2, 3 says:
“Consider it all joy, my brothers,
“when you meet with various trials,
“knowing as you do
“that this tested quality of your faith
produces endurance.”
I think about that scripture a lot
because soon I’ll probably be sent
to prison for refusing military service.
Being courageous with that classmate
helped me build the faith
and courage that I need now.
I can give up anything for Jehovah.
I might live in a small cell for now,
but in Paradise,
I’m going to travel everywhere.
Sometimes I get lonely, but that’s OK.
It’s a choice that I’ve made
to stay in my assignment right now.
In the future, if I choose to get married,
I hope to have a marriage like my parents.
I really hope that Lucas is resurrected
so I can show him around Paradise
and teach him more about Jehovah.
I showed him pictures,
but the real thing will be so much better.
Then I can hold my baby girl again.
Our program
has focused on the many ways
that Jehovah is with us.
He’s with us
as we work toward dedication
and baptism.
He’s with us at our congregation meetings
and when we are with our spiritual family.
He’s with us as we successfully face
persecution and hardship.
And Jehovah is with us
when we share the good news of his Kingdom
with everyone we meet.
And, Brother Marais,
I appreciate that you were here with me
for this month’s program.
Thank you, Brother Lösch.
We end this month’s program
with a visit to our brothers
and sisters in Tenerife.
Tenerife is the largest
of the Canary Islands,
an archipelago
off the northwest coast of Africa.
These islands
were formed by volcanic eruptions.
The highest point
is the dormant Teide volcano on Tenerife.
Here the weather
is mild and sunny throughout the year.
This has made the Canary Islands famous
for their extensive banana plantations.
Tenerife is a popular tourist destination.
It’s home to nearly a million people,
but more than ten million visitors
come every year to enjoy the beaches,
the lush terrain,
and the food.
The island of Tenerife has 33 congregations
and more than 3,000 publishers,
492 of whom are regular pioneers.
Because of the influx of visitors
from all over the world,
our brothers and sisters
preach in over 15 languages,
including Russian,
German,
French,
Hindi,
and Romanian.
They preach everywhere
—in the cities
as well as the rural and mountainous regions.
Our brothers and sisters in Tenerife
send you
their warm Christian love and greetings.
From the World Headquarters
of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
this is JW Broadcasting.