“If they have persecuted me,
they will also persecute you”
—Jesus’ words.
And Paul saw the truth of Jesus’ words.
As a follower of Jesus, Paul experienced
much persecution and tribulation.
And isn’t it true
that we see the same today?
Satan still challenges
the integrity of Jehovah’s people.
In fact, the Bible indicates
that Satan will increase his attacks
on Jehovah’s people in these last days.
And we see this happening.
As we look at the attacks being made
on Jehovah’s people around the world,
we think of our brothers in Eritrea,
our brothers in Korea,
in Russia, other places,
and even smaller attacks
that we may not even personally hear about.
Truly, Jesus’ words
are being fulfilled today.
But the question
we want to consider today is,
What about us personally?
See, the text says
that ‘if they’ve persecuted me,’
Jesus said,
‘they will persecute you.’
At 2 Timothy 3:12, it says:
“All those desiring
to live with godly devotion . . .
will also be persecuted.”
So that means we’re not exempt.
And as our text highlights,
things can quickly turn.
Sometimes it’s outright persecution
from governments
or opposition from family members.
In other cases,
it may be efforts to block our work
or hamper a theocratic project
or another initiative.
How will we do
when faced with persecution
and opposition?
Now, it’s easy to say “Trust in Jehovah,”
and we know we need to do that.
But what does that mean?
How do we know what decisions to make?
What’s the right decision?
What’s not the right decision?
Are there principles that can guide us?
Well, let’s consider three of them.
The first one is
that the apparent easy solution
out of a situation
may not be the right solution.
Look in Isaiah chapter 30,
and we’ll look at a solution
that the kings of Israel and Judah
fell back on from time to time.
Isaiah chapter 30,
and let’s read verses 1 and 2.
It says:
“‘Woe to the stubborn sons,’
“declares Jehovah,
“‘who carry out plans that are not mine,
“‘who make alliances, but not by my spirit,
“‘in order to add sin to sin.
“‘They go down to Egypt
without consulting me,
“‘to take shelter under Pharaoh’s protection
and to take refuge
in the shadow of Egypt!’”
You see, the nation
thought it was a good solution
to enlist Egypt’s aid
to keep off the Babylonians and others.
That seemed to be the best choice,
and we saw over and over again
that the unfaithful kings
of Israel and Judah did that.
They chose to strike deals
with Jehovah’s enemies
to protect them
from other enemies of Jehovah.
And so when under attack,
when facing opposition,
we too may be encouraged to strike a deal
—maybe a bit of a compromise
to lessen the pressure.
But now, at other times,
we notice that Paul and others
did appeal to government officials
or appealed to Caesar,
and Jehovah blessed that.
So what’s the lesson?
Well, the lesson is that we need
to make sure that we’re following a course
that is in harmony with Jehovah’s purpose
and that is backed by his spirit.
So we need to prayerfully make sure
that the arrangement
that we’re working out is Jehovah’s will
and to remember that the logical solution
from man’s perspective
may not always be Jehovah’s solution.
Second principle:
and that is not to become distracted
from our main focus and our main work.
And we have a good example of that
when considering Nehemiah.
As we know, Nehemiah
was blocked by enemies of Jehovah
who were trying to stop him
from completing his theocratic project.
Look, for example, at Nehemiah 6:2.
Nehemiah 6:2, and it says:
“Sanballat and Geshem
immediately sent this message to me:
“‘Come, and let us
set a time to meet together
“in the villages of the Valley Plain of Ono.’
But they were scheming to harm me.”
Now, the distance between Jerusalem
and the Valley Plain of Ono
was about 30 to 35 miles,
or about 50 kilometers, away.
Sanballat was not looking
to get together with Nehemiah
to work out how they could help them.
He was scheming to divert the work,
to slow down the work,
to oppose the work;
and Nehemiah knew what they were up to.
Notice what he says in verse 3.
He says:
“I sent messengers to them, saying:
“‘I am engaged in a great work,
and I am not able to go down.
Why should the work stop
while I leave it to come to you?’”
See, Nehemiah did not allow himself
to become distracted
from his main assignment
—from the work
that he had been given to do.
Now, when that didn’t work,
his opposers tried
to get him to choose a solution
that would harm his reputation
and bring reproach on Jehovah’s name.
Look over in verse 10.
See, this says:
‘Well, come into the temple.
Let’s shut the doors of the temple
because they’re coming to kill you.’
Well, look at verse 13.
He says: “He had been hired
to frighten me and to cause me to sin,
“so that they would have grounds
to damage my reputation
in order to reproach me.”
Well see, likewise,
at times we may be offered
solutions out of a situation
or to relieve pressure from opposition
which will distract us
from our primary work
—our service to Jehovah.
Or it may be an initiative
that’s a little bit in a gray area.
Yes, everybody does it,
but it’s a gray area.
And it could damage our reputation
or bring reproach on Jehovah’s name.
So again, what do we do?
Will we seek Jehovah’s direction?
Will this solution distract us
from our main commission?
How will it appear to onlookers?
What will it do to Jehovah’s name?
Now, these first two principles
do not mean that we do not do anything;
and that leads to our third principle.
And that is we do what we can
from a practical standpoint.
We give Jehovah something to bless,
and then we wait on Jehovah.
And the account of Hezekiah
is a beautiful example of that.
We had the drama
at our convention this year,
where the ruthless king of Assyria
was determined to take Jerusalem.
Rabshakeh taunted Hezekiah
and tried to get the people to surrender
and make a deal with Assyria.
What did Hezekiah do?
Well, he displayed
wisdom and military strategy
while waiting on Jehovah.
He did what he could
to give Jehovah something to bless.
Remember what they did?
They went and diverted
the water sources outside the city
so that if there was a siege,
the Assyrians
would have trouble getting water.
They strengthened the city’s fortification
—the walls.
They made missiles in abundance and shields.
They did what they could,
but they trusted in Jehovah.
Remember what Hezekiah said to the people
as recorded at 2 Chronicles 32:7, 8?
He says:
“Be courageous and strong. . . .
There are more with us
than there are with him.”
So they did what they could,
but they relied on Jehovah
for the real solution.
And interestingly, in this case,
Jehovah did not use
anything of what they did.
He provided an angel to deliver them.
So likewise,
when facing persecution today,
facing opposition today,
we do what’s in the power of our hand to do
while keeping in mind
those first two principles
and then we see
what Jehovah works out in our behalf.
So, what’s the lesson for us?
Well, the lesson
is that in the face of persecution,
when we’re going through opposition,
the way through the situation
may not be clear.
It may not be readily apparent.
But look for principles
that can help us to make good decisions.
And, really, it all boils down
to our most effective means
of dealing with persecution and opposition.
Notice what it says at Psalm 9:10.
Psalm 9:10,
it says:
“Those knowing your name will trust in you;
you will never abandon
those seeking you, O Jehovah.”
“Those knowing your name will trust in you.”
We know Jehovah.
We know Jehovah’s name.
We know what his name means.
We know that Jehovah can become,
he can cause us to become,
he can cause any of his creation
to become whatever is needed
to fulfill his purpose.
We just need to trust in him.
He will never abandon us.
So yes, as followers of Jesus,
we will be persecuted.
We will face opposition.
When those days come, how will we do?
Well, may these and other principles
help us to make good decisions,
and may we ultimately trust in
and wait on Jehovah,
convinced that he will never abandon us.