In the past few graduation programs,
we’ve had a new feature entitled
The Inside Story,
and we’re going to have another “inside story.”
One of the instructors, Brother Trent Lippold,
is now going to present that to us.
From far in the North Atlantic
to the islands of the South Pacific,
you will meet
some cool and colorful brothers
and sisters in this 145th class.
They serve on 5 continents,
represent 31 countries,
and speak
more than 45 individual, or different, languages.
So let’s meet our first guest,
and he’s from the Central European branch,
Brother Alex Scholz.
Welcome, Alex.
Good.
Alex, I understand in your assignment,
you have quite, how shall we say,
quite an expansive assignment.
Well, I work with a team
that helps foreign-language circuits.
OK, very nice.
So foreign-language circuits in Germany?
Not just Germany.
Farther.
Foreign-language circuits
in the Central European branch.
Even a little farther, Trent.
OK. Alex, you’re going
to have to help me out with this.
What exactly does your assignment involve?
Well, our team in the Central Europe branch
works with 22 other branch offices
to form and coordinate
foreign-language circuits that span the continent
in languages that are assigned to the project
by the Service Committee
of the Governing Body.
Wow, that sounds huge.
There must be a good reason for it.
Yeah.
Sure, there is.
I mean, as we know, normally a circuit
consists of a group of congregations
and perhaps a few groups
within one branch territory.
Now, in Europe,
we know we have quite a number of countries
and also a number of branch territories.
So, what happened in the past
is that in some languages,
there were foreign-language congregations
or groups that had to be visited
by a local circuit overseer
who didn’t speak the language.
And that was simply
because perhaps in this branch territory,
they didn’t have a circuit overseer
who speaks the language
or they didn’t have enough congregations
to form their own foreign-language circuit
in that branch territory.
And that, of course, poses a challenge
if the CO doesn’t speak that language
or he’s not so familiar
with the territory or that language field.
Sure, I can see that.
Then it would be difficult for him to really give
specific direction to the congregation.
That’s the thing.
And some publishers
in these groups perhaps felt isolated.
Besides,
they didn’t necessarily have circuit assemblies
or pioneer meetings
in their language or in their vicinity.
Right. But I know the Governing Body
made a change about that.
Yeah, and that was excellent.
I mean, it’s a beautiful project.
Since 2016, we now have what we call
foreign-language circuits
that span branch territories in Europe.
OK. Well, how does this work now?
Well, imagine Europe,
or perhaps it’s best we take a look at a map.
We have a map of Europe?
OK. We have a map.
Super. Very good.
So this is how we look at Europe in this project
—Europe without borders.
OK.
All we want to see is,
Where are
the foreign-language congregations and groups?
And maybe it’s best we can see this
in one example with the Chinese field.
Wow.
So we look at all the congregations and groups
(we see them depicted here),
and simply what we do
is we group them together
by a number of parameters into circuits.
But this is regardless of any national borders.
And what results is all these groups
and congregations are in actual circuits.
They have their circuit events,
they have their pioneer meetings,
they have their circuit overseer
who speaks their language,
and they meet together
for circuit assemblies.
More people come together
from various countries.
It’s a wonderful atmosphere.
Very nice.
That’s incredible.
So this is the Chinese circuit.
That’s Chinese.
We have Russian here with . . .
OK.
. . . the 20 circuits
that we have right now that span Europe.
And here’s the Romany field
with growing circuits in Europe.
Very interesting.
I mean, how many are we talking about, Alex?
Right now we have in the project 115 circuits
with more than 4,000 congregations
and groups involved.
Wow.
And to date, 18 languages
have been assigned to the project.
That is remarkable.
So, what would you say?
How have the brothers and sisters
in these foreign-language congregations
and circuits been affected?
Well, we have
very positive reflections from the field.
The publishers often appreciate
the fact that they now receive
theocratic care by a circuit overseer
who speaks their language,
and that’s a beautiful aspect.
Besides that, because of this
now theocratically borderless Europe,
if we want to call it this way,
we as branch offices
have more opportunity to work together
—to organize conventions in these languages,
circuit assemblies, schools, pioneer meetings.
And all of this furthers the preaching work,
and that’s amazing to see.
Well, that’s the benefit, isn’t it?
That’s tremendous.
You know, Alex, for us in Gilead,
most of the instructors of Gilead,
we’ve been in the circuit work.
So circuit work is close to our hearts.
As I’m looking at these huge circuits,
I’m asking myself,
‘How do these circuit overseers
care for such huge territories?’
What is it like?
You know, that’s a very good question
because these brothers and sisters
work so hard in these fields.
Actually, we have a little video
that follows one traveling couple,
Brother and Sister Dietrich.
They are traveling in one of the Albanian circuits
that span branch territories in Europe.
And if you’d like, we could take a look
at the video and see how they’re doing.
Excellent.
Let’s look at the video now then.
Today, many Albanian Witnesses are settled
in different countries,
but they are not isolated.
Edlira and I are serving
one of three Albanian circuits in Europe
that span branch territories.
Serving a multinational circuit
takes extra effort and planning.
But seeing Jehovah’s care for his people,
no matter the situation, is worth it.
We’re a small congregation in a foreign country.
Our circuit is now supported
by Albanian-speaking brothers
from several European countries,
and we feel the unity
in our brotherhood even more.
At this regional convention,
brothers and sisters
are attending from Germany,
Austria, Belgium, Great Britain,
and Switzerland.
We have met many friends
who speak our language.
We are learning a lot about them
and are encouraged by their examples of faith.
In the circuit, those in northern Italy
are together with others
in Germany, Austria, and Slovenia.
They are united across national borders
with others who speak Albanian.
That’s beautiful, Alex
—united in the spiritual paradise—
no borders.
Absolutely.
That’s true.
I think about this, though, Alex.
You know,
some say that language actually divides.
I mean, that goes back to the Tower of Babel.
And some might feel that, well,
by grouping people into language groups,
you’re actually dividing people.
How would you answer that?
Well, you know language
definitely has the potential to divide
—no question.
But, honestly,
by the way the organization is using language,
I see the opposite effect taking place.
You know, this project is not about promoting
particular cultures or particular languages.
What this project allows us to do
is to reach across man-made borders
to unite our brothers and sisters
by using their local language
to teach the true and pure language.
And that is unity, as we’ve seen in the video.
Well, we look forward to hearing
about more of those details.
Thank you.
Just maybe in conclusion, Alex,
one final thought.
Thinking about your assignment,
is there one particular thought from Gilead
(I know there’s probably many),
but is there one particular thought
that you would like to especially apply
in your assignment?
Yeah, you’re right.
There are many.
Maybe just one
that was repeatedly mentioned in class
is how Jesus worked with others
—never as a superior,
but as a friend, as a confidant—
open, trusted communication.
And that’s a beautiful example.
And I just hope that I can pick up
a little bit of this wonderful example
when I have the privilege
to talk to the circuit overseers
out there in this huge field.
Or when we talk
to the other responsible brothers
in the other branch offices,
that it is this open, trusted communication
as friends and as fellow workers.
We all have the same goal
—furthering the preaching work.
That’s a goal I have.
Very nice.
It’s a valuable point for all of us.
Well, Alex, may Jehovah richly bless you
and your wife, Tabitha, in your assignment.
Thank you very much.
Thank you.
Let’s welcome our next guest,
and it’s Brother Thomas Bohnfeldt
from Greenland.
Hi, Thomas.
Hi.
Hey, welcome Thomas.
Thank you.
You look very comfortable.
Oh, thank you.
I am.
So, what do you call that?
This is an anorak.
You know,
it’s all about staying warm in Greenland.
So, actually, this is traditional formal wear,
and it is used for special occasions.
So many brothers wear it
at the conventions on the day of baptism.
This is very special.
Well, I like Greenland already;
I can tell you that.
When I think of Greenland, though,
I’m not thinking green land;
I’m thinking ice, snow.
Yeah, you are right.
It is really a land of ice and snow.
Most of Greenland lies within the Arctic Circle.
The biggest part of the land
is the Greenland Ice Sheet,
and it’s up to 3,000 meters thick in the center.
And from there,
huge icebergs break off out to the sea.
Icebergs like this one.
Yes.
Yeah, that definitely sounds cool to me.
So, what I wonder though is,
What are the people like in Greenland?
Ah, that’s where the warmth is.
People in Greenland
are very kind and warmhearted.
Greenland is part of the Kingdom of Denmark.
So many speak Danish,
but the majority
—the native Inuit—
speak Greenlandic.
Greenlandic—when I think of Greenlandic,
the only thing that comes to mind is long words.
Yes, that’s the first thing
many people notice about Greenlandic.
For example,
we have the title of The Watchtower on two lines.
Can you say it?
Ah, I don’t think I can, actually.
But you said it so well.
As I look at that, though, I wonder,
Do you have spelling contests in Greenland?
No, we don’t have time for that.
You and Peninna, do you speak Greenlandic?
Yes, we do now.
But we are still learning.
Of course.
How did you learn Greenlandic?
So we are originally from Denmark
and brought up in Denmark.
But, interestingly,
my parents actually were special pioneers
when they were young in Greenland
and helped form a congregation.
Well, that’s very interesting.
That’s a nice spiritual heritage to have.
And some years ago,
we visited Greenland as a family,
and we see pictures here.
You still look relaxed, Thomas.
Actually, back then I remembered,
‘Perhaps I could serve in Greenland sometime.’
But that thought just—
Really?
I forgot that thought.
Yeah, but then years passed.
I began to court Peninna,
and when we were engaged to marry,
we asked the branch where we could serve.
And to our surprise,
they asked us to start learning Greenlandic.
So we moved to Copenhagen
and took some language courses.
And after three years,
we were sent to Greenland as special pioneers
and helped support the translation office.
That’s amazing.
So it’s almost like you were following
in your parents’ footsteps, then, to Greenland.
Yes.
So was it an easy adjustment?
Denmark? Greenland?
No.
Denmark and Greenland are very different.
But with the help from Jehovah
and also with support from brothers, we adapted.
Yeah,
it looks like you’ve fully adapted, actually.
I understand that your assignment
has changed a little bit over the years.
So now we are at the RTO in Nuuk,
in the Greenlandic RTO.
There are four of us full-time, and we have
more than ten part-time commuters.
OK, so that’s more than 14
in the RTO but still a small group.
That’s a lot of work for a translation office.
Are there benefits?
Have you seen the benefits
from the work you’re doing?
Yes, definitely.
So in Greenlandic,
there’s not much published secularly
but our publications
have been published for many years.
And they are very well-known.
So people really love
when they see our literature.
And besides that,
our videos in Greenlandic are a great support
for many of the need-greaters
coming to support the ministry in Greenlandic.
Right.
Now, I wondered what the ministry was like.
Now, we did a little homework on Greenland.
I know there are five congregations in Greenland,
about 170 publishers,
and around 56,000 people that live in Greenland.
But we also understand
that a lot of them live in very remote villages.
So how do you reach
those people in these isolated areas?
Yes, well, that’s all about timing.
Timing?
Yeah.
But to help you understand it, we have a video
from a congregation far north of Nuuk
in the village of Ilulissat,
meaning “icebergs.”
Well, let’s have a look,
and let’s visit the icebergs.
For about seven months of the year,
Greenland looks like this.
But when the ice melts,
signs of life begin to emerge
and the brothers and sisters get moving!
The Danish congregation
in the town of Ilulissat also preaches
to Greenlandic-speaking people.
It’s the northernmost congregation
in Greenland.
They travel to many remote villages
to spread the good news
in Greenlandic.
Their territory spans hundreds of miles.
Today, they are preaching
in the village of Oqaatsut.
It’s good to be out of the boat
after their long journey,
but their work is just beginning.
They’ve had good results
in these villages before.
This is Sara from a village farther north.
She wanted to study,
but she lived too far away for a regular visit.
So a sister in Ilulissat
studied with her over the phone.
She would tie in to the meetings
during the long, cold months of winter,
but she felt that wasn’t enough.
So she moved some 300 miles to Ilulissat.
She remembers the tears at her first meeting.
Sara was now with her spiritual family.
In time, she was baptized.
The weather and distances
make it difficult for the brothers and sisters,
but they return to these villages year after year,
searching for more ‘friends of peace’
in the vast and isolated regions
of northern Greenland.
That was fantastic, Thomas.
But it looks like there is
a lot of work to do in Greenland.
Yes, there is.
And arrangements have been made
so that Sarah and other native speakers
can tie in to the Greenlandic meetings
in Nuuk for some parts of the meeting.
And besides that, at our meetings in Nuuk,
we also use simultaneous translation
using headphones and radio
so that whether you speak
Danish or Greenlandic,
you can participate and benefit.
Wow!
That is absolutely amazing.
How do you say “wow” in Greenlandic?
I’ll leave that for you.
Thank you very much for being with us, Thomas.
And, again, for you
and your wife Peninna as well,
we wish you
Jehovah’s blessing in your assignment.
Well, so far we’ve been talking
about unity and language.
And some of the students have prepared
a song that addresses just those themes.
So let’s enjoy the song
that they’ve prepared to sing to their classmates.
That was a beautiful song
sung in the 24 languages
of the heart of their classmates
but with one voice.
Let’s welcome our next guests,
Meraf and Yohannes Gorems from Ethiopia.
Welcome, Johnny.
Welcome, Meraf.
Thank you.
Please.
I understand they call you Johnny, actually.
Johnny, you and Meraf
have a different assignment.
Could you explain what your assignment is?
We are not Bethelites.
We serve in the circuit work.
But you like Bethelites?
I like.
Good.
So, what is the circuit work like in Ethiopia?
What are the people in Ethiopia like?
Ethiopian people
are generally kind, warm,
hospitable, open to talking,
and most are religious people.
It is easy to start conversations
because they love spiritual matters.
OK.
Is there maybe one experience,
one special experience,
that stands out to you?
We were assigned a circuit
in the southern part of Ethiopia.
Two special pioneers served there.
One of them asked me if I would go with him.
He had a return visit.
Two years ago, he met this man
and now he wanted to go back again.
Wait, so this is after two years.
He had a nice call;
he studied with people there;
and now two years later,
he wants to go back.
So why did he wait so long?
Because it was too remote.
How remote was it?
It takes three days
from a nearby city to get there.
We started by bus,
and we arrived in one small city.
Then we took a truck, seven to nine hours.
Sometimes we spent all night on that road.
So sleeping on the road
—OK, there is a picture.
Yeah, but I slept well.
So I presume you took a truck
because there were no more buses.
So the buses end, and now you take the truck.
After the truck, you walked?
I walked the rest of the way.
Short walk?
Depends what you call short.
If 11 hours is short to you, then yes.
Eleven hours?
So, what was it like
walking 11 hours to this village?
When we walked in the jungle, I got scared.
I think I was thinking,
‘If something happens here,
how could I get out of this jungle?’
How could you get out?
Yeah, so I prayed.
Immediately,
my thoughts changed from fear to boldness.
I was thinking
that this is a privilege, like the apostles.
Interesting.
Now, Meraf, you were not with Yohannes.
So, what were you thinking while he was gone?
I mean,
this is three days already he was gone.
That was the hardest part of my life
because there was no network to contact him.
I didn’t know whether he
was alive, wounded, or lost.
I had no idea.
And we were in a circuit visit,
so I should look strong in front of others.
So I couldn’t say anything,
but I was praying and crying a lot.
So you reached the village
after your 11-hour walk.
You found the interested person?
Uh-huh.
He had other Bible students.
The interested person had Bible students?
The interested person.
How long did you stay?
My plan was one or two days
to spend there, but I couldn’t.
Because of the interest, you couldn’t leave?
Yeah, because of two things.
The first thing: They were very interested,
so I had to stay there.
The other thing was our legs were like wood.
Like wood?
Yeah.
From 11 hours of walking?
Eleven hours, yeah.
But when we arrived there, we became strong.
Our tiredness was lifted
because the interested person
really enjoyed that conversation.
When did you leave the village?
Sunday
—Sunday morning.
Your legs were feeling better?
Yeah, we spent nine hours.
We got to one area
where we had a telephone,
so I could call her.
So you walked nine hours to get to a telephone.
What was that phone call like, Meraf?
As I told you,
I wanted to cry because I was so worried.
And he called and said my name.
So I was so happy, and I started to cry.
What’s happened since then, after that visit?
Do you know what’s happened to them?
Most of them now have gotten baptized.
Recently, one circuit overseer
and one special pioneer visited them.
I have a video.
Maybe you would like to see them?
No maybe.
Let’s have a look at the video, please.
Our journey begins here in Sodo.
Sodo has a thriving Amharic congregation
and three congregations in Wolaita.
And yet, the brothers travel to support the search,
even in villages far away.
Today, their destination
is the small village of Salaysh.
The journey is long, but the brothers settle in
and enjoy the beautiful countryside.
The first stop is Sawla,
where our brothers
and sisters are waiting for them.
This is the end of the line for the bus ride.
How nice it will be to have a good night’s rest.
It is time to start walking,
unless you can catch a ride on one of these.
Today, they cross valleys,
mountains,
and rivers
—some small
and some not so small.
Here, the brothers
have to wade through the river first;
then the drivers bring the motorbikes across.
I wish I had this option on my first trip.
One more stop;
time for a delicious meal
in Layha with the local brothers.
I can still smell
the fresh roasted coffee.
Finally, they make it to Salaysh.
How I miss these brothers and sisters!
I met this brother years ago on my first visit.
There are ten publishers now in Salaysh.
They conduct 24 Bible studies,
and many are attending the meetings.
To think this all started
with just one interested person.
How do our brothers feel
to be part of God’s organization?
Jehovah loved us.
Because of his love, he drew us to him.
He made us a part
of the international brotherhood.
We are very happy, and we thank Jehovah.
We thank him from our heart.
And I am thankful to Jehovah
that he included these dear friends
to join him in the search for more sheep.
You must be very happy to see those faces.
Yeah.
Just thinking about that trip,
when you were out there walking in the jungle,
going all of that way,
what did you learn from that?
I saw Jehovah’s hand
during that difficult trip.
Jehovah carried me.
We didn’t fear,
because we saw Jehovah’s hand.
We felt we were in Jehovah’s hand.
Beautiful.
What about you, Meraf?
Waiting alone,
not knowing what was happening to Yohannes,
what did you learn from that experience?
At that time, I was thinking,
‘I know that Jehovah can protect him.’
So I was telling myself this,
and that kept me strong.
Doing Jehovah’s will, Jehovah can protect him.
Very nice.
Yohannes and Meraf, thank you so much
for your experiences
and being with us on The Inside Story.
Thank you.
Every one of the students has a story.
You have a story, and maybe one day,
we’ll all get to hear them.
But for today,
we’ve just scratched the surface.
It’s been so encouraging to see the lengths
that our brothers and sisters will go
to find ‘friends of peace.’
And it has been
very touching to hear the lengths
that Jehovah will go
to find his “little sheep” to bring them back.
We look forward to seeing you again
on another episode of The Inside Story.
And that’s all for this time from the 145th class.
Well, we’d like to thank all those
involved with producing The Inside Story.
It truly was appreciated by each one of us.