Welcome, brothers and sisters!
Here are some of this month’s highlights:
How should we view counsel?
Does it apply to us
even if we don’t like
the way it was given?
In times of crisis,
how does the organization
respond to help our brothers and sisters?
And we will go behind the scenes
of last year’s convention drama
about King Hezekiah.
This is the May program
of JW Broadcasting!
Let’s begin by visiting a family
in Stockholm, Sweden.
The parents, Usama and Kristina,
have two daughters,
Talita and Isabella.
When Talita was born,
the doctor found cataracts
in both of her eyes.
A cataract is a clouding
of the eye’s natural lens.
So the doctor had to operate
so that Talita wouldn’t lose
her sight completely
—a terrifying situation
for any parent.
Today, Talita is seven years old
and almost blind in one eye
but completely blind in the other.
Teaching a child about Jehovah
in this system of things
is already a challenge
even without physical ailments involved.
But let’s find out how Talita’s parents
rose to the challenge,
making sure that she received
a proper spiritual education
despite her poor vision.
I look forward to not having
poor sight anymore
and that I can play
with a bear and a lion
and to sit
on the back of a tiger.
Jehovah gives us
a fantastic promise at Isaiah 35:5:
“The eyes of the blind will be opened.”
It’s been a challenge
to get to where we are today.
We thank Jehovah
for all the help he has given us.
As soon as Talita was able
to leave the house after the operation,
we made sure
to go to the meetings.
It helped us a lot to be able
to throw our burden on Jehovah.
We prayed together;
we cried a lot together
because it was so hard.
One of the challenges
is that we have to give
Talita audio description constantly.
We have to tell her who is coming in
and what is happening.
We get so many amazing materials
on jw.org
and also through the congregation.
She really loves to read
Learn From the Great Teacher.
It has questions
which make her a part of the story.
She has a very good memory,
and therefore she remembers
a lot of what she reads.
So when we are with friends,
she often quizzes them.
I really like to sing
the songs in my songbook.
Talita’s spiritual goal
is to learn more
of our Kingdom songs.
We get so much help
from the beautiful music
on the website
and also
from the Caleb and Sophia videos.
She knows many of the stories
from My Book of Bible Stories,
so she can answer in her own words.
We will ask a question like,
Do you know this about David?
And if she knows the answer,
then we encourage her
to answer at the meeting.
When I give an answer
at the meetings,
Jehovah becomes happy
because he loves children.
She often asks the friends,
“Do you love Jehovah?”
So she feels very united with them.
One of the best moments where we saw
that Talita’s spirituality had grown
was when she came home from a sleepover
at her grandparents’ house.
My parents are not Jehovah’s Witnesses,
and her grandmother had said
that God doesn’t exist.
So when Talita came home, she said,
“And then when I was going to sleep,
I prayed to Jehovah,
“‘Would you please help Grandmother
to realize that you do exist
—that you are real?’”
We try to keep
our wonderful hope alive,
so we often talk  about
what we will do
in Paradise.
We really look forward to when Talita
will be able to see again
and live in a paradise
with all our friends.
It’s going to be wonderful!
I think that Jehovah
looks forward to looking at me
when I play with a tiger.
I’ll have to make sure that I remember
the names of Joseph’s brothers
in case I meet Talita
and she decides to quiz me!
Her parents have done a good job
in raising such a fine young sister.
And together with them,
we eagerly look forward
to the benefits of the new system.
Isaiah 35:5 says:
“At that time the eyes
of the blind will be opened.”
Such divine reminders
can truly warm our heart.
And Jehovah’s reminders
not only provide us comfort
but can also help us
make important decisions
in our everyday life.
This brings us to our music video
which is entitled
I Keep Your Reminders.
What should I do?
Who should I look to?
This could just be harmless,
could be respectable.
There may be no need
for me to reject it all.
Oh, what is the right course for me?
Which path will it be?
What should I do?
Take which point of view?
It could be excessive,
with many dangers there—
All the kinds of things
that could prove to be a snare.
Oh, what is the right course for me?
Jehovah, give ear to my plea.
I keep your reminders,
and I love them dearly.
I’ll treasure them every day,
monthly, yearly.
All the things I have heard in accord
with your Word, help me understand.
I know what’s required.
I’d better inquire.
I don’t want to act
in a way to cause offense,
But it sounds like
there likely would be consequence.
It’s clear what’s the right course for me
—the key, the guarantee.
I keep your reminders,
and I love them dearly.
They strengthen my heart
and help me to see clearly.
All the things I have heard in accord
with your Word, help me understand.
I keep your reminders,
and I love them dearly.
They strengthen my heart
and help me to see clearly.
As I read day and night,
my life fills up with light.
I’ve got you by my side
as I think of your might.
All the things I have heard in accord
with your Word, help me understand.
Did you notice
that it was a Bible-trained conscience
that helped our sister
make a wise decision?
She knew what potential danger
lay ahead.
Yes, the reminders
from God’s Word guided her.
The theme for our program this month is
“Treasure Jehovah’s Reminders.”
And it’s based on Psalm 19:7,
where we’re told:
“The reminder of Jehovah is trustworthy,
making the inexperienced one wise.”
In the original language,
the word here translated as “reminder”
comes from a root word meaning
“to go over again, to repeat.”
Reminders have always been
an essential part of Jehovah’s teaching.
In ancient Israel,
God’s people continually received
commandments,
regulations, and reminders.
In fact, Jehovah tells us
that he sent
his prophets “again and again”
to repeatedly remind his people
of their responsibilities.
The apostle Peter
felt the need to give reminders
even to those
who were “well-established in the truth.”
Notice how he describes this
at 2 Peter 1:12, 13:
“For this reason I intend always
“to remind you of these things,
“although you know them
and are well-established
“in the truth that is present in you.
“But I consider it right,
“as long as I am in this tabernacle,
to stir you with reminders.”
In verse 15,
he goes on to give the reason
why he felt the need
to give the brothers reminders.
He says:
“I will always do my utmost
so that after my departure,
you may be able to recall
these things for yourselves.”
So Peter was determined
to help the brothers and sisters
in his day to remember, or recall,
the teachings they had already learned.
It shouldn’t come as a surprise, then,
if today a lot of our teaching
involves reminders.
It follows the pattern set
by Jehovah in ancient Israel
and with the first-century Christians.
But why do we need reminders?
Let’s consider three reasons.
First, let’s look at Psalm 103:2.
There it says:
“Let me praise Jehovah;
may I never forget all that he has done.”
Why, then, do we need reminders?
Simply put, because we forget.
If we had perfect memories,
we wouldn’t need so many reminders.
Even in everyday life,
many of us use little notes
to remind ourselves
of what we need to do.
And who of us
hasn’t seen the need
for a list of reminders
when going shopping,
only to realize when we returned
that we forgot to get one
of the important items
we needed to purchase?
If reminders are important
in everyday life,
how much more so in matters
that involve our relationship
with Jehovah.
Let’s read Luke 10:39, 40.
Speaking of Martha, we are told:
“She also had a sister called Mary,
“who sat down at the feet of the Lord
“and kept listening to what he was saying.
“Martha, on the other hand,
was distracted
with attending to many duties.”
What was Martha’s problem?
She was distracted.
So the second reason
why we need reminders
is that, like Martha,
at times we too become distracted.
Although we may already know
a vital fact,
that fact might get put
into the back of our mind,
figuratively speaking,
because other matters
are demanding our attention.
Satan is the great Distracter.
He tries to turn our attention away
from the true issues of our day.
People in general have become
more and more distracted
by entertainment
and other nonessential matters.
No wonder that Satan
has succeeded in misleading so many.
They don’t even realize
what has happened.
Reason number three
is alluded to
at Matthew 24:45:
“Who really
is the faithful and discreet slave
“whom his master appointed
over his domestics,
to give them their food
at the proper time?”
Notice that the spiritual food
is given to us “at the proper time.”
Our circumstances in life
are continually changing.
How often do we hear,
“That was just what I needed?”
We’ve all experienced that,
haven’t we?
So, what are three of the reasons
why we need reminders?
One,
because we tend to forget things.
Two,
we often become distracted.
Three,
our changed circumstances
may require a reminder
of something we already knew
but didn’t fully need at that time.
So that brings us to the next question:
What will help us to remember?
It’s interesting to note
that Jehovah has used many ways
to remind his people
of what they should do.
At Numbers 10:10, we’re told
that the various festivals
were given as reminders,
especially the celebration
of the Passover.
That means
that every time the Israelites
prepared and celebrated
one of these festivals,
they were reminded
of important matters,
such as how Jehovah
provides for his people
and how he has saved them
in the past.
Something similar happens today
at the commemoration
of the Lord’s Evening Meal.
Not only do we hear
the reminders from God’s Word
but the act of passing
the bread and wine
also serves as an action
that reminds us
of what Jesus did in our behalf.
But what do we need to do
in order for those reminders
to have a beneficial impact
on our lives?
Notice what Psalm 119:99 says.
It tells us:
“I have more insight than all my teachers,
because I ponder over your reminders.”
Yes, we need to ponder
over these reminders.
That means not just
listening to or reading them,
but it involves thinking deeply
about them—
meditating on their value.
Just to listen or read  without meditating
is like looking through the lens
of a movie camera
without pressing the record button.
We see things and hear things,
but nothing is recorded.
So we need
to meditate, visualize,
and review these reminders.
This will help us
to remember what we learn.
But, figuratively speaking,
there is something else
that we can do
to press the record button.
That means we don’t have to wait
for someone else
to give us a reminder.
We can make our own reminder.
How can we do so?
The answer to that question
is highlighted
in Jehovah’s instructions to Moses
as found at Exodus 17:14:
“Jehovah now said to Moses:
“‘Write this as a memorial
“‘[or the footnote says: “reminder”]
in the book and repeat it to Joshua.’”
What’s the point?
Write down new things
we want to remember.
Some brothers use a notebook,
or exercise book,
to write down a list of interesting points
that they want to remember.
Then they look through the book
from time to time
to remind themselves of those points.
Many of us do this with our notes
from conventions and assemblies.
Of course, to do that successfully,
you need to remember
where you put the notebook.
Additionally,
we have to be careful
that we don’t write down
every little fact.
Otherwise, we may become overwhelmed
with all the information.
We can make
these notes either on paper
or electronically using computers
or electronic devices.
Whatever system we use,
let’s make lists of things
that we want to remember.
Many brothers have found it good
to have two separate lists.
One list could be subjects
—perhaps points that we want to use
in the ministry or in our own lives.
Another, scriptures
—explanations that clarify
the meaning of certain verses.
With regard to notes on scriptures,
let’s ask a very important question:
Do you have a study Bible?
What is a study Bible?
Perhaps it’s a separate Bible
to the one you take in the ministry.
It’s a Bible for you to write in
so that you’re reminded
of things that you’ve learned.
These are some of the things
we can do with a study Bible:
Highlight or underline some words or verses.
That will make it easier to find them again.
But remember not to make
too many highlights or marks;
otherwise, nothing will stand out.
Write a summary of points and scriptures
you want to remember
on the blank pages in the front
or the back of your Bible.
Write notes in the margin
—that’s what Gilead students often do.
Of course, you need
the right type of pen or pencil
that won’t bleed through
to the other side of the page.
What type of things
could you write in the margin?
Perhaps new points
that you learn while reading magazines
or attending meetings and assemblies.
If you learn a new point, ask yourself,
‘What verse is being explained?’
And then write a brief comment
in the margin next to that verse.
Let’s take an example.
Perhaps you are reading
the Sermon on the Mount
and you get to Matthew 7:24-27.
That’s the illustration
about the two men who built houses
—one on sand and the other on rock.
As you research this
in Watchtower Library
or the Research Guide,
you come across the article
“Are You Building on Sand or on Rock?”
in the November 1, 2008, Watchtower.
What points could you write in the margin
to help you remember the explanation?
Well, perhaps you could write:
Sand equals build on the surface.
Rock equals dig down deep.
Digging equals doing and applying.
You might even put Luke 6:46-48 there.
Now, if you still have room
and your writing is small,
you could add something like this:
Not hearers only, but doers.
Both houses in same location,
same tests, foundations different.
Now every time
you read those verses,
you will be reminded
of what they mean.
Perhaps like me,
you’ve had several study Bibles
over the years.
I think back to the first one I used.
It was like this big green Bible.
Then, later that was replaced
by another Bible
—this black covered Bible.
And then, further still,
we had another Bible
—the Reference Bible.
And, of course,
now for most of us,
we have the large-print Bible.
This does, however,
highlight a challenge
we might experience.
It can be frustrating
when a new edition
of the Bible comes out.
How do you transfer all your study notes
over to the new Bible?
Additionally, our beloved study Bible
may wear out
or, worse still, be lost, stolen, burned,
ruined, run over, blown away.
So that’s the advantage
of using an electronic list;
it doesn’t matter
what type of file you use.
It can be updated very easily,
and you can even make copies
—not like the printed copy
that already has
the old idea written in the margin.
Even now in English,
we have the books
of Matthew, Mark, and Luke
in our electronic study Bible
on jw.org and WOL.
Later in the program,
we have some exciting news
about how JW Library
will help us in this regard.
But I’ll leave that for later.
Really, having a study Bible
is not only helpful
but it also makes our personal study
far more interesting.
How so?
Every time we read
or study a publication,
we’ll find ourselves
searching for new points
that we can write
in our study Bible.
This way, we’ll be doing
what the psalmist expressed
at Psalm 119:111:
‘We will take Jehovah’s reminders
‘as our permanent possession
(or heritage),
for his reminders
are the joy of our hearts!’
But do you agree that sometimes
the reminders we get
may be less than pleasant?
Maybe they even hurt!
In this dramatization,
pay attention to how
we should respond to counsel.
Today started out well.
But after the meeting tonight,
my feelings were hurt.
Earlier in the week, we invited
some friends over to watch a movie.
And apparently,
this new young elder heard about it,
so he counseled me about it
after the meeting,
saying that I should give
my movie choices
some thought.
I just didn’t like
the way he gave the counsel.
He’s only 27.
That’s too young.
The next day,
we had plans to go out in the ministry
with Brother Kang and his wife.
But the motivation
just wasn’t there.
I asked to speak
with Brother Kang alone.
I told him what happened
and how we didn’t feel
the counsel applied to us.
I can understand
how you might feel.
But, Byong Soo,
be absolutely honest with me.
Do you feel there is no valid reason
for that counsel?
Mm.
Well, maybe there were some scenes
that could have been less violent.
But the way he gave the counsel
—he didn’t even ask how we felt.
Byong Soo, what is the only way
for us to receive perfect counsel?
From a perfect man.
That’s right.
And is Jesus here on the earth today?
He was right.
Counsel can only be perfect
if it’s given from a perfect person.
Still, this counsel
about our movie choices
would have been so much easier
if it came from someone older
and more experienced,
like Brother Kang.
Well, he must have sensed
what I was thinking
because he helped me to remember
something from the Bible.
When Job underwent severe trials,
it was the younger Elihu who helped Job
adjust his thinking correctly.
It required humility on Job’s part
to listen to someone younger
and less experienced.
He then read Proverbs 19:20:
“Listen to counsel and accept discipline,
in order to become wise in your future.”
The point was clear:
Keep our focus on the counsel,
not the counselor.
I later shared
Brother Kang’s comments with my wife.
We both realized that we should welcome
all counsel from Jehovah.
It’s for our good.
I’m sure it took courage
for that young elder
to approach me about the matter.
But I’m so glad he did because,
in the end, his counsel
was just another example
of God’s love.
Yes, we all need reminders.
And did you notice some
of the main teaching points
in this dramatization?
First,
we need to be humble
when we receive counsel.
Second,
we need to keep our focus on the counsel,
not the counselor.
And the young elder likely learned
from the experience too.
Perhaps next time,
after conferring with a seasoned elder,
he might handle matters
with a little bit more tact and discretion.
But we can’t rely solely
on receiving reminders from others
to keep our spirituality intact.
We need to do our part.
One of the tools that can help us
to actively search out reminders
is JW Library.
This amazing app has been installed
on over 15 million devices.
But do you know
how much work it takes
to develop and maintain this app?
Well, we are now going  to look
behind the scenes
and meet some of the brothers
who have either worked on this project
or helped to organize that work.
This really is an opportunity to visit
an area in Bethel
that you don’t get to see on tour.
Of course, there are many brothers
associated with the work.
But we would like you
to get to know three
of these very hard-working brothers,
and let me introduce them to you.
First of all, Brother Per Christensen,
the overseer of MEPS Programming.
Now, Per, you’ve been in this country
working in the U.S. Bethel
for a number of years.
But where are you from originally?
I was born in Denmark
and served there in the branch for years.
So when did you and your wife, Berit,
come to the United States?
In 1994.
And our first year was in Brooklyn.
And then we had 18 years in Patterson
and then back to Brooklyn again
for three and a half years.
And now we’re in Warwick
since November last year.
Well, I know you worked
in Translation Services for a while
because, in fact,
the two of us worked together
in the same department
there for a while.
But what type of work
have you been involved with
since you’ve come
to the United States?
Lots of exciting and challenging jobs.
Working in Translation Services
—that was training and support
for our translators worldwide.
Now in MEPS Programming
—that is all about
distribution of spiritual food
to all our brothers and sisters.
So we have a ton of work
and a lot of challenges.
But I’m also working with a lot
of very, very talented
brothers and sisters.
So it’s a lot of fun,
and it’s great going to work every day.
That’s great to hear, Per.
In fact, I’m even tempted
to come back and work with you.
Oh, we would love that.
I think I’d love it too.
Well, let’s turn our attention
to Brother Alfredo Serna.
Now, you are the assistant overseer
of MEPS Programming.
In fact, you and I worked together
in Mexico back in 2003.
Could you tell us a little bit
about what you were doing at that time?
My last work assignment involved overseeing
the large Translation Department there.
It was an amazing privilege to work
with translators in sign language
and the indigenous languages,
a true joy to contribute
to preparing publications
for those in the minority groups.
So when did you and your wife, Gina,
come to the United States to work here?
We arrived at Patterson in 2007.
We have fond memories of that time,
and it’s something we still treasure.
Very good.
And now,
Brother Paul Willies,
where do you originally come from
along with your wife, Su-lin,
and when did you come
to the United States?
Well, we’re both originally
from South Africa,
and we served there in Bethel
for a number of years.
And then in 2010,
we were transferred to work
along with MEPS Programming
here in the U.S.
So, what type of work
have you been involved with,
particularly recently?
Well, most of my time in Bethel
I’ve been working
on the Watchtower Translation System,
or WTS.
Actually,
I was working along with Per.
Per was in headquarters,
and I was working
on the programming team
that we had in South Africa.
WTS is the program
that the translators use
to help organize and manage
their translation work.
And then, of course, most recently
I’ve been working on the mobile apps
—the JW Library app
and the JW Library Sign Language app.
Very good.
Well, now all of you work
in MEPS Programming.
Per, can you just tell us a little bit?
We’re familiar with the term MEPS,
but what really is it?
Well, MEPS stands for
Multilanguage Electronic Publishing System.
That didn’t help me at all.
Sorry.
Can you make it a little bit
more simple so we can understand?
We make the tools, or the programs,
that the organization needs
to make publications
and have them translated
into hundreds of languages.
So I can illustrate it this way:
that we are not making
the spiritual food,
but we are building
a conveyor belt for the spiritual food
from the faithful and discreet slave
down to the printing presses
or to our website
or to Watchtower Library,
ONLINE LIBRARY
or, like in this case, JW Library.
Thanks so much.
Now, at long last, I do understand
a bit more
about what MEPS means.
Now, as I travel around,
the brothers and sisters,
they tell me how much
they love JW Library.
But there seems to be no end
to the suggestions
for improvements and features
—and long lists of suggestions.
Can you give us a little bit
of an idea of what’s involved
with trying to develop
a new feature for JW Library?
Yes, the brothers and the sisters
really love using the app,
and because of that,
they’re keen to get many new features.
Of course, we wish we could just add
all those new features into the app,
but the truth is we just can’t.
Yes, adding each new feature
involves a lot of work.
And we also need to determine
whether a feature
that’s requested is just a “nice to have”
or is it something
that’s going to address a real need?
For example, will it really help an elder
who is out on a shepherding call
or maybe a pioneer sister
who is at the public witnessing carts
or at her Bible study or return visit?
Also, very important
to us is trying to make
each new feature
very simple to use . . .
Ah, thanks for doing that.
. . . especially for a first-time user,
someone who’s never used the app before.
And then, of course,
before we start working on anything,
we always get approval
from the Governing Body.
Ah, that’s a good thing to do too.
Like one feature
that many have been asking for
is the ability
to add notes into the app.
And, of course,
before we start programming it,
we have to make sure
that it actually does what is wanted.
We made a video
that shows how we go about that.
You have?
Would you like to see it?
Well, of course.
I’d love to see it!
Hello.
How are you?
Good, good, good.
Welcome!
Thanks for coming.
How about yourself?
Fine, thank you.
Have a seat.
All right, so glad you could be here!
Thank you so much.
Oh, so fancy.
Yeah!
So we get to talk about JW Library today.
So, what are some ways
that you use JW Library?
I mean, it’s revolutionized
going to meetings.
Oh, my.
I go to meetings
and sometimes I just carry my iPad.
So the fact that you can make
the text larger. . .
It’s easy to listen
to the readings right in the app now,
and so I—I find myself doing that.
So if we were
to make a notes feature,
what are some things
that you’d like to be able to do?
I mean, if you could see
all your notes without tapping on
each one that would be great.
And even if you make a note in,
maybe, your phone
and it can also be saved in your tablet,
that would be really nice.
Yeah.
Well, what if I told you
that in front of you
is an early version of JW Library?
Whoa!
Cool!
Oh, fantastic!
This is it?
With notes—yeah.
Ooh.
So a few months ago,
the Governing Body
gave us approval to start working
on the notes feature.
We got together as a team,
and we’ll do, like, these rough sketches,
and programmers write code.
But before we release an update,
we have a group of testers.
And, you know, they’ll find
little glitches or bugs or things,
but they’ll try to work it out
with the programmers.
After that, we have
a pretty stable version of JW Library.
The goal is to show it to you,
and you can let us know
what you think.
So now that you’ve seen
the new notes feature
in JW Library, what do you think?
I love that I can tag the personal things
that I need to work on
or a comment or a scripture
that I can encourage someone with.
This is fantastic!
Yeah.
It’s great.
I like that I can find my notes,
especially using the search feature.
It’s great!
And it’s really neat
how my comments—
I can place it right next
to the paragraph for meetings,
and it doesn’t cover the actual text.
The ability to back it up
so you can restore it to another device,
that’s going to be really helpful.
I love it!
Amazing!
OK.
Go ahead.
Yeah.
Go ahead!
So you’re telling us we can proceed.
That’s fantastic!
But, brothers, you can’t show us
something like that
and not tell us when
we’re going to get it.
Well, we said on the website
that it was coming soon.
I know you said that on the website,
but when?
Is it OK to be more specific than that?
I think that’s why they invited us here.
Paul, let’s hear it.
Well, we’re happy to tell you
that the notes feature
in JW Library
will be coming soon,
and by soon we mean
during May of 2017—this month!
So we can go and check
the app stores for an update.
Oh, that’s wonderful to hear.
So all of us will be happy
to be able to put our own reminders
right there in the JW Library app.
Well, I’m looking forward
to being able to do that as well.
But now,
while I’ve got you here,
we’re not going to let you go
until we ask this big question:
What are you working on now?
In other words, what can we expect
to see soon with JW Library?
We have another brief video showing
what the team is working on
to support the Study Bible
on the JW Library app.
Would you like to see it?
That’s wonderful.
Let’s have a look.
Later this year,
work will begin on adding
the Study Edition
of the New World Translation
to JW Library.
When this edition becomes available
in your language,
you will be able to discover
spiritual gems in the study notes.
And the new media gallery
will help you
to visualize the people, places,
and things you read about.
You will also see
the new overviews of each book,
play the introductory videos,
and study additional appendix material.
All of this and more
is coming soon to JW Library!
That sounds so exciting.
So we’ll all look forward
to getting that feature.
You said, “coming soon,” didn’t you?
Anyway,
we’d like to thank you very much
for the fact that you’ve come along
and you’ve explained so much to us
about what goes on
with MEPS Programming
and the JW Library app.
But before you go,
we’d like to ask you,
when you go back to your department,
please, take an expression
of our appreciation
back to the hard-working
brothers and sisters
who are working behind the scenes
in providing this tool for us.
Will do.
Happy to.
Thanks.
Thank you very much.
And speaking of behind the scenes,
do you remember the beautiful dramas
we had at the regional convention
last year?
One of them was
about King Hezekiah.
We saw not only
the threat Jehovah’s people faced
but also the protection
Jehovah provided.
In producing the drama,
the Audio/Video Services Department
used a lot of visual effects.
Let’s go behind the scenes
and find out what the work entailed.
The goal of our visual effects team
is to take the work done
during film production and expand it.
Our work was driven by the Bible account.
The audience needed to feel
the intimidating power of the Assyrian army
while not endangering our actors.
And the use of visual effects
had the added benefit
of drastically saving donated funds.
But this meant creating hundreds
of digital arrows, war machines,
cities, tents, soldiers,
and even an Assyrian palace.
In some cases, the foreground elements
had to be separated
from the background
so digital components could be added.
This was a time-consuming process,
as many foreground elements
had to be cut out frame by frame,
24 times for each second of video.
Our research team ensured
that the world created
was as accurate as possible.
For example,
having period-correct materials
for the temple
as well as accurate stone reliefs.
After filming was complete,
the research team noted
some scenes in the treasury
were accidentally shot
showing priests wearing sandals.
As this was inaccurate,
the issue was corrected
by generating additional digital treasures
and placing them in the foreground.
As we didn’t have
the luxury of 185,000 extras,
actors were dressed in ancient costumes
and their pictures were taken.
We then used these pictures
to create digital extras,
using crowd-simulating software
to place them in the scenes
and drive their movements.
The angel shot proved to be
one of the most challenging.
The original version didn’t have
the dramatic feel needed for the scene.
So the entire sequence was recreated
to more accurately convey
the immense power
that those present must have witnessed.
Finishing this project
on schedule had many challenges.
After hearing about just a few of them,
one industry expert said
what we were attempting was impossible.
But like Hezekiah
when hearing negative reports,
we stayed positive
and relied on Jehovah.
With His help,
the film was completed on time
and is now a wonderful tool
to bring this Bible account to life.
A beautiful drama,
and how encouraging it was
to see Jehovah rescue his people!
The 2016 regional convention
was excellent,
don’t you agree?
But you’ll be happy to know
that we have prepared a little glimpse
of what is to come
at this year’s convention
to whet your appetite.
Are you OK?
Brian, I’m worried.
You need more money.
Jehovah will take care of us.
He always has.
We have enough.
Maybe enough for today,
but what if you get sick?
Gloria’s mother keeps badgering her
and me to move up.
I can get a job
at my uncle’s real estate firm.
Maybe this is an answer
to our prayers.
What about your pioneering?
What about it?
I can do both.
Gloria, I must congratulate you
on your hard work with my company.
But you must learn
to keep your religion in its place.
We’re neglecting
family worship, study, service.
We’ve even become too busy,
or maybe too ashamed,
to even pray together.
I’m concerned about you.
One of the things
that you always talked to me about
was Matthew 6:24:
‘You cannot slave for God and for Riches.’
You’re not the same person
that I once knew.
Dad,
where is Mom?
She is coming, right?
Is it really wrong
to try to improve our life?
Mom.
“Remember the wife of Lot.”
If you have yet to make definite plans
to attend your regional convention this year,
don’t delay.
Our conventions are a loving provision
from Jehovah.
Whatever it takes
—talking to your boss to get time off work
or making travel plans—
yes, whatever it takes,
our efforts are worth it
because we truly treasure
Jehovah’s reminders.
Jesus’ words
at Matthew 11:28
are very appropriate
considering everything
we go through
in this system of things:
“Come to me, all you who
are toiling and loaded down,
and I will refresh you.”
Yes, conventions
can be of refreshment to us,
giving us the boost we need.
But such refreshment
is also available
when the world around us
seems to be falling apart.
How does the organization
help our brothers and sisters
in times of national crisis?
We met two Witness couples
who personally experienced
two of the largest terrorist attacks
in recent years.
Not a day goes by
when we don’t think
about our son, Paulie.
There was horror and suffering,
things we don’t want to witness anymore.
September 11
was a very scary, terrifying day.
As for me,
when I really understood
what was happening, I got scared.
I didn’t know what to do.
I didn’t know what to think.
I felt helpless.
When the second tower fell,
Paulie was on the 110th floor
and everybody was shouting, crying.
I was praying to Jehovah
because I was heartbroken.
We live on Voltaire Boulevard;
it’s a broad avenue.
There is a concert hall called the Bataclan.
When the doors of the Bataclan are open,
we can hear everything that goes on inside.
That night, three men
entered the Bataclan concert hall,
and they started shooting into the crowd.
We immediately grabbed our “go bag.”
And then we sat in front of the sofa,
and we begged Jehovah for his holy spirit
so we could face the situation.
It was around 10:00 p.m.
when there was a news flash
that announced that there was an attack.
I was in shock when I heard the news,
and then I immediately thought
about our brothers and sisters.
I quickly got in contact
with the circuit overseer
in order to get some news
about our brothers and sisters,
to know how they were doing.
Then,
very early the next morning,
we set up an emergency committee
made up of several brothers
from the Service Department.
We decided to write a letter
and make other arrangements
to assist the friends who,
in one way or another,
were affected by this event.
In turn,
the circuit overseer
would make an effort
to rapidly get in touch
with the elders
who oversee
the affected territory.
One of our challenges, on a personal level,
was whether we would even be able
to encourage our brothers and sisters
because we had never experienced
such a terrible event.
We organized ourselves;
we paired up as elders
and headed off to do shepherding.
We started calling midmorning
on Tuesday.
We received a report back
from all the traveling overseers
by the end of Thursday.
And unfortunately,
we learned that 14
of our brothers and sisters
had lost their lives.
We knew that we needed
to encourage the families;
we knew that we needed
to shepherd them as soon as possible.
The elders immediately came.
We went over the book of Job,
and I just listened.
You know, I was just listening.
I’ve heard the same words before,
but it was different now.
The things that were being said
went straight to my heart.
A few days later, we were visited
by two brothers from Bethel.
It was very touching
that they came to see us
and that they
were concerned about us.
It shows us that Jehovah
was aware of how we felt that night.
Our brothers were there.
They were ready
to help one another out.
Then there was
so much empathy and love shown.
When we were ultimately granted
access to ground zero
and we started encountering
the first responders,
we let them know how much
we appreciated their hard work
and that they had a skill set
that we didn’t have.
But yet our skill set
was trying
to offer comfort to them.
We shared a scripture with them.
Immediately, we could tell
that that was something
that caused emotion
to rise up in them right away.
And they expressed
great appreciation for that.
It’s one of the beautiful things
about the Scriptures
—that they’re calming,
soothing, comforting.
And the Scriptures
did not let down the workers
that were there at ground zero either.
The visit of the brothers
from Bethel was really
a gift from Jehovah.
It showed his genuine interest in us.
It was really wonderful.
After the brothers visited us,
we felt so comforted,
so encouraged,
that we said to each other:
“We have to get back in the ministry
“and comfort people in the territory.
We have to console
our brothers and sisters as well.”
We can only thank and glorify Jehovah,
who really is a God of love.
I kind of felt
Jehovah’s hand just reaching out to me,
which I needed.
But I cannot wait till the day
that I’m totally refreshed.
Where I can see,
I can actually see,
Paulie.
I can see him just coming back
into our lives,
and I want to embrace him so much.
After something like this,
we are not the same.
But
with the help of the organization
—the brothers—
Jehovah is there for us.
So that—
That is refreshing.
And I thank Jehovah a lot
for what he wants to do for me
and also for the millions of people
that feel the same way.
What these couples went through
was a horrible reminder of Satan’s rule,
but we look forward
to the relief from Jehovah
—the only true hope we have.
Reminders of Jehovah’s care,
such as these interviews,
can be ‘the joy of our heart,’
as the psalmist said.
Yes, “the reminder
of Jehovah is trustworthy,
making the inexperienced one wise.”
Before we conclude,
let’s visit our brothers
and sisters in India.
India is the second-most-populated country
in the world,
with a population
of some 1.2 billion people.
The Kingdom preaching work
is conducted
by some 45,000 brothers and sisters
in 627 congregations,
and last year,
close to 125,000 people attended
the Memorial of Christ’s death.
Our visit brings us to Peermedu,
which is located in the southern tip
of the Indian Peninsula,
in the state of Kerala.
This town is located
some 914 meters,
or almost 3,000 feet, above sea level.
It is a land of spices and lush greenery,
with tea and coffee plantations.
The two congregations
there have a total of 70 publishers.
Many of them work in tea estates
and struggle to make a living.
They are eager users of the JW Library app,
which they use to share
our videos
and publications
in the ministry.
As Peermedu is a hill station,
their territory consists
of rugged and uneven terrain.
Since the congregations there are watching
this program together with all of us,
we wanted to take this opportunity
to convey their warm Christian greetings
to all of Jehovah’s people
around the world.
We love you very much.
This is JW Broadcasting
from the world headquarters
of Jehovah’s Witnesses.