Welcome, brothers and sisters!
As Jesus’ followers,
we’re happy to be related in the faith.
This month’s program
is full of faithful examples and ways
you and I can act in faith
to make things happen.
We’ll visit with the Lachmuth sisters
at the Canada branch.
How did their faith help them adjust
to leaving their home in Canada
to serve in a missionary assignment
in India?
For decades,
the apartheid laws in South Africa
separated our brothers from one another.
How were their neutrality, brotherly love,
and faith in Jehovah
put to the test?
And our music video depicts
how a person’s faith grows
from when they first study the Bible
to when they face trials
as a dedicated Witness of Jehovah.
This is the April 2017 edition
of JW Broadcasting!
Has fear of failure
ever held you back
from doing something good,
even something for Jehovah?
Some have hesitated
to dedicate themselves to God
and get baptized,
for fear of breaking God’s laws.
In other cases,
we might not reach out for a form of service
because we feel
we cannot do a good job.
In this dramatization,
a Bible student faces his fear of failure.
It’s based on lessons found
in chapter 1 of the book
“Keep Yourselves in God’s Love.”
Look for what helps him
overcome his fear
and move ahead in faith.
When is your turn, Dad?
Our family was contacted
by Jehovah’s Witnesses
a few years ago.
Rachel started studying first.
Soon, we all joined in.
For the first time, we were all learning
what the Bible really teaches.
It wasn’t long
before we were sharing
the truth with others.
Well, most of us were.
I knew it was the truth,
but I didn’t know if I could live up to
everything Jehovah asks.
Get away.
What if I let everyone down?
What if I let Jehovah down?
You know,
can you just give me one second?
Yeah, no problem.
All right.
Yeah.
A kind elder named Ben
noticed I was struggling.
You OK?
He took the initiative to help.
He asked,
“What drew you to Jehovah
in the first place?”
I guess it was learning
that Jehovah isn’t harsh and demanding,
but that he’s a loving Father.
Ben agreed and said,
“When we do our best to serve Jehovah,
he does the rest.”
He explained that Jehovah
knows our limitations
and doesn’t expect perfection.
And he’s always there to help
because he wants us to succeed.
Then he read Isaiah 41:10:
“Do not be afraid,
“for I am with you.
“Do not be anxious,
“for I am your God.
I will fortify you, yes, I will help you,”
Help!
“I will really hold on to you
with my right hand of righteousness.”
I don’t need to be perfect to serve Jehovah.
I just need to love him and trust him.
And he’ll do the rest.
Our brother learned
what the love of God means.
As 1 John 5:3 tells us,
it means “that we observe
his commandments;
and yet his commandments
are not burdensome.”
Jehovah is a loving Father
who wants us to succeed.
As our brother concluded,
we need to trust Jehovah,
knowing He’ll do the rest.
That lesson provides
an excellent introduction
to our discussion for this month.
The theme is
“Faith in Jehovah Makes It Happen.”
During his earthly ministry,
Jesus miraculously healed
many sick or disabled persons.
At times,
he would say to such ones
the expression we find
at Matthew 9:29:
“According to your faith
let it happen to you.”
The principle of what Jesus stated
applies in every aspect
of our Christian life and ministry.
But today we will discuss how this principle
that faith in Jehovah makes things happen
can work for us in three areas.
We will see:
1) how our faith has made positive things
happen in our personal life,
2) how we can accomplish
things in God’s service
that would not be possible
without faith in Jehovah God,
and 3) how faith moves us
to step out of our comfort zone
to do more in Jehovah’s service.
The principle that faith in Jehovah
makes things happen
is well illustrated in one
of the miracles Jesus performed.
Please open your Bible to Mark chapter 5,
and let’s read verses 25-29:
“Now there was a woman
“who had had
a flow of blood for 12 years.
“She had suffered much
at the hands of many physicians
“and had spent all her resources,
“and she was no better but,
rather, had become worse.
“When she heard
the reports about Jesus,
“she came up behind him in the crowd
and touched his outer garment,
“for she kept saying:
“‘If I touch just his outer garments,
I will get well.’
“And immediately her flow
of blood dried up,
“and she sensed in her body
that she had been healed
of the grievous sickness.”
In the following verses,
Jesus asked who had touched him.
The woman then revealed
before the crowd
what she had done
and how she’d been cured.
Now notice Jesus’ response in verse 34:
“He said to her:
“‘Daughter,
your faith has made you well.
“‘Go in peace, and be healed
from your grievous sickness.’”
What comforting words
Jesus spoke to this trembling woman:
“Your faith has made you well.”
What did Jesus mean?
Let’s examine the account more closely.
It says that the woman
heard “reports about Jesus.”
Many others heard the same reports,
but not all put faith in Jesus.
And think of the circumstances
that could have prevented her
from even coming to Jesus.
She had been disappointed many times
over the past 12 years.
She might well have thought:
‘What’s the use?
‘I’m tired and weak and poor.
I’m staying home.’
Or ‘I would like for Jesus to see me,
‘but there is such a crowd.
‘How will I ever get through to him?
‘And after all,
I’m in an unclean state,
‘and if the people discover this,
perhaps they will punish me.’
No, she did not allow
these negative thoughts
or doubts to fill her mind.
She left her home.
She found Jesus
despite the large crowd.
And what was she saying?
Did she say,
“If I touch just his outer garments,
maybe I will get well”?
No, she said,
“I will get well.”
Now, it was not the case
that her faith healed her.
No, but her faith moved her
to come to Jesus,
and she was healed
by the power from Jehovah
that flowed through his Son.
Faith to approach Jesus
made it happen for her.
If you are a dedicated,
baptized Christian,
don’t you agree
that your faith has already made
positive things happen
in your personal life?
No, you were not miraculously healed
of your physical sicknesses.
We look forward
to physical healing of our ills
during the Thousand Year Reign of Christ.
But today Jesus Christ directs a program
of spiritual healing.
When we were a part
of this godless world,
many of us were sick spiritually,
morally, and emotionally.
No one could cure us.
Perhaps we desperately
tried material things or pleasures
to fill our spiritual need,
but our condition only got worse.
We were helpless and hopeless.
But then we heard “reports”
—the good news
of God’s Kingdom under Christ!
We studied the Bible.
Our faith moved us
to make positive changes in our life
and to associate
with the Christian congregation.
Today, we enjoy
good spiritual health and happiness.
Our faith has made it happen.
Faith has also made it possible
to accomplish things in God’s service
that perhaps
we never thought we could do.
Please open your Bibles
to Hebrews chapter 11.
In this portion
of Paul’s letter to the Hebrews,
he focuses on faith.
He begins with a definition of faith.
But then, starting in verse 4,
Paul acts as a sort of tour guide,
walking us through the corridor
of thousands of years of Bible history.
He stops along the way
to point out the extraordinary things
that men and women of the past did
by means of faith in Jehovah God.
Just glance down the columns
in this chapter
and notice how Paul introduces
each paragraph
with the words “by faith.”
This expression “by faith”
appears 18 times in this one chapter.
Now, when we look at the names
Paul lists in this chapter,
we may think,
‘Well, these were spiritual “giants.”’
But in reality,
they were ordinary humans
with weaknesses
like all of us have today.
The thing they all had in common
was faith,
and faith in Jehovah
made it possible
for them to do amazing things.
Let’s look at some of them
and compare what they did
with what many of you
are doing today
by faith.
Let’s read verse 5:
“By faith Enoch was transferred
“so as not to see death,
“and he was nowhere to be found
“because God had transferred him;
“for before he was transferred
“he received the witness
that he had pleased God well.”
The book of Jude, verses 14 and 15,
informs us that Enoch boldly proclaimed
that Jehovah was going to destroy
that ungodly world.
It appears that wicked, violent men
were going to take Enoch’s life
because of his bold witness.
So God chose to take him
—that is, gently cutting short his life,
sparing him the pangs of a violent death.
In modern times, like Enoch,
many brothers and sisters
have boldly declared God’s judgments
even when faced with death.
One brother,
after receiving a death sentence
at Nazi hands during World War II,
wrote these words
shortly before his execution:
“I have such peace, such tranquillity,
that you can’t possibly imagine!”
Faith made such boldness
and calmness possible.
In many ways, you very likely
have shown the same faith as Enoch.
By faith,
you stand up to an ungodly world
by not adopting its corrupt ways.
By faith,
you boldly declare God’s Word
from house to house
and in public places.
Before you became a baptized Witness,
you may have thought you would never do
this preaching work!
But you are doing it,
sometimes even in the face
of verbal abuse and opposition.
Faith has made it happen.
Let’s read verse 7:
“By faith Noah,
“after receiving divine warning
of things not yet seen,
“showed godly fear
and constructed an ark
“for the saving of his household;
“and through this faith
he condemned the world,
“and he became an heir
of the righteousness
that results from faith.”
Nothing in the Bible indicates
that Jehovah chose Noah
to construct an ark
because he was an experienced builder.
Certainly, he never had built
such a gigantic vessel
as what Jehovah
had asked him to construct.
Noah likely pondered many questions:
‘How will I get all the building materials?
‘Do I have the right tools to do the job?
‘How will I gather all the animals?
‘What food will they need, and how much?
‘When, exactly, will the Deluge begin?
‘How long will it last?
Where will the ark land
after the Flood subsides?’
Nothing in the record indicates
that Jehovah gave Noah
all the details in advance.
What Noah did have was faith.
Faith moved him to begin building.
His faith saved him and his family.
Faith in Jehovah made it happen.
Like Noah, during this time of the end,
Jehovah’s people have taken on
challenging theocratic building projects.
Certainly, constructing
the new world headquarters
at Warwick, New York,
was one of these projects
that required much faith.
A committee of brothers was assigned
to complete this vast project
in less than four years.
To do so, they knew they had to begin
by July 2013.
They moved ahead in faith.
Though the town
had not yet approved the site permits,
they began inviting workers to the site
with that date in mind.
Time was passing quickly.
The invited volunteers
were buying plane tickets.
Bethel was arranging rooming
and other details.
Yet, the committee
still did not have site permits.
Would they cancel these invitations?
They state:
“We spent a lot of time praying about it.
“We decided we needed to act in faith.
“And we were just convinced
Jehovah was going to make it happen.”
As the deadline approached,
the brothers had done everything possible
to obtain the permits.
The town planning board
was holding a public hearing.
And to the brothers’ great surprise,
within 15 minutes
of the start of the meeting,
the town board voted
to approve the project.
These overseers commented,
“When the approval came through,
“we knew it was
only by Jehovah’s spirit
that that happened.”
True, but it was
also the brothers’ faith
to act that made it happen.
Those experiences
are found in the video
World Headquarters
—History Is Being Written.
You can find it
in the “Our Activities” section
under the “Construction” category.
Now let’s read Hebrews 11:8:
“By faith Abraham, when he was called,
“obeyed by going out to a place
“he was to receive as an inheritance;
“he went out, although not knowing
where he was going.”
What faith it took
for Abraham
and his submissive wife, Sarah,
to leave the prosperous city of Ur
and to go wherever
Jehovah would lead them!
It meant leaving the security
of a pleasant home
and moving to some strange
and potentially hostile land
some 1,000 miles,
or 1,609 kilometers, away.
Do we see such faith today?
Absolutely!
Since 2014,
thousands of brothers and sisters
have attended the School
for Kingdom Evangelizers,
agreeing to be assigned
to wherever
there is a need
by the organization.
Faith has made it happen.
When a call goes out
for skilled volunteers
to help build
or expand branch facilities,
faith moves brothers and sisters
to simplify their lives
and to leave their comfort zone
in order to assist.
For example, in 2009,
the congregations
in the United States were informed
that an expansion project
at Wallkill, New York,
was being planned.
One couple moved out
of their newly built
2,200-square-foot,
or 200-square-meter, dream home
and into a 270-square-foot,
or 25-square-meter, apartment
so that they could make
themselves available.
What happened?
They explain:
“One month after we moved
into our small apartment,
“we received an invitation to serve
“as temporary volunteers at Wallkill.
“It was clear to us
that by simplifying our life,
we had given Jehovah
something to bless.”
Faith made it happen for them.
So, what have we learned today?
Faith in Jehovah God
is a powerful motivating force
that impels us to act
in harmony with his will.
Jehovah rewards such faith.
Remember, the very meaning
of the name of our God, Jehovah,
is “He Causes to Become.”
Truly, he is a God
who makes things happen!
Brothers and sisters,
let us continue to act in faith.
Jehovah will continue
to make wonderful things
happen in our personal life.
We will accomplish things
we never could do
through our own personal efforts.
We will be able to do more
in Jehovah’s service.
May it happen to you
“according to your faith.”
We met two examples
of faith at the Canada branch.
Tillie and Leona Lachmuth
showed faith like Abraham’s
when they stepped out of their comfort zone
to preach in a faraway land.
But that wasn’t the only
big adjustment they would make
in their long theocratic history.
In their interview,
look for the challenge that came
after nearly 50 years in their assignment.
We were brought up
in a small town in Saskatchewan.
It was friendly.
I don’t think they moved to other places.
They stayed right there.
One time, our father said:
“Why do you have to go so far as India?
Why can’t you preach in Canada?”
Dad was very strict.
Very strict.
When we were out playing
and he came out and called us,
we had to come immediately.
They were strict.
Don’t question; just do what you’re told.
Yeah, do what you’re told.
Yeah.
That’s right.
Strict.
My father was the one that was interested,
but he never came into the truth.
He enjoyed having Witnesses
come to our home,
but he never ever thought
of himself as being
one of Jehovah’s Witnesses.
Coming into the truth, I think,
changed our life,
and we had a different purpose.
So that was when we decided,
“Well, I guess we should pioneer now too.”
And we only pioneered two years,
and we were called to Gilead.
So then we graduated in 1953.
On your application for Gilead,
one question is:
Are you willing to go
any place in the world?
Brother Knorr always would say,
“A one-way ticket.”
So that was on your mind.
We were happy to go.
And if we didn’t get back, that was OK.
And then the 13 of us, for one month,
we all went together back to India
on a ship.
Well, we were a bit nervous
because we didn’t know
just what kind of people
we would be meeting
or what kind of atmosphere
we’d be experiencing.
That was why it was a shock
when we landed in Bombay
because all we could see
was people,
people everywhere and noise.
And then they gave us such hot food.
We were burning all the way down.
And then when we arrived there,
the missionary home had no furniture
and we had to sleep on the floor
for quite a few months
before the furniture was made.
We boiled our water;
we filtered our water.
When we went to the market,
we’d bring all our vegetables and fruit home
and we washed them with a solution.
And we were very careful in that respect.
It was all a shock to us in many things.
Yes.
We made up our mind, I guess,
that it’s not going to be
the same as Canada, we know.
We didn’t worry about the things
we had to put up with
because we had the joy in the ministry.
The Society wanted us
to get the Joy booklet out,
and we had to just stand on the street
with this carton of literature
and just keep calling out to the people,
and everybody would take it.
And they were so appreciative,
really appreciative.
Yeah, they were.
Yeah.
In those days,
we had to put in 150 hours.
And in South India, after 4:00 p.m.,
women were not out.
So we had to get all our time in
early in the morning
and work right through until four o’clock.
We sure did.
We were using the Malayalam language,
and the children repeated what we said.
They’d run ahead and tell people
what we were talking about.
And they’d all yell,
“Ma’damma, ma’damma.”
“White woman, white woman.”
Yeah, and we had many studies then.
We enjoyed the ministry,
and we enjoyed the hospitality.
Be with the brothers and go to their homes
and eat their food and do things
the way they do things.
So we had to make India our home.
We lived in India about 50 years.
And then the news came
that we had to leave.
So that was why the Governing Body said,
“Well, you go to the Canada branch then.”
Well, it was like a culture shock too
after being so many years in India.
Yes.
A lot of things we had
to sort of adjust to here now.
I’m working down in the laundry, folding.
Same.
Folding and folding until we fold in.
Well, we always tell the younger ones
to be in the full-time service
serving Jehovah.
This, we think,
is a wonderful life to choose.
It’s good for the young people
to learn when they’re young like that.
And, no doubt,
they’ll make progress in the truth too.
We’re glad we started pioneering
and moved about.
Yeah.
We lacked nothing, really.
We have nothing to complain about.
It wasn’t easy,
but Tillie and Leona
adapted to a culture in India
that was very different
from what they knew.
It was interesting, however,
that they felt a similar culture shock
when returning home to Canada.
But through all of it,
Jehovah rewarded their faith.
After more than 67 years
of full-time service,
they can say with confidence
that they lacked nothing.
Young ones,
why not imitate the faith
of ones like Tillie and Leona
and set a goal for a form of service
that’s new to you?
And, older ones,
if an assignment you treasured
for many years comes to an end,
know that Jehovah remembers
the love you showed for his name
and wants you to find joy
in your new assignment.
No matter our circumstances,
Jehovah wants us all to do
what was recently discussed
at a Bethel morning worship:
Seek first the Kingdom.
Our text for discussion today,
here at Matthew 6:33,
contains two parts.
The first part is what we have to do;
it says:
“Keep on, then, seeking first the Kingdom
and his righteousness.”
The second part is what Jehovah will do:
“And all these other things
will be added to you.”
We think carefully about these words.
Jesus actually was educating his disciples
to make a dramatic change
in their lifestyle.
What do we mean by that?
Well, look at verse 31.
He says: “So never be anxious and say,
“‘What are we to eat?’
or, ‘What are we to drink?’
or, ‘What are we to wear?’”
Did Jesus say never?
Yes!
But those are the things we normally do.
We are anxious about our existence,
and Jesus recognizes
that most people are that way.
He says in verse 32:
“For all these are the things
the nations are eagerly pursuing.”
But then he says:
“Your heavenly Father knows
that you need all these things.”
Here in this chapter,
Jesus outlines a number
of very important principles
that actually change the way we look at life
and the way we see our existence
in relationship to Jehovah God.
He puts service to Jehovah
in the first place,
regardless of our circumstances.
Let us have a look
at two of these principles.
The one that’s here
at Matthew 6:24,
he says:
“No one can slave for two masters;
“for either he will hate the one
and love the other,
“or he will stick to the one
and despise the other.
“You cannot slave
for God and for Riches.”
It is just not possible.
Some have tried, but they’ve failed.
Satan approached Jesus and said to him:
‘I will give you riches.
I’ll give you all the kingdoms
of the world and their glory.’
Of course, Jesus refused.
Why?
Because he knew
there was a price attached to it.
What is the price?
Worship
—divided worship—
which is impossible.
He knew that it is impossible
to worship both Jehovah and Riches.
In verse 21, Jesus says:
“For where your treasure is,
there your heart will be also.”
The second principle is in verse 25:
“On this account I say to you:
“Stop being anxious about your lives
“as to what you will eat
or what you will drink,
or about your bodies
as to what you will wear.”
And here is the principle:
“Does not life mean more than food
and the body [more] than clothing?”
You can have a storehouse full of food;
if you don’t have life, you cannot eat it.
You can have a warehouse full of clothes;
but if there’s no body, you cannot wear it.
Jesus illustrated this principle
beautifully in Luke.
Turn to Luke
chapter 12
and from verse 16:
“With that he told them an illustration,
saying:
“‘The land of a rich man produced well.
“‘So he began reasoning within himself,
“‘“What should I do now
that I have nowhere to gather my crops?”
“‘Then he said, “I will do this:
“‘“I will tear down my storehouses
and build bigger ones,
“‘“and there I will gather
all my grain and all my goods,
“‘“and I will say to myself:
“‘“‘You have many good things
stored up for many years;
“‘“‘take it easy, eat,
drink, enjoy yourself.’”
“‘But God said to him,
“‘“Unreasonable one,
“‘“this night they are demanding
your life from you.
“‘“Who, then, is to have
the things you stored up?”
“‘So it goes with the man
who stores up treasure for himself
but is not rich toward God.’”
Jesus didn’t say this man was dishonest
or that he’d never thought about God.
The mistake the man made was
that his priorities were wrong.
He focused primarily on amassing wealth.
He did not do what it says in verse 21.
He did not store up treasure for himself—
He ‘stored up treasure for himself,’
but did not store up treasure
with God in heaven.
He was “not rich toward God.”
And that is the key element, isn’t it?
Our service to Jehovah God,
our life for Jehovah,
that is the key element.
And as Jesus says in verse 15,
the second part of verse 15:
“Because even when a person
has an abundance,
“his life does not result
from the things he possesses.”
So these are
the two very important principles
we’ve covered.
First of all,
make our service to God a priority
and not amassing wealth.
And the second one:
“Keep on, then,
seeking first the Kingdom
“and [God’s] righteousness,
and all these other things
will be added to you.”
We do not know precisely
when the end will come,
but we want to keep on
seeking first the Kingdom.
Rather than putting our trust
in the securities of this world,
we want to put our trust
in our heavenly Father.
Jehovah gives everything;
he gives more than what we need.
In Ecclesiastes 5:19,
it summarizes this whole principle.
It establishes the truth
—the reality of the matter.
It says, Ecclesiastes 5:19:
“Also, when the true God
gives a man riches
“and material possessions
“along with the ability to enjoy them,
“he should take his reward
“and rejoice in his hard work.
This is the gift of God.”
Did you note two things
that Brother Marais
said could prevent us
from seeking
the Kingdom first in our lives?
One was being divided
—trying to serve Jehovah
while seeking riches
or other things in the world.
The second was anxiety
over what we need to survive.
We can avoid both of these distractions
by building up our faith
that Jehovah cares for us.
We’re assured that he will provide
for our needs in this system.
And in the new world,
we know he’ll satisfy
any wholesome desires
that we choose to sacrifice for now.
It may help to recall
what Jehovah has already done for us.
Can you remember your faith growing
when you first studied the Bible?
when you began your ministry,
sharing the Kingdom good news?
when you dedicated your life to God?
or when he helped you
through a serious trial?
If so, you can say with conviction
that faith makes things happen
and you can appreciate
the experiences depicted
in this encouraging music video.
A heart full of questions,
a life so unsure,
I heard what you told me;
I wanted more.
What you told me,
Unanswered questions
were answered that day.
The worry I was feeling
melted away.
All my worries
faded away.
It’s a long road we’re going down,
But faith can make things happen.
When there’s no way through
and no way round,
Faith can make things happen,
Make things happen.
I love what I’m learning
and share what I know.
I’m ready and waiting,
so here I go.
Yes, I’m ready
To share what I know.
My faith is like a fire
that burns within my heart.
I’ve got to keep it burning
and do my part.
Keep it burning
deep in my heart.
It’s a long road we’re going down,
But this I’ve not forgotten:
When there’s no way through
and no way round,
Faith can make things happen,
Make things happen.
Seeing sad days, bad days,
bring stormy weather.
Praying over and over,
staying close to Jehovah.
He said, “If you put your trust in me,
I’ll give you strength, and then you’ll see
The trials that came to be,
We faced them together.”
It’s a long road we’re going down,
But this I’ve not forgotten:
When there’s no way through
and no way round,
Faith can make things happen.
Now I’m so sure, I have no doubt,
When there’s no way through
and no way round,
Faith can make things happen,
Make things happen.
Nothing we experience
is too difficult for Jehovah.
That may be easy to remember
when things are going well.
But when anxiety or trials come,
can we remember to trust Jehovah?
What was one thing
our sister did to build her faith?
She prayed!
Even Jesus’ apostles begged him:
“Give us more faith.”
We can ask Jehovah for more faith
and then act with the courage
and strength that he provides.
Jehovah gives us his holy spirit,
both individually and as a group.
To see evidence of that,
we need only go to a part of the world
where Jehovah’s people
were put under intense pressure.
In South Africa, for example,
the government’s policy
of racial segregation, called apartheid,
lasted for 46 years, until 1994.
Our brothers were pressured
to take sides in armed conflict.
Their freedom to worship together
was limited.
And the prevailing attitudes
towards people of different races
threatened their unity.
In this report, we learn
how our South African brothers
remained united and neutral
and in support of God’s Kingdom.
One afternoon
when we came to the station,
there were men who were directing things
and we were directed
to a coach for whites only.
That was the first time
that we saw apartheid being law enforced.
You could not leave the black areas
where your home was
without getting a permit.
We were even given a permit that stipulated
which area we were allowed
to do the preaching work in.
People would always ask us:
“What are you doing to fight apartheid?”
We had to boldly tell them:
“God’s Kingdom is the only solution.
“God will help the whole earth
to live in peace one day,
so we cannot take sides
on political issues now.”
Here at home in Soweto,
we heard the sound
of children running in the streets.
We heard the sound of gunshots;
tear gas was everywhere.
When my husband came home that day,
we sat with the children
and took out the book
Your Youth—Getting the Best out of It
and we studied the topic
“How Do You View Your Parents?”
This was appropriate
because children had the spirit of rebelling
against their own parents.
They went as far as burning people.
They came shouting my son’s name:
“Aquila, Mathiba, come out, come out!”
And one of them defended him and said:
“No, no, no, not Aquila!
“Aquila does not do these things.
He will never protest.”
Ahh, I saw Jehovah’s hand in this.
Even under those circumstances,
Jehovah helped our children
not to dwell on the madness
in the streets,
and we focused on spiritual things.
In 1968, when I was 19 years old,
I was sentenced to jail
for refusing to do military service.
Over a period of 20 years,
close to 1,000 young white Witness men
similarly took their stand
for neutrality in this country.
We used to pray
for our white brothers in prison.
People in the black townships respected us
for the stand these brothers were taking.
In 1974,
over 30,000 black and white brothers met
for the afternoon session
of the “Divine Victory” Assembly.
When we first arrived,
there were policemen everywhere.
But after half an hour,
they saw how peaceful it was
and so they left.
For those few hours
in the dark era of apartheid,
we felt
the glorious brotherly love
as we praised Jehovah
together.
Brother Moses Nyamussua was asked
by a group on their way to a political rally
to weld weapons for them.
He refused to do so.
After their rally,
they went back to him and said:
“You refused to weld our weapons,
“and some of our comrades
were killed in a fight at the rally.
Now you will die.”
Brother Nyamussua maintained his neutrality
all the way to death,
and Jehovah will remember him.
In 1993, I was amazed
when a white person
came preaching house to house.
They came with another white man
who could speak Venda fluently.
That excited me a lot,
and as time went by,
I came to realize
that this is the true religion
because they were faithful friends
and they spoke to me like we were family.
In the late 1980’s,
the government granted us permission
to come in and build Kingdom Halls
in the black townships.
The local community
was absolutely amazed
to see all these whites
pouring in and working hard
along with their black brothers
to build these beautiful Kingdom Halls.
It was a wonderful privilege
to get to know other young people
of different races.
Everyone in the congregation feels
like family
as long as they serve Jehovah.
Just see yourself.
Just see me too.
Just see us all. . .
. . . in a world that is new.
Today, in South Africa,
there are more than 100,000 Witnesses
worshipping together in spirit and truth.
South Africa has 11 official languages.
Yet, across that cultural variety,
our brothers and sisters
are all speaking the “pure language”
—the truth about Jehovah God
and his purposes.
When we build strong faith
in times of peace,
we can find courage during times
of testing and persecution.
Brother Rocky Webb
from the United States
learned to be a fighter
as a young man.
But as his faith grew,
he learned that Jehovah is there
“to help us and to fight our battles.”
All of us are going to be tested
one way or the other
before we make it into the new world.
And if we can endure
those tests faithfully,
faithfully,
then we’ll make it.
My dad and my mother
taught me the truth.
What drove me to be baptized
was the convention in Washington, D.C.
Brother Rutherford gave the talk
on “the meek shall inherit the earth.”
It touched my heart in a way
that it’s never left
from that minute on,
right on up to now.
It gave me faith to stay
with Jehovah all the way.
The bullies would come
and jump onto me,
and I would come home
pretty well beat up.
So that’s when I started training for boxing.
I was offered $40,000 for a fight
—win or lose.
And if I won the second fight,
they would double the amount.
Brother Macmillan was like a second
dad to me and my brother.
And he asked me, and he said,
“Would you do me a favor?”
He said, “Don’t put the gloves on no more.”
And so I didn’t put them on anymore.
I think he knew
that it wouldn’t be very long
before there’d be an article on it.
It came out and told
that boxing wasn’t for Christians.
I was drafted during this time,
and I refused to serve
and was sent to prison.
All the time,
I never, never,
ever slowed down
on my theocratic deals,
never.
I kept right on on it.
The jail warden overheard me
witnessing to another inmate.
He told me,
“Don’t do anymore of that.”
He said, “We don’t allow it here.”
Three days had passed by,
and he’d seen me talking to him again.
And they put me in a car that was shaded
—you couldn’t see out.
I didn’t know where I was going.
It was an old, old prison,
just dark as could be in there.
It was three feet (1 m) around.
And they called it “the Sweat Box.”
All the time I was in there,
I’d just sweat, sweat, sweat.
And I went in
weighing 213 pounds (97 kg),
and I came out
weighing 133 pounds (60 kg).
Psalm 144 says:
“May Jehovah, my Rock, be praised,
“who trains my hands for battle,
my fingers for warfare.”
I gave my life
to give Jehovah my faith.
I lived in Wewoka.
Several congregations
would come together to work.
We were confronted by mobs.
There were a lot of them
that were injured.
I had 80 stitches up here,
and I had 13 in the side there,
on each stab.
I was really, really beat up.
But I couldn’t have stood up
if it hadn’t been for Jehovah.
I knew he was with me
some way or another.
So we sued the town and won $20,000.
The Society called us and said:
“You did very good
in what all you’ve done”
but said,
“Remember, we’re not out for money.
Make sure
that that’s made known to them.”
When we walked up to the desk,
they slid the papers out to us
and said, “Sign them up.”
And we just took them and slid them back.
It came out in the papers,
‘Tell them to come back
and do all they want to do
in the way of their witnessing.’
It said, ‘We won’t touch them.’
They really highly respected us
for what we did,
and so that opened it up.
And we had
a real good congregation there
that got started and everything.
My first wife was a blessing for me,
but when she died,
Jehovah stepped in
and gave me another good one.
We mow the lawns together.
No, no, we do most everything together.
We study to where
we can feel it in our hearts.
When you give your faith to Jehovah,
you’re giving your life to him.
He’s permitted these things
to come upon me;
I knew that.
But he protected me.
Brother Webb is now 94 years old.
But as we saw,
he and his wife, Charlene,
keep themselves spiritually active.
What lessons did you see
in Rocky’s experience?
For one, we heard
that Rocky learned to be a boxer
to protect himself from bullies;
yet he responded in faith
to loving counsel to quit
—even before God’s people
had a clear understanding
of violent sports.
Making that change
helped Rocky to continue cultivating
a Christlike personality.
That prepared him to stand firm
when imprisoned for his faith,
and it helped him
to not return evil for evil
when persecuted for his ministry.
He had faith that although Jehovah
permitted these things to happen,
He was also there to protect him.
Examples like those of Rocky
and the others we’ve considered
warm our hearts and let us know
we’re never alone
in our fight for the faith.
Like you,
our brothers around the world
are standing firm
and earnestly seeking out people
to show them what the Bible teaches.
Later this month,
you’ll enjoy hearing a report
from the Central America branch.
Preaching campaigns organized
by the branch are reaching people
in seldom-worked territories
across several countries,
such as Mexico, El Salvador,
Costa Rica, Panama,
Nicaragua, and Guatemala.
Later, when it is posted,
you’ll find it in the
“Video on Demand” section
under “Our Meetings and Ministry.”
We’d like to conclude our program
with a visit
to the Catania Fleming English Congregation
on the beautiful island of Sicily.
The small congregation
has 46 publishers
and 16 pioneers,
but they’re conducting on average
more than 60 Bible studies.
Critical times in this system of things
are also giving them
special opportunities
in the ministry.
Their territory includes
one of the largest refugee camps
in Europe.
It provides shelter
to people coming from countries
such as Nigeria, Gambia, Ghana,
Eritrea, and Somalia.
Each week, a group of publishers
drives an hour to the camp
to give a witness and conduct studies.
Residents from the camp also come by bus
to attend the weekend meeting.
The brothers and sisters
of the Catania Fleming English Congregation
send you their love and greetings.
We thank Jehovah for their willing spirit
to bring comfort to others
with the good news.
Thank you for being with us this month.
From the world headquarters
of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
this is JW Broadcasting!