‎My father was a self-made factory owner.
‎He started a business working
with rubber and plastics,
‎and we led a financially comfortable way of life.
‎But in the middle of the 1970’s,
‎things started going badly with his work.
‎For this reason,
‎he fell into a depression,
and he committed suicide.
‎This was a great shock.
‎I went to the wall and wrote the words
‎“He lives.”
‎I didn’t want to believe that from that day on,
‎I wouldn’t see my father again.
‎At the age of about ten, I began to develop
‎strong antireligious tendencies.
‎And later, at the age of 17,
‎I also expressed them by participating
‎in the most important incident
‎of the student movement
against the military junta
‎that was prevailing in Greece
and ruling the country.
‎I became a member of the Communist Party.
‎I went to Santorini and started a business.
‎I opened a bar.
‎Of course, all this included unsavory things
‎like immorality, drugs,
‎and plenty of alcohol.
‎A few months later,
I left to study in Germany.
‎It was the first time I met
a brother engaging in street work.
‎People would approach him,
‎and some would swear;
some even spat at him.
‎It impressed me immensely
‎how he stood calmly
and accepted this treatment.
‎We had interesting conversations.
‎My studies ended, and I returned to Greece
‎to take on the responsibility of the factory.
‎When I finished my studies in Germany,
‎I left with a sense of deep respect
‎for Jehovah’s Witnesses.
‎The influence of my friends
‎led me to go into the military,
‎and there I saw a huge amount of corruption.
‎The hope I had that we humans
‎would be able to succeed
without external help
‎—without God—
began to collapse,
‎and then the things I had heard
‎from Jehovah’s Witnesses
suddenly came to my mind.
‎The same afternoon,
I sought out a family friend,
‎the mother of a childhood friend, named Lily.
‎I said to her, “Please give me a Bible
‎and some Bible study publications
because I want to study them.”
‎I read everywhere,
‎and anything that I didn’t understand,
‎I wrote down in a notebook.
‎I got to the point, in just a few days,
‎where I had written down 80 to 90 questions.
‎Harry impressed me
‎because every time I asked him a question,
‎he gave me the answer from the Bible.
‎That convinced me that I’d found the truth.
‎So in that moment,
‎I decided to leave the military
and to quit smoking.
‎A few months passed by,
‎where I was occupied mostly with the factory,
‎until I recognized
‎that for me to make progress in the truth,
‎I had to sell my shares in the factory.
‎And on July 7, 1984, I was baptized.
‎The authorities
—the police, the mayor,
‎the health inspectors—
began to demand money
‎so that I could keep the bar open.
‎I refused all the things they asked of me,
‎and so the war became harder
‎until one night when I went
to open the door to enter my home;
‎I heard a tramping from behind,
‎I tried to turn and see,
and as I turned,
‎I was hit in the face.
‎During that time,
‎when all of this was happening,
my brother Dimitris arrived.
‎As brothers,
we never really had a relationship.
‎When he came to Santorini
and began to talk to me
‎and help me understand
what was happening to me,
‎I realized that this was a different Dimitris.
‎I said to him, “I want us
to start studying the Bible together.”
‎I had the Bible with me
almost everywhere I went
‎so that I could read it.
‎I realized that Jehovah was helping me
to understand what I was living for.
‎He was helping me to understand
‎that I could have a real goal, a purpose,
‎and a hope.
‎On the day of my baptism,
I felt that I was drawing closer to Jehovah.
‎I felt like my smile went from ear to ear.
‎And now with Lydia,
‎I have the great joy of serving
‎in the Romany territory.
‎We enjoy very nice Bible studies.
‎It is truly something
‎that shows you Jehovah’s love,
‎interest, and affection
‎—things that I had felt
‎many years ago
when I studied with my brother.
‎Today, my brother and I
love each other very much.
‎It is a relationship characterized
‎by brotherly love
‎as it is expressed in the Bible.
‎We are very close to each other.
‎This is really a change.
‎Now we are truly brothers!