Welcome to the program,
brothers and sisters!
During the next hour,
you will hear the story of a brother
who previously protected
the president of a country.
But seeing the love among God’s people
made him refocus his life
to bearing witness
about the Sovereign of the universe.
We cherish our international brotherhood.
Our brothers and sisters
in the former Soviet Union took great risks
during the Cold War to convey their love
to fellow Witnesses
on the other side of the globe.
Does our love for Jehovah motivate us
to avoid living a double life?
This dramatization
will remind us of key principles
to protect us when we are tempted
to draw closer to Satan’s world.
This is the July program
of JW Broadcasting!
In the book
Insight on the Scriptures,
under the heading “Christian,”
it makes clear that claiming to be Christian
requires more than simply
a mere confession of faith.
It is more than
being a nominal Christian
—a Christian in name only.
For example,
according to the Bible,
it is necessary that belief
be demonstrated by works,
not just words.
And since we were born
as sinners,
those who become Christians
need to repent,
to turn around,
to dedicate their lives to Jehovah,
to worship and serve him,
and then to submit
to water baptism.
They must keep themselves
clean from fornication,
from idolatry,
and from consuming blood.
They are to strip off
the old personality,
including such things
as fits of anger, obscene talk,
lying, stealing, drunkenness,
and as Galatians chapter 5 says:
“things like these.”
Yes, they are to bring their lives
into accord with Bible principles.
Christians are to be
kind and considerate,
mild-tempered and patient,
and are to exercise self-control.
They provide
and care for their own
and love
their neighbor as themselves.
That’s a lot, isn’t it?
It’s not a matter
of just glibly saying,
“I am a Christian.”
But despite all of those
impressive characteristics
that we just enumerated,
what did Jesus say
the main identifying quality
of a true Christian would be?
Most of you know the answer to that,
but let’s read it again
from John 13:34, 35.
It says: “I am giving you
a new commandment,
“that you love one another;
just as I have loved you,
“you also love one another.
“By this all will know
that you are my disciples
—if you have love among yourselves.”
Those are the theme verses
for my discussion
with you this month.
The topic is:
“Love—The Identifying Mark
of a Disciple of Jesus.”
Did you notice
in verse 34 that Jesus said
that he was giving them
at that time a “new commandment”?
But it sounds like
a very old commandment, doesn’t it?
Why, over 1,500 years
before Jesus said
the words we just read,
the Law given to Moses said:
“You must love
your fellow man as yourself.”
—Leviticus 19:18.
So, what was “new”
about Jesus’ command
in John chapter 13?
He said that true Christians
were to love each other
“just as I have loved you.”
That is what was different.
That was new,
not just love the other person
as you love yourself,
but love him just like
Jesus loved His followers.
Well, what kind of love
would that be?
Self-sacrificing love
—and usually we think
of Jesus’ ultimate sacrifice,
his willingly giving his life
so that we might have the hope
of everlasting life.
But when you think about it,
that aspect of Jesus’ love
was exemplified
in a self-sacrificing death!
Now, it is true,
that as a Christian,
we might at some time have to give
our life for a fellow Christian.
But we hope
it doesn’t come to that.
So instead of talking
about a self-sacrificing death,
we want to discuss
showing this new kind of love
as evidenced
in a self-sacrificing life,
not necessarily our death.
You see, Jesus’ life
—his three-and-a-half-year ministry—
was a self-sacrificing life
of loving others.
In addition to doing good
when something requires it,
a true follower of Jesus
is to take
the initiative to help others
spiritually and otherwise.
He is to work actively
for their good.
The preaching and teaching
of the good news to others
—some of whom may even be hostile—
is one of the greatest expressions
of love, for it can result
in everlasting life
to the recipients.
However,
according to Paul’s words
at 1 Thessalonians 2:8,
a true Christian must
‘impart not only the good news of God
but also his very self’
in helping those who
accept the good news.
It’s that kind of love
that Jesus said would be
an identifying mark of his disciples,
not specifically that his followers
would all be dying for each other,
but more so that they
would all be living for each other.
Yes, displaying self-sacrificing love
for one another
every day of their lives.
The four Gospels
are a treasure trove
of Jesus’ self-sacrificing love.
And yet,
they do not cover his actions
every day of his life
as the Christ.
His three-and-a-half-year ministry
amounts to nearly
1,300 days of life and love.
The written record
of Jesus’ life is admittedly brief,
but it is grand indeed!
However, the reality
of observing Jesus every day
must have been far grander
than what we have in print.
What we have in print
might be likened
to a photo album
of Jesus’ life,
some snapshots.
By comparison,
what his apostles experienced
with Jesus day after day
was like a continuous video
of his example of love.
No wonder that,
at John 21:25,
the apostle said:
“There are also . . .
“many other things that Jesus did,
“which if ever they were written
in full detail,
“I suppose the world itself
could not contain the scrolls written.”
It said there were
‘many other things Jesus did,’
not many other things
that he said,
but that he did,
yes, deeds or acts
demonstrating
his self-sacrificing life of love!
We already mentioned
the all-important preaching work
as being an act
of love on our part.
But how else
do we manifest
the most obvious trait
of a genuine Christian
—love like Jesus had?
Let’s start by thinking
of the elders in the congregation.
At Philippians 2:17,
Paul said that he
had ‘poured himself out
to the congregation
like a drink offering.’
What did that mean?
It meant that he
drained himself out,
both physically and emotionally,
to support the Philippians.
Many of the elders
in our congregations
have the same self-sacrificing love
for those under their care.
They give of their time
to shepherd
and readjust those in need.
They take the lead
in the ministry.
They respond when there is
a serious health issue or tragedy.
They pour themselves out for the friends,
thus identifying themselves
as disciples of Christ.
But we do not have
to be an elder
to provide a word
of encouragement, do we?
If we all keep focused
on others in the congregation,
not just ourselves,
we will know
who needs to be bolstered
because of trials
or circumstances that they face.
Giving in this way
is evidence of Christlike love.
You may be thinking,
‘But I’m just a little old sister
‘who finds it hard to squeeze out
a word of encouragement to others.’
Perhaps you don’t have
to say anything,
just be there
at the meetings
or in the service.
When others see your face,
they are encouraged.
Follow along
as I read Acts 28:15.
It reads:
“From there the brothers,
“when they heard the news about us,
“came as far
as the Marketplace of Appius
“and Three Taverns to meet us.
“On catching sight of them,
“Paul thanked God
and took courage.”
Paul “took courage”
just by seeing the brothers
who came out to meet him.
You encourage your brothers
and sisters by your presence.
Please follow along as I read
Philippians 2:1-4.
Paul here describes it
as “encouragement in Christ.”
He says:
“If, then, there is
any encouragement in Christ,
“if any consolation of love,
“if any spiritual fellowship,
“if any tender affection
and compassion,
“make my joy full by being
“of the same mind
and having the same love,
“being completely united,
having the one thought in mind.
“Do nothing out of contentiousness
or out of egotism,
“but with humility
“consider others superior to you,
“as you look out not only
for your own interests,
but also for the interests of others.”
Did you notice
the self-sacrificing aspect
of this love and encouragement?
Yes, he talked about having love,
but then he said,
“not . . . for your own interests,
but . . . for the interests of others.”
That type of love
—in the interests of others—
is the identifying mark
of true Christians.
What about visiting
the sick in your congregation
or those who are housebound?
Sometimes these dear ones are
“out of sight, out of mind.”
We visit with those we see
when at the Kingdom Hall,
but do we think about those
who are shut-ins?
What was a major part
of Jesus’ loving acts when on earth?
There are numerous accounts
of Jesus and his apostles
healing the sick.
It’s true that we
cannot heal the sick,
but it is in our power
to visit the sick.
And what a healing
that is to their spirit!
It means so much when
they are not just prayed for
at a meeting,
but when those words of prayer
are backed up
with an act of love
—a visit to them in person.
That is Christlike love in action.
Why not scroll down the list
of those in your service group
with the thought in mind
of checking on those
who have been missing
from the meetings?
Do they need a meal?
Do they need some help
perhaps around the house?
Do they need transportation
to the doctor?
Can we allow our love
to expand to fill their needs?
Contributing to the worldwide work,
which cares for the needs
of our brothers around the world,
is another act of love.
It demonstrates that we are
a true disciple of Christ.
Related to that, many of you have,
at your own expense,
traveled to far-flung places
to help rebuild
after a natural disaster has struck.
The overwhelming response
from the victims is evidence
of your self-sacrificing life
and love for your brothers.
It is hoped
that the reminder of Jesus
at John 13:34, 35
will be good for all of us,
not just for this month,
but for our whole course of life.
You know, about one third
of the world’s population
claims to be Christian.
But how many of them
show self-sacrificing love
outside of their immediate family?
Most are like a baseball team
in a uniform.
They think having the word “Christian”
emblazoned across the front
of their uniform
is all that is required.
However, most of them
simply “sit on the bench,”
or on a pew in church,
and many do not even attend
“the game.”
They do not live
the life of a Christian.
Jesus made clear
that being a true disciple of his
is not merely
“wearing a uniform,”
simply claiming to be
his follower.
No, it involves
actively demonstrating
works of love,
“swinging hard for the team,”
imitating the all-time greatest examples
of love,
Jehovah God and his Son,
Jesus Christ.
As Paul said
at 2 Corinthians 8:8,
we need “to test
the genuineness of [our] love.”
Yes, we need to daily prove
that we are
a genuine disciple of Jesus.
Brother Reinmueller will now
share some examples of how
the Bible principles
we just discussed
have helped people
around the world.
Alex.
Thank you, Brother Herd,
for that warm encouragement.
We’re more motivated than ever
to prove our love for Jehovah and others.
We recently met Mamuka Tektumanashvili,
from the country of Georgia.
He was a high-ranking officer
in the special forces there for many years.
What made him realize
that defending his country
is not the highest honor
a man can have in his life?
This is his story.
For 18 years
I served in a special unit
responsible
for presidential security.
This mission
demanded total self-sacrifice.
For example,
the first and the last vehicles
of the presidential escort
belonged to this unit.
So if an attack
occurred on the president,
we were the first ones
to be hit with the fire.
For the last ten years
of service, I worked
as an instructor
and trained new staff
to provide
presidential security in the future.
Those working in this field
must be fearless.
They must be professionals,
and that is what I taught
to succeeding generations.
I just loved my job.
I was a fervent patriot.
I had a special regard
for the flag of my country.
In one bag,
I always had weapons and the flag.
Patriotism
was so deep-rooted in me
that I would beat up a person
simply because he was
of another nationality.
I always thought
that God would never allow
people like me
to draw close to him.
One day, Jehovah’s Witnesses came
and preached to my wife and me.
We were so interested
in the truth that my wife
even expressed
a desire to study the Bible.
Because there were rumors
circulating about Jehovah’s Witnesses,
I decided first to make sure that everything
was decent at their meetings
and only then allow my wife
to associate with them.
After the meeting,
I was absolutely thrilled.
Everyone was well-mannered,
with friendly, smiling faces.
I realized that there was nothing there
to threaten my wife’s well-being.
On the contrary, their association
would be beneficial for her.
Soon my wife
and our eldest daughter got baptized.
As for me, I enjoyed associating
with Jehovah’s Witnesses.
Later, I also started
to study the Bible.
I knew that I had to make
drastic changes in my life,
but my job
prevented me from doing so.
Moreover, I felt
that door-to-door preaching
was far more difficult
than engaging in combat.
I respected Jehovah’s Witnesses
for their courage and strength.
Little by little,
I too was changing for the better.
I wanted to quit my job and inform
my colleagues about my religious beliefs.
So I wrote down all the Bible verses
I had recently learned
and then pinned them
on the wall in my office.
I also started to think
about how to make a living
after leaving my job
and decided to learn a trade.
I started to buy tools
in order to be ready
to take care of my family.
I realized that the time
had come to make a decision.
The day I quit my job
was one of the happiest days
of my life.
Since then, I’ve been able
to dedicate every minute of my life
to Jehovah
with a clean conscience.
In a few months, I got baptized.
In the beginning,
we were hardly making a living.
However, this taught me
to trust in Jehovah.
I tried my best to keep
service to Jehovah in first place.
I deeply appreciate
the support of my brothers
and sisters
and association with them.
Before, I used to carry out
the orders of men
—some of which
I carried out reluctantly.
But now I am happy to carry out
an assignment from Jehovah
with the same spirit
that the prophet Isaiah had,
who said:
“Here I am! Send me!”
As a family, we decided to move
where the need was greater,
and this has united
our family even more.
This is the bag
in which
I always carried weapons,
but now they are replaced
with a Bible and Bible literature.
In the past, I thought
I could never preach
from door to door.
But now I can say with conviction
that the words of Jesus
have proved true in my case:
“All things are possible with God.”
Brother Tektumanashvili
now serves as an elder,
and he has also been
a regular pioneer since 2014.
While Brother Tektumanashvili
served the government for many years,
there are those who live
on the other side of the law.
How does Jehovah’s unprejudiced love
reach out to them?
Join us as we travel
to the Democratic Republic of Congo
in Africa,
where our brothers make
special efforts to reach people
we would not normally
find from door to door.
I could say that my past
was really an unhappy past.
I went through very difficult times
during my childhood.
I lost hope
that I could ever have
a better life.
Because of that,
I started to associate
with the wrong people in my life.
One night, I was arrested
and sent to Buluo Prison.
It is a high-security prison
in Congo.
Prison is a very dangerous place.
But I was surprised how they
accepted the truth so easily.
Really, I was amazed.
We needed to obtain permission
to be able to continue
to preach in the prison.
We had so enjoyed
the preaching work there.
I went to see the authorities in the city
to find out what was required
so that we could have permission
to preach in the prison.
To my great amazement,
they simply handed me a paper
and told me to put
my request in writing.
They asked me to wait.
Within minutes,
I had the authorization
in my hands
without paying anything at all.
Every time the situation
seemed insurmountable to us,
impossible to us,
we saw the hand of Jehovah
providing us
with the suitable solution.
The authorization gave a great boost
to this special witnessing initiative.
In harmony with 1 Corinthians 9:22, 23,
the brothers could then
‘become all things to people of all sorts,
so that they might
by all possible means save some.’
Some religious leaders
who were also prisoners
were extremely opposed
to our presence.
They conspired and had us
thrown out of our meeting place.
The prisoners themselves
were concerned about this.
They found another meeting place
even more spacious than the former.
Since Buluo is eight kilometers
away from our congregation,
to transport the group who support
the preaching work and meetings,
the body of elders organized two minibuses
to go out every Saturday to Buluo.
Once they arrive,
they begin the preaching work at 8:30,
and at 10 o’clock
the meetings start.
All the meetings of the week
are held on the Saturday.
Concerning Jehovah’s Witnesses,
personally, I am very impressed.
It’s more than three years they’ve been
more active in helping the detainees.
The reeducation of the prisoners
is assured by Jehovah’s Witnesses.
This is a good collaboration
on the part of Jehovah’s Witnesses.
With this I’m very happy.
One hundred
and seventy-five attended
the circuit assembly
in December 2014,
which was held in the prison,
and seven were baptized.
Local media covered the event.
This is the first time I have seen
Jehovah’s Witnesses
baptized here
in the Buluo Prison.
This is a good thing.
I encourage you
to continue with this assistance.
Every week there are
more than 80 in attendance
and sometimes
more than that, even 140.
In the attendance
there are the 36 publishers
—the brothers who learned
the truth in Buluo Prison—
30 are baptized
and 6 unbaptized.
I visited many churches
because I had a lot of questions,
but I never got
any exact answers.
When I went to see
Jehovah’s Witnesses,
they gave me accurate answers
from the Bible.
To know that Jehovah
is compassionate
and ready to forgive,
these are the qualities
that touched me.
I used to be a soldier.
I was in the military.
I attended various churches
because I had a question
that bothered me a lot.
I wondered why God allows
bad things to happen
to people all the time.
While I was in prison,
Jehovah’s Witnesses came to visit
and talk to us.
I asked them
the same question,
“Why does God allow sickness
and suffering to continue?”
They replied by using
three Bible verses.
I was very happy because I received
the answer to my question.
Papy Okito is a brother
who learned
the truth in prison.
He made
such remarkable progress
that those in charge
now have confidence in him.
Like Joseph in the Bible,
he has been placed in a position
of supervision over the other prisoners.
He also made further progress,
and thus, the management has requested
that his prison sentence
be reduced.
When I arrived in the prison,
I had lost hope.
I thought for me
it was the end.
By means of the Bible,
I have found joy
and hope in my life.
That is why today I am happy
even though I am still here.
But I know
that the Paradise is for me.
It’s been five years
since the brothers
started preaching
in the Buluo Prison.
At times, the publishers place
up to 500 magazines in one weekend.
Although our success is not
measured by the number of placements,
this response does paint
a clear picture
of the spiritual thirst
among these prisoners.
In the last few months,
inside these prison walls,
11 more unbaptized publishers
have been approved.
What a loving act by Jehovah
and his organization
to help such individuals satisfy
their spiritual needs!
In the late 1950’s,
the opposition
against Jehovah’s Witnesses
in the former Soviet Union
resulted in homes being searched,
brothers being followed,
and many of our brothers
and sisters being sent
to Communist concentration camps
in Siberia,
among other places.
In 1956 and 1957,
over 462,000
convention delegates worldwide
unanimously adopted a petition
which clearly outlined the treatment
Jehovah’s Witnesses were enduring.
It was sent
to the Soviet authorities,
but sadly, not much changed.
The next year,
at the 1958 international convention
at Yankee Stadium
in New York,
a talk was given entitled
“Behind the Iron Curtain.”
During the talk,
delegates were surprised
when a recording of greetings
and songs from brothers
and sisters in the Soviet Union
was played.
Despite the risk of losing
their freedom,
the brothers produced
and sent these recordings.
Well, a few months ago,
some of those who were involved
in making the recording
were able to listen to it
for the first time
Several of them
found out only then
that the recording had been played
at the convention at Yankee Stadium.
Our team was present
at that gathering.
The brothers told us
to prepare songs for a recording.
When we were singing,
I never imagined
that it was for a convention,
because I did not know about that.
We sang as usual.
The chorus was made up
of about 20 persons,
and the recording
was made in a room
in a barrack-like building.
I just looked after the chorus
to give them the right tone.
If someone sang a little off-key,
she would right away remark:
“Altos, you are off!”
or “Tenor, you are off!”
so that there would be no slips,
no mistakes.
We had to be very careful
when we were recording.
And so we knew not to talk.
I could not tell
anyone about it.
It was secret
—absolutely secret.
They chose a brother
who spoke very good Russian,
who had good intonation,
and who had a good voice.
And as I recall, we made
the recording on our first attempt.
Brother Yuriy Dobychin
said the greetings.
I was young then,
and I had a good voice.
So I had to say
the greetings
from the brothers
in the Soviet Union
for the brothers gathered
at Yankee Stadium.
As the brothers who made
the recording told me,
the most difficult assignment
for them
was how to get this recording
across the border.
The brothers cut it up
into pieces
and sewed it
into the lining of a jacket
because that’s how
confidential letters were sent.
One married couple
from Poland,
who were vacationing
in Russia,
agreed to take it
back with them
—to take it
out of the Soviet Union.
And that’s where they ran
into serious problems.
From Brother Scheider’s letter,
who received
the audio recording in Poland:
“The security officers separated
our brother from the others.
“Then an officer said to him:
‘Please give us the film
and the three letters you have with you.’
“The brother saw now,
of course,
“that there had been
a traitor somewhere.
“He and his wife
were now thoroughly searched.
“Every square centimeter
of their cases
“was carefully examined
together with their contents.
“Then both were stripped naked.
“While this was going on,
they yelled at the brother:
‘Tell us where you have hidden everything
or to whom you have given it!’
“They were absolutely convinced
that he had everything with him.
“Several times they took him
to the office
“of the frontier police
and to the security police,
“searching him
again and again
“and being terribly angry.
“But they finally had to give up.
“They kept him back
for 24 hours
“and questioned him
in the presence of ten specialists.
But he came out victorious.”
Sadly, even the brothers
who were involved
don’t know who this couple
who brought the tape
into Poland was.
Well, for me it was, of course, a great joy,
since the goal was reached after all.
Everything was so wonderful
at that time.
I really enjoyed it all!
Nothing could describe
the joy I felt.
I was overwhelmed with feelings.
And so my voice was recorded,
and the greetings were heard
in New York
at Yankee Stadium.
These dear brothers and sisters
have no regrets.
They are happy
that their efforts encouraged
so many thousands
back then and today.
The kind of love
these brothers and sisters showed
is often noticed
by those not in the truth.
A young couple from the United States,
Jeremiah and Holly Draper,
experienced just that.
The blessings that I enjoy today
are so numerous.
I have a true inner sense
of joy and happiness.
I can’t help
but be appreciative,
so grateful
for all that Jehovah does.
But it wasn’t
always this way for us.
It was a dark world growing up.
I never knew
what being a child was like.
I was afraid
of who I would grow up to be.
I felt like I had no choice.
Then at a very young age,
I, as well,
started to partake
of what I saw going on around me.
I learned quickly that it helped numb
the feelings that I had.
Drugs were a way
to escape that.
I was in a lot of trouble
with the law.
I knew I needed change,
so I joined the military
at a young age.
Around my teenage years,
my life became difficult.
I started to turn to drugs and alcohol
and self-destructive ways,
but none of these things
were making me happy.
I was very lonely.
No one knew me;
no one cared to know me.
I felt so lost,
and I was trying
to fill this big hole in my heart
with so many things,
and none of it worked.
One of my many car accidents,
due to drugs and alcohol,
ended me up in jail
for 30 days straight.
I felt like a hopeless mess.
I just knew
something’s got to change.
So I joined the military,
thinking it was going to be
the positive great change
that I needed,
but it was not.
I remember
joining the military
hoping that it
would bring some sort
of authority into my life,
but I again started
to spiral
into my anger,
my alcohol and drug abuse.
The military decided
to let me out.
But during deployment
is where I met Holly.
Holly also got
out of the military,
and we started
to live a life together.
But we were still searching
for something to fill
the emptiness
that we both felt in our lives.
Jeremiah and I were both working
in a steel factory in Montana.
During this time,
I was being trained on a drill
by one of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
a sister named Molly.
Molly said, “You’re
going to have down time
“on this machine,
maybe a couple of hours,
so feel free to read
whatever I have in my tool box.”
I opened it
and immediately
a little yellow book,
What Does the Bible Really Teach?,
caught my eye.
I loved the pictures.
The scriptures
at the beginning of the book,
they touched my heart immediately,
and I felt like,
‘These answer all the questions
I’ve been searching
for my entire life!’
Another sister came over,
her name was Cory,
and she said:
“Molly and I can come over,
“and we can talk to you
about the Bible tomorrow.
If you have any questions,
we’d love to answer them using the Bible.”
I said, “Yes, come over!”
I was a little bit
more apprehensive.
I stayed just to make sure
nothing got weird,
but this was finally
something very different.
And I realized what they were saying
came from the Bible.
I’d never seen that before.
They invited us
to the Kingdom Hall.
We went in,
everybody had their Bible,
had time to look
the scriptures up together,
and everybody was
so warm and inviting.
These were the people
I’d been searching for my entire life.
All of a sudden change
was possible.
We knew what changes
we needed to make in our life.
What we were doing,
our actions,
we had to clear out things
that Jehovah hates.
Like just going through
our house and deciding
what it is
that we need to get rid of.
By allowing the truth
to transform our lives,
Holly and I’ve received
many blessings,
and eventually we were able
to come here together and serve at Bethel.
We got the truth in a weld shop,
and now I get to weld
here in Jehovah’s house for him.
I perform maintenance
on water fountains,
refrigerators, coolers.
Being trained by the brothers
and sisters I work with
just helps me to refine
my Christian personality.
It’s so nice to know
that Jehovah
is looking down on us;
that he was able
to see through
all of the trash
that was there in our life.
He was able to find something
and decided to work with it.
And I really think of a scripture,
Psalm 145:19:
“He satisfies the desire
of those
“who fear him;
he hears their [cry] for help,
and [he] rescues them.”
Jehovah did that for us.
If you ask Jehovah
to display his hand in your life,
no doubt at all in my mind,
that will happen.
Did you notice how
Jeremiah and Holly were touched
by the Christian love shown to them
when they visited
the Kingdom Hall for the first time?
Jeremiah said that everybody
was so warm and inviting.
Yes, love truly is
the identifying mark of Jesus’ disciples.
But Jesus taught that love
for fellow believers and our neighbor
is second to our love for Jehovah.
Being kind and encouraging to others
is of little value if it’s not rooted
in a deep desire
to please our heavenly Father.
In the following dramatization,
a young brother is reminded of the value
of carefully examining his heart.
My name is Shawn.
I was raised in the truth.
I was doing everything right.
But I was doing everything wrong.
I was in my senior year of high school.
Everything was going great
until this new girl joined our school.
I really don’t know
how it even started.
We just sort of hit it off
and became good friends.
I mean, she was so easy to talk to.
Before I knew it,
we were texting all the time.
Then, one thing led to another.
Honestly, when things
started to get physical,
I thought I could control it,
but it was only getting worse.
I didn’t want to let my parents down.
So I started lying to them,
and then I started lying to myself.
I thought if I could just keep
going to the meetings and do my parts,
it could somehow be OK.
But I was far from OK.
The next night, we had family worship.
We were reading about the account
of Ananias and his wife, Sapphira.
When a special fund was set up
for needy Christians, Ananias sold a field.
But then, he boldly claimed
he was contributing
the entire proceeds of its sale.
In reality, though,
Ananias had “secretly held back
some of the price”
for his personal gain.
Peter boldly said to him:
“You have lied,
not to men, but to God.”
Jehovah wasn’t fooled
by their pretense.
Then we read Psalm 44:21:
“[God] is aware
of the secrets of the heart.”
Reading this account of Ananias
and Sapphira made me realize
I wasn’t just lying
to my parents or my friends.
I was lying to Jehovah.
As much as I didn’t want
to let my parents down,
even more so,
I didn’t want to let Jehovah down.
I prayed long that night.
I didn’t hold anything back.
By the next morning,
I knew what I wanted to do.
It wasn’t easy,
but my parents were very supportive,
and I also got the help
I needed from the elders.
It’s been a few years,
but as I look back now,
I was one of those kids
living a double life.
But now with Jehovah’s help,
I’m living the best life.
What a clear warning this is,
not only for young ones
but also for those of us
who have served Jehovah
for many, many years.
As we well know, serving Jehovah
faithfully for many decades
is only valuable
if we ‘endure to the end.’
By developing
intense love for Jehovah,
we’ll be able to overcome
whatever temptations or trials we face.
And speaking
of enduring to the end,
Brother Mark Sanderson recently spoke
at morning worship in Bethel
about how our eager expectation
of the day of Jehovah
will help us to endure faithfully
in this system of things.
Pay close attention
to some of the ways
we show such expectation.
Well, here’s the question
we want to ask this morning:
Is it actually possible
to speed up the day of Jehovah?
Well, if we look at our text this morning
at 2 Peter 3:11,
we’ve had that read for us,
so we know
that expression at the end
that we should “consider
what sort of people you ought to be
in holy acts of conduct
and deeds of godly devotion.”
But then it goes on to say:
“As you await and keep close in mind
the presence of the day of Jehovah.”
Well, now, if you look at the footnote
on this expression in verse 12,
you’ll notice that the expression
“keep close in mind” literally means
to “speed up” the day of Jehovah.
Well, now, how can we do that?
Well, it’s true we cannot bring
the day forward of Jehovah
even one day,
nor can we move it
back even one day.
That is not within our power.
That day is set.
But how can we, then,
“speed up”
the day of Jehovah
as it says there in verse 12?
Well, we keep that day
close in our mind.
We never let it be out of our sight.
As the footnote also says,
we “eagerly desire” it.
Well, now,
if we’re persons like that,
Peter says
that we’re going to be busy
in “deeds of godly devotion.”
Well, now,
just as a quick reminder:
What is godly devotion?
Well, just looking
at our New World Translation glossary,
here’s the definition:
It’s “reverence, worship,
“and service to Jehovah God,
with loyalty
to his universal sovereignty.”
Well, what do we get
from that definition?
Did you notice
—reverence, worship, service?
You see, godly devotion
is not passive; it’s active.
It’s reflected
in action and in activity.
Well, that’s why the apostle Peter
used the expression in verse 11,
“deeds of godly devotion.”
Well, what are some of the ways
that we demonstrate this quality?
Well, some of them are just very small.
For example, what about hospitality?
At 1 Peter 4:9,
when the apostle Peter
wrote his first letter, he said:
“Be hospitable
to one another without grumbling.”
Well, there are
so many opportunities
for us to imitate Jehovah
and be hospitable
—to share with others
according to their needs.
And this really is an expression
not only for another person
but it’s an expression
of our love for Jehovah
—our desire to want
to imitate him.
Well, we all acknowledge that.
But here’s the question:
When was the last time
that you acted hospitably?
Or when was the last time
I acted hospitably?
You see, it’s not enough just to love
the quality of hospitality.
If we are going
to have deeds of godly devotion,
we’re going to have to practice it.
Here’s another one.
What about helping the elderly
that are in our midst?
You know,
our elderly brothers need help.
They need help
to get to the meetings.
to get out in the field ministry.
Some of them
are confined to their homes.
Well, if that’s the case,
they may need help from younger ones
to assist them
with shopping or doing errands
or just doing
some chore around the house.
Well, that’s something
that has been mentioned
in many Watchtower articles.
It’s been mentioned
at many conventions and assemblies.
at many congregation meetings.
But now here’s a question:
When was the last time
that you did something
for an elderly brother or sister?
Or when was the last time I did?
You see, we need to think
about not just loving these ideas
but what are we doing to really help?
See, that’s showing
deeds of godly devotion.
Well, of course, we also have to think
about the more major things.
What about attending
our congregation meetings?
Hebrews 10:23-25
—that scripture
that we quote so many times—
says that we should ‘not forsake
our meeting together.’
But it goes on to say
that we should ‘encourage one another.’
So it’s not enough
just to be at the meeting.
When we’re there, we want to reach out
and do everything that we can
to encourage our brothers
and really participate in the meeting.
You see, godly devotion
is not passive; it’s active.
And so, what sort of persons ought we to be
when we’re at the meeting?
Well, we know we want to be active,
fully involved with the program.
But now, of course,
what’s the most important way
that we exercise
these deeds of godly devotion?
Well, you’ll remember
that the apostle Paul
at 1 Timothy 3:16
referred to ‘the sacred secret
of godly devotion,’
and he showed there
that Jesus really was that secret.
You see, he was
the one who demonstrated
godly devotion
in a perfect sense.
Now, Paul in that verse,
1 Timothy 3:16,
went on to say that Jesus
was ‘preached among the nations.’
Well, then, that really is
a vital part
of our deeds of godly devotion
—preaching about Christ Jesus,
his Kingdom,
and everything
that will be accomplished.
But brothers,
how much incentive we have today
to be involved fully
in our preaching work.
We have tools today
like we have never had before.
You know, over the summer
as I was attending
a number of different regional conventions
in different parts of the world,
I enjoyed so much,
no doubt just as you have,
using the JW Library app
and downloading
the Why Study the Bible? video
in a number of different languages.
We had one real interesting experience
when we were in Europe.
We got into a taxi
with a driver from Africa.
And right away,
we asked him what his language was.
Well, he told us it was
a language not familiar to us at all.
But while he was driving,
we managed to download
the Why Study the Bible? video,
and it automatically
began to play as we were in the car.
Well, as soon as the man heard it,
he started shouting:
“What’s happening?
What’s happening?”
I think he thought
he was hearing a voice from heaven
when he heard
his own language in the taxi.
But we reassured him
that that was not the case.
But he was so moved.
He almost didn’t want to take the fare,
if you can imagine,
and initially
he had been quite unfriendly.
But when he saw
what was available on our website,
he was deeply moved.
Well, maybe
you’ve had a similar experience.
Just as a note of future reference:
It’s probably not a good idea
to play the video
when someone is driving.
Well, if we have
real godly devotion that’s active,
we’re going to be busy
in doing deeds of godly devotion.
You know,
there’s an old saying that says:
“Time flies when you’re having fun.”
Well, you know, even scientists
acknowledge that there’s truth in that.
A study that was published
in the year 2012
in the journal
Psychological Science said this:
Although we tend to believe
that time flies
when we’re having a good time,
these studies
indicate that what it is
about the enjoyable time
that causes it to go by more quickly.
It seems to be the goal pursuit
or achievement-directed action
we’re engaged in that matters.
Just being content or satisfied
may not make time fly,
but being excited or actively pursuing
a desired object can.
Isn’t that interesting?
Well, now, if we’re
the sort of persons that are busy
with holy acts of conduct
and deeds of godly devotion,
reaching out for that most important goal
of everlasting life,
we will speed up the coming
of the day of Jehovah
in our hearts and our minds.
What deeds of godly devotion
do you remember
from that fine presentation?
Among other things,
Brother Sanderson explained
that one deed of godly devotion
is to be hospitable to one another.
Hospitality is also the theme
of this month’s music video,
which is entitled
“Follow the Course [of Hospitality].”
It might be a meal or snacks or coffee
Or fun and games, maybe just talking.
Jehovah is the one who put it on our table.
So could we be able . . .
“Follow the course of hospitality.”
Imitate God above.
Do it with true impartiality.
That’s what it means to love.
The roof above our heads
is from our heavenly Father.
But if we need to share,
would it be a bother?
Let’s feel the joy
that only ever comes from giving!
That’s Christian living.
“Follow the course of hospitality.”
Imitate God above.
Do it with true impartiality.
That’s what it means to love.
Some people don’t have what we have.
It’s up to us to share.
Disaster strikes, then they’re without.
Will we really care?
Could we open up our home
and host a friend in need?
Do a kindly deed.
“Follow the course of hospitality.”
Imitate God above.
Do it with true impartiality.
That’s what it means to love.
What a nice song!
And while that music video
brings this program to its conclusion,
we’d like to encourage you to watch a video
that will be posted later this month
about Sister Cindy McIntosh.
She was in the military for many years
and described herself as having become
a “dark and uncaring person.”
But then Jehovah taught her
what true love means.
The video is entitled I Put Down My Rifle
and is available on Video on Demand
in the “Interviews
and Experiences” category.
Yes, love truly is
the identifying mark of true Christians.
That’s what stands out
when you
visit other congregations,
perhaps when traveling.
One good example
is the Nong Khai Congregation
in the northeastern corner of Thailand.
The 32 publishers send their love.
There’s a great need in Thailand,
which is why half
of the 10 appointed brothers
in the congregation
and half of the 18 pioneers
are “need greaters.”
Witnessing carts have been set up
at a nearby border crossing,
with ten languages
regularly featured.
Many copies
are placed with visitors
from countries
where our work is restricted.
Sometimes over 1,000 pieces of literature
are placed in a single day
at the border crossing.
The Nong Khai Congregation
had the privilege
of being a host congregation
when a special convention
was arranged
in October of last year.
And during the convention,
they were surprised and overjoyed to hear
that the New World Translation
was now available
in the Thai language.
We pray that Jehovah continues to bless
the brothers and sisters in Thailand.
And all of you around the world,
we love you very much!
This is JW Broadcasting
from Brooklyn, New York.