There are many exciting things happening
in Jehovah’s organization.
Why, month after month, we read articles,
watch videos, and hear personal experiences
about our brothers and sisters
who are doing more for Jehovah.
They are serving where
the need is greater or reaching out
for the School for Kingdom Evangelizers.
They are working
on construction, renovation,
maintenance of Kingdom Halls,
or other theocratic projects.
No doubt,
many of you watching this program
are excitedly looking forward
to expanding your ministry
in one of these areas.
We encourage you to do so.
You can be assured
that you will receive much fulfillment
and many blessings from Jehovah.
On the other hand,
there are others
who are watching this program
who may feel discouraged
because their circumstances
may seem to limit
their being as involved as they would like.
What are some of these circumstances?
These may include our age, our health,
our economic situation,
or our physical limitations.
For some of us,
perhaps our upbringing
or past errors
we have made in our life
may cause us to feel
that we are limited
as to what we can do
for Jehovah.
As we know well,
focusing on our limitations
can affect our joy,
causing discouragement.
What can we do?
There are many examples
in the Scriptures of men and women
who had circumstances
beyond their control
that seemed to limit how much
they could do for Jehovah.
Others had to deal with the effects
of their upbringing and family life
or with serious errors they made.
Did they allow themselves to be limited
by their circumstances or their past?
How did Jehovah feel about them?
How does Jehovah feel about us?
That is what we are going to discuss
in this month’s broadcast,
which has the theme
“Are You Defined by Your Circumstances?”
Let’s start by looking at some
who could have let
their circumstances limit them.
Consider first the example
of Joseph in the book of Genesis.
Now, Joseph faced injustice at its worst.
His situation was especially hurtful
since it was initially brought on by those
who should have been closest to him
—his family!
As a slave in Egypt
and later as a prisoner,
Joseph was indeed limited
in what he could do.
How might Joseph have reacted?
Well,
Joseph could have become so preoccupied
with what he could not do
that he lost sight of what he could do.
Did Joseph let his circumstances
paralyze his life?
No!
He chose to make
the best of his situation.
In fact,
note what Joseph did
while serving as a slave
in Potiphar’s house
if we turn together
to Genesis 39:4:
“Joseph kept finding favor in his eyes,
“and he became his personal attendant.
“So he appointed him over his house,
and he put him
in charge of all that was his.”
Joseph worked diligently
within the limitations
of his circumstances.
He took a similar approach while in prison.
Joseph focused on what he could do
despite suffering the effects of injustice.
As a second example,
consider Hezekiah.
Hezekiah is one
who might easily have felt
that he was defined by his upbringing.
Look at the terrible example
that was set by his father, Ahaz,
as recorded in 2 Kings chapter 16.
Second Kings chapter 16,
and notice what verse 3 says about Ahaz:
“Instead, he walked in the way
of the kings of Israel,
“and he even made his own son
pass through the fire,
“following the detestable practices
of the nations
that Jehovah had driven out
from before the Israelites.”
Hezekiah’s father did detestable things
in opposition to Jehovah.
But Hezekiah showed
that he was not the helpless victim
of a poor parental example.
What did he do?
Well, turn in your Bibles
to 2 Kings chapter 18
and notice verse 3,
what it says about Hezekiah:
“He kept doing what was right
in Jehovah’s eyes,
just as David his forefather
had done.”
Verse 5 says of Hezekiah:
“There was no one like him
among all the kings of Judah.”
He became fully involved in true worship.
Verses 6 and 7 say that Hezekiah
‘held fast to Jehovah,
and Jehovah proved to be with him.’
How encouraging
Hezekiah’s example is for us!
We can choose to be loyal to Jehovah
and do much in our worship of Jehovah,
even if we did not grow up in a family
that served Jehovah fully.
We are not helpless victims
of our environment.
Hezekiah’s example
reassures us that our past
does not have to control our future.
As a third example,
consider the apostle Paul.
He did not let his own past mistakes
involving religious prejudice and violence
stop him from giving his all to Jehovah.
How did Paul feel about his past?
Well, let’s read together
at 1 Corinthians 15:9:
“For I am the least of the apostles,
“and I am not worthy
of being called an apostle,
because I persecuted
the congregation of God.”
“I am the least of the apostles.”
Later, when writing to the Ephesians
as recorded at Ephesians 3:8,
he calls himself
“less than the least of all holy ones.”
Finally, at 1 Timothy 1:15,
he now calls himself
the “foremost” of all sinners.
Yes,
Paul’s prior treatment of the congregation
weighed heavily upon him.
Could Paul have reasoned
that he was damaged?
Could he have reasoned that his past
limited what he could do for Jehovah?
He could have,
but Paul did not do that.
He poured himself out
for the congregation.
Why, Paul was privileged to write
more books and letters
in the Christian Greek Scriptures
than anyone else.
He demonstrated
an outstanding zeal for the ministry.
Paul did not let his conduct in the past
dictate what he could do for Jehovah.
And there are many other examples as well.
For example,
are we in a difficult economic situation?
The account in 2 Corinthians chapter 8
tells us about the Macedonians.
Paul says that they were in deep poverty.
Yet they begged to have a financial share
in the relief work.
Are we older in years?
We may think of Anna.
The account at Luke 2:36-38
tells us that she was 84 years old
and that her husband had died
after just seven years of marriage.
Yet,
“she was never missing from the temple.”
She rendered
‘sacred service day and night.’
What lessons do we learn
from these accounts?
Our dear brothers and sisters
in Bible times were just like us.
Many were in circumstances
that they would not have chosen.
Yet,
they did not let their circumstances
or their past define them.
They joyfully did what they could
within the limits of their situation.
And these are just a few examples.
There are many others in the Bible.
Why not make it a personal study project
to research faithful ones
who were in circumstances
similar to yours?
How did they stay involved
in Jehovah’s work?
We are sure
that you will be greatly encouraged.
Now,
we’ve considered examples of those
who did not let
their circumstances hinder them
from giving their all to Jehovah.
But another question is:
How does Jehovah
view his faithful servants
despite their limitations?
Now, I’ve often thought
about the example of John the Baptizer.
As we know, he was arrested
shortly after Jesus started his ministry.
John could have felt
that he was no longer of use
to Jehovah or the work.
Yet, as recorded at Matthew 11:11,
Jesus said about John:
“Among those born of women,
there has not been raised up
anyone greater than John the Baptist.”
Jehovah’s and Jesus’ view of John
was not based
on the man’s circumstances
of being in prison.
Their view of John was based on
who he was on the inside
and on his relationship with Jehovah.
Jehovah did not focus on the limitations.
In Jehovah’s eyes,
John was great.
He was still a faithful servant
doing the best that he could,
and that was all that really mattered.
Another example
that may come to your mind
is that of King David.
As we know,
King David committed serious sins.
Yet,
David repented for his sins,
and there is no record
that he repeated them.
How did Jehovah view him?
Did Jehovah see David as damaged,
as a man who would always be
limited in serving him?
Notice Jehovah’s words
directed to King Jeroboam
at 1 Kings 14:8:
“But you have not become
like my servant David,
“who kept my commandments
“and who walked after me
with all his heart,
doing only what was right in my eyes.”
Jehovah viewed David
as a special servant.
He says that he
“kept my commandments.”
He did
“what was right in my eyes.”
That’s what Jehovah remembered.
How encouraging that is for us!
If we have repented
of our past mistakes
and set matters straight
to the best of our circumstances,
we too can be assured
that Jehovah loves us dearly.
He appreciates whatever we can do
in our worship of him.
So, what’s the point?
Well, our past
or our present circumstances
do not define our value before Jehovah.
Our Father loves us for who we are,
and he values our efforts
as we do the best
that we can to serve him.
Why do you think it is important
that we strive to see ourselves
as Jehovah does?
Because we can weaken,
discourage, or limit ourselves
if we see ourselves only
in the framework of our circumstances.
May we work hard not to do that.
What does Jehovah see
when he looks
at his faithful servants today?
Well, turn, please,
to 1 Samuel 16:7.
And the setting is
that Samuel was about to go
to anoint the next king of Israel;
and he goes to the house of Jesse;
and Jesse lines up all of his sons,
except for David,
who is still out in the field;
and Samuel walks in
and he sees Eliab.
And based on what he sees,
Samuel concludes that this surely must be
the next king of Israel.
Yet, note what Jehovah saw.
Please read with me 1 Samuel 16:7:
“But Jehovah said to Samuel:
“‘Do not pay attention
to his appearance and how tall he is,
“‘for I have rejected him.
“‘For the way man sees
is not the way God sees,
“‘because mere man sees
what appears to the eyes,
but Jehovah sees into the heart.’”
That’s the way Jehovah sees.
He does not look
at our outward appearance and our abilities;
he sees into our hearts.
He sees what we would be doing
if all of the limitations
were lifted off of us.
Why, just the fact
that we keep going,
that we keep putting
one foot in front of the other,
endears us to Jehovah.
We understand the truth
of that statement,
and we all may agree
that this is how
Jehovah views his people.
However, we may have
a hard time convincing ourselves
if this really applies to me.
Have you ever wondered:
‘Does Jehovah really see me?
‘Does he see what’s in my heart
and value my desire to do more for him?’
The answer is yes.
In fact, Jehovah has already seen
what is in your heart.
Think about this:
Why are you watching this program?
Why do you care about spiritual things?
Why are you, perhaps,
the only one in your family
who is a dedicated,
baptized servant of Jehovah?
Or why are you, perhaps,
the only one at your place of employment
or the only one near where you live
who’s serving Jehovah?
Is it because you are
so much more studious
or smarter than everyone else?
No!
Haggai 2:7 tells us
that Jehovah
“will shake all the nations,
and the precious things
of all the nations will come in.”
John 6:44 says
that ‘no man can come to Jesus
unless the Father draws him.’
Jeremiah 31:3, Jehovah says:
“I have loved you with an everlasting love.
That is why I have drawn you.”
So again, why are you serving Jehovah?
Because Jehovah loves you.
Jehovah drew you.
As he was shaking the nations,
he looked down into your heart
and he saw something very precious
and he drew you to him.
He said,
“I want to draw this person to my Son.
“I want to draw this person to me.
I love this person.”
Jehovah drew you,
not because you have
perfect circumstances,
but because of your heart
and because he loves you.
He greatly appreciates
that his servants give their best to him.
Remember,
not the way man sees is the way God sees
—Jehovah sees what the heart is.
May we work hard
to see ourselves as Jehovah does
and be determined to never give up.
May we never forget that it is
the privilege of bearing Jehovah’s name,
having a relationship with him,
and our love for Jehovah that defines us.
Jehovah is happy
if we give the best that we can.
So may we do our part
by not limiting ourselves
due to our circumstances,
but always look for ways
to give our best to Jehovah.
You beautiful older ones,
even those with severe health problems,
can do much to help
in the great work that’s taking place today.
Now, you may wonder
what can you do.
You can pray for your brothers and sisters.
We need your prayers.
Pray for the Governing Body.
Pray for those who are taking the lead.
Pray for the elders in your congregations.
Pray for those who
are going through difficult times.
Do such prayers help
the work of the organization?
Absolutely!
James 5:16 tells us
that ‘a righteous person’s supplication
has a powerful effect.’
No matter who we are
and whatever our situation in life,
may we find joy
in giving what we can for Jehovah.
And may each one of us
rejoice at the privilege we have
of being part of what Jehovah
is accomplishing in these last days.