There’s a railroad sign
that most of us have seen
before we cross a railroad track.
It says: “Stop, Look,
[and] Listen.”
And some will say:
“and Live.”
Now, why is
this sign there?
Because we know that
crossing a railroad track
can endanger our lives.
But the danger
is not so evident;
it’s not immediately seen.
It must be deduced
—you must use
your thinking abilities.
And that’s why
one sign says:
“See Tracks? Think Train!”
So we first must stop
and then look both ways
and then even engage
the sense of hearing to listen.
Do we hear a rumble?
a vibration in the earth?
Do we see a headlight coming our way?
Is a whistle blowing?
You see, all these indicate a danger.
The train is not in front of us immediately,
but we have to be aware
of the danger because,
as this picture shows, a fast moving train
just cannot stop immediately
if we happen to be in the middle
of the railroad tracks.
If we were there,
we definitely would be killed.
To avoid such a tragedy,
we therefore must use what the Bible calls
our “perceptive powers”
to discern the danger that is before us.
And then we must take appropriate action
to find safety to make sure
that we are not victimized by the danger.
Now, this well illustrates
what Jehovah has been telling us
through his Word
and through his organization.
Jehovah is telling us today to stop,
look, and listen.
Look around you.
Discern the times that we’re living in.
We’re living in the last days.
The end is very near.
The great tribulation is about to take place.
Now, it’s necessary to have discernment
in order to come to this conclusion.
Jesus said you would need discernment.
At Luke 17:20, 21,
he says that the Kingdom
would not be “coming
with striking observableness.”
It would take discernment
to understand the signs
and what it would mean
and what action to take.
This ability to discern requires cultivation
—we need to work on it.
The Bible at Hebrews 5:14
calls it the “powers of discernment”
or what we used to call
the “perceptive powers.”
And as we learned in yesterday’s text
when it referred to the prophet Daniel,
he was exemplary
in using his perceptive powers
to perceive, or to discern, the will of God.
And it was necessary for him to do so
in order to avoid the dangerous situation
that he and his companions were in
there at the palace in Babylon.
Now, Daniel continued to cultivate
these powers of discernment.
Later on in his life,
he made a deep study of the prophecies,
especially those of Jeremiah.
And then he concluded, or discerned,
where they were in the stream of time
—that the end
of the 70-year desolation of Jerusalem
was coming to its conclusion.
And this moved him to take
specific action to prepare himself
as well as other faithful Jews
so that they could proceed
with Jehovah’s will and purpose.
He therefore understood the times
and events that were taking place
because of the deep study that he did,
and he was able to discern
what was taking place
in the world around him.
Now, Jesus taught us to do
something very similar.
He told us to cultivate discernment,
and he used
a beautiful illustration to do that.
Open your Bibles, please,
to the book of Luke,
and we’ll look at chapter 21
and verses 29-31.
And here Jesus uses this technique
of “stop, look, listen, and live.”
He says in verse 29:
“Notice the fig tree
and all the other trees.”
So stop and look around you, he says.
And verse 30, it says:
“[And] when they are budding.”
In other words, look at these plants
and “you see it for yourselves
and know that now the summer is near.”
So discern it;
perceive what is taking place here.
And then he tells us and listen in verse 31:
“Likewise also you,
when you see these things happening,
know that the Kingdom of God is near.”
So here Jesus was telling us
to stop, look, listen,
and then we would live.
Now, “the faithful and discreet slave”
—they’re guided by the head
of the congregation, Jesus Christ.
And he is providing direction
to us in a very similar way
to help us sharpen
our powers of discernment
to comprehend and understand
what’s going on around us.
It’s through the pages of The Watchtower
and our assemblies and conventions
that we are told to stop
—leave off your everyday life and concerns
and stop for a moment;
and then look into God’s Word
—read it and see what the Bible has to say
about Jehovah’s will and purpose
and especially our time period;
and then take time to listen
to the explanations provided
through “the faithful and discreet slave”
about prophecies and about our time period
and the nearness of the great tribulation.
Now, today, we are receiving
a very clear message
from Jehovah God’s organization
through Jesus Christ
and through “the faithful and discreet slave”
that the great tribulation is imminent.
Now, how should this information affect us?
Well, for one thing, the anxieties of life
—the things that immediately confront us
on a day-to-day basis—
can sap our energy
and can totally distract us
away from the bigger issues.
And Jesus warned us against this.
In fact, going back to the book
of Luke chapter 17,
there Jesus uses the accounts
of Noah as well as Sodom and Gomorrah
to be a warning to us.
There He says that the days of the Son of man
would be like the days of Noah and Sodom.
And why?
Because people would be distracted
with the mundane cares of life.
It’s these mundane cares of life
that can truly dull our powers of perception.
We would not be able to discern
where we are in the stream of time
or the danger that is confronting us.
So we have to really be careful
that we don’t allow these things
to dull our powers of discernment.
Otherwise, we can find ourselves
just wandering onto a railroad track
and not really looking,
not listening, being distracted,
and before you know it,
a train could overtake us.
And that’s exactly what is happening
to people in the world today.
They’re distracted by these things,
and they’re failing to take notice
that Jehovah God is coming
at them at full speed
to execute judgment
against Satan’s wicked world.
However, when we sharpen
our powers of discernment,
we clearly see the signs.
And Jesus said that you would.
He said at Luke 17:24
that it would be like lightning flashing
from one end of the sky
to the other end of the sky.
But it would be only
because our powers of discernment
would see these things and understand them.
Now, we see very clearly.
We look around at the political world today,
and we can see
these “lightning flashes” all around us.
In Daniel’s vision of chapter 2
—the iron and the clay
of the final world power—
we see how fragmented they are,
how weak and ineffectual
this world government is.
At 2 Timothy 3:1-5, the attitudes of people,
including those who are leaders in the world,
are arrogant and blasphemous and haughty.
These are clear indications
that we are very near the time of the end.
In fact, these individuals
and these governments
are very much like
an illustration that we saw
in the October 15, 1971,
issue of The Watchtower
of a little ant standing on a railroad track,
and here we see
God’s Kingdom coming at them.
And we, obviously,
see what the outcome will be.
They will be completely pulverized
by the power and speed
of Jehovah’s executional forces.
So we see, therefore, it’s important
for us to sharpen our powers of discernment
—to cultivate this quality—
so that we are not caught off guard,
we always see the danger,
and we can take appropriate action.
So every day, let us stop, look,
and listen to Jehovah’s warnings.
This will help us stay out
of the danger zone,
and we’ll be able to survive
the end of this system of things,
and the great tribulation
will not catch us off guard.