Jesus called the apostle Paul
“a chosen vessel.”
He was among the most dynamic ministers
who ever lived.
But when he wrote
his second letter to Timothy,
he was in prison bonds,
which severely limited
what he could personally do
to spread the good news.
But that situation did not dishearten him.
His letter refers to what others were doing.
Luke was there
with him in Rome but still free.
Aquila and Priscilla
were still working hard in Ephesus.
He asked for Mark to come
to assist him with the ministry and,
of course, he gave instructions
to his beloved son Timothy.
But most important,
notice what he said
at 2 Timothy 2:8, 9.
Second Timothy 2:8, 9:
“Remember that Jesus Christ was raised up
“from the dead and was David’s offspring,
“according to the good news I preach,
“for which I am suffering
and being imprisoned as a criminal.
Nevertheless, the word of God is not bound.”
Yes, Paul was in chains,
limiting what he could do,
but “the word of God”
—the message that he
and others had been proclaiming—
was not bound.
It was alive; it was in the hearts
of thousands of people
that they had preached to.
And it was to be recorded
in countless copies
of the Scriptures in time.
Once this message was unleashed,
the power of it could never be bound again.
I’ll just read Hebrews 4:12, the first part.
It connects with this scripture.
It says:
“For the word of God
is alive and exerts power.”
Now, on the second expression
“exerts power,”
the Greek word
according to the Kingdom Interlinear
says that it is “living” and “energetic.”
In fact, we derive
the English word “energy” from this word.
But the context shows,
both in Hebrews and in 2 Timothy,
that “the word of God” refers to the message
or expression of God’s purpose.
And, of course, that message
is closely connected to the Bible today
because that’s the book
that contains that message for us.
And through the centuries,
opponents have tried
to lessen the power, or energy,
of the Bible in these three ways:
first, by removing God’s name
from copies of the Bible;
second, by destroying copies
of the Scriptures in past centuries and,
more recently, by making it difficult
to obtain in many languages;
and third,
by means of inaccurate translation
and dead language.
These three developments have been
like a short circuit in an electric line.
The power is hindered
from reaching its destination.
Jehovah’s organization has moved
in the opposite direction
on these three fronts.
And tonight, we’re going to consider
three roles of the New World Translation
in ensuring that the power
of Jehovah’s Word is not bound:
first, by making
God’s name known earth wide;
second, by making
the Scriptures freely available to all;
and third, by making God’s message
accurate, clear, and alive.
And we’re also going to discuss
the role of the worldwide Bethel family
in this regard.
So first, we’re going to consider
the role of the New World Translation
in making God’s name known earth wide.
Before Christ’s brothers began work
on the New World Translation in the 1940’s,
English Bibles
like American Standard Version, Rotherham,
and others had already restored
the divine name in the Hebrew Scriptures
based on the strong manuscript evidence
that they found.
Translations like The Emphatic Diaglott
even used it in the Greek Scriptures.
But these translations
were like the proverbial “dead lion”
of Ecclesiastes 9:4.
In the 1940’s,
people almost exclusively read
the archaic King James Version
with its four occurrences of Jehovah’s name.
The first real challenge to the dominance
of the King James Version in English
was the Revised Standard Version,
which was published in 1952.
But the committee of that version
strongly rejected
the American Standard Bible policy
of using the divine name,
and they substituted it everywhere
with “Lord.”
And today, almost all English Bibles
follow that policy.
There are a few exceptions,
but this is the mainstream.
In fact,
here are the five
best-selling English Bibles,
according
to the Christian Booksellers Association.
The total occurrences of the name Jehovah
in these five Bibles
are the four occurrences
in the King James Version
plus the seven occurrences of Yahweh
in The New Living Translation.
There are no occurrences
in any of the other three Bibles:
New International Version,
New King James Version,
and English Standard Version.
That means
that all of these popular Bibles say:
“I am the Lord, that is my name,”
or “The name of the Lord
is a strong tower.”
Consider Exodus 6:3 in the popular,
actually,
the best-selling New International Version;
it’s even passed the King James Version:
“I appeared to Abraham, to Isaac,
“and to Jacob as God Almighty,
“but by my name the LORD
I did not make myself fully known to them.”
There are four names here in the Hebrew text:
Abraham, Isaac, Jacob,
and the Tetragrammaton, Jehovah.
Now, a primary reason given
in the Revised Standard Version
and many other Bibles
for substituting “LORD”
is because “Jehovah”
is not the original pronunciation
or that it should be “Yahweh.”
But the fact is we don’t pronounce
Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob
the same way that the ancient Jews did.
We probably don’t know
exactly how they pronounced it.
It may have varied over the centuries.
But following their reasoning,
their translation should say:
‘I appeared to your forefather,
‘and to his son,
‘and to his grandson as God Almighty,
‘but by my name the LORD
I did not make myself fully known to them.’
Now, this is obviously
an unreasonable approach
to translating the first three names,
don’t you agree?
But that’s exactly what they did
with the fourth name.
They said,
‘We don’t pronounce it the same way,
so we’re not going to translate it.’
But taking this even a step further,
if they were so concerned that “Jehovah”
is not the exact pronunciation of God’s name,
what about the name Jesus?
Acts 4:12 says:
‘There is no other name that has been given
by which we must get saved.’
So is its pronunciation equally important?
In fact, scholars don’t even agree
on whether Jesus and his disciples
spoke Hebrew or Aramaic,
which would affect the pronunciation.
Hebrew would be something like Ye·shuʹa‛;
Aramaic, Ye·shuʹ
—something like that.
But what about
the poor Greek-speaking disciples
who didn’t have the “s-h” sound?
They said I·e·sousʹ.
But that was the form
recorded in the inspired Scriptures.
The most corrupted pronunciation
is “Jesus” in English.
It’s nothing like they would have said it
in the first century,
but that doesn’t prevent
its use some 900 times
or even more in all of these Bibles.
So their position on removing God’s name
on the grounds of pronunciation
is indefensible.
In legal terms, the Legal Department
would call it a crime of omission.
But the situation
regarding God’s name is the same
and even worse in other languages.
Well, you ask, ‘How could it be worse?’
When God’s name is substituted
with the name of a local god.
That was done
with the Chichewa Bible in Malawi.
This journal,
it’s called The Bible Translator,
sets policies for translators
of the United Bible societies worldwide,
and it explains why Jehovah’s name
was replaced with the name Chauta.
Here they give the reason:
“In this respect the important revelation
“for Chewa people today
“is that the foreign deity Yehova
“is really Chauta,
“the God they’ve always known
“and worshipped
“and the God whom their ancestors
“also turned to for help
in the time of trouble!”
It’s incredible reasoning, isn’t it?
No wonder our Chichewa brothers
refuse to use this Bible,
even though it was far easier to understand
than their previous Bible.
This is one of the so-called solutions
found in this special issue
of The Bible Translator from October 1992
on the topic translating the names of God.
And these policies are still current
among translators today.
The editor’s opening comments give an idea
of the direction given.
“It has become clear in recent years . . .
“that no one solution to the problems
“we face in translating the names of God
will meet all situations.”
First, their wording gives the impression
that God has a number of personal names.
Also, these consultants
frequently call it a “problem”
because for them it is a genuine problem.
They know that God’s name
is the most frequently occurring name
in the whole Bible.
It occurs thousands of times
in the Hebrew text.
And they also know
why others include it in the Bible.
In fact, on page 409
of this journal,
there’s a quote from the foreword
of the American Bible Society,
of the American Standard Bible Society:
“This personal name [Jehovah],
“with its wealth of sacred associations,
“is now restored to the place
“in the sacred text to which it has
an unquestionable claim.”
And that’s
what the American Standard Bible did,
and it sounds reasonable.
But notice the conclusion:
“It cannot be denied
“that this [American Standard] view
“influenced the thinking
“of scores of evangelical missionaries
“who were sent out to various places
“in Africa, Asia, and Latin America. . . .
“Consequently, the name “Jehovah”
“was mistakenly introduced
“as a translation of the name of God,
“a name which would remain undisputed
“and be considered unchangeable
for many years to come.”
So they viewed “Jehovah” as a mistake.
They don’t say “Jesus” was a mistake,
even though, as we saw,
the same pronunciation issues apply.
But this so-called mistake
led to an interesting situation.
As they say, scores of Bibles were produced
by those missionary translators,
and they used the name thousands of times.
But many of those missionaries
who translated those Bibles
were not native speakers,
so their translations
were often difficult to understand.
In the latter half of the 20th century,
translators like Eugene Nida led a movement
to revise many of those older Bibles
to make them more understandable.
But Nida, whom The New York Times
refers to as “the father
of modern Bible translation,”
expresses his view
about the divine name in his book
The Theory and Practice of Translation.
He says:
“There is a kind of divine ambiguity
“in the use of the same term
to apply both to God and to Jesus Christ.”
Ambiguity, yes, but not divine.
Such statements
are repeated in other references
—for example, by consultants
for the Wycliffe Bible Society.
And they show the real reason
why so-called Christian translators
are so ready to omit the name Jehovah:
because it creates confusion
between Jehovah and his Son, Jesus Christ.
Because of these developments,
brothers in fields
like Chichewa, Hindi, Thai, and others
were left with a choice:
either use a hard-to-understand Bible
containing God’s name
or a readable one that omitted the name.
What do you think the brothers did?
In almost every case,
they chose the difficult Bible,
even if it was harder for them
to read and understand,
because it had Jehovah’s name in it.
To understand the frustration,
imagine this sister in India
trying to explain
why we are called Jehovah’s Witnesses
to this householder.
She could read Isaiah 43:10,
but if her Bible said,
“‘You are my witnesses,’ declares the Lord,”
she might have to explain that in Hebrew
there are four letters here
that should say “Jehovah.”
The woman might ask:
‘What is Hebrew?
What does Hebrew have to do with this?’
After explaining, she might ask our sister,
‘So do you know Hebrew
so that you can explain this to me?’
Some brothers have been so frustrated
that they would read “Jehovah”
even when their Bibles said “Lord.”
But when the householder
would see that they
were reading something different,
they would become suspicious.
But it’s interesting
talking about the context of India.
This Bible Translator has an article
about the reaction in Christendom
—not among our brothers,
but in Christendom—
where Jehovah’s name was replaced
by the word Prabhu or “Lord”
in Hindi and Nepali Bibles.
The article entitled
“What Is His Name?
Translation of Divine Names
in Indian Languages” explains:
“Not all Christians are happy
“with this solution however. . . .
“[He’s talking about Christians
in Christendom.]
“The first reason is an emotional one:
“the readers have been so used to reading
“and hearing the transliteration Jehovah
“that they have come to attach
“some kind of sacred significance to it.
“[Poor people.]
“They have become
“so emotionally attached to the name
“that no amount of argument
“can make them change their minds.
“The second reason . . . ,
“as some Nepali Christians told me,
“they are often asked by Hindus
for the name of the Christian God.
“The Hindus claim that all Hindu gods
“and goddesses have a personal name
“such as Ram, Krishna, Brahma, . . .
“and when they know the names
“of the gods and goddesses
they can relate themselves to the deities.”
Now since Prabhu or “Lord” can be used
for “husband,” “master,” and “god,”
Hindus will not accept it
as being God’s name.
So he continues in his article:
“Hindus are not interested
“in the title of God;
“they want to know
“the personal name of God,
“and unless they know the name,
“they cannot relate themselves
to the one who bears it.”
Now notice his conclusion:
“Having said all that, however,
“and having argued in favour of translating
“the name YHWH by [LORD], . . .
“I must concede
“that in the light of recent studies . . .
“a new approach may become necessary.
“That means that the last word
“has not been said
“on the question of rendering
“the ‘Tetragrammaton’ YHWH in North Indian
(and other) languages.”
Well happily,
this is the last statement
we’re going to read
from The Bible Translator,
and it’s the only one we agree with.
In fact, the last word
for some languages of India
was spoken one month ago.
On September 4, 2016,
a video of Brother Herd was broadcast
throughout India, in Sri Lanka
and to brothers in other locations,
as he announced the release
of the complete
New World Translation in Hindi,
Malayalam, and Tamil
and the Christian Greek Scriptures
in Marathi and Telugu.
The whole New World Bible
was already available in Sinhala;
in the Greek Scriptures,
in Kannada, Gujarati,
Nepali, and Punjabi.
So our brothers in India,
Nepal, and Sri Lanka
have all these Bibles available
to make Jehovah’s name known
in that vast field of 1.3 billion people.
Jehovah says at Ezekiel 38:23:
“I will certainly magnify myself
and sanctify myself
“and make myself known
before the eyes of many nations;
and they will have to know
that I am Jehovah,”
—not ‘that I am the Lord,’
not ‘that I am Prabhu,
or Señor, or Chauta,’
but Jehovah.
The undeniable trend
in Bible translation worldwide
is to omit God’s name.
And Jehovah is countering that
by using the New World Translation
to figuratively unchain his people
from Bibles that fail
to honor and sanctify his name.
And we’re happy
that 95 percent of our brothers in India
and over 90 percent worldwide
have a modern translation
of at least the Christian Greek Scriptures
that uses the name Jehovah.
Second, we’re going to discuss
the role of the New World Translation
in making the Scriptures freely available.
In the past,
opponents like Roman Emperor Diocletian
and the clergy of the Middle Ages
gathered and burned copies of the Scriptures.
The Bible survived,
and copies are freely available
in languages like English,
French, Spanish, and others.
But today, economic and copyright issues
have made the Bible
difficult to obtain in many languages.
A South American missionary wrote:
“The Bible societies translate
into many Amerindian languages,
“but it seems like every
new translation is just a trophy.
“It is translated, printed in a few copies,
and then forgotten.
“Usually these translations
are expensive, complicated,
and simply not available
to the people who need them.”
A request was made
to translate the New World Translation
into a language of the Pacific
because the only Bible
had removed the divine name completely,
and it is not readily available,
since only small quantities
of this Bible were originally printed,
and it is not currently being reprinted.
Yes, it’s true
that the Bible has been translated
whole or in part
into 2,800 or more languages,
but it is readily available
in just a fraction of those languages.
And Bibles are especially poor in areas
where the population
doesn’t have money to spend on Bibles,
printing is unprofitable,
and it’s often in areas
where we have great increases.
In some languages,
a Bible may cost up to a monthly salary.
And the copies that brothers get
for their monthly salary
are often missing pages
—sometimes whole Bible books—
and sometimes they are
just roughly-bound photo copies.
When a branch office
tries to obtain Bibles at reduced cost
or even offers to reprint
the Bible in such languages,
they’re often rebuffed
by the copyright holders.
In Malawi, for example,
our brothers were told
not even to quote
the Bible in our publications
so that the sales of their Bible
would not be threatened.
Visitors to some African lands
have been shocked
to see over a hundred brothers
sharing two or three Bibles
in the congregation.
A brother wrote:
“Most Tshiluba-speaking brothers
in Congo did not own a Bible.
“Each copy was passed around
like a microphone
when a ‘read’ scripture was called.”
Otetela congregations in Congo
often just had one or two copies.
Brothers used to go to the Kingdom Hall
to practice their talks with the Bible.
Well, this makes these images
of Brother Lösch in Congo
releasing the Christian Greek Scriptures
in Tshiluba, Kongo,
and Otetela even more meaningful.
This brother’s reaction
may seem dramatic to us,
but it may have been
his first personal copy of the Bible.
And you see this crowd
carefully studying their new Bibles.
I notice they’re not comparing it
with their previous copy,
likely because for many of them,
there was no previous copy.
Think also: If brothers had
such a hard time getting a Bible,
how easy would it be
for a Bible student to get a copy?
The Rwanda branch
wrote that 18 Bible students
there in an isolated group
hesitated to start preaching
because no one in their group had a Bible.
When they received
the Kinyarwanda Christian Greek Scriptures,
they felt confident
to begin their public ministry.
In other language fields
where Bibles were scarce,
they would not sell them
to Jehovah’s Witnesses
even if they had the money.
When Kyrgyz brothers
tried to buy Bibles at a religious bookstore,
they would be asked,
“What is God’s name?”
If they gave the answer, no Bible.
Similar situations
used to exist for Albanian, Isoko,
Malagasy, Tzotzil, and many other fields.
Now the tables have turned
in many of these places.
The easiest way to get a Bible
is to go visit a Kingdom Hall.
An elderly man
from the mountains of East Timor
traveled down to the capital
in search of a Tetun Bible.
The closest thing he could find
was an Indonesian Bible
at the store for 45 U.S. dollars
—two weeks’ salary for him—
not even in his language.
The storekeeper said,
“You should go and find Jehovah’s Witnesses.”
Well, after searching all day that day
and most of the next day,
he finally found the brothers,
and he was delighted
to receive Bibles, Bible literature,
and also have a discussion with them.
He said it was the answer to his prayers.
The brother said he now sends
text messages from the mountains
with questions about what he’s reading
in his Tetun Bible.
A Hiligaynon-speaking brother
from the Philippines wrote:
“People now ask,
‘What will happen to your organization
“‘since you
are freely distributing this Bible?’
“They’re worried
about us running out of money.
“The usual answer:
“‘It is Jehovah’s will
to let all people know his name.
Do you think he will let the funds run out?’”
And the brothers always say
good conversations are generated from that.
It’s true that the generous contributions
of Jehovah’s people
in more prosperous lands make this possible.
But it also makes us think of Isaiah 55:1,
and let’s turn there to Isaiah 55:1.
It says there:
“Come, all you thirsty ones,
come to the water!
“You with no money,
come, buy and eat!
Yes, come, buy wine and milk
without money and without cost.”
Now, if you read further in this chapter,
it’s clear that this is a Messianic prophecy.
And we have no doubt that Jesus Christ
is the one orchestrating this campaign
of distribution of millions of Bibles,
along with Bible literature,
to the poor and the humble people
of the earth.
He won’t allow the power of God’s Word
to be bound by economic or copyright issues.
Next, we’re going to discuss
the role of the New World Translation
in making the Bible’s message
clear and alive.
The existence of thousands
of languages and their subtle differences
is a natural obstacle to communication.
To illustrate, a Brazilian Bethelite
was asked where a visitor was.
He responded, “He passed away.”
When he saw the shocked reaction
of the brother, he said:
“No, no, no. He passed out.”
The other brother was still concerned.
And he finally pointed,
and he said, “He went that way.”
Obviously, this brother struggled
with the nuances of English.
Now, think about Bible translation.
It involves understanding the nuances
of what was written thousands of years ago
in ancient Hebrew, in Aramaic, and in Greek
and translating those thoughts
into English and hundreds of other languages.
It is an enormous challenge.
But remember that many Bibles
previously used by our brothers
were translated by individuals
who knew that God’s name was in the Bible,
and they refused to put it in the text.
Now, imagine these same individuals
who believed that God
and Jesus are the same person
or that the dead
live on in heaven and hell.
How do you think it affects their translation
of difficult doctrinal passages?
As an example,
the traditional Thai Bible
says at Ecclesiastes 9:10:
“There is no work
nor planning nor knowledge
nor wisdom in ghost city
where you are going.”
At Acts 2:27,
the Chinese Union Version says about Jesus:
“You will not leave my spirit
[or it can be understood as “ghost”]
in the yin world”
—that is, the netherworld.
Now, this actually reflects
what many Chinese people
think happens to the dead.
And it’s why they offer food and objects
that they think people
will need in “the yin world.”
But it’s interesting
that even a word-by-word translation
of the pre-2013 English New World Translation
was confusing in Chinese.
The previous word for “soul”
sounded like “spirit ghost.”
And “Hades”
sounded like a geographical location,
like “Haiti” might sound to us.
So saying, ‘You will not leave
my hún [or soul ghost] in Hades,’
sounded like Jesus’ “ghost”
was stuck in a place called Hades.
The Chinese translators
were the first to receive approval to say:
“You will not leave me in the Grave.”
Straightforward.
This set a pattern.
Almost all languages
following the Chinese used this solution.
Then, in 2013,
the English New World Translation
did the same.
But translating such verses
as ancient Bible writers understood them
has lifted a huge burden
from the shoulders of our brothers.
They used to try
to explain the correct meaning
using a Bible
that distorted the meaning.
But the need for clarity
goes beyond doctrinal issues.
Let’s consider the challenge
of translating verses like Matthew 5:3.
It says there:
“Happy are those conscious
“of their spiritual need,
“since the Kingdom of the heavens
belongs to them.”
The original Greek literally says:
“Happy the poor as to the spirit,”
which makes no sense in English
or even in modern Greek.
The English rendering beautifully expresses
the idea of being aware
of one’s spiritual poverty.
But since a word-for-word translation
of the English or Greek
is often impossible in other languages,
Bible translation teams have submitted
37 questions on this verse alone.
For example, is “happy” better expressed
by “elated,” “jubilant,” or “blessed”?
Can “conscious of” be better expressed
by “recognize,” “thirst for,”
or “hunger for”?
Saying “belongs to them”
or “the Kingdom belongs to them”
sounds like they own the Kingdom.
Is that the idea?
Or is it better to say “meant for them”?
Then the expression “spiritual need”
is a problem in many languages.
Translated literally, it could sound
like the philosophical need in some languages
or in other languages,
like their need for wicked spirits or ghosts.
One African trainer observed:
“In many African languages,
“there is only one vernacular equivalent
“for ‘spiritual,’ ‘wind,’ ‘air,’
‘oxygen,’ ‘gas,’ and ‘spiritism.’”
So a literal translation is confusing
and often gives a completely wrong meaning.
It could sound like,
‘Happy are those who know they need oxygen.’
So translation teams
might test out many different variations
before finalizing such a verse.
Another example
is Ecclesiastes 8:9:
“All of this I have seen,
“and I applied my heart to every work
that has been done under the sun,
during the time that man
has dominated man to his harm.”
Now, we often focus
on the part after the comma.
But in languages where the heart
is simply an organ
of the body that doesn’t think,
saying “applied my heart”
makes no sense at all.
Saying “under the sun”
gives a strange picture
of things happening directly below
where the sun is located at a certain time.
So before even reaching
the main point of the verse,
there are a number
of linguistic stumbling blocks
that the translators have to address.
In some languages,
like Hindi,
this verse might read:
“All of this I have seen,
and I have paid attention
“to all the things happening in the world
“[not under the sun]
“and seen that during this time
“man has only brought problems to man
by ruling over him.”
Now, you can imagine
each project involves a lot of research,
long discussions, and fervent prayer
to ensure an accurate and clear translation.
Now, another issue that arises
has to do with the language registry.
Some think that Bible language should sound,
somehow, loftier or holier
than everyday language.
For centuries, the Catholic Church
kept the Bible in the dead Latin language.
Greek Orthodox clergymen today
still chant the Bible in ancient Greek
—a beautiful language
that hardly anyone understands.
And many are still enamored
by the archaic King James Version.
And this kind of thinking
has affected Bibles in other languages.
For example, a lot of the Bibles in India
use terms that are derived from Sanskrit
—terms that people hardly know.
The previous Maltese, Myanmar,
Twi, and Vietnamese Bibles all use
—among many others—
very difficult-to-understand vocabulary.
So just using simple, everyday language
greatly enhances Bible reading.
For example, previous Thai Bibles
used the literary royal style.
Now, in Thai, pronouns can take many forms
depending on who is speaking
and who is being spoken to.
For example, kings like David
would require one pronoun,
nobles another,
the common people a different one,
God a different one.
There are 17 different ways
to say “I” in Thai,
if you could imagine,
and some of those ways
are never used in everyday speech.
And that’s why one sister wrote and said:
“I like how the Thai New World Translation
“uses pronouns that we use in daily life.
“In Psalm 5, when David
expressed his feelings to Jehovah
“using the pronoun ‘I’ that we use,
“I can now see David as a real person
“and can feel how depressed
David felt at that time.
“I read that chapter with a tear in my eye
“and felt like I was David,
expressing my feelings
and problems to Jehovah.”
All that from using normal pronouns.
The Armenia branch wrote:
“Prior to its release,
readers put lots of effort
“into understanding what they read
“from their archaic Armenian Bibles.
Now they put
that same effort into studying it.”
A Turkish brother said
about the New World Translation in Turkish,
“The apostle Paul, especially,
finally speaks understandable Turkish.”
Now the following video
is going to show how the ASL Bible
has enhanced Bible study
for thousands
of our deaf brothers and sisters.
I would always think:
‘I want to be able to read
the Bible from start to finish too!
I should read the Bible every day.’
And so I decided to do just that.
However, whenever I started,
I would read a bit and eventually stop.
I would try again only to stop.
I could never get far.
It was very difficult to feel moved
or to see Jehovah as a real person
when reading the Bible in English.
Then something very special happened.
It was at a district convention in 2005.
I’ll never forget this.
They announced
that the Christian Greek Scriptures
would be translated
into American Sign Language!
Everyone, including myself, was thrilled.
A few months later,
the Bible book of Matthew
was released on DVD.
I remember the first time
putting the DVD into the player
and watching the signer on the screen.
I was astounded.
I could see the facial expressions,
the emotions,
the signs all coming to life
and helping me to understand
what was being said in the Bible!
I watched it all the way through
again and again and again.
And I would do this every time
until another Bible book was released in ASL.
The Bible presented in my language
helps me to see Jehovah.
I can see his love for me.
I see him counseling me like a father.
He encourages me and cherishes me.
I can see all this,
not when I am reading the Bible in English,
but in sign language.
I always thank Jehovah for this gift.
Her comments help us to see
how Jehovah is fulfilling his word
at Deuteronomy 30:13, 14.
Deuteronomy 30:13, 14:
“Nor is it on the other side of the sea,
“so that you have to say,
“‘Who will cross over
to the other side of the sea
“‘and get it for us,
so that we may hear it and observe it?’
“For the word is very near you,
“in your own mouth
and in your own heart,
so that you may do it.”
Previously, for many brothers
to understand the Bible,
it was like crossing the sea.
It was such an effort in study
and in understanding what the Bible said.
But now, with the New World Translation
in such an understandable style,
it’s penetrating people’s hearts
and enhancing the effect
of God’s Word on their mouth
by making their preaching
of the good news more effective.
Jehovah today is ensuring
that his inspired message
is not bound by language differences.
Now we’re going to briefly consider
the role of the worldwide Bethel family
in this effort to produce
the New World Translation.
In 1989,
the Governing Body established
a world headquarters department
to support
the New World Translation development,
and at that time,
it was available in 11 languages
—in whole or in part.
This chart
shows that the number of languages
will reach 148
by December of this year,
including 8 sign languages.
And you see that the increase is dramatic,
especially since 2005,
because that was the year
when the Governing Body
made Bible translation
a higher priority.
Just in 2016, by the end of the year,
we will have had 21 releases.
Over 500 Bethelites serve
on some 100 Bible translation
or revision teams.
As we saw,
translators carefully study each verse
to make sure that they
get the right understanding
and render it correctly.
And there is
a full-time staff at headquarters
to field their questions.
Over the years,
more than 100,000 questions
have been asked.
In 2015 alone,
8,500 questions were answered.
But besides Bible translators,
outside readers review the text;
others do proofreading,
composition, digital publishing.
The brothers in Thailand
even created a beautiful new font
for their Thai New World Translation
to make it easier to read.
Over the years,
MEPS programming has developed
a specialized computer system
for Bible translation.
The U.S. and Japan printeries
have worked two and three shifts
to make sure that release dates were met,
including that of the English revision.
Bindery workers, for example,
with this Thai Bible,
have to hand-feed each copy of the Bible
because of the extra pages needed
to make the font big enough to be legible.
This Bible is over 2,300 pages.
It’s much bigger
than our English New World Translation.
But the brothers in Japan
willingly and happily do that
for their Asian brothers.
Each Bible requires
the united effort of hundreds.
Each one has a story
involving training, long hours,
problem solving, and great sacrifices.
For example,
an experienced translator and father of ten
was in his 60’s
when he was asked to work on
the translation in his language.
He commuted two hours a day for years
to work on that project.
Two elderly couples moved
from their comfortable homes
in Central Europe
to work and live on,
basically, a construction site
for years in barracks
until their project was finished.
A brother in the final stages
of Parkinson’s disease
checked every verse for accuracy.
These are just a few of the hundreds
of examples we could mention.
Like the apostle Paul languishing in prison,
many of us are now limited
in what we can personally accomplish
in Jehovah’s service,
but our worldwide Bethel family
can feel great satisfaction
to see God’s Word
and publications based on it
being made freely available
throughout the earth.
Jehovah is the one
who confused the languages,
but he foretold that his message
would not be bound by languages.
He is causing it
to penetrate language barriers.
A Hindi brother
wrote about the recent release:
“My wife and I just read
the book of Proverbs.
“It is very, very encouraging
to hear Jehovah’s voice
“in a tongue that touches our hearts.
“I previously felt as if the Bible
was covered over by a net.
“Though we were able to read it,
we could not see everything clearly.
Now I feel as if everything
is happening right before my eyes.”
A Tamil reader said,
“Thank you
for completely changing our opinion
“that the Bible
can never be understood and,
in fact, for making it
so easily understandable.”
A Rwandan Witness said:
“I now understand the feelings of Jehovah
“and of persons mentioned in the Bible.
“Jehovah now speaks Kinyarwanda,
and it seems
that the Hebrews were Rwandans.”
Such comments make all the hard work
of the translators worthwhile.
Now let’s read Philippians 2:13.
Philippians 2:13 says:
“For God is the one who for the sake
of his good pleasure energizes you,
giving you both the desire
and the power to act.”
This reminds us of Paul’s words
in Hebrews 4:12,
where it said that “the word of God
is alive and [energetic or] exerts power.”
But the difference here in Philippians
is that God himself
is the subject of the sentence.
He is the One who exerts power.
He is the One that provides the energy
and the motivation to his people.
And there is no doubt
that Jehovah is the one who energized
and moved his anointed servants
to embark on this campaign
of Bible translation and distribution.
He has also energized members
of the great crowd to support that work.
And what has been the result?
First, millions of Jehovah’s people
daily use a Bible that honors his name.
Second, God’s people have been given
the energy and motivation
to distribute Bibles and Bible literature
so that even the poor
are hearing the good news
in harmony with Matthew 11:5.
And third,
Jehovah is breaking the language barrier
so that his people
are enjoying unprecedented clarity
in their Bible study.
And we’re especially grateful
to have all the new Bibles and revisions
based on the simple, clear 2013 revision.
It is exciting to see how Jehovah
is already using the New World Translation
to communicate his will
to millions of his sheep
in over 140 languages.
The result of this great effort
has been enhanced spirituality,
unity of thought as an organization,
and a powerful tool to carry on
the greatest preaching campaign in history.
We can’t help but echo
the words of Psalm 118:23:
“This has come from Jehovah;
it is wonderful in our eyes.”
We now look forward to seeing
how Jehovah will use this translation
to sanctify his great name
before all of earth’s population.
Yes, we’re grateful to Jehovah
for the New World Translation
—a translation
that strengthens our conviction
that the power of his Word
can never be bound.