‎I promised Akil I’d go out
in service with him after school.
‎Hey, we’re just waiting in the car.
‎And I kept my word,
‎but my head just wasn’t in it.
‎Akil could tell, so he tried
to see if everything was OK.
‎Honestly, at the time,
‎I would have rather been playing
video games,
‎but I couldn’t tell him that.
‎I mean,
he’s a pioneer, a ministerial servant.
‎He wouldn’t understand.
‎Later that week,
‎Akil invited me
to go mountain biking with some friends.
‎It was actually really fun.
‎. . . and your croissant.
‎Great, thanks.
‎Please let me know
if there’s anything else, OK?
‎All right. Thanks.
‎So, Danny,
you’re obviously good at biking.
‎What else do you like to do for fun?
‎OK, so I have this game and it’s called . . .
‎Soon I was showing him my video games.
‎And surprisingly,
he liked video games too.
‎But he said he chose to be selective.
‎He began to describe
the gladiators in ancient Rome.
‎People would come from all over
‎to watch them fight to the death.
‎And while the spectators
weren’t in any physical danger,
‎the real danger came over time.
‎Repeatedly watching
the bloodshed and the killing,
‎it was dulling their senses,
and they wanted more of it.
‎This was a big test
for the Christians who lived back then.
‎Akil helped me to reason on the scripture
‎at Romans 12:9:
‎“Abhor what is wicked;
cling to what is good.”
‎So, Danny,
‎the games may have changed over time,
‎but the violence is still the same.
‎I like video games,
‎but I avoid the ones
that promote what Jehovah hates.
‎Jehovah’s people can still have fun.
‎And, yeah,
we can even play video games.
‎I just want to make wise choices.
‎I want to show Jehovah
that I hate wickedness
‎and make his heart glad.