Hello, and welcome to this month’s broadcast!
With me I have a good friend
as my cohost, Leon Weaver.
Leon, what do we have
to look forward to this time?
Thanks, Brother Lösch.
We’ll see a young brother who must choose
between his loyalty to Jehovah
or to a close friend.
Which will he choose?
Then we’ll hear the story of Rafika Morris,
a young woman
who desperately fought for racial equality
but eventually discovers
the real path to peace.
And we’ll also enjoy a new music video
that beautifully highlights the importance
of putting our confidence in Jehovah.
We have much to look forward to
in this March 2018 edition
of JW Broadcasting!
The theme for this month is
“In Whom Do You Trust?”
Do you trust me?
I hope so.
All of us want to be trusted.
Trust is a basic element of everyday life.
To trust others is a normal reaction.
Many of us have traveled on a train or a bus.
Did we worry whether
the conductor or driver
would bring us safely to our destination?
Normally, we do not worry.
We trust an airplane captain
to take us safely to our destination.
We trust that when we enter an elevator,
it will not crash at the bottom of the shaft,
but safely take us to the desired floor.
When we marry, we trust that
our partner will remain faithful.
In many situations in life we need trust.
What is trust?
Trust is the “firm belief in the reliability,
truth, or ability of someone or something.”
Webster’s dictionary says
that it is “confidence”;
a “reliance [or] resting
of the mind on the integrity,
“veracity, justice, friendship,
or other sound principle, of another person.”
Trust is related to confidence,
belief, faith, and assurance.
Experiments conducted
by Professor Dr. Michael Kosfeld,
a professor at a university
in Frankfurt, Germany,
led him to the conclusion that trust
is “a biologically-based part
of human nature.”
Kosfeld discovered that when
there is interaction between two people,
the human brain releases
a hormone that stimulates trust.
“It is, in fact,
one of the distinguishing features
of the human species,” Kosfeld states.
In everyday life, how discouraged
some are if they are not trusted.
The phrase “Don’t you trust me?”
is frequently heard with an undertone
of sadness or complaint.
Sometimes children or teenagers
ask their parents
“Don’t you trust me?” when the parents
place some restrictions on them,
perhaps in connection
with leisure-time activities.
Parents do that because they
love you young ones
and want to prevent any spiritual
or physical harm befalling you.
If you cooperate, you will see that parents
will gradually trust you ever more
and grant more liberty to you.
You can prove to them
that you are trustworthy.
In the world,
many people are not trustworthy.
Since we are living in the time of the end
and the demons are desperate
and have influenced many people,
we have to admit that
trusting in everybody is not wise.
Many trusted in religion
and were disappointed.
Others trusted in governments
or the United Nations,
but they were disappointed.
They trusted political leaders
that made all kinds of promises
but did not keep all of them.
Some politicians were
even exposed as being liars.
Proverbs 14:15 says:
“The naive person believes every word,
but the shrewd one ponders each step.”
If somebody, even in the truth,
promises us big monetary returns
if we give him money
for his planned investment,
we need to be careful
and not believe every word.
Some that spent their money
were in for a disappointment
when they learned that everything was lost.
We also should not trust everything we read
in newspapers or see on television.
There is another thing
we should not trust in—riches.
Psalm 49:6 speaks
about “those who are trusting in their wealth
and who boast about their great riches.”
Trusting in riches
often leads to disappointment.
“The one trusting in his riches will fall,”
says Proverbs 11:28.
It is not wrong to be rich;
just do not trust in riches.
Riches are a risk factor.
Many people today are dishonest and cheat.
Some business owners have installed
cameras at the workplace,
since they do not trust their employees
to put in a full day of work.
They know that some would play
video games during work hours.
But Jehovah created us
with the inclination to trust.
We can especially trust
our spiritual brothers.
True, once in a while
such trust is misplaced.
A few commit serious sins
and have to be disfellowshipped.
But that is rare.
Jehovah himself is
the best example of trusting in others.
He trusted the Logos to faithfully cooperate
with him as the “master worker”
in creating the universe,
the earth, and all the living things
on earth, including mankind.
What tremendous trust Jehovah showed
in Jesus when He sent him to the earth.
Jehovah trusted that
Jesus would remain faithful
and redeem mankind
so that His will and purpose with mankind
and the earth could be accomplished.
Jehovah trusted him so much
that he arranged for prophecies
to be written that foretold
that he would die faithfully.
This trust on the part of Jehovah
was not a risk.
It was based on the collaboration
between the two for aeons of time.
Think of the prophecy at Psalm 16:10:
“For you will not leave me in the Grave.”
Jesus had free will.
This means that theoretically
he could have sinned.
If he could not have sinned,
Satan probably would not have tried
three times to tempt Jesus to sin.
If Jesus could not have sinned,
why would he be so heavily distressed
in the garden of Gethsemane
that he was sweating blood?
Why send an angel
to comfort and strengthen him
if he could not sin or fail anyway?
No question that Jesus
felt the unfathomable load
on his shoulders to remain faithful,
since not only the salvation
of mankind depended on him
but also the vindication
of Jehovah’s sovereignty.
He did not want to disappoint Jehovah.
Jesus used his own free will
and was determined to stay loyal.
How glad we are that he did!
On the other hand,
Jesus also trusted Jehovah completely.
He trusted Jehovah that he would
resurrect him if he would die faithfully.
Actually, Jesus was publicly known
to trust in Jehovah.
People that passed by when he was
on the torture stake were saying:
“He has put his trust in God;
“let Him now rescue him if He wants him,
for he said, ‘I am God’s Son.’”
Another example of trust was Abraham.
When God told him
to kill his beloved son Isaac,
Abraham was willing to do so.
He trusted that Jehovah could resurrect him.
Hebrews 11:19 says:
“He reasoned that God was able to raise
him up even from the dead,
and he did receive him from there
in an illustrative way.”
First Corinthians 13:7 says that
love “believes all things.”
Love trusts that prophecies will come true.
It also believes what our brothers tell us.
It also helps to grant others
the benefit of the doubt
if a matter could be interpreted
in different ways.
Yes, trusting others
is an expression of love.
If you love somebody, you only assume
and think the best of him.
Another example of trust
in Jehovah was Moses.
He led the nation of Israel
out of Egypt into the desert
—a nation upwards of three million people.
And they had flocks
of cattle and sheep with them.
When he left Egypt,
did he know how to provide
these great crowds with water in the desert?
Did he know what they would be eating
after the initial foodstuffs
that they took out of Egypt ran out?
Did he know in advance that Jehovah
would miraculously provide the manna?
It doesn’t seem so.
But he trusted that Jehovah
would take care of the people.
The three friends of Daniel
were another fine example of trust.
They did not bow and worship
in front of an idol
that King Nebuchadnezzar had set up.
They were told they would be thrown
into a fiery furnace if they disobeyed.
They remained firm
and were protected by an angel,
so that the fire did not do any harm to them.
After that
“Nebuchadnezzar then declared:
“‘Praised be the God of Shadrach,
Meshach, and Abednego,
“‘who sent his angel
and rescued his servants.
“‘They trusted in him and went against
the command of the king
“‘and were willing to die rather than serve
or worship any god except their own God.’”
As we are getting ever closer
to the great tribulation,
we might be confronted with scary challenges
and tests related to nationalism.
Will we keep trusting Jehovah?
We trust we will.
Jehovah will miraculously save his
people throughout the great tribulation
and arrange for their survival.
Today, the faithful slave is put in charge
of providing spiritual food for God’s people,
who number into the millions.
The slave also shows
complete trust in Jehovah
that he will guide them with his holy spirit.
What makes it possible
for the “faithful and discreet slave”
to provide precious spiritual food?
“I will give you insight and instruct you
in the way you should go,”
says Jehovah at Psalm 32:8.
Today, Jehovah provides direction
to the slave through Jesus.
Jesus, in turn,
provides direction for his people
through “the faithful and discreet slave.”
We can therefore have full confidence
in the Scriptural insight,
understanding, and guidance.
Satan tries to sow mistrust.
Under Communist dictatorship in Romania,
secret police officers
forced a responsible brother
to walk with them
on a heavily frequented street
hoping that other brothers would see this
and wrongly conclude that this brother
works with the secret police.
Did the scheme work out?
No, it failed.
Brothers did see him but kept trusting him.
We learn that we should not quickly
lose trust in our brothers.
Satan also has the scheme
to spread rumors about faithful brothers,
including the faithful slave.
The method of spreading rumors is not new.
When Jesus was resurrected
and the tomb was empty,
the soldiers who reported it
were told to spread the rumor
that the disciples came
and stole the body at night.
Matthew 28:15 relates:
“So they took the silver pieces
and did as they were instructed,
and this story has been spread abroad
among the Jews up to this very day.”
Another rumor in the first century
was that Christians
were responsible for the great fire of Rome.
Could such an accusation be true?
Historians say that it was Nero,
the emperor, who set fire to the city.
Today, rumors are occasionally being spread
in electronic form about the faithful slave.
This has caused some concern
on the part of some brothers,
especially when the reports
are commenting on court cases
where some in the organization were accused.
Sometimes reference is made to certain quotes
and then readers think,
‘How can a quote be a rumor?’
A quote can be taken out of context.
Critical reports often
give only part of a matter
and leave out other aspects.
Often, such rumors play on the emotions.
Ask yourself: ‘Am I prone to believe rumors?
‘And even if I am, should I spread it
‘and undermine the trust
that others have in the slave
or in representatives of the branch office?’
Avoid sensationalism
by not saying something like
“Can you believe what I heard
about this matter or that matter
or this person or that person?”
referring to a statement
that may have appeared
on Facebook, YouTube, or Twitter.
The spread of rumors is like wildfire
that is hard to control.
It spreads distrust
and can undermine someone’s faith.
This is not to say that the slave is perfect
and never makes mistakes.
But Jehovah and Jesus
trust the imperfect slave
who cares for things
to the best of his ability
and with the best of motives.
Shouldn’t we then trust
the imperfect slave as well?
To appreciate the extent of Jehovah
and Jesus’ trust in the faithful slave,
reflect on what he has promised its members.
He has promised them
immortality and incorruption.
Soon, just before Armageddon,
the remaining members of the slave
will be taken to heaven.
Since 1919 of our Common Era,
the slave has been put in charge
of some belongings of Christ.
According to Matthew 24:47,
when the anointed are taken to heaven,
Jesus will at that point entrust
“all his belongings” to them.
Does this not reveal immense trust?
Revelation 4:4 describes
these resurrected anointed
as corulers with Christ.
Revelation 22:5 says they will rule,
not only for a thousand years
but “forever and ever.”
What immense trust
Jesus shows toward them!
Since Jehovah God and Jesus Christ
completely trust
“the faithful and discreet slave,”
should we not do the same?
Many servants of Jehovah in the past
showed trust in Jehovah
when confronted with obstacles or opposition.
We can trust that Jehovah will not let us
be tested beyond what we can bear
but will provide a “way out”
so we can remain faithful under trials.
So whom do you trust?
You fully trust in Jehovah,
Jesus, and the faithful slave.
To a reasonable degree, you also trust all
your fellow brothers and sisters.
The writer of Psalm 119:42
mentioned something else we need to trust in
—God’s Word.
He wrote:
“For I put my trust in your word.”
The prophecies in God’s Word
have always come true at the proper time.
Based on that, we can fully trust that
the remaining prophecies
pointing to the survival
of the great tribulation
and to the Paradise to follow
will also come true,
without the slightest possibility of failure.
Of course, we should trust
not only Jehovah, Jesus,
the faithful slave, and the Bible
but also our fellow brothers.
The apostle Paul is a fine example of this.
He wrote to Philemon
asking him to kindly receive back
the runaway slave Onesimus
who had become a brother.
Paul wrote at Philemon 21:
“I am confident that you will comply,
so I am writing you, knowing that you
will do even more than what I say.”
When we speak of trust,
we sometimes think of a little child
walking hand in hand with his father.
The child does not question
where the father will take him.
The child trusts the father.
All throughout the last days,
true Christians have faced hostility
of so many in the world.
How strengthening Jehovah’s promise is
in view of the impending attack
by Satan’s hordes!
When they attack, Jehovah’s people
will seem as defenseless.
But we do not need to quake with fear.
We trust that Jehovah, Jesus, and the angels
will fight to deliver us.
We will not shrink back in fear.
At Hebrews 10:39, Paul wrote:
“Now we are not the sort
who shrink back to destruction,
but the sort who have faith
for the preserving of our lives.”
Today and after Armageddon, all can say,
according to Psalm 26:1 and 52:8:
“I have trusted [in Jehovah]
without wavering.”
“My trust is in God’s loyal love,
forever and ever.”
Therefore, keep trusting in Jehovah
and those who are proving loyal to him.
Back to you, Leon.
Thank you, Brother Lösch.
In line with that,
we all want
good friends
we can trust
—the type
mentioned at Proverbs 18:24,
where it says:
“There is a friend
who sticks closer than a brother.”
But at times,
we may find that a close friend
needs spiritual help.
Do we fear losing
that friendship if we speak up?
What does Jehovah want us to do?
In the following dramatization,
the young man Danny
faces these same questions.
I had a secret.
Only it wasn’t mine to tell.
It was my best friend’s, Julian.
This was not the Julian I knew.
At the end of the meeting,
Brother Max wanted to know
if I was OK.
I shrugged it off.
I just didn’t know
who to talk to at that point.
A few years ago,
when my parents
stopped attending meetings,
Julian was there for me.
I didn’t want to lose my friend.
But did I really know him?
I decided to ask Julian
about the pictures he posted.
I told him it wasn’t right.
He needed to talk to the elders.
Then he got really defensive about it.
I knew I did the right thing.
When was I supposed
to take care of this bill?
I’ve been telling you
for the past month!
I just needed someone to talk to.
When did you tell me?
I’ve been working
for the past couple of weeks.
Well, as if I don’t work?
Oh! Now you’re going
to blame everything on me.
Brother Max wanted to know
how I was really doing.
He could tell something was wrong.
So I opened up.
I told him everything.
I didn’t want to get my friend in trouble.
Max understood.
He asked me to read James 5:14, 15:
“Is there anyone sick among you?
“Let him call
the elders of the congregation to him,
“and let them pray over him,
“applying oil to him
in the name of Jehovah.
“And the prayer of faith
“will make the sick one well,
and Jehovah will raise him up.”
Max showed me that the elders
can encourage and strengthen
a spiritually weak person.
Covering up a friend’s wrongdoing
prevents him from getting
the spiritual help he needs.
All this time,
I was focused on Julian and his deception,
and I didn’t speak up.
I’m glad I was honest with Brother Max.
The elders are like our spiritual doctors,
and even more, they’re our friends.
They want to help us.
Julian might receive discipline,
but that’s an expression of Jehovah’s love.
It could save his spiritual life.
Julian got the spiritual help he needed.
And I kept my best friend.
Did you notice how our young brother
put trust in the Bible and acted accordingly?
How can we do the same?
Brother Ron Curzan’s morning worship
comments share some thoughts
on specific ways we can continue
to make spiritual adjustments
as we encounter
a variety of life’s challenges.
These were very practical comments.
And they all tie in well
with what the apostle Paul was trying to tell
those in the Ephesian congregation
about examining themselves.
The same way we have to do today
—examining ourselves
so that we please Jehovah.
If you’d like,
please open up to Ephesians chapter 5,
and we’ll read verse 10,
which is our theme scripture.
Ephesians 5:10, it says:
“Keep on making sure
of what is acceptable to the Lord.”
And then it goes on in verse 11:
“And stop sharing in the unfruitful works
that belong to the darkness;
rather, expose them for what they are.”
So it’s very clear to us,
in this chapter of Ephesians chapter 5,
that there are things
that Jehovah views as acceptable
and things he views as unacceptable.
Jehovah’s standard of what is unacceptable
is outlined in quite a few
of the verses in chapter 5 here.
If you would just scan
through verses 3, 4, and 5,
we’ll see that unwholesome talk about sex,
shameful conduct, obscene jesting
—and then verse 18, drunkenness—
well, these are things
that will bar us from God’s Kingdom.
When you think
about entertainment today,
it’s nearly impossible
to try to find something
that is acceptable to Jehovah
that does not have
immoral sex, pornography,
spiritism, and violence.
Satan has thoroughly saturated
all forms of the media.
So thoroughly,
that it’s in our literature,
it’s in movies,
it’s in electronic games,
and everything that we
can think of Satan has infiltrated.
Yes, he knows that Jehovah
hates these things,
and he doesn’t mind if part of our heart
hates these things
as long as part of our heart
loves these things.
So we do well to ask ourselves:
‘Does the entertainment that I choose help me
‘in my being acceptable to Jehovah?
‘Does it help me to have the qualities
‘that Jehovah endears in me,
and will he draw closer to me?’
Well, the spirit of the world
reflects rebellion of the Bible,
which outlines
Jehovah’s qualities and his standards.
We want to show respect for the Bible,
which teaches us
to love what Jehovah loves
and hate what he hates.
And what will help us to do this
and resist the spirit of the world
and draw closer to Jehovah
and be acceptable to him?
Let’s notice verse 17,
chapter 5 and verse 17, it says:
“On this account stop being unreasonable,
but keep perceiving
what the will of Jehovah is.”
We need to constantly think:
‘What would Jehovah want me to do?’
Well, verse 1 and verse 2
help us to appreciate this, it says:
“Become imitators of God,
as beloved children,
“and go on walking in love,
just as the Christ also loved us
“and [he] gave himself [up]
for us as an offering
and a sacrifice,
a sweet fragrance to God.”
So, bottom line,
we need to imitate Jehovah and Jesus.
Our sacrifices need to be
acceptable to Jehovah
as was Jesus’.
What made Jesus so pleasing?
Well, he did everything
the way Jehovah wanted him to do.
In fact, he said something
that we want to say one day:
“I always do the things pleasing to him.”
And one day in perfection,
we will be able to say that.
Jesus was pleasing
in his word, in his deed, in his actions.
Well, how can we imitate Jesus
and thus imitate Jehovah?
Well, let’s briefly discuss three ways.
First: Pray for God’s holy spirit.
When confronted with trials,
what did Jesus do?
He did not rely on himself;
he petitioned Jehovah for help.
So if we’re struggling with a temptation
—a certain fleshly weakness—
it’s vital that we do the same.
We can also talk to the elders
—our loving shepherds—
who will pray with us,
and they will definitely help us
to remain faithful
with words of encouragement.
Number two: Obey Jehovah completely.
Jesus always did things
that were pleasing to his Father.
Luke 22:42 says:
“Let, not my will, but yours take place.”
Remember,
there is no substitute for obedience.
We cannot be acceptable without obedience.
Number three: Know the Scriptures well.
Jesus used God’s Word as his authority.
His whole life revolved around knowing
and obeying and encouraging others
about God’s laws.
We all have busy schedules.
We have work to do
—busy in the congregation.
It’s more than just trying to find time
to dig deep into God’s Word;
we must make the time.
So, what do our schedules tell us
about our love for Jehovah?
our love for his Word?
Do we read the Bible daily?
And if we do,
how much time do we take
to let it sink into our mind
and our heart and to meditate?
Are we content with just looking
at the basics
—the surface—
or digging deeper and deeper
below the surface?
It’s vital that we train
our minds and our hearts,
but it takes time
and it takes effort,
just as a marathon runner
must devote much time and effort
to his training to run a race.
In fact, as we know,
Christians are likened
to running a race,
and it’s a race for life.
Let’s see
what the apostle Paul had to tell us.
If we go over to 1 Corinthians,
1 Corinthians chapter 9,
a scripture we know very well,
and we’ll start in verse 24.
And there are a few key elements
that we would like to extract
as we’re reading these verses.
Here Paul said:
“Do you not know
that the runners in a race all run,
“but only one receives the prize?
“Run in such a way that you may win it.
“Now everyone competing in a contest
“exercises self-control in all things
[there’s a key].
“Of course, they do it
to receive a crown that can perish,
“but we, one that does not perish.
“Therefore, the way
I am running is not aimlessly;
“the way I am aiming my blows
“is so as not to be striking the air;
“but I pummel my body
“[and the footnote says,
“punish; strictly discipline”]
“and lead it as a slave,
so that after I have preached to others,
“I myself should not become disapproved
[or the footnote says, “disqualified”]
somehow.”
So we definitely want to have
self-control like a runner.
We need to say no to Satan’s world
and yes to things
that are acceptable to Jehovah.
And we definitely want
to make sure that we are acceptable
and never to be disapproved.
Perhaps we can illustrate this.
In the 1994 New York City Marathon,
there was a young man named German Silva,
and he ran an outstanding race.
In fact, there was only half a mile
to the finish line in Central Park,
and somehow he got distracted.
He took the wrong path.
Did he lose the race?
Well, the lead runner took over.
Well, he got redirected;
he went back on the path;
he began to run faster and faster.
He passed up the lead runner,
and he won the New York City Marathon
by two seconds.
What does this tell us?
It tells us that sometimes
we can lose our focus, we can be sidetracked,
or we could get involved
in unacceptable conduct.
But allow God’s Word
and loving shepherds to readjust our course.
Never give up.
Just a few years later, after that
—1997—
German began running again
in a New York City Marathon.
He thought he had this one all in the bag;
he thought he was going to win this race.
But he started to run slower.
He began to—
He dehydrated.
Instead of taking
just a few seconds to hydrate,
he skipped that.
He thought he could do it.
Well, what could this tell us?
Well, we cannot afford to take shortcuts.
We need to have
a regular intake of spiritual food
to keep pace with Jehovah’s organization.
We do this
by what the commenters told us today,
that is, a regular intake
of God’s Word and meditation.
As we run the Christian course
—the race for life—
remember, it’s not the speed,
it’s the direction
—that’s what matters the most.
And may we always run in such a way
that is acceptable to Jehovah.
As Brother Curzan mentioned,
certainly a regular intake of God’s Word
can have a dramatic effect on our lives.
Take the example of Rafika Morris.
Her life led her on a search
for ways to achieve racial harmony
through human means.
But after years of frustration
and disappointments,
how would studying the Bible
affect her search for answers?
Growing up in the South
during the time of segregation
—blacks and whites—
we couldn’t mix.
And not only that, they had signs
to keep you knowing
where you were supposed to go.
I couldn’t understand
why we couldn’t get along.
Fifty cents.
Yes, Sir.
Thank you, Sir.
Grandma, he’s just a boy.
Why are you saying “Sir”?
Be quiet.
I want you to know your place.
I told her after we got back on the truck:
“You know what?
I’ll never hold my head down!”
My grandmother
knew I had a love for the Bible
because I would
always read the Bible as a kid.
But I couldn’t understand it.
I used to pray,
“What makes us so different?”
You know,
“Why can’t we live together?”
I met a group,
and this group was like
what I really wanted to be in.
They were about politics.
They said, “We’re fighting injustice.”
And when they said
that word “injustice,” it was like,
‘Yeah, this is what I want to be in, right?
‘To be part of something that can change
and make people united, right?’
That was my goal.
We started protesting about police brutality,
and I think that’s what a lot of people,
you know,
were focusing on.
I liked some of the things
that they were doing,
but they trained us every,
every day in military training.
We learned how to use weapons
and stuff like that.
And so I’m thinking:
‘This is not what I want to be in.
This is not what I joined.’
So I started going back to God again
—to reading the Bible—
because it was like
I’m not changing anything.
The Bible that I was reading
was the King James Version.
So I was reading it, reading it, reading it,
but I couldn’t understand it.
We went to Jamaica,
and we saw this Bible,
the New World Translation.
And I started reading it,
and it made so much sense!
And I could understand it,
and it wasn’t “thee” and “thou.”
I was like, ‘Wow!’
You know, like,
‘This is the one I want to get.’
One day, two women knocked on the door.
I didn’t know they were Jehovah’s Witnesses.
All I could see was that Bible.
And I said,
“Where did you get that Bible from?”
And they said,
“OK, we’ll bring you one.”
And they did.
So they brought me the Bible,
but I didn’t know I was going to have
a Bible study that came along with it.
The first time I went
to a convention of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
it was like ten thousand people.
When I went in there and I saw
all these different faces
and different colors,
it was like Jehovah showing me:
“Hey, Rafika, remember you were asking me
“about all different people
getting together and being one?
See, I’m not partial;
they do get along; we are unified.”
And it just made me feel so good inside.
Yes!
This is the organization
that I want to be in.
I just see people as people, you know,
and I can preach
and be friends with anybody.
Now that I know
what the Bible really teaches,
I have a wonderful life
because I know
that only God and his government
can bring about peace.
Just like how Jehovah
unified everybody,
I want everybody
to be unified
and come to know Jehovah,
just like I know him.
Jehovah answered my prayer.
While Rafika faced unique challenges
early in her spiritual life,
she learned to trust in Jehovah.
Trust is also needed
if we choose to extend ourselves
in a new form of Kingdom service.
This is especially true
of those who have had the privilege
to attend the School
for Kingdom Evangelizers.
Their personal experiences confirm this.
I have an illness
that affects my level of energy,
so I didn’t feel that I could accept
just any kind of assignment.
Since the end of this system is near,
I want to do whatever I can
that Jehovah wants down to the very end.
So I applied.
Before attending SKE,
when I received my invitation,
all of a sudden I had challenges
or worries about myself.
I felt unworthy, even unqualified.
Being a single sister,
going into the class with so many couples,
I thought I would be out of place.
I used all my abilities.
I felt like my head was swelling up.
Even so, I felt
that I was really being refined
and ended each day feeling fulfilled.
Something that I
really enjoyed about SKE
was Friday afternoons.
That’s when we had a talk
from one of the Governing Body members.
That was special.
During the eight weeks of school,
such an emphasis was placed
on serving where the need is greater.
So this way of thinking
became more important to us.
After eight weeks of attending the school,
you are even ready to be sent to the moon.
When I was told
that my next assignment
would be in Mesa, Arizona,
I thought, ‘Where is that?’
And then I thought,
‘Oh, no, scorpions!’
And then I thought, ‘OK,
this is where Jehovah thinks
I should be, so I’m ready to go.’
One of the challenges in my new assignment
was finding suitable accommodations.
There was a couple in the congregation
who had two rooms that they rented
in the back of their property,
but it needed some renovations.
So the brothers very quickly came together,
helped sort it out,
and even built an extra
little kitchenette lounge.
So now we have a beautiful little home
to go back to after a long,
hot day in the ministry.
I always thought that I’d do much better
in the cold than I would in the heat.
So the brothers and sisters
were very helpful
in making sure that I stayed hydrated,
making sure I knew
how to handle myself in the heat,
giving me pointers on things to carry,
and they made sure that I had
an extra-large water bottle with me.
We really felt supported by the congregation
because they found us an apartment.
This meant that we could concentrate
on our ministry.
One of the things that really helped me
was an experienced brother
who gave an encouraging comment
about whether my health
would permit me to attend the school.
He said, “If she can pioneer,
then it’s also possible for her
to attend the school.”
The education that we received at SKE
especially helped us with our qualities,
our personality
—putting on the new personality.
That really will help us
not only now in our assignment
but right through into the new world.
I think there are many
who could meet the qualifications
with just a little more effort.
Please know that there is
a wonderful education program,
and we were able
to experience it in our 60’s.
We could get through it.
So if others are thinking of applying,
I want to tell them
that we were able to do it,
and by all means,
I want them to taste
the same joy that we experienced.
You could be nervous
and have performance anxiety
and worry about,
‘How will I handle answering,
‘and how about all
of the student assignments
and the tests?’
—worries like that.
But for my own part,
it was two months
with an incredible amount of joy.
And you have to focus on that.
It is a gift
—it is a wonderful gift from Jehovah.
I wasn’t sure if I was going
to put in the application
because I thought maybe
I wanted to do it as a couple
rather than as a single person.
But I prayed to Jehovah about it,
and I put my application in.
I wouldn’t be experiencing the happiness
that I have now if I had waited.
So I’m happy
that I just put my application in
and let Jehovah do the rest.
And now, sometimes I’m driving
down the freeway, and I think:
‘Wow, Jehovah, I am so happy!
Thank you!’
These experiences remind me
of Colossians 3:23, 24 which reads:
“Whatever you are doing,
“work at it whole-souled as for Jehovah,
“and not for men,
for you know that it is from Jehovah
“you will receive
the inheritance as a reward.
Slave for the Master, Christ.”
Certainly, these brothers
and sisters are doing just that.
If you personally find yourself in a position
to reach out for a privilege,
such as attending this school
or moving to where the need is great,
give it consideration.
Now we travel to Costa Rica,
where we find our brothers
and sisters relying on Jehovah
as they prepare for a very special assembly.
Why was trust in Jehovah
essential for this project?
First, we asked the branch for permission.
Once they gave us approval,
we began to make preparations
for the assembly,
though we had absolutely nothing.
So one brother lent us a property
for the assembly site.
Our brothers have brought
many different skills to the project.
There are metalworkers ,
cabinetmakers, and bricklayers.
Many brothers
have given of their resources
and used their abilities
so that this project could go ahead.
This has really made us stand out here.
People were asking each other:
“What is happening here?”
and “Who paid for all of this?”
They say people are surprised
at how many workers are coming to help.
And I wonder,
‘If this is getting attention now,
what will the assembly be like?’
A comfortable, practical,
and secure Assembly Hall
was constructed using materials
acquired locally.
Expectations grew
as the special day drew closer,
and when it finally arrived,
those in attendance
experienced something truly moving.
With Jehovah’s help,
many interested ones,
along with our brothers and sisters,
have come here today
to celebrate our first assembly
in the Bribri language.
Friends, this is wonderful!
When the program started in Bribri, I cried.
I’m so happy
to have participated in the assembly,
especially because it’s in my own language.
It’s what we wanted.
We hope it continues just like this.
We walked a long way to invite these people,
and to see them here,
it makes me very happy.
The information presented
in the local language
touched many hearts.
This was truly a historic event
for our indigenous brothers in Costa Rica.
Jehovah has made it possible
for more people in this isolated region
to enjoy his spiritual blessing.
Did you note why trust in Jehovah
was so essential for this project?
At the start the brothers had nothing.
But they trusted
that Jehovah would assist them,
and he did through donated land,
materials, and willing volunteers.
Yes, we can truly put
our confidence in Jehovah
as he guides us
through this system of things.
Such trust in Jehovah
is highlighted
in this month’s music video entitled
Confident in You.
Like a tree planted in the ground,
Your words have sunk deep down
Into my heart and soothed my mind
with gentle thoughts of peace.
’Cause no matter what may come,
With this wisdom from above,
I always have these truths
to keep reminding me to
Go on; don’t be afraid.
Hold on to what Jehovah says.
Through all the storms, your words have
Given me strength to endure.
And every day I am more
confident in you.
When this world tries to pull me down,
To give up on what I’ve found,
I turn to you and know that you
are always there.
It takes time to meditate—
Get the words from off the page
And in my heart so they can help
and guide me to
Go on; don’t be afraid.
Hold on to what Jehovah says.
Look beyond any adversity.
Focus on the things that I can’t see.
Through all the storms, your words have
Given me strength to endure.
And every day I am more
confident in you—
In you.
Go on; don’t be afraid.
Hold on to what Jehovah says.
Look beyond any adversity.
Focus on the things that I can’t see.
Through all the storms, your words have
Given me strength to endure.
And every day I am more
confident in you.
This month we have seen
how trusting in Jehovah
and his guidance
can assist us in a variety of ways:
addressing issues with a close friend,
our choices in entertainment,
and even coping with a world
filled with social injustice.
Certainly, Jehovah
is someone in whom we can trust!
But we have one last treat
for you before we end our program.
We’ll briefly travel to Cádiz, Spain.
Cádiz is considered to be one
of the oldest cities in Western Europe
and was founded by the Phoenicians.
It is situated on a narrow slice
of land surrounded by the sea.
Cádiz has a wealth of vistas
and well-preserved historical landmarks.
On the outskirts
lies Puerto de Santa María,
where an English-speaking
congregation meets.
This congregation is made up mainly
of brothers and sisters
serving as need-greaters.
They have come from other parts
of Spain as well as distant lands,
such as Australia, Britain,
Canada, and the United States.
Cádiz has a high rate of unemployment,
so finding work is not easy.
One couple travels nearly 300 miles
(or 483 km)
every Thursday to their territory,
and on Monday morning they make
the trip back to where they live and work.
In spite of these financial challenges,
many are still serving
as construction volunteers,
remote Bethel workers, and pioneers.
Our brothers and sisters
in Puerto de Santa María
are thrilled to send their love
and greetings to you all.
This is JW Broadcasting
from the world headquarters
of Jehovah’s Witnesses.