‎Welcome, brothers and sisters,
to JW Broadcasting!
‎In this edition,
‎we’ll glorify Jehovah’s name
in our discussions and segments.
‎For example:
‎How was the discovery
of this ancient manuscript
‎a tremendous help
to the New World Bible Translation Committee?
‎How did it support
their decision to restore God’s name
‎in the Christian Greek Scriptures?
‎We’ll find out.
‎We’ll visit the Quechua-speaking people
in the Andes Mountains.
‎What special efforts
have our brothers been making there
‎to spread the good news?
‎And what new tool do they have
to glorify God’s name in Quechua?
‎How did you feel
when you finally found Jehovah?
‎And how does it feel now
‎when you can help
someone in his or her search
‎to know the true God?
‎You’ll enjoy a new original song
‎about the search for Jehovah.
‎You’re watching JW Broadcasting
‎for October 2018.
‎It’s hard to believe
that it’s already been five years
‎since the release
of the revised New World Translation in English.
‎What a wonderful blessing
from Jehovah it has been!
‎Do you remember why the Governing Body
saw the need for a revised edition?
‎One reason was to honor God’s name,
‎including it in six more places
where new evidence made it possible.
‎Another reason to revise the English text
‎was to allow Bible translation
into even more languages.
‎Thousands of questions
from Bible translation teams
‎showed where the English text
‎could be made
more clear and understandable
‎without sacrificing accuracy.
‎It’s our prayer that, in time,
‎more of our brothers can have
‎a revised New World Translation
in their language.
‎The Governing Body feels
that Jehovah is answering that prayer.
‎Revised translations
are now available in 13 languages.
‎Listen to brothers and sisters
from four European-language groups
‎explain how the revised Bible
has benefited them
‎in their study and in their ministry.
‎The release of the revised version
‎of the New World Translation
of the Holy Scriptures
‎in the English language in 2013
‎had a wonderful impact
on the English-speaking world.
‎As Brother Jackson noted,
‎more than 60 years had passed
since the release of the first volume
‎of the New World Translation,
and during that time,
‎the English language had changed as well.
‎During 2017,
‎the revised version
‎of the New World Translation
of the Holy Scriptures
‎has been released
‎in some major European languages,
‎such as Italian (originally released in 1963),
‎Dutch (also originally released in 1963),
‎Greek (originally released in 1997),
‎and Hungarian (originally released in 2000).
‎How do the brothers and sisters feel
‎about the revised New World Translation
in their particular language?
‎The modern language
‎in this revised version of the Bible
‎helps me to understand Bible passages
‎because now it flows better
and is much simpler.
‎This helps me to meditate more
on what I have just read.
‎At Numbers 14:24,
‎Jehovah speaks to Moses.
‎In the older version,
Jehovah says about Caleb
‎that “a different spirit
has proved to be with him.”
‎In the revised version, the verse reads
‎that ‘my servant Caleb thinks differently’
‎—very clear
and doesn’t need further explanation.
‎Psalm 7:9 now says
‎that Jehovah “examines the hearts
‎and the deepest emotions,”
‎whereas previously it said
he examines the ‘hearts and the kidneys.’
‎Now it’s easier to understand.
‎Besides all the aspects of helping to get
‎a better understanding of God’s Word,
‎why are brothers and sisters
happy to use this revised version
‎in field service?
‎When reading a scripture,
‎you can tell that people understand
‎it more quickly;
‎there is less need to explain more.
‎And that’s great.
‎I particularly like the glossary;
‎it’s a kind of mini Insight book.
‎It has been very useful
‎when I study and also in the ministry.
‎Furthermore, I like
‎that at the beginning of the Bible,
‎there are 20 introductions
‎that answer questions
that people in the territory often ask,
‎and they have Bible verses
and very nice illustrations.
‎So they are very clear and practical.
‎To achieve such an awesome result
by revising the New World Translation,
‎which important aspects did
the translators have to keep in mind?
‎Thanks to the modern language
‎that is used in the revision,
‎readers can understand
most Bible passages as they read them,
‎without having to stop
and read them over again.
‎This is possible, in part,
‎because the text
is not cluttered with too many words
‎—trying to copy
the Hebrew syntax and style of expression.
‎Thus, the use of modern language
‎contributes to naturalness and clarity.
‎The language used
‎in the revision also now allows
‎the emotions of the characters
to come through more vividly.
‎You straightaway notice when someone
‎is angry or desperate or sad.
‎Like in Matthew 11,
when Jesus invites us to take his yoke upon us,
‎his warmth is immediately obvious.
‎In the 2003 edition,
‎only one sentence was packed
‎into seven verses,
‎and its length was half a column,
‎making it very cumbersome
to follow the line of thought.
‎In the revised Bible,
this part was cut into more sentences,
‎so it is easier to grasp the idea.
‎Many parents have told us
‎that now when they read the Bible
‎with their children,
‎they don’t have to stop to explain words
‎and the reading is much more enjoyable.
‎The revised New World Translation
will be made available
‎in more languages in the near future.
‎We know that Jehovah wants
all his people to listen
‎as he speaks to them in clear,
understandable language.
‎This will help us
to come to know Jehovah even better,
‎and our love for him
‎will keep growing
‎while we read his Word with joy.
‎In addition to being clear and accurate,
‎what should be the primary goal
of any Bible translation?
‎The answer is found
‎in the theme of our program this month:
‎“Father, Glorify Your Name.”
‎It’s based on Jesus’ words
‎recorded at John 12:28.
‎Let’s start by examining
the context of those words
‎as found in verses 27 and 28:
‎“‘Now I am troubled,
and what should I say?
‎“‘Father, save me out of this hour.
‎“‘Nevertheless, this is why
I have come to this hour.
‎“Father, glorify your name.’
‎“Then a voice came out of heaven:
‎‘I have glorified it and will glorify it again.’”
‎Jesus uttered these words
‎just four days before his agonizing death.
‎But even though Jesus was very troubled
‎about what was soon to happen to him,
‎what was his primary concern?
‎It was for Jehovah’s name to be glorified.
‎We today are likewise concerned
‎about the glorification
of Jehovah’s name and his reputation.
‎But how can someone
be glorified, or made famous,
‎if nobody knows his name?
‎Knowing God’s personal name, Jehovah,
‎is closely tied in with glorifying his reputation.
‎In fact, knowing Jehovah’s name
‎is the very first step in that process.
‎The June 2015 program of JW Broadcasting
‎discussed why God’s personal name
‎should appear in all translations of the Bible.
‎You might find it helpful to review that program.
‎But this month, we will consider
another aspect of this subject
‎that is far more controversial, namely,
‎Should the divine name appear
in the Christian Greek Scriptures,
‎or what is commonly called
the New Testament?
‎Many scholars who agree with us
‎that the divine name should appear
in the Hebrew Scriptures
‎disagree with our use of the same name
‎in the New Testament.
‎So, what prompted the translators
of the New World Translation
‎to restore the divine name 237 times
‎in the Christian Greek Scriptures?
‎The answer to that question
involves some fascinating events
‎that seem to be too amazing
to be just coincidence.
‎It also requires us
to do some detective work.
‎Sound intriguing?
‎It is!
‎So let’s start our journey together.
‎First of all, imagine that you
are back in the late 1940’s
‎—the time when
the New World Bible Translation Committee
‎was translating the book of Matthew.
‎As they started the project,
‎no doubt they realized
that Matthew’s account contains
‎many quotations from the Hebrew Scriptures.
‎Many of these contain the Tetragrammaton,
‎that is, the divine name
in Hebrew letters in the original text.
‎For example,
let’s consider Matthew 22:44.
‎This verse records Jesus
quoting the words of Psalm 110:1:
‎“Jehovah said to my Lord:
‘Sit at my right hand.’”
‎But did Jesus use the divine name
when making this quote?
‎Or did he substitute the divine name
‎with an equivalent such as “Lord”?
‎Well, the brothers would have realized
‎that many editions of the King James Version
‎did something
very interesting at Matthew 22:44.
‎In that verse, the English word “LORD”
‎is written in capital letters.
‎This technique is used
throughout the King James Version
‎to indicate where
the original Hebrew text uses the divine name.
‎So using “LORD”
in capital letters in this verse,
‎in effect,
acknowledges that the name of God
‎was originally in this quote.
‎The implication is
‎that Jesus used God’s name
when making this quote.
‎However, in the years prior
to the release of the New World Translation,
‎many scholars argued
that long before Jesus came to earth,
‎the Jewish people
had already removed the Tetragrammaton
‎from the Greek translation of the Hebrew text
—the Septuagint.
‎If true, that would mean
‎that copies of the Holy Writings
used in Jesus’ day
‎would not have contained
the divine name.
‎So, what should the Translation Committee do?
‎Should they use the divine name
in their translation or not?
‎This is where the story becomes intriguing.
‎Around that time,
some exciting discoveries
‎were made that proved those scholars wrong.
‎One of these discoveries
was documented by the brothers
‎in the foreword of the 1950 edition
‎of the New World Translation
of the Christian Greek Scriptures.
‎It involved
some papyri copies of the Septuagint
‎that dated
back to around the time of Jesus.
‎What did these papyri fragments reveal?
‎Let’s find out in this documentary report.
‎In 1950,
‎the New World Translation
of the Christian Greek Scriptures was released.
‎“I have the extreme pleasure of releasing
‎“the New World Translation
‎of the Christian Greek Scriptures!”
‎This translation was unique
‎in that it restored
the divine name, Jehovah,
‎237 times in the main text
‎of the so-called New Testament.
‎But how could they do that,
considering that for centuries
‎many Bibles did not use Jehovah’s name?
‎And why did the divine name
need to be restored?
‎The oldest copies we have available
‎do not use the divine name
‎in the Christian Greek Scriptures;
‎they use substitutes like God or Lord.
‎Very early on,
‎the copyists of those original manuscripts,
‎they simply replaced
‎—they got into the practice of replacing—
God’s name.
‎We know that this is not a translation
‎because one is a name
and the other one is a title.
‎And it’s not even
a synonym for Jehovah, for a name.
‎Since the Greek Scriptures
‎were an inspired addition
‎to the sacred Hebrew Scriptures and,
‎in fact,
‎Jehovah’s name, God’s name,
‎was used some 7,000 times
in the Hebrew Scriptures,
‎the sudden disappearance
in the Greek text is inconsistent.
‎Even though
the New World Bible Translation Committee
‎believed that Jehovah’s name should appear
‎in the text of the Christian Greek Scriptures,
‎they also knew that at that time
‎virtually all Bible scholars
disagreed with that belief.
‎Those scholars argued
that by the time of Jesus,
‎even the Greek translation
of the Hebrew Scriptures, the Septuagint,
‎no longer contained the divine name.
‎So why would the writers
of the New Testament
‎use the divine name when their copies
of the Holy Scriptures in Greek
‎did not contain the Tetragrammaton?
‎This view was based on faulty information.
‎How so?
‎Did the Septuagint still use
‎the divine name in Jesus’ time?
‎Let’s consider one piece of evidence
‎that answers this question.
‎Something amazing happened in 1944.
‎A theological journal published a picture
‎of a Greek Septuagint fragment
‎from the Papyrus Fouad 266 collection.
‎Now, inside that fragment
there was the divine name.
‎In the Greek text,
you had the Tetragrammaton,
‎not just once but throughout.
‎Now, this fragment was very old,
dating back to the first century B.C.E.,
‎but the important point is
that this was proof, clear proof,
‎that the divine name was originally there.
‎Two Jehovah’s Witnesses were asked
‎to obtain photographs
of these fragments,
‎which were located in Cairo, Egypt.
‎The New World Translation Committee
was very interested in this
‎because they started translating
‎the Greek Scriptures in 1947.
‎After obtaining permission,
pictures of 12 of the fragments
‎were published in the foreword
of the New World Translation
‎of the Christian Greek Scriptures.
‎What amazes me about this is the timing.
‎When our brothers
—this New World Translation Committee—
‎did their research, before even translating,
‎suddenly something that was unknown
‎until essentially 1944
‎came to light that confirmed
‎that the eternal name of God
‎had to be revealed;
it could no longer be hidden.
‎It should be shown to everyone
who wants to worship Jehovah.
‎This careful preservation
supports what Jesus said in prayer
‎at John 17:26,
when he said to his Father:
‎“I have made your name known . . .
and will make it known.”
‎As Jehovah’s Witnesses,
we are proud to be “a people for his name.”
‎Knowing his name
is essential to knowing Jehovah himself,
‎and the fact that Jehovah
has provided this arrangement
‎through his people
‎makes it very clear
‎that he was gathering
“a people for his name.”
‎This is why
this Bible translation is so beautiful,
‎because it brings us closer to Jehovah.
‎Jehovah is not just a Lord somewhere,
which could apply to anyone,
‎but he is Jehovah, our God.
‎He extends his hand to us and says, well,
‎‘I’m Jehovah; call me by that name.’
‎What an amazing find!
‎They found proof
that the divine name in Hebrew letters
‎was included in the text of the Septuagint
‎that would have been
available in Jesus’ day
‎and just at the right time
‎—the time when the members
of the Translation Committee
‎were making the decision
as to whether they should use
‎the name Jehovah in their translation
of the Christian Greek Scriptures.
‎We are so happy that the brothers
were able to find this information
‎because these fragments
were not released for general publication
‎until much later in 1971
‎—years after the time when the committee
needed to make that vital decision.
‎But that’s not all!
‎Do you remember
what other important material
‎was discovered starting in 1947?
‎It was the Dead Sea Scrolls.
‎Many of these scrolls were dated
to around the time when Jesus was on earth.
‎And what did these scrolls
contain over and over again?
‎You guessed it
‎—the Tetragrammaton—
the divine name.
‎Isn’t it interesting
‎that these discoveries
were made around the time
‎when our brothers were translating
the New World Translation?
‎Is this just coincidence
‎or do you see Jehovah’s hand in this?
‎What has happened
in the years since that time?
‎It’s important to note
‎that the divine name is consistently used
‎in fragments of the Septuagint
‎that date from the first century B.C.E.
‎and the first century C.E.
‎This has led some scholars
to acknowledge the possibility
‎that Jesus and his disciples
‎used the divine name
when making these quotations.
‎But we need to remember
that Hebrew Scripture quotations
‎account for approximately one third
‎of the 237 times
‎the New World Translation
restores the divine name
‎in the Christian Greek Scriptures.
‎So, what about the other
two thirds of occurrences?
‎Well, this brings us
to the part of our program
‎that involves some detective work.
‎Imagine that you are a detective,
‎and you catch an art thief
‎who has stolen
over 200 original pieces of art
‎from various museums and art galleries.
‎This thief not only stole each piece of art
‎but he also substituted it with a copy.
‎So you need to start an investigation
‎and follow the clues.
‎First of all, you need to find out
‎where each painting was located originally.
‎Once you have verified
that fakes are hanging in those locations,
‎you would be in a position
to return the originals
‎to their proper locations.
‎In a similar way,
we have solid evidence
‎that a crime was committed
in the second and third centuries C.E.
‎Apostate Christians removed the divine name
‎from manuscripts of the Bible
‎and replaced it with Kyʹri·os,
the Greek word for “Lord.”
‎There is much evidence for this conclusion.
‎So they are like the art thief in our illustration.
‎They stole something valuable
‎when they removed Jehovah’s name
from the Christian Greek Scriptures.
‎But we have a problem.
‎There are no copies
of the Christian Greek Scriptures
‎from the first century for us to examine.
‎The earliest existing manuscripts
‎that would have a bearing on this matter
‎date from the late second century onward
‎—a time when we know that the crime
had already been committed
‎and Jehovah’s name
had already been removed.
‎So how do we know where Jehovah’s name
‎originally appeared in the Greek text
‎before the apostates removed it?
‎Well, just like the detective in our illustration,
‎we need to start an investigation
‎and follow the clues.
‎To do our work properly,
‎we need to examine every time
the word “Lord” appears in the text
‎and see if it refers to Jehovah, to Jesus,
‎or to some other person with the title “Lord.”
‎Basically,
there are five clues that will help us
‎to find out where the original artwork,
‎that is, Jehovah’s name,
needs to be returned to.
‎Let’s scrutinize these clues.
‎The first clue is,
‎as we have already mentioned,
the easiest clue,
‎where the title “Lord” appears
‎in quotations from the Hebrew Scriptures
‎that originally used the divine name.
‎The second clue is
‎where the Greek text contains a Hebrew idiom
‎that would normally contain the divine name.
‎For example,
if someone says in English,
‎“He escaped by the skin of his . . . ,”
‎what word do you expect?
‎Teeth, not eye.
‎Yes, the expression is “skin of his teeth.”
‎This is similar with Hebrew expressions.
‎Some of these contain the divine name.
‎For example,
the expression found at Matthew 1:20
‎is “the angel of Jehovah.”
‎So whenever we find
a Greek translation of a Hebrew idiom
‎that uses the divine name,
‎this is another clue
that Jehovah’s name should be there.
‎The third clue
‎is where the term “Lord” appears
‎in the context surrounding a quotation
‎that is originally attributed to Jehovah.
‎An example of this is Matthew 1:22:
‎“All of this actually came about to fulfill
‎what was spoken by Jehovah
through his prophet, saying . . .”
‎The quotation
that immediately follows at Matthew 1:23
‎is taken from Isaiah 7:14.
‎This is a prophetic message
‎spoken by Jehovah through Isaiah.
‎The fourth clue
‎is when we see in the Greek text
‎where there is no definite article
before Kyʹri·os, the Greek word for “Lord,”
‎in places where the Greek grammar
normally expects a definite article.
‎This clue may indicate
that a proper name, such as Jehovah,
‎originally was there in the text
‎and was removed from later manuscripts
and replaced with Kyʹri·os.
‎To illustrate the importance of this clue,
‎imagine that you are a newspaper reporter
‎who is reporting on a car accident.
‎You report that Joe Smith,
the driver of the vehicle,
‎was killed in the accident.
‎But just before the story goes to press,
‎your editor informs you
that Joe Smith’s relatives
‎have not yet been notified of his death.
‎So you are told to remove
his name from the report.
‎You do that, but in doing so,
‎you forget to add
the “the” before the word “driver.”
‎What would happen?
‎Your report would say,
‎“As a result of the accident,
driver was killed.”
‎That sounds strange, doesn’t it?
‎It sounds like “driver”
is the name of the person killed.
‎That’s because you suppressed the name
‎and forgot to add the appropriate article.
‎That is similar
to what our symbolic art thieves did
‎when removing
Jehovah’s name from the Bible.
‎An example of this
‎is found in the Greek text of Mark 13:20.
‎“In fact, unless Lord had cut short the days,
‎no flesh would be saved.”
‎That sounds like “Lord” is a name,
‎and clearly it should be Jehovah’s name.
‎That’s why the New World Translation
restores the divine name in this verse.
‎However,
even in cases where the definite article
‎occurs before the word “Lord,”
‎there may be other strong reasons
‎for viewing “Lord”
as a substitute for the divine name,
‎like the ones we already discussed.
‎The final clue
‎is where the divine name
needs to be added to avoid ambiguity.
‎An example of this
‎is in Mark 5:19.
‎There, Jesus says to a man he healed:
‎“Go home to your relatives,
‎“and report to them all the things
‎Jehovah has done for you
and the mercy he has shown you.”
‎How do we know that “Lord”
here refers to Jehovah
‎and not Jesus?
‎Well, in recording the same event,
‎Luke 8:39 uses the Greek word The·osʹ (God),
‎supporting the thought
that Kyʹri·os (Lord) at Mark 5:19
‎is used with reference to Jehovah God.
‎So these five clues helped
the New World Bible Translation Committee
‎to ascertain where the name Jehovah
‎should be restored to the Biblical text.
‎In this way, they were able to right the wrong
‎that was committed by apostate Christians
‎in the second and third centuries or,
‎in other words, they were able to return
‎the figurative pieces of stolen artwork
‎to their proper places.
‎If you would like to review these five clues,
‎you will find a detailed explanation in Appendix C
‎of the Study Edition of the New World Translation.
‎You can either find this in the JW Library® app
‎or online at Watchtower ONLINE LIBRARY.
‎In the same Appendix C,
‎you will find a list
of what we call J-References
‎that support these decisions.
‎But you might ask,
‎‘What role did these J-References play
in making these decisions?’
‎Well, to help us understand
the answer to that question,
‎I’d like to introduce to you
a brother with whom I work,
‎Brother Nick Ahladis.
‎He’s the assistant overseer
of Translation Services.
‎Nick, thanks so much for being willing
‎to come along
and answer some questions for us.
‎Yes, I’m glad to come.
‎Well, now that we’ve got you here,
the first question I’d like to ask you is,
‎What really are these so-called J-References?
‎Well the “J” in the J-References
‎stands for Jehovah.
‎And this is mainly a list of Bibles
‎in Hebrew and other languages
‎that use the divine name, Jehovah,
‎in the main text
of the Christian Greek Scriptures
‎—or at least some form
of the name Jehovah.
‎And this list began to be compiled
‎by the New World Bible Translation Committee
‎in the 1940’s.
‎So where would we find a list like that now?
‎Well, originally there was
a list of 21 such references
‎in the 1950 edition
of the Christian Greek Scriptures.
‎Then, in 1984,
‎27 such references were included
‎in the Reference Bible in English.
‎And since that time,
many more J-References have been found,
‎and now the list includes
‎over 90 such translations and reference works.
‎And you can find an up-to-date list
‎in Appendix C4 of the [Study] Bible.
‎Very good.
‎So I guess the main question
we’re interested in asking you is,
‎Do these J-References prove in themselves
‎that the Tetragrammaton should be
in the Christian Greek Scriptures?
‎Actually, no; they don’t.
‎Ah, now, I’m sure most of us
weren’t expecting you to say that.
‎So can you explain it a little bit more please?
‎Well,
the New World Translation Committee
‎did not rely on the J-References
as the basis for their decision
‎to restore the divine name
in the Christian Greek Scriptures.
‎You already discussed
the basis for the decision
‎earlier in the broadcast.
‎Rather,
these J-References provide proof
‎that other translators
have made similar decisions
‎when restoring the divine name
‎to their editions
of the Christian Greek Scriptures,
‎or the so-called New Testament.
‎So, now that you’re talking
about these other Bible translators,
‎could you give us an example
of who you’re talking about?
‎Well, a number of them
were well-known Bible scholars.
‎For example, 19th-century
Lutheran theologian Franz Delitzsch
‎is still considered to be
a foremost Bible scholar
‎and a scholar of Biblical Hebrew.
‎Delitzsch’s translation
‎of the New Testament in Hebrew
was produced in 1877,
‎and it’s one of the J-References.
‎In fact, it’s still one
of the best-known New Testaments
‎in the Hebrew language.
‎In that translation,
he discerned when to use Jehovah’s name
‎in places where the Greek text
‎contains the term Kyʹri·os, or Lord.
‎The New World Bible Translation Committee
‎studied all those occurrences
from his translation
‎as well as the occurrences
in others of the J-References.
‎So how would you summarize
what the value is of these J-References?
‎Well, all the J-References,
‎including the new ones in the Study Bible,
‎represent the view
of translators and scholars
‎who arrived at the same conclusion
‎that the New World
Bible Translation Committee did,
‎namely, that Jesus Christ and the apostles
‎used the name Jehovah
in their teaching and in their writings.
‎And this conclusion is reflected
‎in their translation and reference works.
‎Very interesting.
That’s fascinating.
‎So if I’ve got it right then,
‎what you’re saying is
that if we go to Appendix C, in C3,
‎there we’ve got a list of the reasons
‎why the brothers
on the New World Translation Committee
‎decided to put
Jehovah’s name in certain verses.
‎And then C4 is virtually
‎a list of other Bible translations
‎where the translators
made exactly the same decision.
‎Is that right?
‎That’s exactly right.
‎Ah, that’s good.
‎Well, thank you very much, Nick,
for coming along.
‎We really appreciated hearing
those expressions from you.
‎Before you go, though,
can we ask you, please,
‎Can you take back the love and greetings
and an expression of appreciation
‎to all those hardworking brothers and sisters
there in Translation Services?
‎Yes, I’d be happy to.
‎Thank you very much.
‎Why does the organization work
so diligently to translate the Bible?
‎It’s not so that we can feel smart
‎when talking to others
about the Bible and God’s name.
‎No, but it equips us to follow
Jesus’ example in the ministry
‎and to glorify God’s name
‎and make it known
to those searching for Him.
‎This month’s original song is entitled
‎“The Search,”
‎and it shows the joy people feel
when they find Jehovah.
‎We heard the words ‘seek and you’ll find’
The very priceless pearl of truth.
‎It was a sea of doubts and questions to God
That the search would take us through.
‎But we carried on with our sails unfurled.
‎Like merchants on a quest,
we knew that truth was out there.
‎The search—the search for the key
To answer all the things,
‎Things that we fight to understand:
‎The origin of man, wondering why we need
God’s Kingdom soon to come.
‎Searching hard to find.
‎We had never known God had a name.
Jehovah is the one to call on.
‎When we were shown, we found a piece
Of what we were searching for.
‎And we carried on with our sails unfurled,
‎Finding truths about where we came from
and where we’re heading.
‎The search—the search for the key
That answered all the things,
‎Things that we fought to understand:
‎The origin of man, a paradise that’s promised
in God’s Kingdom soon to come.
‎Search and you will find.
‎Now we can never hold back
when others are searching
‎For the priceless pearl of truth,
Sailing a sea of unanswered questions.
‎So we help them to get through,
And we share what we’ve discovered.
‎The search—the search for the key
To answer all the things,
‎Things that they fight to understand:
‎The origin of man, living forever
in God’s Kingdom soon to come.
‎Search and you will find.
‎Maybe you once thought similarly
‎to what the lyrics from our song express:
‎“Like merchants on a quest,
we knew the truth was out there.”
‎What a wonderful privilege it is to find Jehovah
‎and then to help others who are still searching.
‎It’s an important way we glorify God’s name
‎and why we’re called Jehovah’s Witnesses.
‎Bearing that name is, of course,
‎both a privilege and a responsibility.
‎How so?
‎Brother Robert Ciranko explains
in this Bethel morning worship.
‎By the time the apostle Peter
‎wrote the words of today’s text,
‎individuals who were Jews,
‎proselytes, Samaritans,
‎and Gentiles had been brought
‎into the Christian congregation
‎as God’s people,
‎the spiritual Israel of God.
‎In the verse before today’s text,
‎Peter outlined what their mission was.
‎Let’s open
to 1 Peter chapter 2 and read that.
‎It’s in verses 9 and 10 of 1 Peter 2.
‎He wrote:
‎“But you are ‘a chosen race,
a royal priesthood,
‎“‘a holy nation,
a people for special possession,
‎“that you should declare abroad
the excellencies’
‎“of the One who called you
out of darkness into his wonderful light.
‎“For you were once not a people,
‎but now you are God’s people.”
‎And, of course, this refers
to the spirit-anointed members
‎of the congregation
who would be responsible
‎for glorifying Jehovah’s name
as his Witnesses.
‎And this harmonizes
with what Peter had said years earlier
‎in the first-century governing body meeting,
‎as reported in Acts chapter 15.
‎So let’s turn there, Acts 15,
‎and we will begin with verse 14.
‎It says:
“Symeon has related thoroughly how God
‎“for the first time
turned his attention to the nations
‎“to take out of them a people for his name.
‎“And with this the words
of the Prophets agree,
‎“just as it is written:
‎“‘After these things
I will return and raise up again
‎“‘the tent of David that is fallen down;
‎“‘I will rebuild its ruins and restore it,
‎“‘so that the men who remain
may earnestly seek Jehovah,
‎“‘together with people of all the nations,
‎“‘people who are called by my name,
‎says Jehovah, who is doing these things.’”
‎Now, what about the rest of us
‎who are not anointed Christians
‎but who call ourselves Jehovah’s Witnesses?
‎Are we also God’s people?
‎Well, most certainly!
‎And what a proud honor it is for us
‎to bear the name of the only true God.
‎But with that name comes responsibility,
‎one that other religious groups
do not want to take on.
‎You see, we are under obligation
‎to bear witness to Jehovah,
‎to tell the truth about him,
‎and to expose false teachings
‎that misrepresent Jehovah.
‎And a classic example
of an unscriptural dogma
‎that God’s people have exposed is the Trinity,
‎which reminds me of another hoax
‎that fooled many people
who should have known better.
‎It’s the true story
about a man named van Meegeren,
‎a Dutch artist, born in 1889,
‎who perpetrated what may have been
‎the most sensational art hoax of all time.
‎You see, he never won the critical acclaim
‎that he thought he was due as an artist.
‎So to get back at the art critics,
‎he decided to demonstrate his talent
‎by producing a painting that would fool them all,
‎and he set out to imitate
‎the famous 17th-century Dutch impressionist,
‎Johannes Vermeer.
‎Well, van Meegeren spent 4 years figuring out
‎how to make
a new painting look 300 years old.
‎The canvas was the easy part.
‎He just took a lesser-known painting
‎from the 17th century
and removed the picture.
‎His biggest problem was getting oil paint
‎to harden thoroughly,
which usually takes 50 years.
‎He solved it
by mixing his pigments with a synthetic resin
‎instead of oil and then baking the canvas.
‎Well, van Meegeren produced six paintings
‎that were passed off as Vermeers.
‎His greatest sold in 1937.
‎It was entitled
Christ and the Disciples at Emmaus.
‎The most authoritative art historian of the day
‎said it was a genuine Vermeer masterpiece,
‎untouched, on the original canvas,
‎and that it had no restoration done to it.
‎But in reality, it was a fake.
‎The critic’s opinion was taken
as gospel in the art world,
‎so much so that this critic
had been nicknamed “The Pope.”
‎Eventually, though,
a chemical analysis proved
‎that the paint contained
an ingredient that had not been discovered
‎until two centuries after Vermeer died,
‎and that’s what exposed
van Meegeren as a fraud.
‎Well, something similar
went on during the apostasy
‎that took place
after the death of the apostles.
‎Less than 300 years
after the Bible was completed,
‎a Trinitarian added to 1 John 5:7 the words
‎“in heaven, the Father,
the Word, and the Holy Ghost:
‎and these three are one.”
‎However, this addition does not appear
‎in the oldest Greek manuscripts,
‎proving it’s a fake;
it’s a corruption of God’s Word.
‎And yet for centuries,
the churches propagated the Trinity doctrine.
‎As recently as the 19th century,
‎almost all Bible translations
‎had this spurious addition.
‎As late as 1897, Pope Leo XIII
‎upheld the corrupted text
‎of the Latin Vulgate.
‎Interestingly, the New Catholic Encyclopedia
‎comments on this
and says: “The Trinitarian dogma
‎“is in the last analysis
a late 4th century invention.
‎“Among the Apostolic Fathers,
‎“there had been nothing
even remotely approaching
‎such a mentality or perspective.”
‎Well, Jehovah’s anointed Witnesses
‎firmly rejected Christendom’s Trinity dogma.
‎In 1915,
The Watch Tower exposed the foolishness
‎of teaching a doctrine
that contradicts the Bible.
‎The Watch Tower said:
‎“In what a jumble of contradictions
‎“and confusion
do they find themselves who say
‎“that Jesus and the Father are one God!
‎“This would involve the idea
‎“that our Lord Jesus acted
the hypocrite when on earth
‎“and only pretended
to address God in prayer,
‎“when He Himself was the same God. . . .
‎“The Father has always been immortal,
hence could not die.
‎“How then, could Jesus have died? . . .
‎“The Scriptures declare,
however, that He did die. . . .
‎“If they admit that Jesus really died,
they take the other horn of the dilemma;
‎“for believing that their three Gods
‎“are all one person as many do,
‎“when Jesus died
they must all three have died.
‎“If they all died, who raised them to life?
‎“How foolish all this sounds! . . .
‎“Shall we thus contradict the Apostles
and Prophets and Jesus Himself,
‎“and ignore reason
and common sense, in order to hold
‎“to a dogma handed to us
from the dark, superstitious past,
‎“by a corrupt apostate Church?
‎Nay!” says The Watch Tower.
‎Well, Jehovah’s people
continue to uphold the excellencies
‎ of the only true God.
‎Whether in ancient times,
as with the natural Israelites
‎or in modern times, as with spiritual Israel,
‎Jehovah’s words through Isaiah are still true.
‎Look at it at Isaiah 43:21.
‎Of course,
we know in Isaiah chapter 43
‎Jehovah declares:
“You are my witnesses.”
‎And in verse 21 he says:
‎“The people whom I formed for myself
‎so that they might declare my praise.”
‎And the effort that Jehovah’s Witnesses​
‎—God’s people​—
have put forth to expose
‎ Bible teachings that are false,
‎to teach the truth about Jehovah,
‎and to sanctify God’s name
has taken on proportions
‎never attained by any other religious group.
‎And Jehovah takes notice of that.
‎Look at Malachi the 3rd chapter.
‎Malachi chapter 3,
‎beginning with verse 16.
‎Malachi 3:​16:
‎“At that time those
who feared Jehovah spoke with one another,
‎“each one with his companion,
‎“and Jehovah kept paying
attention and listening.
‎“And a book of remembrance
was written before him
‎“for those fearing Jehovah
and for those meditating on
‎“[or the footnote says,
possibly, “treasuring”] his name.
‎“‘And they will be mine,’
says Jehovah of armies,
‎‘in the day when I produce
a special property.’”
‎So Jehovah truly does love those
‎who fear him and treasure his name,
‎making them truly God’s people.
‎Jehovah can remove any obstacle
‎to sanctifying his name
and declaring the good news
‎—even long-held false teachings.
‎And what is more amazing,
‎he uses his people
—his special property—
‎to get the work done.
‎The challenges may be different where you live,
‎but the results are the same:
‎Jehovah blesses your efforts to glorify him.
‎Let’s see an example in this report from Peru,
‎where our brothers are reaching the hearts
‎of Quechua-speaking people
in the Andes Mountains.
‎My name is Faustino Camacho Quispe.
‎My family and I speak Quechua or,
‎as we say, runa simi
‎—the language of the people.
‎We live in an agricultural community
‎in the mountains of Peru.
‎Our way of life depends on farming.
‎We grow crops such as corn,
‎potatoes, wheat,
‎and quinoa.
‎We also raise a small amount of livestock.
‎Many people who speak Quechua
have moved to larger cities,
‎but others, like us, still enjoy
‎a more traditional way of life in the country.
‎My family and I are Jehovah’s Witnesses.
‎Most of our brothers and sisters in this area
‎would never have been able to learn the truth
‎had there not been someone
sent here to preach in Quechua.
‎In 1992,
‎the Peru branch office began to expand
‎the work in the Quechua-language field.
‎In order to reach those living in isolated areas,
‎zealous brothers and sisters climbed narrow roads
‎in the frigid elevations of the Andes Mountains.
‎Great efforts were made in order
‎to bring Quechua-speaking people
‎the good news in their own language.
‎The people loved having publications
in their mother tongue.
‎However, there were some challenges
‎in carrying out this work.
‎One problem was not having a good translation
‎of the Holy Scriptures in Quechua.
‎The commonly used translations here in Peru
‎omit God’s name in the main text.
‎It can be found in the glossary of some Bibles,
‎and sometimes we used that in order to preach.
‎But even so, it didn’t have the same impact
‎as seeing it in its proper place.
‎That, along with the influence of false doctrines,
‎made it difficult for us to teach the truth.
‎When we teach people about the Bible,
‎we want them to draw close to God;
‎we want them to become his friends.
‎But no one can be God’s friend
‎if they don’t know his name.
‎For people to be able to come to love God,
‎they have to know his name,
‎and they have to understand what it means.
‎It was difficult for us
to use the Bible at the meetings,
‎in the field ministry, and in our family worship.
‎How could Jehovah’s great name be sanctified
‎throughout this mountainous region?
‎How could the Quechua people get to know God
‎when his name was hidden?
‎The answer to our prayers came
‎when Quechua congregations
throughout the country
‎were invited to a special program
‎on May 1, 2016.
‎Imagine the great joy we felt
when Brother Jackson
‎of the Governing Body
announced the release
‎of the New World Translation
of the Christian Greek Scriptures
‎in two Quechua languages!
‎Language number 136:
‎It’s the Christian Greek Scriptures
‎in Quechua Ayacucho!
‎But we also have number 137:
‎It’s Quechua Cuzco!
‎What a wonderful gift we’ve received today!
‎This new Quechua Bible
‎is a grand victory for Jehovah’s great name.
‎God’s name is no longer hidden
from the Quechua people,
‎giving them the precious opportunity
‎to come to know our loving Creator, Jehovah.
‎I feel proud to use our new Bible to teach
‎my family and neighbors Jehovah’s name.
‎I am thankful every day
‎that Jehovah sent this good news to the mountains
‎to us who speak runa simi
‎—the language of the people.
‎It was a privilege
to be at such a happy event
‎and to see our brothers’ joy
‎when they received
the Christian Greek Scriptures
‎in two Quechua languages.
‎May they use their Bibles
to draw close to Jehovah
‎and glorify his name in the Andes Mountains.
‎Our program now goes
‎to the South Pacific,
‎where we conclude
with greetings from Tuvalu.
‎Most of Tuvalu’s nine islands
are ring-shaped coral atolls
‎surrounding peaceful lagoons.
‎These small islands barely rise out of the sea.
‎On Funafuti, Tuvalu’s capital,
‎the island is just wide enough in some places
‎for the main road and a single house.
‎The motorbike is the preferred way
to travel on the island.
‎So it’s good that our witnessing carts
come equipped with sturdy wheels.
‎Tuvalu has a busy remote translation office.
‎In 2011,
‎the New World Translation
of the Christian Greek Scriptures in Tuvaluan
‎was released.
‎In October of last year,
the complete Bible was released,
‎making Tuvaluan
the smallest language group
‎to receive the New World Translation.
‎I was assigned to Tuvalu in 1979
‎and enjoyed the challenging task
‎of helping to establish Tuvaluan translation.
‎There were
only 3 other baptized publishers back then,
‎but in 2017,
‎Tuvalu reported a peak of 125 publishers.
‎They preach to a population
‎of around 10,000 people.
‎Tuvaluans are warm and friendly,
‎and our brothers and sisters thoroughly enjoy
‎the time they can spend together.
‎They send their love
and greetings from the South Pacific.
‎Alofa atu in Tuvaluan means
‎“We send our love to you all.”
‎We send them our love
and pray for Jehovah’s continued blessing.
‎This is JW Broadcasting
‎from the world headquarters
of Jehovah’s Witnesses.