You and I make a lot of decisions every day.
Now, some have a little impact on our lives;
others have a very big impact.
And we can appreciate that we can make
choices and decisions for ourselves.
Think of how life would be
if you made no decisions for yourself
—someone tells you when to go to bed,
they pick out your clothes,
and they tell you what to do for work.
Well, none of us would like that!
Jehovah gave each of us free will,
and that’s the precious gift
of making choices for ourselves.
Now, have you ever thought
about why Jehovah gave us this gift?
I mean,
why trust us with free will
when he knew that we could make
bad choices or decisions?
Well, one powerful reason is love.
The only way to give us the gift of love
is also to give us the gift of free will.
The two are tied together.
You really can’t have
one without the other.
For example,
if I programmed my computer
to give me a message
every day at 2:00 p.m.:
“John, I love you.
I think you’re a wonderful guy,”
I think there’d be a little something
wrong with me if I thought:
‘Aw, isn’t that nice?
My computer, it loves me.’
Yeah, love only exists
if it comes truly
from a free-will expression.
Now, did Jehovah place
any boundaries on free will?
Yes.
They were stated in the Law
to the nation of Israel.
And Jesus later repeated them
at Matthew 22:37-40:
“He said to him:
“‘“You must love Jehovah your God
with your whole heart
“‘“and with your whole soul
and with your whole mind.”
“‘This is the greatest
and first commandment.
“‘The second, like it, is this:
“‘“You must love your
neighbor as yourself.”
“‘On these two commandments
the whole Law hangs,
and the Prophets.’”
So our use of free will
has love of God
and love of neighbor
as its boundaries.
Notice, for example,
what people are doing
in this picture,
both inside the circle boundary
and outside.
See, free will allows us to do
any of the things
we see in the picture.
But love of God
and love of neighbor
move us to reject
what’s outside the circle
and choose
to do the kinds of things
that we see inside the circle.
Now, to stay
within those boundaries,
Jehovah gave us
a marvelous brain
and a built-in conscience,
but he also knows
we need more help.
And that’s why
he also gave us Bible principles
—basic truths from the Bible
that can help us
to make good decisions.
And it can safely be said
that any decision we face
can be guided
by Bible principles.
Now, our Creator, Jehovah,
knows what’s best for us.
And he also trusts us
to make decisions
based on Bible principles
because he knows
that when we do that,
then we’re really,
truly going to be happy, content,
and at peace with him
and with others.
So in review so far:
Jehovah gave us free will
—that’s the privilege
to make choices for ourselves—
and he also gave us
Bible principles
as the boundaries
to our choices.
But making difficult decisions
requires that we train ourselves
to recognize Bible principles
and apply them.
Now let’s read Romans 12:1,
and let’s see how this verse
describes the decision-making process.
“Therefore, I appeal to you
“by the compassions of God, brothers,
“to present your bodies
as a living sacrifice,
“holy and acceptable to God,
a sacred service
with your power of reason.”
So are we using
our “power of reason”
to understand Bible principles?
For example, young children
ask lots of questions.
But has a child ever asked you:
“What happens when I drop a ball?
a pencil? a book?”
No, they don’t ask that.
They know what happens
to anything they drop.
It falls down!
See, the child doesn’t need
rules for every object
but has quickly grasped the principle.
Anything he drops falls down.
Now,
what if an 18-year-old asked you,
“What’s going to happen
when I drop this pen?”
Well, it’s obvious
he’s not been paying attention
to basic principles of life.
So by us paying attention
to Bible principles,
we can very quickly see
the pattern
of love of God
and love of neighbor
and know
the right thing to do
without a long list of rules
for every situation.
Well, how can we train
our “power of reason”?
We train it by paying attention
as we read and study the Bible.
Now, we don’t need rules
for which movies to watch,
which songs to listen to,
or what clothes we can wear.
If we’re paying attention
when we’re reading the Bible,
we train our conscience
with Bible principles
so we can make
such decisions
without needing
a long list of rules.
You know,
we could compare our training
of our “power of reason”
to a blind person
using a guide dog.
Now, an untrained dog
would be very helpful
to a blind person.
It would bark when others
were around, for example.
However,
a dog trained
in specific skills
is amazingly helpful.
The dog knows
when to stop at curbs
and walk around obstacles
that the person
might run their head into.
A guide dog
is also taught a skill called
“intelligent disobedience.”
And even if the blind person
encourages the dog forward,
it won’t obey,
but it’ll pull
the person back from danger.
Now, it can take a year or more
of training for the dog to learn
the amazing skills
that are so helpful to a blind person.
Likewise, our raw,
untrained “power of reason”
can help us to a degree.
However, it can be amazing
if we take the time to train it.
Now, here are
three skills that we can use
to train our “power of reason.”
They are illustrating,
analyzing,
and balancing.
Now, to consider our first skill,
illustrating,
let’s use the general topic
of forgiveness.
What Bible principles
could help with forgiveness?
Please think of as many principles
and scriptures as you can.
Now, if it helps,
you can pause the program now
and write down
the principles that come to mind.
Now, your list
may include principles like these:
Matthew 18:22 says
to forgive “up to 77 times”;
Proverbs 12:18 says:
“The tongue of the wise is a healing”;
and Colossians 3:13 tells us
to ‘forgive one another freely.’
Now, the skill
we want to learn is illustrating
—creating a mental picture
of an idea or principle
to see its real meaning
and impact.
Now, even if we
are not skilled artists,
all of us can and do create
pictures in our minds.
When illustrating,
pay attention to things that are similar
or like the thing
you are trying to visualize.
For example,
if sin is like debt,
then forgiveness
is like someone canceling the debt.
If a hurtful remark
is like a cut,
then forgiveness
is like seeing it heal.
If sin is like a mark
on a blackboard,
forgiveness is like erasing it.
Proverbs 12:18
is a great example
of using the “like” technique.
“Thoughtless speech
is like the stabs of a sword,
but the tongue of the wise
is a healing.”
Imagine what your skin
would look like
if you still had
every open cut, bruise,
or bleeding scratch
since childhood.
See, Jehovah
wonderfully designed our body
to heal such minor cuts
and bruises.
And we can now visualize
how the forgiveness of others
helps us to heal emotionally.
Now, learning to illustrate,
or visualize,
takes time and practice.
However, it can be one
of the most powerful skills we use
to train
our “power of reason,”
and it can also be
quite enjoyable.
You know,
try at your family worship
to take
the principles for a topic
and see
how many similarities,
or “likes,”
you can come up with.
Now, granted,
they all won’t be amazing,
but you may be surprised
by the insights
that come from seeing
something from a new perspective.
Well, let’s consider now
our second skill:
analyzing.
Now, analyzing something means
“examining it carefully in detail.”
And let’s use
the topic of wrong desires.
Now, in this case,
let’s say that we’ve already found
the principle
at Colossians 3:5:
“Deaden, therefore, your body members
that are on the earth
“as respects sexual immorality,
uncleanness,
“uncontrolled sexual passion,
“hurtful desire, and greediness,
which is idolatry.”
Now, what can we learn
from analyzing Colossians 3:5
to help when we struggle
with wrong desires?
Again, feel free
to pause the program
if you want some time
to think about it.
Look carefully
at each step outlined.
Did you notice, for example,
what appears to be
a reverse order
of the steps leading to sin?
This verse works its way
from sexual immorality
back to the very roots
of the problem.
Now, let’s take each phrase
starting with the last,
“greediness, which is idolatry.”
So, sexual immorality
starts with selfishness,
greedily putting our needs
ahead of anything else.
Next is “hurtful desire.”
Greediness leads to “hurtful desire.”
It’s like a person
hanging around a bakery,
smelling the bread and cakes
when he can’t pay for it.
Likewise,
hanging around immoral entertainment
or bad associates
can feed “hurtful desire”
for what is not ours.
Next is listed
“uncontrolled sexual passion.”
So “hurtful desire”
has now turned from an idea
into a strong emotion
of passion,
causing one
to look for an opportunity
to fulfill the desire.
Next, “uncleanness.”
The previous steps have now led
to inappropriate physical conduct
with another person.
Finally, “sexual immorality”
—serious sin.
Sexual immorality
has occurred between persons
that are not married
to one another.
So analyzing Colossians 3:5
can really help us to eliminate,
not stimulate, wrong desires.
And we can see
how important it is
to get rid
of wrong desires immediately.
It’s easier
to walk away from sin
when we’re still in the early stages,
rather than later.
So we need
to practice the skill
of not simply
just reading scriptures
but analyzing them
until we’ve learned
all that we can.
And we can use
the many research tools we have
to find valuable comments
and application.
Now, let’s consider our third
and final skill: balancing.
And to do that,
let’s use a question
on the topic of alcohol.
What Bible principles
could help a couple to decide
whether to serve alcohol
at their wedding?
What principles and scriptures
do you think would help them
make a balanced decision?
Again, you’re welcome
to pause the program
if you’d like to write down
what comes to mind
or to research something.
Now, your list probably has
some of these principles.
At John 2:9,
Jesus made wine for a wedding.
However,
1 Corinthians 6:10 says
that ‘drunkards
will not inherit the Kingdom.’
And 1 Corinthians 10:31, 32 says:
“Whether you are eating or drinking . . . ,
do all things for God’s glory”
and to “keep from becoming
causes for stumbling.”
Now,
it doesn’t seem
that any one principle
provides the answer.
The couple could simply say:
“Well, Jesus served wine at a wedding,
so we can too.”
However, there’s really more
to it than that, isn’t there?
It’s clear that a balance
of all these Bible principles
is needed.
Will relatives
or others be there
who might be prone
to overdrinking?
Would serving alcohol bother
the conscience of many present
because of local customs
and feelings about alcohol?
It’s often the case
when making decisions
that we need to balance
several Bible principles,
not taking any one principle solely
on its own merit.
Jehovah expects us
to use our “power of reason”
to balance Bible principles
and make good decisions.
Ecclesiastes 7:16-18
gives us good advice
about being balanced.
“Do not be overly righteous,
“nor show yourself excessively wise.
“Why should you bring ruin to yourself?
“Do not be excessively wicked,
nor be foolish.
“Why should you die before your time?
“It is best to grasp one warning
“without letting go of the other;
for the one who fears God
will heed them both.”
How true.
Such balance between extremes
is often necessary
when we apply
Bible principles.
We need to heed them both,
so to speak.
We need to balance
all the Bible principles
so we can come
to the decision
that would show love of God
and love of neighbor.
We could illustrate the balance
between different Bible principles
and applying them with this model bike.
It was a gift from a brother in Malawi.
Now, a bicycle has
three basic principles of operation:
the brakes, the pedals, and the steering.
Now, the brakes are really like principles
that slow us down
or stop us from doing the wrong thing.
And the pedals are really like the principles
that move us forward
in showing love for Jehovah
and our brothers and sisters.
And the steering is like our free will
to choose a direction in life
that pleases Jehovah.
So making decisions
is like riding a bicycle.
We have to balance
several Bible principles.
So in review,
Jehovah gave us free will
to use within the boundaries
of love of God and love of neighbor
and many other fine Bible principles.
Making difficult decisions requires
that we train our “power of reason”
to recognize Bible principles
and apply them.
And we discussed
how to train
our power of reason
with the three skills:
illustrating,
analyzing,
and balancing.
So no matter what decisions
you are faced with,
we encourage you:
“Let Bible principles guide you.”