Welcome to JW Broadcasting!
On our program for this month,
we’ll hear the experience
of Brother Jim Brown.
He studied the Bible with Jehovah’s Witnesses
off and on for 30 years!
What motivated him to make changes
and dedicate his life to Jehovah?
When serious problems arise in marriage,
how will Bible principles help you?
The candid and heartfelt interviews
with these couples
will show how the Bible
saved their marriages.
It’s important for youths to develop
good spiritual habits early.
How can teenagers get the most
out of their daily Bible reading?
We have a lot to look forward to
on the April 2018 edition
of JW Broadcasting.
As God’s Word touches
the heart of a Bible student,
they may need to make significant changes
to live by Jehovah’s standards.
We start our program with just such a story.
Meet Jim Brown,
a brother from Key Largo, Florida,
in the United States.
Before becoming one of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
he was on a dangerous path
of vice and violence.
What changes did he have to make
on the road to true worship?
I’m 53 years old.
I was known as a troublemaker.
I was fighting in the bars.
It comes to a point to where
you begin to enjoy it.
He was flat-out scary.
He was a very mean and violent man,
so everybody
kind of kept their distance from him.
My language was detestable.
I would make grown men blush
by the things that I would say
and things that I would do.
I was involved with some bikers,
and they were trying to prospect me
into getting into their club.
Things were escalating.
We got married very young,
and we were 17.
And we had my oldest daughter.
I was the mom,
and he lived a life
of being out with his friends
and partying.
About that time, my wife started studying
the Bible with Jehovah’s Witnesses.
It was a big change for her,
but she explained the reasoning behind it.
I couldn’t argue with it.
She talked me into studying.
I studied from 20 years old to 30.
I had always seen it.
I had always seen that it was good.
I knew that this was where I needed to be.
Somehow, I just could never break free
of the person that I was.
My mom always raised us in the truth,
growing up, and that’s what we knew.
So, then, to see my dad,
where he was so different
but yet believed it to be the truth,
and then to see that his lifestyle
didn’t do him any good
was kind of a good example
of a bad example, if that makes sense.
I was afraid of the change.
People accepted me for who I was,
being the tough guy, being Jimmy Brown.
The scripture comes to mind:
“I planted, Apollos watered,
but God kept making it grow.”
Many brothers have studied with Jim
from time to time over the years.
I just happened to be the one
at the time in his life
when he was taking the truth
and running with it.
I wanted to be a better person.
I truly knew that this was just
not the way of life that I wanted anymore.
He changed his friends;
he changed his life;
he changed his dress and grooming;
he changed his speech patterns;
he changed the way he was a grandfather;
he changed the way he was a father;
he changed the way he was a husband.
Everything changed about him.
I knew the work that Witnesses do
—going out door to door talking to people.
I thought I could never do that.
Whoa!
Me, going door to door?
I’m going to run into people that I know,
that I drank with for years and years.
How can I face them now?
I had always told my wife,
“It would be much easier for me
to become a Witness if I didn’t live here.”
But how wrong I was
because what a witness my changes have been
to so many people in town.
One of my favorite things to do
is bridge witnessing with my granddaughter.
People are fishing on the bridge
—some have been there all night.
I even have return visits that I do
because people regularly
come down on the weekend
to fish on the bridges.
I seize every opportunity.
My kids laugh at me.
He’ll witness to anybody, anytime, anywhere.
You’ll see some raggedy-taggedy,
old, rough guy
that he knew
and brought to the Kingdom Hall.
In a few weeks,
he’s got a new suit on,
got a haircut,
clean-shaven, and just—
This is the effect he has on the people
that he comes in contact with.
I love life now.
I have true friends.
I know that I have hope for the future.
Jehovah has seen something in me,
and he’s brought it to light
that I am a good person.
I can be a good human being;
I can help other people;
I can be loved by Him.
It’s priceless.
Are you a Bible student who is undecided
on whether to “commit your way to Jehovah”?
Take note of the trust and confidence
Brother Brown showed
in dedicating his life to God.
Be assured that Jehovah
will guide and care for us
if we give him the opportunity.
Brother Brown now enjoys the blessing
of living under Jehovah’s protection,
serving as a ministerial servant
and regular pioneer.
You too can experience
Jehovah’s spiritual protection,
as we’ll learn throughout our program.
The theme of our broadcast
is a very comforting one:
“Being ‘Securely Wrapped
in the Bag of Life With Jehovah.’”
Perhaps the thought
of being securely wrapped
makes us think of a safely swaddled baby
or of being enveloped
in a warm blanket on a cold night.
In the Bible, these words
were uttered by the woman Abigail
to Jehovah’s servant David.
To understand the meaning of the words
and their importance today,
let’s review the context
of 1 Samuel chapter 25.
David and 600 of his men
were dwelling as fugitives.
They eventually encountered men
who worked as shepherds
for Abigail’s husband, Nabal.
David and his men began
to help guard Nabal’s flocks
and serve as “a protective wall”
for Nabal’s flocks and servants
against thieves and invaders
who roamed through the wilderness.
It was likely challenging
to find enough food for 600 soldiers,
so David decided to send ten of his men
to kindly ask Nabal for food
in repayment for the services
that they had performed.
But at 1 Samuel 25:10, 11,
note Nabal’s reply:
“Nabal answered David’s servants:
“‘Who is David, and who is the son of Jesse?
“‘Nowadays many servants
are breaking away from their masters.
“‘Do I have to take my bread and my water
“‘and the meat
that I butchered for my shearers
and give it to men who come
from who knows where?’”
This was not the response that David
and his men were expecting to hear.
The Bible describes Nabal
as a very harsh, worthless man,
and this is certainly evidenced by his reply.
“He screamed insults”
at the messengers and ridiculed David,
comparing him to a runaway servant.
So David decided
to take matters into his own hands
and resolve the situation
the way many people today might
—by fighting.
In verse 13,
he has 400 of his men
prepare themselves for battle,
with one mission
—to wipe out every male
in Nabal’s household.
Eventually, word got back to Abigail
about what her husband had done.
Without telling Nabal,
she gathered an abundance of food
and went out to meet David.
When she met up with him,
she poured out her heart at length,
asking David to forgive her personally
and making a powerful plea for mercy
on behalf of her husband and her household.
She acknowledged that Nabal
was a foolish and senseless man,
so she urged David not to take any action
that might bring bloodguilt upon him
or cause him to be affected
by a troubled conscience.
As Abigail concluded her appeal to David,
notice what she tells him in verse 29,
the theme of our discussion:
“When someone rises up
to pursue you and seeks your life,
“the life of my lord will be wrapped securely
“in the bag of life with Jehovah your God,
“but the lives of your enemies
he will hurl away like stones from a sling.”
Just as we might wrap up something valuable
in order to protect and preserve it,
Abigail was telling David
that that is how his life
would be in Jehovah’s hands.
Jehovah would protect and preserve
David’s life from his enemies
as long as he did not seek
to save himself by personal efforts
but waited on Jehovah,
trusting in the One to whom he owed his life.
What lessons can we learn from this account?
As David saw, his relationship
with Jehovah was a protection.
In verse 32, he acknowledges
that God had sent Abigail with the warning.
We learn
that Jehovah’s spiritual protection for us
is related to the quality
of our relationship with him.
That’s why the Bible tells us at James 4:8:
“Draw close to God,
and he will draw close to you.”
Jehovah invites us to draw near to him
because he wants to receive us
into his favor as his friends.
When we dedicate our lives
and vow to serve him unconditionally,
we gain an approved standing with him;
we’re figuratively put in that “bag of life.”
And as we work to develop
a close personal relationship with him,
then we can experience
Jehovah’s friendship and protection.
We would never want
to restrict Jehovah’s protection
by not looking to him for guidance
or relying on our own thinking.
Now, can we think of areas or situations
that might require us to wait on Jehovah?
Perhaps we’re experiencing
literal opposition at work or at school.
Like Abigail, we might face the challenge
of living with a difficult marriage mate.
Maybe we’re battling a health issue
and loyalty is needed
regarding our medical choices.
Or it may be that we live in a country
where we cannot preach freely
or that we face opposition for our beliefs.
Really, it could be any number of situations.
But it is our response
—the way we handle the situation—
that indicates how much
we are allowing Jehovah to help us.
Do we trust him enough
that we can leave the matter in his hands
and see how he works
things out in our behalf?
We have to manifest
Christian qualities in order to do that.
Think about what qualities displayed
by Abigail and David impress you most.
Two that come to mind
are patience and reasonableness.
Patience is closely connected with endurance
and enables one to put up
with difficult circumstances
while maintaining a positive attitude.
Reasonableness describes
a person who is fair,
considerate, willing to yield to others.
How well this describes Abigail!
It must have been quite a challenge
to live with someone like Nabal.
But nowhere do we read
that she was ever disrespectful of him
or that she belittled him.
Even when she referred to him
as senseless in verse 25,
from Jehovah’s standpoint,
her comments were proper
because Nabal’s actions
put his entire household in danger.
How about David?
He was in a position of authority,
but he showed great patience
and reasonableness in listening to Abigail
and having the good sense
to know that she was right.
That’s not always easy to do
in the heat of the moment
or when we’re upset.
Perhaps you recall that at our
“Don’t Give Up!”
Regional Convention last year,
when discussing 2 Peter 1:5-8,
we learned a nice formula
that can help us
to cultivate and strengthen
Christian qualities.
We were encouraged to study them,
meditate on them,
and put them into practice.
If we apply this formula
with the qualities
of patience and reasonableness,
it can help us to endure
our trials successfully.
And we’re confident
that Jehovah will supply us
with whatever power we need
so that we will not tire out
as we continue to endure
and put our trust in him.
In addition to developing these qualities,
something else that can help us
is our spiritual routine.
Our consistent routine
of study, meeting attendance,
and the ministry will help us remain busy,
stay active, and make good decisions.
We’ll have no time
to become curious or occupied
with the things this world has to offer.
It’s good to remember
the people during the days of Haggai.
When the Jews lost their focus
and started neglecting Jehovah’s temple,
they lost his blessing
and protection spiritually.
And what was the result?
Well, notice how Haggai draws our attention
to a different type of “bag”
at Haggai 1:6:
“You have sown much seed,
but you harvest little.
“You eat, but it is not to satisfaction.
“You drink, but you do not drink your fill.
“You put on clothing, but no one gets warm.
“The one who hires himself out puts his wages
in a bag full of holes.”
The Jews sowed seed
but had a meager harvest.
They lacked enough food
to satisfy their needs.
They were unable to clothe
themselves with warm garments.
Because Jehovah withheld his blessings,
Haggai rightly compared them to a man
who “puts his wages in a bag full of holes.”
Imagine the disappointment
of discovering that hard-earned wages
had gradually disappeared
through a leaking bag!
Of course,
our focus is not material prosperity,
because, whether we have
an abundance of material things or not,
if we fail to receive Jehovah’s blessing,
our spirituality is jeopardized.
So we must be determined
never to lose our focus
and keep Jehovah
in the forefront of our lives.
When we examine the life of David,
it’s evident that he enjoyed
a preserved and protected
relationship with God.
When you read the book of Psalms,
take note of how David
describes Jehovah’s protective care
in Psalm 18,
Psalm 31, and Psalm 34
as he went through distresses
—just beautiful accounts!
Now, did David always do
everything the right way?
No.
Think of his encounter with Nabal.
While his angry reaction was understandable,
his way of expressing it was not correct.
But David learned from his mistakes,
and each new trial that he went through
strengthened his relationship
with Jehovah even more.
For example,
after the ordeal with Nabal,
a short time later,
David married Abigail.
They were still fugitives,
but he found a king that befriended them,
and he gave David’s men
and family a land to dwell in.
One day, while all the men were away,
the Amalekites raided and burned the city
and carried off all the men’s wives,
children, and flocks.
Upon returning
and seeing what had happened,
David and his men wept.
Grief quickly turned to bitterness,
and David’s men spoke of stoning him.
This was likely quite stressful for David.
He was concerned
for the safety of his family,
and likely he was frustrated
that his men had turned on him.
Maybe he felt disrespected again,
as he had with Nabal.
So how would he handle this situation?
We get a glimpse of David’s feelings
at 1 Samuel 30:6:
“David was very distressed,
“because the men were talking of stoning him,
“for all the men had become very bitter
over the loss of their sons and daughters.”
But notice,
how did David handle the situation?
The verse continues:
“But David strengthened himself
by Jehovah his God.”
How did he do this?
Verse 8 says:
“David inquired of Jehovah.”
This time, David has
a different thought process and response.
Immediately he remembers
to consult Jehovah.
Isn’t this a nice reminder
that when you and I are going
through difficult trials and situations,
we want to immediately pray to Jehovah
and seek his direction
through the pages of his Word, the Bible?
This is essential
for our spiritual protection.
So in review,
as we face difficult situations in life,
may we look for opportunities
to show and develop our Christian qualities
—such as patience and reasonableness.
These qualities show Jehovah
that we want to be like him,
that we have
the mental disposition of Christ,
and that we will allow Him
to guide us constantly.
Next, may we keep focused and busy
“in the work of the Lord.”
By drawing close to Jehovah through prayer
and engaging in spiritual activities,
we make the best of our situation now.
But we will also find
everlasting protection in Jehovah’s hands,
safely swaddled
and securely wrapped in his “bag of life”!
We need to rely on Jehovah’s guidance
even in the most severe trials.
It’s possible that you
may face a life-threatening issue
where there’s no desirable option,
but a decision is necessary.
In the following dramatization,
Emma is faced with a situation like this.
What will she do?
And how will God’s Word
help her to make a decision?
When Thomas and I first learned
I was pregnant,
we were both really shocked.
But then we grew more and more excited.
And we were so thrilled when we saw
our little girl for the first time.
We really didn’t care
if it was a boy or a girl;
we just wanted the baby to be healthy.
Unfortunately, our hopes
were completely destroyed
when the doctor told us
that the baby would likely be born
with severe problems and could even die.
My husband and his parents
are not Jehovah’s Witnesses,
but they do feel abortion is wrong.
Still, they thought that we should listen
to our doctor’s advice.
I couldn’t believe this was happening.
I even questioned why Jehovah would allow it.
I really felt it was more than I could bear.
Thomas asked me what I wanted to do,
and I told him
that I could never have an abortion.
He agreed that normally it would be wrong
but felt that in our situation
God would understand.
I was so overwhelmed.
I was being pressured
to make a decision I knew was wrong
but that everyone
was telling me was best for my child.
I had never felt so alone.
I needed Jehovah more than ever,
so I poured out my heart to him in prayer.
And then I did research.
I showed Thomas the scripture I had found.
“If men should struggle with each other
“and they hurt a pregnant woman
“. . . if a fatality does occur,
then you must give life for life.”
Jehovah views even the unintentional killing
of an unborn child as a serious sin.
So how could we intentionally take
the life of our child?
I made my decision clear to our doctor
and to my in-laws.
There was a chance
the diagnosis was incorrect,
and I’d love to say that’s what occurred;
but it did not.
My daughter Chloe only lived
a few weeks after she was born,
and losing her was the hardest thing
I’ve ever had to endure.
But Jehovah gave me the courage
to explain my beliefs to my husband,
my in-laws, and the medical staff,
and they all expressed admiration
for my strong faith.
And I’ve never regretted the decision I made.
Even though Chloe only lived those few weeks,
I’m so grateful for the time I had with her.
I know Jehovah remembers
every detail about her,
and he’ll give her back to me
in the resurrection in perfect health,
because all life
is truly precious in his eyes.
Getting Jehovah’s thinking on a matter
should be the first thing
we do when making decisions.
This is especially true
when well-intentioned friends or family
offer advice that may conflict
with Bible principles.
As we weigh a variety of options,
follow Emma’s good example
of consulting God’s Word
and our Christian publications.
This will help us make decisions
that bring honor to Jehovah.
Emma’s Christian conduct
helped her to navigate
a potentially divisive moment
in her marriage.
But unfortunately,
this system of things and our imperfect flesh
can create extreme tension in a marriage.
Can the Bible save
a marriage that’s in danger?
The following interviews,
while very frank,
will show the exceeding value
of God’s own Word, the Bible,
to preserve that divine union.
Almost from the start of the marriage,
it was not running smoothly,
to say the least.
We were fighting constantly.
Even the smallest things
we would argue over,
and it would just get blown
out of proportion.
We couldn’t communicate
without it being an argument.
Steadily the arguments increased
in frequency and intensity.
And you think, ‘Well, I’m not happy here,’
and that’s when I threatened to leave.
Sometimes I felt
like completely giving up on the marriage.
There would be arguments
where you’d be packing the bags
and saying you’d wished you’d never done it.
And ultimately it would end in insults.
Jehovah was missing in our marriage,
and that was the essential part
of making our marriage work.
A brother and sister
that we’d known for a long time
initially offered us a Bible study.
They invited us
to their Family Worship evening
to have dinner
and to do The Watchtower with them,
which we accepted.
The Family Worship arrangement helped
because it wasn’t just Bible principles
that you read about,
but we saw them being applied
in this couple’s life.
And so all of a sudden,
I could see the cause and effect
of a Bible principle.
But the impact
that it was having was tremendous
because we could see how to apply
a Bible principle and make it work.
I think it took a long time
before things got better, honestly,
but the turning point
was coming back to Jehovah.
There were many principles
that all of a sudden
were like little light bulbs going off,
such as Jesus at John 13:34
when he recommended his example.
Ephesians 5:33
eventually had an impact on me,
because there were articles that pointed out
how important it is for a husband
to feel respected by his wife,
and I don’t think
I’d ever really appreciated that before.
I just viewed it as a mechanical process:
He’s the head;
he needs to have respect from his wife.
I didn’t recognize that it’s important
for a husband to feel respected
to be able to take on his role as head.
We’re so thankful
to Jehovah for his patience.
The Bible principles were always there;
we just weren’t making application of them.
As soon as we started to make application,
our marriage did a complete turnaround.
Where we are now is totally different.
The relationship that we have
is what we wanted at the start
but didn’t know how to get.
It’s just that application
of Bible principles
that has made it possible.
We were 17, actually, when we met
and 20 when we got married.
Life was good for Tony and me;
we were happy.
But then I got into another business
that became the main focus in my life.
It had quite a dramatic effect
on our spirituality.
We went through a time
when we hardly saw each other,
so there was a great deal
of time that we spent apart.
Bible principles were ones
that weren’t brought into our life.
At that time,
Bible reading was out of the picture.
I started delving into viewing things
that were really, really inappropriate.
And then it eventually happened
where I didn’t really care what I viewed,
and I didn’t think about the consequences
and of the unhappiness that it would cause.
It made me feel very, extremely, unloved.
I felt very angry about his behavior.
I felt a lot of resentment
towards him, a lot of bitterness.
We ended up in separation, to begin with.
I left Tony; I walked away from him.
I walked away from the marriage,
walked away from the business
and, eventually,
ended up unscripturally divorcing Tony.
The elders who were assisting me
helped me to see exactly how Jehovah felt
about what I’d been doing
and where my relationship was with him,
and it was quite poor.
I felt that because of the betrayal
that I had experienced,
I did not have a problem with my conscience
at all in going through the divorce.
It seemed the logical
and best way for me to go.
With my Bible reading,
I got to see Amos 5:15.
It really had an effect on me
because I needed to “hate what is bad,
and love what is good.”
One scripture that affected me
was from Malachi
about how Jehovah felt about divorce.
Altogether, it took us 15 years
before we got together again.
I was just enjoying
a day out in the field midweek,
and I got home in mid-afternoon.
And all of a sudden, my mobile phone rang,
and I heard Rhonda’s voice.
What a delight it was
that she was inviting me
to accompany her
for a cup of coffee somewhere
to talk about things!
If I hadn’t started
having a Scriptural intake
and learning to love God’s Word,
my life wouldn’t have changed.
Without the Bible,
Tony and I would not be together.
The marriage
would never ever have reconciled.
We have become best friends,
so we really enjoy
being in each other’s company
and serving Jehovah together.
Our married life now has certainly benefited
by both of us seeing
how beneficial the Scriptures are.
Tony and I are now very much a couple,
and so no matter what we deal with,
it’s us together.
When situations like these arise,
it’s not just our marriage that’s affected.
Our relationship with Jehovah is on the line!
Our dear sister, for example,
reached an emotional point
where she felt the only solution
was an unscriptural divorce.
As we make our decisions in marriage,
Jehovah’s feelings on the subject,
found at Malachi 2:16,
should be carefully considered:
“‘For I hate divorce,’
says Jehovah the God of Israel.”
If you find your marital peace is threatened,
review articles like the one
in the May 15, 2012, study edition
of The Watchtower entitled
“Take a Positive View
of a Strained Marriage.”
It provides powerful counsel that can help
to save and strengthen your marriage bond.
In our program, we’ve seen a few ways
that Satan will exert pressure on those
‘securely wrapped in the bag of life.’
True Christians
courageously stand up to the Devil,
never allowing him to pry us
away from Jehovah’s protection.
At a recent Bethel morning worship,
Brother Mark Sanderson
of the Governing Body discussed 1 Peter 5:9
and outlined how we take
our stand against Satan.
Is it possible to survive
the attack of a roaring lion?
Well, now, I did some
—just quick—checking
on various wildlife websites,
and here’s what they say.
Basically,
they all give the same advice
if you’re being attacked by a lion.
They say: “Hold your ground.
Never run or turn back.”
In fact, one website says:
“A lion can run 50 miles per hour (80 km/h).
“So stand still.
If you run, you will only die tired.”
Well, that’s true.
First Peter 5:9
gives us exactly the same advice.
It says: “Take your stand against him.”
Well, in this case
not against a literal lion,
but against that “roaring lion,”
Satan the Devil,
who is seeking to devour
every single one of us.
Our ability to stand firm
when facing this lion
—to be able to oppose him,
to refuse to be intimidated by him,
to refuse to run away or turn back—
requires what the apostle Peter
next mentions there in verse 9,
and Brother Crane
so nicely covered in his comment.
We have to: “Take [our] stand against him,
firm in the faith.”
To be successful,
we must have complete trust
and complete confidence in Jehovah.
Well, now, in that regard,
let’s look at an example
of someone in Bible times who had
that kind of confidence in Jehovah.
This is in the days of King Jehoshaphat,
when Judah was threatened
by the combined forces
of Moab, Ammon,
and the inhabitants
of the mountainous region of Seir.
Now let’s begin by opening our Bibles
and reading 2 Chronicles 20:12.
So here Jehoshaphat is praying to Jehovah;
he’s pouring out his heart to him,
and see what he says:
“O our God,
will you not execute judgment on them?
“For we are powerless before this large crowd
“that is coming against us;
“and we do not know what we should do,
but our eyes are toward you.”
Well, Jehoshaphat was facing the lion.
He said to Jehovah:
‘We don’t know what to do.’
But Jehoshaphat had complete and total trust;
he had firm faith in Jehovah.
Well, what did Jehovah
tell Jehoshaphat to do?
See verse 17:
“You will not need to fight this battle.
Take your position.”
Does that sound familiar?
“Take your position, stand still,
“and see the salvation of Jehovah
in your behalf.
“O Judah and Jerusalem,
“do not be afraid or be terrified.
“Tomorrow go out against them,
and Jehovah will be with you.”
Well, what did Jehovah tell them to do?
He said: ‘Take a position
in opposition to that military force,
‘stand firm, refuse to run away,
and see the salvation
that will come from Jehovah.’
Well, in order to do that,
Jehoshaphat and the people with him
would need to have strong, firm, solid faith.
Well, now, to help the people,
look at what Jehoshaphat said to them
as they were getting ready for this battle.
In verse 20, you see,
just about the middle of the verse,
it says:
“Jehoshaphat stood up and said:
“‘Listen to me, O Judah
and you inhabitants of Jerusalem!
“‘Put faith in Jehovah your God
“‘so that you may be able to stand firm.
“‘Put faith in his prophets,
and you will be successful.’”
Well, that’s exactly what happened.
See, with that kind of confidence in Jehovah,
with that firm trust in him,
with that standing firm,
what did Jehovah do?
Well, according to verses 22 and 23
—you’ll remember what happened—
the men of Ammon, Moab,
and the inhabitants
of the mountainous region of Seir,
they all went to striking down one another.
And verse 23 says:
“And the Ammonites and the Moabites
“turned against the inhabitants
of the mountainous region of Seir
“to destroy and annihilate them;
“and when they finished
with the inhabitants of Seir,
they helped to destroy one another.”
Well, Jehovah had rewarded
their firm faith in him.
The weapons that had been formed
against Jehoshaphat and his people
had no success.
Well, now,
sometimes we think, of course,
that these kinds of situations
only happened in Bible times.
But it’s amazing to see
how our brothers in our modern day
have had that same kind of faith
and have stood firm against the lion.
Here are just a couple of experiences
that really touched my heart.
Here’s one about a brother
named Pavel from Russia.
In 1958,
Pavel was arrested for religious activities.
“Accompanying me to the train,” he says,
“the officer [with me] said,
“‘Look at your wife for the last time
because you will never see her again.’”
Well, there’s the lion.
“I spent six months
in solitary confinement before my trial.
“During interrogations, . . .
the investigators did everything
“to undermine my faith.
“Sometimes violence was used.
I begged Jehovah
to give me the strength to stay firm.”
But now look what happened.
“During a routine interrogation,
“the investigator called me
into his study and [he] said:
“‘Now we will show you
what your organization is doing.
“Then you can see
if it is God’s work or not!’
“Looking at me intently, he continued:
“‘This year your convention in New York
“‘was attended by 253,000 people
“‘in two stadiums.
“The convention lasted eight days.’
“The investigator strewed
the table with photographs.
“In one of them,
I saw happy delegates
“in colorful native dress
embracing one another.
“Another photo showed
Brother Knorr giving a talk,
“and yet others showed the baptism.
“The investigator could not even imagine
“what I was feeling at that moment.
“I felt that I was attending the convention
“without ever having left the prison.
“I felt new strength flooding into me.
“[It was just what] I had needed.
“. . . And Jehovah generously
blessed me in a special way.
I was ready to endure further.”
Isn’t that amazing?
Here’s another similar experience,
1960, also in Russia,
a large publicized trial
of Jehovah’s Witnesses.
About 300 persons
were present in the courtroom,
including many of our brothers and sisters.
Well, as the evidence—
As evidence against the brothers,
the prosecutor decided to present
a letter from Nathan H. Knorr.
One of the brothers
who attended the trial said this:
“The prosecutor loudly began to read a letter
“that had been intercepted by the KGB
“from Brother Knorr
to the brothers in the Soviet Union.
“For all of us Witnesses present in the hall,
“it was a wonderful gift from Jehovah.
“This letter warmed our hearts!
“We heard wise counsel from the Bible
“and encouragement to serve
our fellow believers lovingly
“and to stay faithful [even] under trials.
“The prosecutor read the letter
“from the beginning to the very end.
“We listened with rapt attention.
It seemed to us that we were
attending a convention!”
Well, now, brothers, what additional lessons
do we learn from these two experiences?
When we stand our ground against Satan,
firm in the faith,
then Jehovah will do just what he promised
at 1 Peter 5:10.
Do you see what it says there?
“But after you have suffered a little while,
“the God of all undeserved kindness,
“who called you to his everlasting glory
in union with Christ,
“will himself finish your training.
“He will make you firm,
“he will make you strong,
he will firmly ground you.”
So, brothers,
can we survive the attack of a roaring lion?
Absolutely!
With firm faith, let’s stand fast
and see the salvation from Jehovah.
Firm faith is needed to resist
the relentless attacks of Satan the Devil.
The modern-day examples brought out
in the presentation are truly inspiring.
However,
did you notice that Brother Sanderson
also applied
the Biblical example of Jehoshaphat?
The Bible is full of accounts that can revive
and renew our courage
every time we read them.
But here’s a question:
When should we develop the type of faith
that can resist the attack
of “a roaring lion”?
Is it something
only longtime servants of Jehovah can do?
Ecclesiastes 12:1 says
to “remember, then, your Grand Creator
in the days of your youth.”
Young ones,
do you find it a challenge
to read the Bible every day?
A few of your peers
have excellent suggestions
based on how they do their Bible reading
and how they get the most benefit from it.
I often put it off until later.
So I come home in the evening tired,
and I like to relax.
Well, very often,
I was tired for many different reasons,
and that is why I didn’t have the motivation
even to start Bible reading
in the first place.
I also had many phases
where it was really tough
to stick it out with Bible reading.
Especially in the age of social media,
there are many other things
you can fill your day with.
One hobby that mainly got in the way
was watching movies.
I really spent a lot of time on that.
This often steals precious time
you could have made better use of.
So something that moved me
was the thought that through Bible reading,
you’re actually talking with Jehovah.
You pray to him, and he
is then answering you through the Bible.
As Jehovah promised, he can give us
both the power and the desire to act.
I just pray to Jehovah, please,
to first give me the power to read
and then the desire follows.
Then I decided
to simply start and stick with it.
I started with reading my favorite book,
and that way it was easier for me.
Well, I started with Genesis
just to get through the whole Bible.
My favorite Bible book is Esther.
And because I think
she was a very special person,
it was especially then that I could imagine
what her situation was like
and what kind of a person she was
and I could see myself in the account.
The weekly Bible reading program
has been such a guideline.
It’s motivating since we discuss
this content at the meetings,
and I could use the study aids
in our workbook too.
You can better relate
to the brothers’ and sisters’ comments
because you’ve read the material yourself,
and I can comment too.
When I’m reading the Bible
in the JW Library app on my phone,
there is, of course,
the risk that it vibrates,
and I get a message.
And then, of course, you have the urge
to check to see who just wrote me.
For me personally, then, it’s really helpful
when I put my phone in airplane mode
so that I can really focus
on what I’m reading
and nothing can distract me.
I like reading at home,
but I also like to do it outdoors
because I think that’s
where you’re closest to Jehovah.
I never just read about the events
that are described in the Bible,
but I ask myself questions like:
‘Why did Jehovah have this written down?
What is in there for me personally?’
This helps me to stay focused
and not just scratch the surface;
otherwise, my mind
would immediately start wandering.
At a convention,
I learned something that helps me
to really take in the things I read.
The point discussed
was to remember to look
in four different directions
when meditating, so to speak.
First, look upwards
to find out exactly what I am learning
from the text about Jehovah;
then downwards to find out
what it teaches me about his purpose,
about what he wants for the earth;
then look at myself,
how I can personally benefit now;
and eventually towards others,
thinking about how I can help other people
with this particular Bible text.
In the JW Library app, there are
four different colors for highlighting text,
so I simply use a different color
for each of the four directions
and highlight them
on my tablet or smartphone.
For example, one of my hobbies is drawing.
I decided, one time,
that I was going to draw
the spiritual suit of armor,
all of its different parts
and their symbolic meanings.
And this especially helped me
to actually see the benefit of it,
to see how many wonderful resources
Jehovah provides us with
and that he never leaves us alone.
Another thing
I like very much is the category
“Bible Study Activities”
where you can directly pick a topic
that you personally find interesting
and then read that.
It’s Jehovah’s Word.
I love him and also want
to please him, of course.
That’s why it’s very important
to understand his Word.
It feels really good when you’ve understood
a difficult phrase by doing it this way.
It actually makes you feel
like you’ve achieved something,
and this brings you a lot closer to Jehovah.
It happens often that you don’t even know
what you should pray about
or what you could thank Jehovah for.
My personal Bible reading
has helped me with this a lot
because now I know exactly
what I want to tell Jehovah.
Daily Bible reading is very important to me
as it gives me some sort
of inner balance when I face situations
that may be unfamiliar or shake me up.
I know that no matter what the problem is,
Jehovah always has the right answer prepared.
At the beginning, it is really hard.
You have to fight to keep it up,
and you definitely need discipline.
But after a while,
you truly start to enjoy it
and it gets easier and easier
and you’re happy
that you started in the first place.
I really think that when Jehovah sees
how much effort you put into it,
he is genuinely proud of you,
and that’s the best thing
that can happen to you.
These young brothers and sisters
didn’t just acquire knowledge;
they drew closer to Jehovah.
This will help them build
a fine foundation for their future,
and you can too.
It may not be easy at first,
but as one young brother suggested,
start with something
that captures your interest.
Try using the JW Library app
or a handy notebook
to keep track of points you hope
to apply or discuss at family worship.
This will make it
a part of your daily routine
that you look forward to.
Each segment
in the program has highlighted
some way we can build
a strong relationship with God.
Our music video depicts the joy of marriage,
where Jehovah is part of a threefold cord
—one that cannot quickly be torn apart.
The song is called “Truly in Love.”
There is a gift that comes from above,
A lovely gift called being in love.
When two hearts begin to beat as one,
Then a wonderful time has begun.
It’s simple, so easy.
And it’s something we know.
With a threefold cord,
Love will grow.
With Jehovah to guide us in all that we do,
How I love to be truly in love
With someone like you,
Someone like you.
Trials will come our way,
But our love will grow stronger each day.
We will build a bond that no one can break.
We will build a love that no one will take.
No, no, no one, no.
It’s simple, so easy.
And it’s something we know.
With a threefold cord,
Love will grow.
With Jehovah to guide us in all that we do,
How I love to be truly in love
With someone like you,
Someone like you.
Nothing can destroy our love.
This precious gift is from our God up above.
Exclusive devotion​
—‘love’s as strong as death.’
You are “bone of my bones”;
you are “flesh of my flesh,”
Such an excellent woman in all that you do.
I will spend all my life loving you.
I want you to know how I feel
’Cause my love for you is so very real.
I bless the day you came into my life.
I bless the day I made you my wife.
Yes, I do.
It’s simple, so easy.
And it’s something we know.
With a threefold cord,
Love will grow.
With Jehovah to guide us in all that we do,
How I love to be truly in love
With someone like you,
Someone like you.
How I love to be truly in love
With someone like you.
So many of our brothers and sisters
can agree with the words of that song:
“With a threefold cord, love will grow.”
In marriage, in youth,
really, in all things we’ve considered,
Jehovah will be there to guide us.
What will be the result?
We’ll find the warmth and security
of being securely wrapped
in Jehovah’s “bag of life.”
We hope you enjoyed our program.
We conclude by heading
to the beautiful tropical island
of Sri Lanka,
off the southeast coast
of India in the Indian Ocean.
Over 6,000 publishers
make up the 112 congregations on the island,
including 13 isolated groups.
As you travel throughout the country,
the scars of the decades-long civil war
are still evident.
However, our brothers and sisters display
the beautiful spirit of Christian unity.
Publishers preach the good news
to those on the coast,
high in the mountains,
and in the bustling cities.
More than 8,000 Bible studies
are being conducted,
and over 650 brothers and sisters
are in the pioneer work.
Because of the dense population
in the city of Colombo,
those in metropolitan witnessing
see an average of almost 17,000 people
in just one 8-hour period.
High in Sri Lanka’s tea mountains
is a small congregation
in the town of Badulla.
Their productive ministry takes them
into banana plantations,
jungles, and mountain tea estates
as they search
for those receptive to the good news.
Despite differing ethnic backgrounds,
they’re completely united
in worship and brotherly affection.
Our brothers and sisters
who are wrapped up
in Jehovah’s “bag of life”
send you their warm love and greetings
from the mountaintops of Sri Lanka!
Thank you for watching.
From the world headquarters
of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
this is JW Broadcasting.