These were very practical comments.
And they all tie in well
with what the apostle Paul was trying to tell
those in the Ephesian congregation
about examining themselves.
The same way we have to do today
—examining ourselves
so that we please Jehovah.
If you’d like,
please open up to Ephesians chapter 5,
and we’ll read verse 10,
which is our theme scripture.
Ephesians 5:10, it says:
“Keep on making sure
of what is acceptable to the Lord.”
And then it goes on in verse 11:
“And stop sharing in the unfruitful works
that belong to the darkness;
rather, expose them for what they are.”
So it’s very clear to us,
in this chapter of Ephesians chapter 5,
that there are things
that Jehovah views as acceptable
and things he views as unacceptable.
Jehovah’s standard of what is unacceptable
is outlined in quite a few
of the verses in chapter 5 here.
If you would just scan
through verses 3, 4, and 5,
we’ll see that unwholesome talk about sex,
shameful conduct, obscene jesting
—and then verse 18, drunkenness—
well, these are things
that will bar us from God’s Kingdom.
When you think
about entertainment today,
it’s nearly impossible
to try to find something
that is acceptable to Jehovah
that does not have
immoral sex, pornography,
spiritism, and violence.
Satan has thoroughly saturated
all forms of the media.
So thoroughly,
that it’s in our literature,
it’s in movies,
it’s in electronic games,
and everything that we
can think of Satan has infiltrated.
Yes, he knows that Jehovah
hates these things,
and he doesn’t mind if part of our heart
hates these things
as long as part of our heart
loves these things.
So we do well to ask ourselves:
‘Does the entertainment that I choose help me
‘in my being acceptable to Jehovah?
‘Does it help me to have the qualities
‘that Jehovah endears in me,
and will he draw closer to me?’
Well, the spirit of the world
reflects rebellion of the Bible,
which outlines
Jehovah’s qualities and his standards.
We want to show respect for the Bible,
which teaches us
to love what Jehovah loves
and hate what he hates.
And what will help us to do this
and resist the spirit of the world
and draw closer to Jehovah
and be acceptable to him?
Let’s notice verse 17,
chapter 5 and verse 17, it says:
“On this account stop being unreasonable,
but keep perceiving
what the will of Jehovah is.”
We need to constantly think:
‘What would Jehovah want me to do?’
Well, verse 1 and verse 2
help us to appreciate this, it says:
“Become imitators of God,
as beloved children,
“and go on walking in love,
just as the Christ also loved us
“and [he] gave himself [up]
for us as an offering
and a sacrifice,
a sweet fragrance to God.”
So, bottom line,
we need to imitate Jehovah and Jesus.
Our sacrifices need to be
acceptable to Jehovah
as was Jesus’.
What made Jesus so pleasing?
Well, he did everything
the way Jehovah wanted him to do.
In fact, he said something
that we want to say one day:
“I always do the things pleasing to him.”
And one day in perfection,
we will be able to say that.
Jesus was pleasing
in his word, in his deed, in his actions.
Well, how can we imitate Jesus
and thus imitate Jehovah?
Well, let’s briefly discuss three ways.
First: Pray for God’s holy spirit.
When confronted with trials,
what did Jesus do?
He did not rely on himself;
he petitioned Jehovah for help.
So if we’re struggling with a temptation
—a certain fleshly weakness—
it’s vital that we do the same.
We can also talk to the elders
—our loving shepherds—
who will pray with us,
and they will definitely help us
to remain faithful
with words of encouragement.
Number two: Obey Jehovah completely.
Jesus always did things
that were pleasing to his Father.
Luke 22:42 says:
“Let, not my will, but yours take place.”
Remember,
there is no substitute for obedience.
We cannot be acceptable without obedience.
Number three: Know the Scriptures well.
Jesus used God’s Word as his authority.
His whole life revolved around knowing
and obeying and encouraging others
about God’s laws.
We all have busy schedules.
We have work to do
—busy in the congregation.
It’s more than just trying to find time
to dig deep into God’s Word;
we must make the time.
So, what do our schedules tell us
about our love for Jehovah?
our love for his Word?
Do we read the Bible daily?
And if we do,
how much time do we take
to let it sink into our mind
and our heart and to meditate?
Are we content with just looking
at the basics
—the surface—
or digging deeper and deeper
below the surface?
It’s vital that we train
our minds and our hearts,
but it takes time
and it takes effort,
just as a marathon runner
must devote much time and effort
to his training to run a race.
In fact, as we know,
Christians are likened
to running a race,
and it’s a race for life.
Let’s see
what the apostle Paul had to tell us.
If we go over to 1 Corinthians,
1 Corinthians chapter 9,
a scripture we know very well,
and we’ll start in verse 24.
And there are a few key elements
that we would like to extract
as we’re reading these verses.
Here Paul said:
“Do you not know
that the runners in a race all run,
“but only one receives the prize?
“Run in such a way that you may win it.
“Now everyone competing in a contest
“exercises self-control in all things
[there’s a key].
“Of course, they do it
to receive a crown that can perish,
“but we, one that does not perish.
“Therefore, the way
I am running is not aimlessly;
“the way I am aiming my blows
“is so as not to be striking the air;
“but I pummel my body
“[and the footnote says,
“punish; strictly discipline”]
“and lead it as a slave,
so that after I have preached to others,
“I myself should not become disapproved
[or the footnote says, “disqualified”]
somehow.”
So we definitely want to have
self-control like a runner.
We need to say no to Satan’s world
and yes to things
that are acceptable to Jehovah.
And we definitely want
to make sure that we are acceptable
and never to be disapproved.
Perhaps we can illustrate this.
In the 1994 New York City Marathon,
there was a young man named German Silva,
and he ran an outstanding race.
In fact, there was only half a mile
to the finish line in Central Park,
and somehow he got distracted.
He took the wrong path.
Did he lose the race?
Well, the lead runner took over.
Well, he got redirected;
he went back on the path;
he began to run faster and faster.
He passed up the lead runner,
and he won the New York City Marathon
by two seconds.
What does this tell us?
It tells us that sometimes
we can lose our focus, we can be sidetracked,
or we could get involved
in unacceptable conduct.
But allow God’s Word
and loving shepherds to readjust our course.
Never give up.
Just a few years later, after that
—1997—
German began running again
in a New York City Marathon.
He thought he had this one all in the bag;
he thought he was going to win this race.
But he started to run slower.
He began to—
He dehydrated.
Instead of taking
just a few seconds to hydrate,
he skipped that.
He thought he could do it.
Well, what could this tell us?
Well, we cannot afford to take shortcuts.
We need to have
a regular intake of spiritual food
to keep pace with Jehovah’s organization.
We do this
by what the commenters told us today,
that is, a regular intake
of God’s Word and meditation.
As we run the Christian course
—the race for life—
remember, it’s not the speed,
it’s the direction
—that’s what matters the most.
And may we always run in such a way
that is acceptable to Jehovah.