During his earthly ministry,
Jesus miraculously healed
many sick or disabled persons.
At times,
he would say to such ones
the expression we find
at Matthew 9:29:
“According to your faith
let it happen to you.”
The principle of what Jesus stated
applies in every aspect
of our Christian life and ministry.
But today we will discuss how this principle
that faith in Jehovah makes things happen
can work for us in three areas.
We will see:
1) how our faith has made positive things
happen in our personal life,
2) how we can accomplish
things in God’s service
that would not be possible
without faith in Jehovah God,
and 3) how faith moves us
to step out of our comfort zone
to do more in Jehovah’s service.
The principle that faith in Jehovah
makes things happen
is well illustrated in one
of the miracles Jesus performed.
Please open your Bible to Mark chapter 5,
and let’s read verses 25-29:
“Now there was a woman
“who had had
a flow of blood for 12 years.
“She had suffered much
at the hands of many physicians
“and had spent all her resources,
“and she was no better but,
rather, had become worse.
“When she heard
the reports about Jesus,
“she came up behind him in the crowd
and touched his outer garment,
“for she kept saying:
“‘If I touch just his outer garments,
I will get well.’
“And immediately her flow
of blood dried up,
“and she sensed in her body
that she had been healed
of the grievous sickness.”
In the following verses,
Jesus asked who had touched him.
The woman then revealed
before the crowd
what she had done
and how she’d been cured.
Now notice Jesus’ response in verse 34:
“He said to her:
“‘Daughter,
your faith has made you well.
“‘Go in peace, and be healed
from your grievous sickness.’”
What comforting words
Jesus spoke to this trembling woman:
“Your faith has made you well.”
What did Jesus mean?
Let’s examine the account more closely.
It says that the woman
heard “reports about Jesus.”
Many others heard the same reports,
but not all put faith in Jesus.
And think of the circumstances
that could have prevented her
from even coming to Jesus.
She had been disappointed many times
over the past 12 years.
She might well have thought:
‘What’s the use?
‘I’m tired and weak and poor.
I’m staying home.’
Or ‘I would like for Jesus to see me,
‘but there is such a crowd.
‘How will I ever get through to him?
‘And after all,
I’m in an unclean state,
‘and if the people discover this,
perhaps they will punish me.’
No, she did not allow
these negative thoughts
or doubts to fill her mind.
She left her home.
She found Jesus
despite the large crowd.
And what was she saying?
Did she say,
“If I touch just his outer garments,
maybe I will get well”?
No, she said,
“I will get well.”
Now, it was not the case
that her faith healed her.
No, but her faith moved her
to come to Jesus,
and she was healed
by the power from Jehovah
that flowed through his Son.
Faith to approach Jesus
made it happen for her.
If you are a dedicated,
baptized Christian,
don’t you agree
that your faith has already made
positive things happen
in your personal life?
No, you were not miraculously healed
of your physical sicknesses.
We look forward
to physical healing of our ills
during the Thousand Year Reign of Christ.
But today Jesus Christ directs a program
of spiritual healing.
When we were a part
of this godless world,
many of us were sick spiritually,
morally, and emotionally.
No one could cure us.
Perhaps we desperately
tried material things or pleasures
to fill our spiritual need,
but our condition only got worse.
We were helpless and hopeless.
But then we heard “reports”
—the good news
of God’s Kingdom under Christ!
We studied the Bible.
Our faith moved us
to make positive changes in our life
and to associate
with the Christian congregation.
Today, we enjoy
good spiritual health and happiness.
Our faith has made it happen.
Faith has also made it possible
to accomplish things in God’s service
that perhaps
we never thought we could do.
Please open your Bibles
to Hebrews chapter 11.
In this portion
of Paul’s letter to the Hebrews,
he focuses on faith.
He begins with a definition of faith.
But then, starting in verse 4,
Paul acts as a sort of tour guide,
walking us through the corridor
of thousands of years of Bible history.
He stops along the way
to point out the extraordinary things
that men and women of the past did
by means of faith in Jehovah God.
Just glance down the columns
in this chapter
and notice how Paul introduces
each paragraph
with the words “by faith.”
This expression “by faith”
appears 18 times in this one chapter.
Now, when we look at the names
Paul lists in this chapter,
we may think,
‘Well, these were spiritual “giants.”’
But in reality,
they were ordinary humans
with weaknesses
like all of us have today.
The thing they all had in common
was faith,
and faith in Jehovah
made it possible
for them to do amazing things.
Let’s look at some of them
and compare what they did
with what many of you
are doing today
by faith.
Let’s read verse 5:
“By faith Enoch was transferred
“so as not to see death,
“and he was nowhere to be found
“because God had transferred him;
“for before he was transferred
“he received the witness
that he had pleased God well.”
The book of Jude, verses 14 and 15,
informs us that Enoch boldly proclaimed
that Jehovah was going to destroy
that ungodly world.
It appears that wicked, violent men
were going to take Enoch’s life
because of his bold witness.
So God chose to take him
—that is, gently cutting short his life,
sparing him the pangs of a violent death.
In modern times, like Enoch,
many brothers and sisters
have boldly declared God’s judgments
even when faced with death.
One brother,
after receiving a death sentence
at Nazi hands during World War II,
wrote these words
shortly before his execution:
“I have such peace, such tranquillity,
that you can’t possibly imagine!”
Faith made such boldness
and calmness possible.
In many ways, you very likely
have shown the same faith as Enoch.
By faith,
you stand up to an ungodly world
by not adopting its corrupt ways.
By faith,
you boldly declare God’s Word
from house to house
and in public places.
Before you became a baptized Witness,
you may have thought you would never do
this preaching work!
But you are doing it,
sometimes even in the face
of verbal abuse and opposition.
Faith has made it happen.
Let’s read verse 7:
“By faith Noah,
“after receiving divine warning
of things not yet seen,
“showed godly fear
and constructed an ark
“for the saving of his household;
“and through this faith
he condemned the world,
“and he became an heir
of the righteousness
that results from faith.”
Nothing in the Bible indicates
that Jehovah chose Noah
to construct an ark
because he was an experienced builder.
Certainly, he never had built
such a gigantic vessel
as what Jehovah
had asked him to construct.
Noah likely pondered many questions:
‘How will I get all the building materials?
‘Do I have the right tools to do the job?
‘How will I gather all the animals?
‘What food will they need, and how much?
‘When, exactly, will the Deluge begin?
‘How long will it last?
Where will the ark land
after the Flood subsides?’
Nothing in the record indicates
that Jehovah gave Noah
all the details in advance.
What Noah did have was faith.
Faith moved him to begin building.
His faith saved him and his family.
Faith in Jehovah made it happen.
Like Noah, during this time of the end,
Jehovah’s people have taken on
challenging theocratic building projects.
Certainly, constructing
the new world headquarters
at Warwick, New York,
was one of these projects
that required much faith.
A committee of brothers was assigned
to complete this vast project
in less than four years.
To do so, they knew they had to begin
by July 2013.
They moved ahead in faith.
Though the town
had not yet approved the site permits,
they began inviting workers to the site
with that date in mind.
Time was passing quickly.
The invited volunteers
were buying plane tickets.
Bethel was arranging rooming
and other details.
Yet, the committee
still did not have site permits.
Would they cancel these invitations?
They state:
“We spent a lot of time praying about it.
“We decided we needed to act in faith.
“And we were just convinced
Jehovah was going to make it happen.”
As the deadline approached,
the brothers had done everything possible
to obtain the permits.
The town planning board
was holding a public hearing.
And to the brothers’ great surprise,
within 15 minutes
of the start of the meeting,
the town board voted
to approve the project.
These overseers commented,
“When the approval came through,
“we knew it was
only by Jehovah’s spirit
that that happened.”
True, but it was
also the brothers’ faith
to act that made it happen.
Those experiences
are found in the video
World Headquarters
—History Is Being Written.
You can find it
in the “Our Activities” section
under the “Construction” category.
Now let’s read Hebrews 11:8:
“By faith Abraham, when he was called,
“obeyed by going out to a place
“he was to receive as an inheritance;
“he went out, although not knowing
where he was going.”
What faith it took
for Abraham
and his submissive wife, Sarah,
to leave the prosperous city of Ur
and to go wherever
Jehovah would lead them!
It meant leaving the security
of a pleasant home
and moving to some strange
and potentially hostile land
some 1,000 miles,
or 1,609 kilometers,  away.
Do we see such faith today?
Absolutely!
Since 2014,
thousands of brothers and sisters
have attended the School
for Kingdom Evangelizers,
agreeing to be assigned
to wherever
there is a need
by the organization.
Faith has made it happen.
When a call goes out
for skilled volunteers
to help build
or expand branch facilities,
faith moves brothers and sisters
to simplify their lives
and to leave their comfort zone
in order to assist.
For example, in 2009,
the congregations
in the United States were informed
that an expansion project
at Wallkill, New York,
was being planned.
One couple moved out
of their newly built
2,200-square-foot,
or 200-square-meter, dream home
and into a 270-square-foot,
or 25-square-meter, apartment
so that they could make
themselves available.
What happened?
They explain:
“One month after we moved
into our small apartment,
“we received an invitation to serve
“as temporary volunteers at Wallkill.
“It was clear to us
that by simplifying our life,
we had given Jehovah
something to bless.”
Faith made it happen for them.
So, what have we learned today?
Faith in Jehovah God
is a powerful motivating force
that impels us to act
in harmony with his will.
Jehovah rewards such faith.
Remember, the very meaning
of the name of our God, Jehovah,
is “He Causes to Become.”
Truly, he is a God
who makes things happen!
Brothers and sisters,
let us continue to act in faith.
Jehovah will continue
to make wonderful things
happen in our personal life.
We will accomplish things
we never could do
through our own personal efforts.
We will be able to do more
in Jehovah’s service.
May it happen to you
“according to your faith.”