Welcome to the program!
Our theme this month is
“Organized to Do God’s Will.”
Among other things,
we will look at how our young brothers
can be encouraged to reach out
so as to take the lead in the congregation.
You will also enjoy this report
on the blessings around the world
from using carts in our ministry,
and we’ll find out how
the organization makes sure
our meeting places are properly utilized.
This is the July program
of JW Broadcasting!
There are people who believe
there is no need
for a religious organization.
They feel they have
their own personal relationship with God
and that is good enough.
They see no need to be associated
with a specific organization.
However, what does
God’s own inspired Word suggest?
That he would use an organization,
or channel,
through which spiritual food
would be dispensed
from his Word, the Bible.
For example,
1 Peter 2:17 says
to “have love
for the whole association of brothers.”
One dictionary definition for “association”
is “an organization of persons
having a common interest.”
We have a very interesting, insightful look
at the organization in the first century.
If we glance down through chapter 15
of the book of Acts,
we can gain some insight.
Verse 1 indicates there was
an issue that caused a disagreement
between some of the members
of the congregation.
Then verse 2 says:
“But after quite a bit
of dissension and disputing
“by Paul and Barnabas with them,
“it was arranged for Paul,
Barnabas, and some of the others
“to go up to the apostles
and elders in Jerusalem
regarding this issue.”
It sounds like an organization to me.
And after considerable discussion
and with the help of God’s holy spirit,
what transpired?
Verses 22 and 23 say:
“Then the apostles and the elders,
together with the whole congregation,
“decided to send chosen men
from among them to Antioch,
“along with Paul and Barnabas;
“they sent Judas
who was called Barsabbas and Silas,
“who were leading men
among the brothers.
They wrote this
and sent it through them.”
Then in verses 23-29
is the letter of direction
that was delivered to Antioch
and other congregations as well.
In fact, in verse 41,
it says Paul and Silas
“went through Syria and Cilicia,
strengthening the congregations.”
Chapter 16, verse 5 says:
“Then, indeed, the congregations
continued to be made firm in the faith
and to increase in number day by day.”
So it was not a matter
of isolated Christians sitting at home
claiming to have
a personal relationship with God.
No, the work was organized,
and congregations
kept being added “day by day.”
That is very similar to what we see
in Jehovah’s organization today.
In fact, the organization
of Jehovah’s Witnesses is patterned
after the first-century
Christian congregation
as set forth in the Scriptures.
I would like to remind
all of Jehovah’s Witnesses
—whether already baptized
or working toward baptism—
of this book,
Organized to Do Jehovah’s Will.
It provides an overall view
of how the Christian congregation
is organized
for getting God’s work done.
The book also offers counsel and direction
to help us maintain unity
with our brothers worldwide.
New ones need to become familiar
with the operation
of Jehovah’s organization
and learn how they can have a share
in the modern-day preaching work.
In fact,
when a Bible student progresses
and desires to join us in the ministry
as an unbaptized publisher,
the elders direct him
to make a study of this book,
including the “Questions for Those
Desiring to Get Baptized”
in the appendix.
Even for those of us
who have been baptized many years,
it may be good to schedule the reading
of one chapter of the book each week
during our personal study
or family worship.
It contains general information
concerning the duties
of elders and ministerial servants,
judicial procedures,
and various other features
of congregation organization.
I would like to take a few minutes
and review some of the information
in chapter 1 of the publication.
Though there are thousands of national
and international organizations
around the world,
they are organized
according to human viewpoints
and philosophies.
But our organization is different;
it is theocratic.
That means it is ruled by Jehovah
as Head over all.
Isaiah 33:22 says that he is our Judge,
Lawgiver, and King.
Many large organizations appoint
a chief executive officer, or CEO.
He is the executive
with the chief decision-making authority
in a business or corporation.
In a similar way,
Jehovah has appointed his Son, Jesus,
to be the one
with chief decision-making authority
over the congregation of God.
Ephesians 1:22
is speaking of Jehovah’s actions
in connection with Jesus.
It says:
“He also subjected all things under his feet
“and made him head over all things
with regard to the congregation.”
We see the structure
of the organization taking shape.
Jehovah is the Universal Sovereign,
the King,
directing the millions of angels
making up his heavenly organization.
But when it comes to directing
the visible earthly part
of God’s organization,
he has delegated
that responsibility to Jesus,
the head of the congregation of God.
Chapter 2 of the Organized book
explains this Scriptural position of Jesus.
And how does Jesus direct
the organization here on earth?
Matthew 24:45 says
that Jesus has appointed
a “faithful and discreet slave”
to serve
spiritual “food at the proper time.”
Today,
seven anointed men
make up the faithful slave,
and collectively,
they are known as the Governing Body.
And Jesus uses the holy spirit
to direct these men
in harmony with the Scriptures.
The Scriptural basis
for this layer of organization
is set forth in chapter 3 of the book.
Chapter 4 is entitled
“How the Congregation
Is Organized and Governed.”
The organizational structure
incorporates Branch Committees,
circuit overseers, elders,
and ministerial servants.
The subject index in the back of the book
can be useful
to quickly gain access to information
on various aspects of the organization.
Suppose you’re a young person,
maybe even
a relatively young married couple.
The circuit overseer is visiting,
and he asks you
what spiritual goals you have.
How would you answer?
Would your mind start racing,
trying to think
of various avenues of service available?
How about now,
before you are asked such a question,
you look in the subject index
under “Goals”?
There are 11 references
to paragraphs in the book on that subject.
After reading about all
of the possibilities
and different categories,
you would be
in a better position to plan your life
for a great future
in the earthly part
of Jehovah’s organization.
At this time,
I would like to draw your attention
to a very important factor
in a new one’s making progress
and attaining spiritual stability.
On page 213 of the Organized book,
it discusses a person
interested in being baptized.
After the elders go over the questions
in part 3 of the book,
it says this:
“If he has not completed his study
of the Bible Teach and ‘God’s Love’ books,
the elders should make arrangements
for someone to help him do so.”
The two books
complement each other so well.
When someone becomes a dedicated
and baptized servant of Jehovah,
we want them to stay
closely attached to the organization.
Yet every year,
there are a number
who stop attending meetings
and become inactive.
At times,
it has been found
that they did not finish
studying the two books.
You see,
the Bible Teach book helps new ones
to have an accurate knowledge of the Bible,
and they often learn to love Jehovah.
The “Keep Yourselves in God’s Love” book
helps us to learn to apply the Bible
and live in harmony
with Jehovah’s standards.
Notice what Jesus told his faithful apostles
at John 15:10:
“If you observe my commandments,
you will remain in my love,
“just as I have observed
the commandments of the Father
and remain in his love.”
Did you notice
that Jesus remained in God’s love
by observing his Father’s commandments?
The same is true of us today.
To remain in God’s love,
we need to apply the truth
in our everyday life.
And what is the result
if we keep ourselves in God’s love?
It is so clearly stated
in Jude 21:
“In order to keep yourselves in God’s love,
“while you await the mercy
of our Lord Jesus Christ
with everlasting life in view.”
Staying in God’s love
results in everlasting life.
It is so important
to make sure our Bible students
complete a study of both books,
and that applies to our children too.
Sometimes as parents,
we can assume
that our children are developing
a trusting relationship with Jehovah
because they have been going
to meetings since they were very small.
A relationship with Jehovah
does not happen by means of osmosis.
A child does not simply absorb
and assimilate truth
and a love for God
just by being in the presence of others
who have a close relationship with Jehovah.
We very much appreciate
all of the videos we have,
including Become Jehovah’s Friend
and JW Broadcasting.
But new ones and young ones
need to be able to go
through the process of deep study
to get to the Bible’s truth
and get it etched into their minds
and lodged deep in their hearts.
Therefore,
if you parents realize
that you have not studied
both books with your young ones,
it would be good to see
that a schedule is established to do so.
The Governing Body gives all credit
for the success
of this organization to Jehovah
and the appointed head
of the congregation, Jesus Christ.
We are just imperfect men trying to follow
the lead of Christ and the holy spirit.
At 1 Corinthians 1:26,
Paul says:
“For you see his calling of you, brothers,
that there are not many wise
in a fleshly way.”
Verse 27 says:
“But God chose
the foolish things of the world
to put the wise men to shame.”
Then verse 30 says that Christ Jesus
“has become to us wisdom from God.”
That is where the direction and wisdom
of the organization come from,
not from mere man.
The words of Jehovah
to the prophet Zechariah fit today
when we see
the amazing advances in the organization.
Zechariah 4:6 says:
“‘Not by a military force, nor by power,
but by my spirit,’ says Jehovah of armies.”
While there are
some well-educated and prominent men
who have accepted the truth
and are now our fellow brothers,
the majority in the organization
come from a more humble background.
For example,
among the first
of Jehovah’s modern-day servants
to introduce the Kingdom message
to people in Denmark
was a shoemaker.
In Switzerland and France,
it was a gardener.
In many parts of Africa,
the message was carried
by itinerant workers.
In Brazil, sailors had a share.
Quite a few of the Polish Witnesses
in northern France
were coal miners.
Jehovah and Jesus use all of us
to get a remarkable work accomplished.
We are proud to be a part
of this spirit-directed organization.
As one older circuit overseer
was heard to say,
“This is the best imperfect organization
on earth!”
There are no perfect organizations on earth.
However, this is the best of them all.
And we appreciate
the contribution all of you make
to the success
of the preaching work worldwide.
With that contribution in mind,
consider for a moment
the huge load elders carry
in caring for our congregations.
Some of them are now advanced in age.
So how can young brothers be trained
to qualify for increased responsibilities?
In this dramatization,
a congregation faces a change
on its elder body
that brought that question to the fore.
We’re very happy for Daniel.
He’s going to be a blessing
in his new assignment.
But we are going to miss him
and everything he was doing
for the congregation.
This will change things for us.
We really want to be there
for our brothers and sisters.
And it’s true:
Having plenty to do
in the Lord’s work is good.
But where will we get more help?
We do have good ministerial servants
like Richie.
But after Daniel left,
our elder body is one fewer now.
That prompted a good question:
Are we doing all we can
to train our brothers?
Richie, do you have some time for me?
I have some calls you can help me with.
Sure, I’d like that.
I realized it had been
a while since we talked
about him qualifying to do more.
He explained that he wanted to help
but didn’t want to appear presumptuous.
He’d been praying about it,
and he wanted to know what else
he could do to keep reaching out.
Talking to Richie
made me think of Jesus’ example.
His disciples offered themselves willingly,
and he trained them.
They were eager but needed his direction.
Jesus’ training gave them confidence
to do the assignments he gave them.
They were happy,
not just to follow Jesus,
but to work alongside him.
And Jesus was happy to share his work.
Up to his final evening with them,
he prepared them for the work ahead.
“Most truly I say to you,
“whoever exercises faith in me
will also do the works that I do;
“and he will do works greater than these,
because I am going my way to the Father.”
I now remember how much training
I had received from the brothers.
It was easy to forget
that I didn’t always get
things right at first.
Soon,
Richie was taking on more responsibility.
And he told me something
that I too once felt.
He just didn’t realize how much work
went into caring for Jehovah’s sheep.
But once he knew,
he was glad he offered himself willingly.
We commend all our hard-working elders
for their fine work
and also those of you who support them,
whether you are a ministerial servant
or perhaps the wife of an elder.
Without your help and support,
it would be very difficult
for our dear elders
to carry out their weighty responsibilities.
While there is a lot of work
to be done on a local level,
there is an unprecedented global effort
to provide spiritual food
to all of God’s people.
Under the direction
of the Teaching Committee
of the Governing Body,
the Audio/Video Services Department,
or AVS,
takes the lead in producing
audio and video publications.
It’s been said that if a picture
is worth a thousand words,
then a video is worth a million!
Videos stir our emotions, don’t they?
And they can be
very powerful teaching tools.
Brother Russell recognized this fact.
Back in 1914,
the small group of Bible Students
presented the “Photo-Drama of Creation”
to over nine million people worldwide,
and the response was overwhelming.
It was clear that Jehovah
blessed their efforts
at spreading the Bible’s message
in a visual way.
Well, over a hundred years later,
“the faithful and discreet slave”
is producing videos.
And for many years, basically,
one large public-release video
was being released,
or produced, each year.
For example, back in 2011,
the video Faith in Action, Part 2
was released.
And it required a tremendous effort
to produce the video master,
the audio tracks, the graphics,
the music, the on-screen text
for one video.
However, just five years later,
the work has grown from producing
an average of one video per year
to one video per day.
This is because videos are now
a regular part of our website,
the broadcasts,
our ministry, the conventions,
meetings, and other special events.
In 2016,
more than 350 videos were produced.
Under the direction
of the Teaching Committee,
Audio/Video Services (AVS)
has been entrusted with this work.
But with this rapid increase
in the amount of videos produced,
how is all this accomplished?
Perhaps you’ve heard the expression
“it takes a village.”
In this case,
it takes an entire globe.
Please enjoy the following video
for a close-up look
at how audio and video work
is accomplished worldwide.
To assist with the growing workload
in Audio/Video Services,
the Governing Body has approved
11 full-time Regional Video Teams (RVT)
in branches around the world.
But it doesn’t stop there.
Bethelites, commuters,
and remote workers in many other branches
also provide valuable assistance.
How do we work with all these teams?
After receiving direction
from the Governing Body committees
for upcoming videos,
AVS then assigns
each video to a capable team.
Once the team accepts the assignment,
we provide them
with the necessary direction
as well as answer
any questions they may have.
Then the team goes to work.
Because of being a small group,
each team member may have to wear
multiple hats to get the job done.
From start to finish,
they all work very hard
to deliver a completed, edited video
to us by the designated time.
Later, you may see these videos
on JW Broadcasting,
jw.org, or other places.
Would you like to meet
some of our RVT family?
It’s a privilege.
We meet friends who have suffered
some hardships and trials,
but because of their trust in Jehovah,
they were able to overcome them,
and we see the results of their loyalty.
I think it strengthens our determination
to also stay loyal.
We are a joyful team
with a lot of humor,
and we work together very harmoniously.
You could say that we
are like a little family.
We look forward to the next day
when we go to work again.
It’s unbelievable how many dear brothers
and sisters we’ve gotten to know
through these projects.
Close ties can develop,
and it is not uncommon
that tears flow when the project is over
and it is time to say good-bye.
Sometimes we would film
on private or state property,
and I would have to approach the manager
and let them know
what we were planning to shoot
at the location.
This wasn’t easy for me
because I’m not very good with words.
And many people in Korea tend to have
a biased view of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
so this made it even harder for me.
So I prayed to Jehovah,
asking for his guidance and wisdom.
I was surprised to find that many
were more than willing to help us.
These experiences help me to realize
that Jehovah always answers
our prayers for strength and courage.
You have to balance your time around work,
around being the head of a family,
being an elder,
or other responsibilities
that you have in the congregation.
That’s when you really see Jehovah’s hand
—when you see the mountain of challenge,
but you overcome it.
And you know it wasn’t you.
It was impossible for you to do it yourself.
When I put even half
the amount of energy and effort
that I do into working for Jehovah
into something secular,
I’m wiped out; I need a vacation.
But the more
I put into working for Jehovah,
the more I want to work.
To know that you
are offering your skills to Jehovah
—that is a blessing.
But, really, the blessing is seeing
your relationship with Jehovah
thrive and become stronger,
and you can see
that he does keep his promises
and that he supports you
more than you’re supporting him.
Many of us aren’t able
to be full-time Bethelites,
but commuting really helps us
get that small snippet of what it’s like
to be a Bethelite
and realize what a privilege it is.
And if you’ve got a specific talent, use it.
One day in Paradise,
someone is going to come to you
and say,
“How did you use your talent?”
Maybe you’re a brilliant artist,
and you’re going
to proudly turn around and say:
“You know what?
I used it for Jehovah.”
Even if you’re young,
you can learn skills
and you can really assist
Jehovah’s organization
now and in the future.
And there is no better boss
to work for than Jehovah.
My advice to young ones: Go for it!
And during this past year,
we were excited to add
a new team to our AVS family
—located in Mira Loma, California.
All in this group
have made themselves available
for video needs out there.
You’re able to take a person—
You’re able to take an individual
that has dedicated their life to Jehovah,
and maybe they
didn’t know at the time
that they were going
to inspire somebody else
and have somebody
somewhere across the planet say:
“Wow! That’s exactly my life too.
“I’m so glad that this person
“was selected to be on here
because that’s my life.
And that has triggered me
to want to do more for Jehovah.”
You know it’s Jehovah’s holy spirit;
he’s putting together a team;
he’s the Great Producer.
And what he really wants
is he wants people who have the talent,
but he wants people
who have the holy spirit more
and are willing to work for it.
But he gives you the ability,
like Oholiab and Bezalel,
to be able to put your talents
that you’ve learned to work for him.
As you can see,
we’re part of a beautiful,
hardworking global team.
With so many hands helping the load
in so many time zones,
we’re literally working on videos 24/7.
It’s a great privilege
to work alongside our extended family.
We learn from each other.
Their willing spirit, humble attitude,
and contagious joy
inspire all of us here in AVS.
Additionally, we receive
incredible support right at home too.
Virtually every department at Bethel
supports the audio/video work in some way,
and we are very, very thankful.
With everyone’s help,
the Bible’s message is being spread visually
throughout the earth
at unprecedented levels.
But how is any of this possible?
Brother Russell said it best:
‘This is not man’s work. It’s God’s.’
Jehovah is certainly at the helm.
As he foretold at Haggai 2:7:
“I will shake all the nations,
“and the precious things
of all the nations will come in;
and I will fill this house with glory.”
There is certainly
a great shaking taking place
worldwide.
And many of these precious ones
are offering themselves willingly
to help Audio/Video Services
accomplish this great work,
thanks to Jehovah God,
our Grand and Visual Instructor.
Our videos are a fantastic provision
from Jehovah,
and what a teaching tool they have become.
We get many letters of appreciation
about the use of our videos
in our midweek meetings.
And I agree;
the videos make the meetings
so much more dynamic.
For example, the week of July 17,
we will be considering the part
“Do You Forgive Yourself?”
which includes a video that we first saw
at the 2016 Regional Convention.
Make it a habit to prepare
for these video considerations
just as thoroughly
as you would any other part.
Your well-prepared comments
will benefit the whole congregation.
And when we arrive
at the Kingdom Hall for a meeting,
don’t you agree
that we all feel refreshed
the moment we see the smiling faces
of our brothers and sisters?
That’s how I feel.
Sometimes we can even take
our beautiful meeting location for granted.
But did you know
that a lot of work goes into making sure
that our Kingdom Halls are well utilized?
The Worldwide Design/Construction
Department, or WDC,
is tasked with analyzing
our worldwide needs
and providing direction
to Local Design/Construction Departments
on how best to use
our dedicated funds.
As we approach the end
of the present system of things,
Jehovah continues to speed up the work.
We now have
more than 62,000 Kingdom Halls worldwide,
and the demand is still growing.
Jehovah’s blessing
on the Kingdom work is undeniable,
as this could not
have been accomplished otherwise.
Many have been working for years
in support of Kingdom Hall
and Assembly Hall construction projects,
most recently as part
of the Local Design/Construction,
or LDC, program.
This program was implemented
during the 2014 service year
and unifies the approach
for construction of Kingdom Halls worldwide.
What has been accomplished
since the program started?
At the end of the 2000 service year,
half of the publishers worldwide
met in suitable meeting places.
However, the other half
—approximately three million publishers—
met in places that were overcrowded
or otherwise unsuitable as Kingdom Halls.
At that time,
27,000 Kingdom Halls were needed.
By 2014,
the number of publishers meeting
in unsuitable facilities had been reduced.
But because of growth in the organization,
this still meant that 1.6 million publishers
did not have a suitable meeting place.
Since 2014,
that figure has been reduced
by 25 percent.
What accounts for this significant reduction
in the backlog,
allowing us to catch up faster
than in the past?
Part of the answer
lies in making efficient use
of the facilities we already have.
When providing food for thousands,
Jesus made it clear
that nothing should be wasted.
The LDC program applies that principle
to the seats in our Kingdom Halls.
As noted earlier,
we have 62,000 Kingdom Halls worldwide.
On average,
only 60 percent of the seats
are filled for congregation meetings.
That means that approximately three
to four million seats are empty
during congregation meetings each week.
There are a number of options
to help make better use of these seats,
which will make the use
of each Kingdom Hall more efficient.
Consider, for example,
a Kingdom Hall in an urban area.
It has 200 seats
and is used
by four congregations sharing the facility.
That means the Kingdom Hall will be in use
for four weeknight meetings
and four weekend meetings.
It would definitely appear
to be fully utilized
and suggests the need
for new construction for further growth.
However,
how many seats were in the Kingdom Hall?
Two hundred.
Multiplied by meetings
for the four congregations,
this facility has a total seating capacity
of 800 people.
Global records indicate that congregations
using this size Kingdom Hall
have an average attendance
of 120 at their meeting.
This could mean
that only 480 seats are used
by the four congregations
in this Kingdom Hall
and 320 seats remain empty
—not very efficient.
If the four congregations were redistributed
into three congregations,
average meeting attendance
for each congregation
would increase
to about 160 per meeting,
while still fitting comfortably
in that Kingdom Hall.
And this would now allow
for an open slot in the schedule,
which could be used
to meet needs in the area
without requiring new construction.
In the first three years of the LDC program,
fully utilizing our existing facilities
played a part in reducing
the backlog of Kingdom Hall projects
from 14,000 to approximately 10,000.
This saved millions of dollars.
Of course, this does not meet every need,
and there is still a significant need
to construct new Kingdom Halls
to provide suitable places of worship.
How does the branch office
make these decisions,
and how are priorities set?
All options are examined
as the Branch Committees
work with their Local Design/Construction
and Service departments.
Transportation needs
—such as distance,
opportunities for carpooling,
and availability
of public transportation—
are taken into account.
In many cases,
congregations can be sized
to make better use of available seats
in Kingdom Halls
that have already been built.
However,
when they are needed,
new Kingdom Halls can be constructed
using simple, standard designs
that make wise use of donated funds.
Of course, all of this must be done
with the big picture in mind.
It is the spiritual needs
of the congregations
that are of the utmost priority.
The structures themselves are not
the focus of these centers of pure worship,
but rather it is the people
who use the facilities.
On one occasion,
as they passed the temple,
Mark 13:1 quotes one of Jesus’ disciples
admiring the structure when he said:
“Teacher, see!
what wonderful stones and buildings!”
However,
Jesus’ reply simply indicated
that the building itself would not last.
It was people Jesus was concerned with.
Likewise,
the Kingdom Halls that we build today
will not last forever.
But these centers of pure worship
bring people together
so that we can serve Jehovah
as a united group
—and that will last forever.
Whether we assist in the construction
of the many Kingdom Halls
that are still needed
or help to renovate and maintain
existing Kingdom Halls,
it is our shared privilege
to help provide
suitable meeting places
for our brothers and sisters.
In this way,
we each support
“the faithful and discreet slave”
as they provide what is needed
so that each congregation
can praise Jehovah
in a suitable place of worship.
Brother Thomas Kalimeris,
who serves at the United States branch,
together with his wife,
has spent close to four decades
supporting various aspects
of the organization’s construction projects.
What has that experience taught him?
That the work is not run by us.
Throughout history, men have built
many beautiful and impressive buildings.
These structures
have usually brought glory to men,
not to God.
But those men are long gone,
and even many of the structures
no longer exist.
How true is the scripture at Psalm 127:1:
“Unless Jehovah builds the house,
it is in vain
that its builders work hard on it.”
In our time too,
Jehovah is using his people to build.
We’re working hard
to build spirituality in interested ones,
and also we build structures
in order to help individuals to learn
about Jehovah and serve him.
In this type of construction
—both spiritual and physical construction—
I’ve been involved for most of my life.
I was born in Greece.
Our family came into contact
with the truth in the early sixties.
I was baptized when I was in high school.
I left school to get
some practical training in architecture,
but I made pioneering my career.
In 1973,
I married my dear wife, Margaret,
and together
we enjoyed many assignments.
We pioneered
—special pioneering.
We went to Gilead.
We were invited to Bethel
in 1979 to work
in the Engineering Department.
We worked on designing new branches,
Assembly Halls, Kingdom Halls,
renovation of existing branches
and remote translation offices.
Before we came to Bethel, we had seen how
Jehovah provided for us individually.
But now we had the opportunity
to see how Jehovah provided
for the needs of his organization globally.
By the year 2000,
it became apparent that the present facility
of the Britain branch
was not meeting their needs.
So a site was located
50 miles (80 km) north of London
to relocate the branch there.
However,
the Governing Body
decided to cancel the project.
So in 2008,
the Governing Body wrote
that now is the time
—Jehovah’s time—
to find property
closer to London.
So a project team was formed,
and a few years went by,
and a number of properties were searched,
and one was located closer to London.
If something we plan falls through,
it could mean
that Jehovah has something else
—or better— in mind to meet
the needs of his organization.
While working in the Haiti branch,
we learned a lesson:
not to compromise on safety.
The Brooklyn Engineering Department
did the drawings for the branch,
and a local contractor was hired
to build the structural work.
Now, the contractor,
when he reviewed the drawings,
told the Branch Committee:
“Really, this is overdesigned.
You’re wasting a lot of money
by putting all the steel in the building.”
So we wrote back and said:
“No, the drawings are OK.
“The branch is designed
according to the seismic zone that it’s in.
And the contractor is to go ahead
with the plans as drawn.”
In 2010,
when the earthquake came to Haiti,
hundreds of thousands of people died
because of inferior materials
and methods of construction.
However,
the branch did not suffer any damage,
and many people went there to find refuge.
We’re so glad that Jehovah did not allow us
to be swayed in this case.
Jehovah continues to direct
a great physical building work
and a spiritual work.
Jehovah trains his people
how to work together
for the work just ahead of us
—the beautification of this earth
to a paradise.
It is so important that we
‘trust in Jehovah
and not to lean
upon our own understanding.’
A life of building with Jehovah
has shown me the wisdom of Psalm 127:1.
If we keep building our lives with Jehovah,
our building work will never be in vain.
The more responsibility a brother
is given in the organization,
the less he feels he is in control.
Instead, he will clearly see how Jehovah
takes the lead in the organization.
And Brother Kalimeris’ experience
confirms that.
The account about how the branch in Haiti
was protected from earthquake damage
sent chills down my spine.
While some buildings looked like this,
our branch looked like this.
And it wasn’t the ingenuity of the brothers
that protected the branch,
but wisdom that only Jehovah can provide.
But how can we apply
that same wisdom in our lives?
Let’s consider three ways we can do so.
Jehovah has warned us that we’re living
in “critical times hard to deal with.”
And Jesus foretold that in the last days
there would be great “earthquakes
in one place after another”
and other “fearful sights.”
Many of us either have or will be affected
by some form of natural disaster.
If this happens, how can we be prepared?
First,
we can prepare spiritually by maintaining
a close relationship with Jehovah.
He is “the God of all comfort,”
and he can comfort us
in times of tribulation.
How does he do this?
We do not expect divine intervention.
But if we pray during times of distress,
his powerful holy spirit
can bring Bible passages
back to mind to comfort us.
Second,
we can take practical steps,
perhaps preparing an emergency kit.
Our kit could contain
the following items if possible:
first-aid supplies,
bottled water,
and nonperishable food.
Also, we shouldn’t forget
to update the elders
with our latest contact information.
If we don’t do so,
valuable time could be lost in a disaster.
Additionally,
during a Family Worship evening,
our family could review
the types of disasters that might happen
and what could be done in each situation
—such as where we meet,
how we contact the elders, and so forth.
And third,
we can help others
when they’re experiencing a disaster,
knowing they’d do the same for us.
How can we do this?
By offering prayers in their behalf,
by volunteering to assist
with disaster relief efforts,
and by contributing donations
to the worldwide work.
No, we can’t avoid all natural disasters.
But if we prepare spiritually,
practically,
and help others currently affected,
we can take comfort in knowing
that in Jehovah’s eyes
we are prepared.
That was great, practical advice
for all of us to take to heart.
But there are some things
we can do to help our local congregation.
Let’s turn briefly
to interview Brother Bram Siegel,
who’s with
the Coordinators’ Committee Office.
Bram, how can all of us cooperate
with the congregation arrangement
when a disaster hits?
Immediately after a disaster occurs,
each field service group overseer
will contact everyone in his group
to make sure that all are accounted for
and to see if anyone needs assistance.
So each of us
should make sure to give the elders
our up-to-date contact information.
That way they can reach us
when something happens.
That’s a very important reminder
—good point!
But what if my area
was not hit by the disaster
but an adjacent town or city was?
Can I just travel there on my own to help,
or what should I do?
We really appreciate
the beautiful spirit the brotherhood shows
when it comes to providing disaster relief.
Really, the best time
to make yourself available to help
is right now,
before a disaster occurs.
Just ask your local elders
for an application.
Later, when there’s a need
to provide disaster relief,
the branch office will know
that you’re willing and ready to assist.
Thank you very much, Bram,
for those important reminders.
Thank you.
When large disasters occur,
our brothers and sisters
may have to relocate
—perhaps even to another country.
As refugees, they face unique challenges.
You will notice that the Watchtower study
for the week of July 3
provides practical suggestions
on how we can support
such brothers and sisters.
And I’m sure you agree
that the guidance
Jehovah’s organization provides,
the love and care that we experience
every day as a people for his name,
the spiritual paradise that we dwell in
—all of that makes us want
to praise our heavenly Father.
This brings us to this month’s
music video which is entitled
We Marvel at Your Work.
The work of the Kingdom,
in my lifetime and before,
Provides me with your written Word,
the truth, and so much more.
Your faithful slave, discreet and wise,
provides increasing light
And sends out men who shepherd me
with loving oversight.
I know expectations
at conventions will be met.
And afterward, I always say,
“Now that’s the best one yet!”
At weekly meetings,
I can feel your thoughtful, loving care
And learn how best to preach and teach
and have a fuller share.
We marvel at your work
And what the Kingdom’s done so far.
We cherish Kingdom rule.
We grow in faith to realize
the kind of God you are.
We look ahead to blessings
that your Kingdom soon will bring.
You give us the honor
to be workers on your side,
Our ministry that lets us show
the love we feel inside.
The depth of understanding
and the peace of mind you give,
They teach us what is pure and true;
they show the way to live.
The songs that express
what’s in my heart so very well
And Fam’ly Worship ev’nings
give your spirit room to dwell.
Our unity, despite whatever language
we might speak,
Proves that our loving brotherhood
in this world is unique.
We marvel at your work
And what the Kingdom’s done so far.
We cherish Kingdom rule.
We grow in faith
to realize the kind of God you are.
We look ahead to blessings
that your Kingdom soon will bring.
That’s beautiful.
And how can we show our appreciation
for Jehovah’s provisions in a practical way?
By taking seriously
our God-given assignment to preach.
And we have seen developments
in our preaching methods
in the past few years.
For example, in 2001,
with the Governing Body’s approval,
our brothers in France
started using a variety of methods
to carry out our public witnessing,
including the use of carts.
The trial resulted
in many good experiences.
As a result, in 2011,
a pilot project with cart witnessing
in New York City, U.S.A., was approved.
Since Manhattan, in New York City,
had a ratio of 1 Jehovah’s Witness
to 657 inhabitants,
this was a perfect choice.
That was the beginning
of a pilot program in Manhattan.
The program lasted one year,
using many graduates
from what was then
the Bible School for Christian Couples.
Although different tables
were used at the time,
it was evident that a mobile cart
had many advantages.
As a result, today,
Jehovah’s Witnesses are well-known
for their public witnessing using carts
designed to display their literature.
By means of this method,
good news from the Bible
can be taken to many places
and easily becomes available
to countless people.
These carts include different posters that:
call attention
to our well-known publications,
invite people to accept
free home Bible studies,
and direct passersby to our official website.
Here are just a few examples of how
this method has had many good results.
My name is Mi Jung You.
The first time I met Jehovah’s Witnesses
was more than 20 years ago.
I started studying
in the You Can Live Forever book,
but about a month later,
I had to stop studying.
After that,
I would accept the magazines,
but I never ended up
studying the Bible again.
In June of 2014, though,
I saw the public witnessing stand.
I realized that it belonged
to Jehovah’s Witnesses.
So many of the different publications
they had caught my eye.
So I asked if it would be OK
if I took a copy of each one.
We ended up exchanging numbers,
and a few weeks later
the brother contacted me.
I began studying
the Bible again with the couple
and one month later
started attending meetings regularly.
I was baptized in October of 2015
and started auxiliary pioneering
right away for ten months.
Now I’m serving as a regular pioneer.
Public witnessing helped me find the truth,
and it’s a way for me to meet people
that are interested like I was.
I have really come to cherish
the public witnessing work.
My name is Jacob Salomé.
I work as a driver and spent most of my life
traveling all over Peru.
Because of this, I had problems
with the woman I was living with.
I never spent time at home
and practically lived in the truck.
I would see Jehovah’s Witnesses preaching
on the streets near the buses.
But since I was always driving,
I couldn’t park or even talk to them.
But once, I saw some Witnesses
preaching in a public square.
So I went up to them to ask them
what the Bible says about family matters.
This marked a change in my life.
My girlfriend and I
began attending meetings,
and then we got married and got baptized.
Now we are Jehovah’s Witnesses.
As Annies and I were standing by our cart,
we met young Sudharshan.
Annies showed him our tract
Can the Dead Really Live Again?
He was surprised and said,
“How is it possible?”
When she explained to him Acts 24:15,
he exclaimed: “I am a Christian.
I never knew this!”
I asked him,
“Would you like to learn more
about such wonderful things
from the Bible?”
He asked,
“Can you tell me right now?”
There and then, I discussed the first chapter
of the Bible Teach book.
That’s how it started.
Sudharshan brought his friend, Sagar.
Sagar, in turn,
brought Shiva and Srikanth along.
Three of them are attending
our meetings regularly.
Sagar even turned down a job offer
that conflicted with Bible principles.
One tract resulted in many Bible studies.
We can really see Jehovah’s blessing
on this form of public witnessing.
Without a doubt,
cart witnessing is being used
to help preach
the good news of God’s Kingdom
“in all the inhabited earth
for a witness to all the nations.”
The examples we’ve seen in this program
truly highlight how Jehovah and Jesus
use all of us to get
an unprecedented work accomplished.
We’ve seen how young brothers are trained
to take the lead in the congregations,
how videos are produced
around the world
for our spiritual benefit,
the work that goes into better
utilizing our Kingdom Halls,
how wisdom from Jehovah
benefits our construction work,
and how appropriate it is to praise
our heavenly Father for all his works.
And last,
we were encouraged to continue
in our public witnessing efforts
as we clearly see Jehovah’s blessing.
Yes, we are proud
to be Jehovah’s Witnesses.
This is the best organization on earth.
To conclude,
we’d like to share
this postcard from Iceland.
Almost 335,000 people live
on this North Atlantic island nation,
of which about 380 are Jehovah’s Witnesses.
Iceland is known
for being the land of ice and fire,
as it has both a lot of volcanic activity
and Europe’s largest glacier.
In their free time,
the Witnesses in Iceland
enjoy hiking in the beautiful nature
or riding on horseback
on Icelandic horses.
The preaching work
in Iceland began in 1929.
Brother Lindal was the only publisher
on the island for nearly 18 years.
Today, the 380 publishers conduct
approximately 270 Bible studies,
and almost 700 people
attended the Memorial of Christ’s death
last year.
In the winter,
the sun is up for only a few hours.
While the Witnesses
use the limited sunlight wisely
—going from door to door
or business witnessing—
they are not scared by the darkness.
Some congregations use tiny lights
on their public witnessing carts
so that the passersby will see the carts.
Also, the weather in Iceland
can change quickly.
To prevent literature from being damaged
by rain or other weather elements,
some congregations use plastic covers
on the literature.
In 2011, a Polish group was established
in the capital city of Reykjavik,
and in 2016, a congregation
with over 40 publishers was formed.
Today, they conduct over 20 Bible studies.
All the brothers and sisters in Iceland
send their warm Christian love.
We pray that Jehovah will continue
to bless their efforts in praising his name.
This is JW Broadcasting
from the world headquarters
of Jehovah’s Witnesses.