‎Welcome to the program!
‎We have many spiritual gems
‎to share with you.
‎For example,
‎how can we build a good relationship
‎with Jehovah despite a difficult upbringing?
‎The story of Dimitris and Agis
‎is very encouraging.
‎And how can we continue
‎to honor our marriage mate,
‎even if he or she is an unbeliever?
‎Notice how Emma has learned
‎to do just that
‎with her husband, Thomas,
‎despite their differences.
‎And this month’s music video highlights
‎who really is a true friend.
‎This is the November 2018 program
‎of JW Broadcasting!
‎Our adversary, Satan the Devil,
‎will do all he can to break our integrity
‎and destroy our friendship with Jehovah.
‎Meet Brother Viktor Winter.
‎He is a Russian brother
‎who lives in Germany.
‎In 1958, at the age of 21,
‎Brother Winter was sent
‎to a Siberian labor camp
‎simply for practicing his faith in Jehovah.
‎In total, he spent 13 years
‎in multiple Soviet prison camps
‎and 5 years in exile.
‎Despite the persecution,
‎he maintained his Christian qualities.
‎On July 24, 1958,
‎I got baptized;
‎and on November 5, 1958,
‎I already got arrested
‎for refusal to do military service.
‎The second time I was convicted was again
‎The next court trial took place in 1963.
‎I got seven years
‎​—⁠and five years exile.
‎They added three years
‎that I did not serve
‎for refusal to go to the army.
‎I was taken to Mordovia.
‎This was the first camp
‎where all believers were put,
‎amongst them 360 of Jehovah’s Witnesses.
‎The detentions were very strict
‎because around this time the governments
‎and party politics changed.
‎They decided that prisoners must suffer hunger.
‎The food rations were cut.
‎This was very difficult, very difficult, I must say.
‎And the winters can be cold.
‎Even in March, it could get as cold
‎as 35 degrees Celsius
‎​—⁠minus 35 (-31°F).
‎Spiritual things were for all of us
‎​—⁠the brothers in this camp​—
‎⁠top priority.
‎First of all, all 360 people
‎were divided into four congregations,
‎and every congregation was divided into groups.
‎Every congregation
‎had responsible brothers as overseers
‎and so had every group.
‎We conducted the study not just once a week,
‎but we conducted the study every day,
‎every day.
‎And brothers took this very seriously.
‎We had no time for any worldly thoughts.
‎Every Saturday and Sunday,
‎we had a very powerful choir​
‎—⁠men’s voices.
‎When we were singing,
‎we stationed guards
‎near the oversight house
‎where supervisors were on duty.
‎And if one of them came out,
‎it was signaled
‎from one brother to the next
‎so that if he or they came closer,
‎we would already be gone.
‎But the most interesting thing
‎was that we were singing in the zone.
‎We were the prisoners,
‎but our listeners were outside.
‎They were sitting up in the trees
‎​—⁠the children of the supervisors,
‎officers, and guards.
‎And they were listening to our choir.
‎All together during that time,
‎I was in seven prison camps.
‎I spent about 13 years there
‎and another 5 years in exile in Siberia.
‎But when I was convicted the last time,
‎the head of the interrogation department
‎came into my cell and said,
‎“Viktor, when you finish all your prison terms,
‎you will have nothing at all​
‎—⁠no family, no children.”
‎I smiled at him and asked:
‎“How do you know this,
‎Citizen Lieutenant Colonel?
‎I don’t know it either,
‎but I do trust in Jehovah.”
‎Today, I do have a family
‎and do have my wife and my children.
‎We continue to serve Jehovah.
‎And my greatest joy
‎is when my six-year-old granddaughter
‎stands next to me in the Kingdom Hall
‎and sings songs that praise Jehovah.
‎Well, to make it simple,
‎I would put it this way:
‎Preserve your love
‎for Jehovah and for your brothers.
‎Joy in Jehovah’s service
‎​—⁠never lose it!
‎We will not fear anything bad
‎​—⁠neither cold nor hunger​—⁠
‎nothing.
‎Did you notice the evil words
‎of the head
‎of the interrogation department?
‎“You will have nothing at all
‎—no family, no children.”
‎Today, Brother Winter
‎is over 80 years old.
‎What a blessing, as you can see,
‎that he is now surrounded by a big family!
‎By maintaining his theocratic routine
‎even under persecution,
‎Brother Winter
‎avoided developing bitter feelings
‎toward his persecutors.
‎In this way,
‎he maintained
‎his relationship with Jehovah
‎and he conquered
‎the evil with the good.
‎And that is also the theme
‎for this month’s program:
‎“Keep Conquering the Evil With the Good.”
‎This challenging exhortation
‎was written by the apostle Paul
‎at Romans 12:21.
‎It’s challenging
‎because we live in a world
‎that is alienated
‎from God and the truth,
‎a world that tries
‎to squeeze everyone into its mold.
‎Isaiah 5:20 shows how the world
‎has changed God-given standards.
‎It reads:
‎“Woe to those who say
‎that good is bad
‎“and bad is good,
‎“those who substitute darkness for light
‎“and light for darkness,
‎“those who put bitter for sweet
‎and sweet for bitter!”
‎By adhering to the standard
‎“of healthful words” in the Scriptures
‎and to the examples
‎of faithful servants of the past,
‎we can ‘conquer the evil with the good.’
‎The faithful man Enoch was born
‎when Adam
‎was about 600 years old,
‎which means
‎that Enoch and Adam
‎were contemporaries
‎for about 300 years.
‎However, there is no record
‎of any contact between them
‎during that period of time.
‎The Scriptures indicate
‎that violence and hate for God
‎were widespread
‎in that pre-Flood world.
‎Many centuries later,
‎the disciple Jude described
‎the fear-inspiring prophecy
‎that God gave to Enoch
‎about Jehovah coming
‎with his holy myriads,
‎legions of mighty angels in battle array,
‎to bring destruction to all the ungodly.
‎Enoch fearlessly went about declaring
‎the coming judgment and destruction and,
‎what is more, he did it alone!
‎The prophecy was fulfilled
‎in the global Deluge,
‎and it set the pattern
‎of a greater destruction yet to come.
‎No wonder that Genesis 5:24 tells us
‎that “Enoch kept walking
‎with the true God.”
‎Enoch’s example gives us courage
‎to remain firm for true worship
‎even if family and friends
‎stand apart from us.
‎Enoch did not try to fit in
‎with the evil crowd
‎of the pre-Flood world,
‎and we don’t want to fit in
‎with the present dying world
‎and its evil ways.
‎We may feel alone at times,
‎but we are reminded
‎that Jehovah never abandoned Enoch,
‎and neither will He abandon
‎His faithful servants today.
‎We imitate Enoch
‎by not allowing
‎the evil surrounding us
‎to undermine our faith in Jehovah.
‎Like Enoch, we can
‎‘conquer the evil with the good’
‎by avoiding bad associations,
‎sticking close to Jehovah God
‎and the earthly part of his organization,
‎and boldly proclaiming the good news.
‎Elisha the prophet
‎refused to engage in ‘paying evil for evil,’
‎even when it seemed justified.
‎The account is found
‎at 2 Kings 6:14-23.
‎Syria was at war with Israel.
‎The king of Syria was enraged
‎because Elisha
‎was able to foresee wherever it was
‎that Syria was planning
‎to ambush the Israelites.
‎Elisha would warn
‎the king of Israel, and he, in turn,
‎would keep his troops away
‎from the place of ambush.
‎The king of Syria became exasperated
‎and wanted desperately
‎to take the prophet Elisha captive
‎to stop him
‎from warning the king of Israel.
‎It came about
‎that the king of Syria learned
‎that Elisha was in the city of Dothan,
‎so the king sent horses,
‎war chariots, as well as a large army
‎to surround Dothan by night
‎in order to take Elisha captive.
‎The following morning,
‎Jehovah listened to Elisha
‎and did something amazing.
‎He struck the Syrian troops
‎with a temporary form of blindness,
‎and Elisha guided all those troops,
‎not back to Syria, but to Samaria,
‎where the king of Israel resided.
‎The king of Israel was anxious
‎to strike down and kill the Syrian troops,
‎but Elisha said to him,
‎as recorded in verses 22 and 23
‎of 2 Kings chapter 6:
‎“‘You must not strike them down.
‎“‘Do you strike down
‎those whom you have taken captive
‎“‘with your sword and with your bow?
‎“‘Give them bread and water
‎so they may eat and drink
‎“and return to their lord.’
‎“So he spread a great feast for them,
‎“and they ate and drank,
‎after which he sent them away
‎to return to their lord.”
‎What a shock this must have been
‎to the Syrian soldiers,
‎who likely thought
‎that they were as good as dead!
‎This astounding turn of events
‎was far better than ‘paying evil for evil.’
‎How do we know it was better?
‎The latter part of verse 23 says:
‎“And not once did the marauder bands
‎of the Syrians come again
‎into the land of Israel.”
‎Can you imagine
‎the men of the Syrian army
‎relating to their king
‎what had taken place?
‎They went out to take Elisha captive.
‎However, Elisha,
‎with the help of Jehovah’s spirit,
‎had taken
‎the Syrians captive without a battle.
‎The Syrian king
‎must have been dumbfounded
‎when he heard the report.
‎And you can be sure
‎that the soldiers
‎of the Syrian army
‎were not only grateful
‎but they acquired
‎a very respectful fear of Jehovah
‎and of his prophet Elisha.
‎The good done to the Syrians
‎would not be soon forgotten.
‎Like Elisha,
‎we want to do
‎what is good for people,
‎including those
‎who do not view us favorably.
‎When tragedies such as fires, floods,
‎earthquakes, and hurricanes strike,
‎we go out of our way
‎to comfort people with the Scriptures.
‎Also, Jehovah’s Witnesses
‎serving as relief workers are well-known
‎for the practical assistance they render
‎to fellow believers and to others.
‎As a result, many people
‎have changed their view of us
‎and have come to appreciate
‎that in these last days,
‎Jehovah does indeed have
‎“a people for his name” on the earth.
‎At 2 Timothy 2:23-25,
‎the apostle Paul encourages us
‎to display qualities
‎that make us different from the world.
‎He says:
‎“Further, reject foolish
‎and ignorant debates,
‎“knowing that they produce fights.
‎“For a slave of the Lord
‎does not need to fight,
‎“but needs to be gentle toward all,
‎“qualified to teach,
‎showing restraint when wronged,
‎instructing with mildness
‎those not favorably disposed.”
‎And then Paul explains the desired result:
‎“Perhaps God may give them repentance
‎leading to an accurate knowledge of truth.”
‎Paul was “gentle toward all”
‎and “qualified to teach.”
‎He ‘showed restraint’
‎when he was imprisoned
‎by the Roman authorities
‎around 60 or 61 C.E.
‎He spent about two years
‎under house arrest in Rome,
‎perhaps even being chained to a guard.
‎He had done nothing
‎to merit imprisonment.
‎However, he did not dwell
‎on the evil done to him,
‎and he did not allow it
‎to make him bitter
‎and resentful of Roman authorities.
‎Rather, at Philippians 1:12-14,
‎Paul wrote:
‎“Now I want you to know, brothers,
‎“that my situation has actually turned out
‎“for the advancement of the good news,
‎“so that my prison bonds
‎for the sake of Christ
‎“have become public knowledge
‎“among all the Praetorian Guard
‎and all the rest.
‎“Now most of the brothers in the Lord
‎have gained confidence
‎“because of my prison bonds,
‎“and they are showing all the more courage
‎to speak the word of God fearlessly.”
‎In his letter to Titus
‎in chapter 3, verses 1 and 2,
‎Paul gives reminders
‎on how Christians today
‎can ‘conquer the evil with the good’
‎by showing proper respect
‎for governmental authorities
‎wherever we may live.
‎He writes:
‎“Continue reminding them
‎[fellow Christians]
‎“to be in subjection and to be obedient
‎“to governments and authorities,
‎“to be ready for every good work,
‎“to speak injuriously of no one,
‎“not to be quarrelsome,
‎“but to be reasonable,
‎displaying all mildness toward all men.”
‎Paul followed his own advice.
‎While in custody in Rome,
‎Paul wrote inspired letters
‎to Christian congregations
‎in Greece and Asia Minor,
‎and we today benefit
‎from the counsel in those letters.
‎Never do we read in his letters
‎criticism aimed at human rulers
‎or encouragement for Christians
‎to favor one political figure
‎or party over another.
‎He was “no part of the world,”
‎and he knew that man’s only hope
‎was the Kingdom of God.
‎Paul was a spiritual man,
‎and he ‘conquered the evil with the good’
‎by following
‎Jesus’ instructions at Mark 12:17
‎of giving “Caesar’s things to Caesar,
‎but God’s things to God,”
‎all the while displaying
‎“a mildness that belongs to wisdom.”
‎At 1 Peter 2:21,
‎we receive further direction
‎about the course that we are to follow.
‎Peter writes:
‎“In fact,
‎to this course you were called,
‎“because even Christ suffered for you,
‎leaving a model for you
‎to follow his steps closely.”
‎Some of Christ’s steps
‎are enumerated
‎in verses 22 and 23,
‎where it reads:
‎“He [Jesus] committed no sin,
‎“nor was deception found in his mouth.
‎“When he was being insulted,
‎“he did not insult in return.
‎“When he was suffering,
‎he did not threaten,
‎“but he entrusted himself
‎to the One who judges righteously.”
‎Jehovah is
‎“the One who judges righteously.”
‎However, the Jewish religious leaders
‎did not judge the Christ righteously.
‎They insulted Jesus frequently
‎and even accused him of having a demon.
‎Jesus did not stoop
‎to “return evil for evil,”
‎hurling insults or threatening people.
‎Insults and threats
‎do not open hearts
‎to accept the good news.
‎When Jesus was on trial,
‎the Jewish religious leaders
‎spurred the crowd on
‎to cry out for his execution.
‎The Roman authorities
‎had Jesus nailed to a torture stake
‎to suffer a cruel and excruciating death.
‎While suffering on the torture stake,
‎what did Jesus speak about?
‎Did he curse the Roman soldiers
‎who had mistreated him
‎and were now executing him?
‎To the contrary,
‎he ‘conquered the evil with the good.’
‎Among Jesus’ last words
‎are those recorded at Luke 23:34:
‎“Father, forgive them,
‎for they do not know
‎what they are doing.”
‎Jesus knew
‎that the Roman soldiers
‎were ignorant
‎of who he really was
‎and did not know
‎what they were doing.
‎He could forgive them with the hope
‎that they would eventually respond
‎to the truth and become his disciples.
‎In every respect,
‎Jesus ‘conquered the evil with the good,’
‎and he always displayed
‎complete confidence
‎in “the One who judges righteously,”
‎Jehovah God.
‎We want to demonstrate the same kind
‎of confidence in Jehovah and in his Word
‎that Jesus displayed.
‎We do our best to imitate the Christ
‎by applying the spirit-inspired counsel
‎at Romans 12:17, 18:
‎“Return evil for evil to no one.
‎“Take into consideration
‎“what is fine
‎from the viewpoint of all men.
‎“If possible, as far as it depends on you,
‎be peaceable with all men.”
‎Heeding this counsel
‎is particularly important
‎in homes that are religiously divided.
‎The Christian mate resists the temptation
‎to repay an unkind word or act
‎with another unkindness.
‎Really, no good comes
‎from ‘returning evil for evil.’
‎On the contrary, such an attitude
‎can only aggravate the situation.
‎In the domestic setting,
‎a wife who shows genuine kindness
‎to her husband
‎after he makes unpleasant comments
‎about her beliefs
‎may well diffuse
‎a potentially explosive situation.
‎At Proverbs 31:12,
‎we are told how a capable, God-fearing wife
‎deals with her husband:
‎“She rewards him with good,
‎not bad, all the days of her life.”
‎Additionally, by taking “into consideration
‎what is fine from the viewpoint of all men,”
‎Jehovah’s people
‎have often overcome prejudice
‎by providing practical assistance
‎to their neighbors as opportunity affords,
‎and particularly when a disaster strikes.
‎We conscientiously adhere
‎to Romans 12:19, which states:
‎“Do not avenge yourselves, beloved,
‎“but yield place to the wrath;
‎for it is written:
‎“‘“Vengeance is mine;
‎I will repay,” says Jehovah.’”
‎The footnote on verse 19 shows
‎that Paul is telling us
‎to yield to “God’s wrath,” or anger.
‎Jehovah is the one
‎who will set matters straight,
‎and he will do it
‎much better than we ever could.
‎As James 1:20 states:
‎“Man’s anger
‎does not bring about God’s righteousness.”
‎The theme of this discussion
‎is summarized exquisitely
‎at Romans 12:20, 21
‎with this direction
‎to all of Jehovah’s people:
‎“But ‘if your enemy is hungry, feed him;
‎“‘if he is thirsty,
‎give him something to drink;
‎“for by doing this
‎you will heap fiery coals on his head.’
‎“Do not let yourself be conquered by the evil,
‎but keep conquering the evil with the good.”
‎Let’s now turn
‎to a modern-day example
‎of conquering evil with good.
‎In South Korea,
‎19,000 of our brothers
‎have at some point
‎been imprisoned
‎for their Christian neutrality.
‎But inside the prison walls,
‎our brothers have the support
‎of their fellow Christians.
‎We met a group
‎of brothers who still cherish
‎the friendships
‎they developed while imprisoned,
‎although it’s been about 40 years
‎since their release.
‎When I was 21 years old,
‎I was sent to prison
‎in the Nonsan military training center
‎because I refused to serve in the military.
‎The soldier working
‎in the military prison came
‎and started to beat me,
‎and he beat me relentlessly.
‎It was late December 1975.
‎Four of the brothers were put
‎into standing solitary confinement cells
‎called dokgeochang.
‎It literally feels like you are in a coffin.
‎The outside temperature dropped
‎to minus 13 degrees Celsius (8°F),
‎and cold air seeped out from the wet walls.
‎The brothers couldn’t lay down to sleep,
‎so they had to crouch,
‎and I could hear them groaning all night.
‎I extended my hand through the iron bars
‎to the brother in the cell next to mine,
‎and he did the same.
‎We held hands
‎and encouraged each other to stay strong.
‎My health condition wasn’t really good
‎while serving my prison sentence.
‎I weighed about 47 kilograms (103 lbs),
‎and without my family’s support,
‎I was mentally and physically weak.
‎Under these extremely difficult circumstances,
‎there were times I wasn’t able to eat at all.
‎During those times,
‎the brothers provided me
‎with porridge
‎—which was easy to digest—
‎warm clothing,
‎and a sleeping bag for the winter.
‎I could really feel their love.
‎Having been sent to prison three times,
‎I truly feel that Jehovah showed interest in me
‎and took care of me
‎just as he promised at 1 Peter 5:7.
‎He especially supported me through my brothers
‎when I was facing difficulties.
‎A day in the prison started
‎with us eating breakfast
‎and then moving 300 bricks.
‎After lunch, we would have
‎to carry another 300 bricks.
‎Because I usually finished my work early,
‎I had a 20-minute break
‎before going back in.
‎However, this brother named Park Byung-Man
‎who was much stronger
‎and bigger than I was
‎carried bricks all day long.
‎I found out later that Park Byung-Man
‎was carrying Choi Sung-Kyu’s share
‎of bricks because of his frail health.
‎This kind of brotherly love really moved me
‎to start studying the Bible.
‎I got baptized a year later
‎in April of 1977 in the Anyang Prison.
‎After getting baptized,
‎my mother passed away,
‎and two months before being released,
‎my father passed away as well.
‎So that time was especially difficult for me.
‎But the brothers encouraged me
‎with their warm words and kind gestures.
‎Their encouragement really touched me
‎and helped me to endure until I was released.
‎One time, I had a severe stomachache.
‎The symptoms were not getting any better
‎with the medication I was given,
‎so I was having a very difficult time.
‎One day, we were served some vegetables
‎as a side dish
‎and one brother crushed
‎and squeezed the vegetables
‎to make juice for me.
‎He cared for me that way for several days.
‎I really would like to see that self-sacrificing
‎and loving brother once again.
‎At the time, none of our publications
‎other than the Bible were allowed into the prison.
‎Of course, that included our songbook.
‎The brothers memorized
‎the lyrics from the songbook,
‎and they would write them down.
‎Also, there were some songs
‎that were sung at the regional convention.
‎Songs like . . .
‎or
‎We sang them silently together
‎even in this isolated place.
‎It was a great source of encouragement
‎to share the love among our fellow brothers.
‎I remember this encouraging scripture
‎from 1 Corinthians 10:13.
‎It says that Jehovah
‎‘does not let us be tempted
‎‘beyond what we can bear
‎and will make the way out
‎so we may endure it.’
‎Although there were many challenges,
‎I was convinced
‎that Jehovah would always
‎make a way out through our fellow brothers.
‎Even though 40 years have passed,
‎when we look back at those days,
‎the memories are still fresh
‎and we are moved to tears at times.
‎So to make a meaningful trip
‎out of our 40 years of friendship,
‎all the friends who went through the same trials
‎decided to visit the headquarters
‎in the United States together.
‎It’s really refreshing to be here
‎with everyone again today.
‎It feels like I’m taking a field trip.
‎I was especially moved to tears
‎when I saw our old prison uniforms
‎there in the museum
‎at world headquarters
‎displayed in the neutrality section.
‎While on the tour, the brothers sat
‎and lay down on the floor
‎inside the dokgeochang
‎and we were able to reflect on the times
‎we spent together in prison.
‎Our gratitude to Jehovah
‎for giving us such loyal friends was renewed.
‎Yes, through their brotherly love
‎and the power and strength
‎given to them by holy spirit,
‎our Korean brothers were able
‎to conquer the evil with the good.
‎Although we may not be imprisoned,
‎having true friends
‎can help us through many trials.
‎But what is a true friend?
‎Where can we find them,
‎and why are they so important?
‎Our music video will answer these questions.
‎It is entitled True Friends.
‎Life can be hard
‎if we walk it alone,
‎living
‎in these last days.
‎Jehovah knows
‎that we need friends
‎to help us
‎along the way.
‎But where do we go?
‎Where do we turn
‎to find those true companions?
‎Well, remember what
‎we learn in his Word.
‎True friends
‎Love you when you’re down,
‎Happy when you’re up,
‎Right by your side when trials come,
‎Speak up if you’re wrong,
‎Commend you when you’re right,
‎Keep you on track
‎in the race for life,
‎Help you keep
‎Jehovah first right to the end.
‎Yeah,
‎that’s a true friend.
‎A true friend
‎shows love at all times.
‎That’s in His Word,
‎we know.
‎So if troubles appear,
‎don’t give in or fight.
‎Say a prayer;
‎let it go.
‎Whether we’re older
‎or whether we’re young,
‎we all
‎got to stick together,
‎And one day soon
‎we’ll be in Paradise.
‎True friends
‎Love you when you’re down,
‎Happy when you’re up,
‎Right by your side when trials come,
‎Speak up if you’re wrong,
‎Commend you when you’re right,
‎Keep you on track
‎in the race for life,
‎Help you keep Jehovah
‎first right to the end.
‎Yeah,
‎that’s a true friend.
‎Someone you trust,
‎Someone who cares
‎about you serving Jehovah,
‎A shoulder to lean on
‎and the right words to help you mend—
‎Yeah,
‎that’s a true friend.
‎True friends
‎Love you when you’re down,
‎Happy when you’re up,
‎Right by your side when trials come,
‎Speak up if you’re wrong,
‎Commend you when you’re right,
‎Keep you on track
‎in the race for life,
‎Help you keep Jehovah
‎first right to the end.
‎True friends
‎Love you when you’re down,
‎Happy when you’re up,
‎Right by your side when trials come,
‎Speak up if you’re wrong,
‎Commend you when you’re right,
‎Keep you on track
‎in the race for life,
‎Help you keep Jehovah
‎first right to the end.
‎Yeah,
‎that’s a true friend.
‎That’s a true friend.
‎Oh,
‎that’s a true friend.
‎What a blessing it is to have true friends
‎around us in the Christian congregation!
‎But at times,
‎our imperfection may create roadblocks
‎between us and our dear friends,
‎and we may start developing
‎negative feelings about them.
‎In this Bethel morning worship,
‎pay attention to how Brother Geoffrey Jackson
‎of the Governing Body
‎helps us deal with such thinking.
‎Well, perhaps we could take our Bibles
‎and turn to Colossians 3:​13.
‎And let’s analyze this verse together
‎and see what it is that Jehovah expects of us.
‎So in Colossians 3:​13,
‎it says:
‎“Continue putting up with one another
‎“and forgiving one another freely
‎“even if anyone has a cause
‎for complaint against another.
‎“Just as Jehovah freely forgave you,
‎you must also do the same.”
‎Well, certainly this verse
‎gives us plenty of food for thought
‎​—doesn’t it?​—
‎areas in which, perhaps,
‎we can work on and improve in.
‎But what two things stand out
‎as being required of us?
‎Well, looking back,
‎you notice the first one,
‎“continue putting up with one another,”
‎and then the second point,
‎“forgiving one another freely.”
‎Well, let’s look at that first expression:
‎“Continue putting up with one another.”
‎Well, what’s the difference
‎between these two expressions?
‎Well, we’re told that this first expression
‎doesn’t refer to serious sins
‎but perhaps talks about things
‎that are irritating, annoying,
‎things that we may not necessarily
‎have a cause for complaint concerning,
‎but they still get us very upset anyway
‎​—these minor things.
‎What are some of the things that annoy you?
‎Let’s be honest.
‎Are you annoyed when someone is always late?
‎Are you annoyed when they’re always early?
‎Are you annoyed when someone is outspoken?
‎Does it annoy you when someone is too quiet?
‎It’s amazing​
‎—isn’t it?​—
‎what the things that annoy us are.
‎I remember back in the ’70’s,
‎Brother Knorr gave an outstanding talk
‎where he alluded to the fact
‎that maybe there’s a sister in the congregation,
‎and she’s hearing
‎this other sister, new in the truth,
‎answering up time after time,
‎and in her heart, she’s thinking,
‎‘Why doesn’t she just keep quiet?’
‎Well, maybe we’ve all
‎experienced those feelings.
‎And if we’re judged on them,
‎perhaps we’ll agree:
‎‘Well, it’s not justified;
‎I don’t really have a cause,
‎but it still irritates me.’
‎It’s true—isn’t it?​—
‎the expression
‎“Sometimes it’s not the mountains
‎ahead of us that cause problems,
‎it’s the pebble in the shoe.”
‎And it’s sometimes the small things
‎that irritate us the most.
‎I remember when I was serving
‎in Western Samoa
‎many years ago at the branch,
‎we had quite a number of brothers
‎from overseas working on construction.
‎And there was one brother who had
‎the habit of first thing in the morning
‎as he arrived before breakfast,
‎saying, “Good morning!” to everyone.
‎Some found that annoying.
‎Maybe you can relate to that.
‎And, no doubt, you feel
‎very happy when you read the scripture
‎at Proverbs 27:14,
‎where it says in one translation:
‎‘A loud and cheerful greeting
‎early in the morning
‎is taken as a curse.’
‎You may be thinking, ‘Amen to that.’
‎And that brother ceased his habit
‎after he read that scripture​
‎—or at least it was read to him.
‎But we may not always be able
‎to find a scripture
‎that backs up this irritation that we feel.
‎So, what do we do?
‎Well, what does it say?
‎“Continue putting up with one another.”
‎“Continue”​—it’s something
‎that we just have to keep on doing.
‎Now, that brings us
‎to the second part of our verse,
‎“forgiving one another freely.”
‎It’s interesting, when we look
‎at other translations of this verse,
‎most follow the King James Version
‎and just say “forgive.”
‎The New World Translation says ‘forgive freely.’
‎The reason is that this isn’t your normal
‎Greek word for “forgiveness.”
‎It denotes generosity,
‎a willingness to go beyond what’s required.
‎It’s interesting
‎that The Watchtower even back in 1882
‎was using that expression,
‎to ‘forgive one another freely,’
‎well before the time
‎of the New World Translation.
‎So this gives us something to think about
‎because it’s not just a matter of forgiving,
‎but we need to be generous about forgiving.
‎We have to be willing to,
‎as it were, bestow a pardon
‎on someone
‎who really doesn’t deserve that pardon.
‎Now, why should we be interested
‎in developing
‎and working on these two aspects:
‎“putting up with one another”
‎and ‘forgiving freely’?
‎Well, we’ve heard
‎the reasons many times before, haven’t we?
‎The first one, of course,
‎is that Jehovah has forgiven us.
‎If we turn back just one chapter,
‎chapter 2 of Colossians and verse 13,
‎this point is highlighted for us.
‎It says in chapter 2, verse 13:
‎“Furthermore, though you
‎were dead in your trespasses
‎“and in the uncircumcised state of your flesh,
‎“God made you alive together with him.
‎“He kindly forgave us
‎all our trespasses.”
‎So this is the model
‎that Jehovah has given us.
‎It’s true,
‎we sometimes can find some reason
‎why we feel
‎we don’t have to forgive someone else.
‎But remember the illustration Jesus gave
‎of the slave who had the huge debt.
‎If you calculated it in denarius,
‎there were 60 million denarii that he owed;
‎he was forgiven that.
‎Then he went after the other man
‎who owed him just a small amount.
‎But have you ever thought
‎that if you asked that slave,
‎maybe he would say: “Well, it’s true.
‎“I really appreciate having everything forgiven,
‎but I still don’t have any money.
‎“I need some money,
‎so that’s why I wanted to get
‎the other slave to give me the money.”
‎Well, there’s always a reason
‎​—isn’t there?​—
‎⁠even if it’s a distorted reason
‎as to why we don’t follow Jehovah’s example.
‎But looking back at Colossians 3:​13,
‎what does it say?
‎“If anyone has a cause
‎for complaint against another.”
‎So that gives us a good idea, doesn’t it?
‎The second reason, of course, is that
‎we do need others to forgive us.
‎The very things that annoy us
‎and irritate us in others are sometimes
‎the same things that we do to others.
‎Have you ever noticed that?
‎And how annoying it is
‎when someone points that out to you:
‎“You’re annoyed with that person?
‎Don’t you realize what you do?”
‎Well, that’s something good for us to remember​
‎—isn’t it?​—
‎the fact that we do need
‎to have others forgive us.
‎And then another reason
‎is that it maintains the peace
‎within the Christian congregation.
‎The Watchtower made a comment on this.
‎It said that in countries
‎where our work is restricted or under ban,
‎many of our brothers
‎have to meet together in smaller groups.
‎And when you do that, you get to know
‎everyone’s weaknesses and idiosyncrasies.
‎It’s so much easier to be annoyed by others
‎when you’re dealing
‎with small groups of persons.
‎The Watchtower then made the comment
‎what good training it is for us now
‎to learn how to put up with one another
‎when we’re in larger groups,
‎because later we may need
‎to worship Jehovah in smaller groups.
‎So it’s good training for us
‎as we keep peace in the congregation.
‎And what can help us?
‎Well, there are many different things
‎that can help us in this regard.
‎The one point in the marginal reference
‎you see there is at 1 Peter 4:​8,
‎and that’s where it tells us we need
‎to “have intense love for one another”​
‎—not just love but “intense love.”
‎And this word “intense” means “full strength.”
‎Literally, it means “to stretch out our love.”
‎So as we come across these things
‎that irritate us, annoy us, in life
‎or if we come across persons
‎who actually do sin against us,
‎what should we keep in mind?
‎“Continue putting up with one another.”
‎‘Continue freely forgiving one another.’
‎That sound advice
‎also applies strongly in marriage,
‎when two people decide
‎to share their lives together.
‎Perhaps your mate is an unbeliever.
‎Differences in belief
‎can cause a level of friction,
‎but how one handles,
‎or conquers, the situation
‎can bring you peace
‎and even be a great witness.
‎How did 15 years go by so fast?
‎We were so young when we got married
‎—maybe too young.
‎We had so little in common.
‎When I started studying the Bible,
‎I thought Thomas would be as excited
‎as I was to learn the truth.
‎But every conversation we had on the subject
‎seemed to turn into an argument.
‎Looking back,
‎I really wish I’d handled it better.
‎As the years went by,
‎he did become more open to discussion.
‎But it’s been hard worshipping God alone.
‎Others in the congregation
‎are able to serve Jehovah together
‎and even reach out for theocratic goals
‎like the School for Kingdom Evangelizers,
‎something I would love to do.
‎Why can’t I have a husband
‎who loves Jehovah like I do?
‎Abigail probably felt the same way
‎but with more reason.
‎Her husband was a bully and a drunkard
‎and was despised by his entire household.
‎At that time,
‎many marriages were arranged,
‎so Abigail had very little control
‎over her circumstances.
‎But her words and actions
‎showed that she was a spiritual woman
‎who didn’t focus
‎on what she could not control
‎but on what she could.
‎I determined to do the same.
‎I meditated on Jesus’ words
‎at Matthew 19:6:
‎“What God has yoked together,
‎let no man put apart.”
‎To Jehovah, marriage is permanent
‎—even my marriage to an unbeliever.
‎So instead of dwelling on changing
‎my husband or my marriage,
‎I focused on changing myself.
‎Thomas does not love Jehovah,
‎but he’s not a “Nabal” either.
‎He is loyal, and he loves me.
‎He is entitled to the respect that the Bible
‎commands wives to show to their husbands.
‎So I’m making an effort
‎to be more respectful and loving to him.
‎Thomas hasn’t developed an interest
‎in the truth or started studying.
‎But I have the satisfaction of knowing
‎my God is pleased with me,
‎and I have the same view
‎of marriage that he does.
‎How exciting!
‎Is Thomas slowly noticing
‎the benefits of the truth?
‎No doubt,
‎Emma’s faithful and respectful conduct
‎has had a deep impact
‎on how he views Jehovah.
‎And the truth can really change a person.
‎Getting to know Jehovah can help someone
‎to get their life back on track.
‎Two fleshly brothers,
‎Dimitris and Agis Sotiropoulos,
‎are good examples of how
‎the good can conquer the evil
‎despite a challenging upbringing.
‎My father was a self-made factory owner.
‎He started a business working
‎with rubber and plastics,
‎and we led a financially comfortable way of life.
‎But in the middle of the 1970’s,
‎things started going badly with his work.
‎For this reason,
‎he fell into a depression,
‎and he committed suicide.
‎This was a great shock.
‎I went to the wall and wrote the words
‎“He lives.”
‎I didn’t want to believe that from that day on,
‎I wouldn’t see my father again.
‎At the age of about ten, I began to develop
‎strong antireligious tendencies.
‎And later, at the age of 17,
‎I also expressed them by participating
‎in the most important incident
‎of the student movement
‎against the military junta
‎that was prevailing in Greece
‎and ruling the country.
‎I became a member of the Communist Party.
‎I went to Santorini and started a business.
‎I opened a bar.
‎Of course, all this included unsavory things
‎like immorality, drugs,
‎and plenty of alcohol.
‎A few months later,
‎I left to study in Germany.
‎It was the first time I met
‎a brother engaging in street work.
‎People would approach him,
‎and some would swear;
‎some even spat at him.
‎It impressed me immensely
‎how he stood calmly
‎and accepted this treatment.
‎We had interesting conversations.
‎My studies ended, and I returned to Greece
‎to take on the responsibility of the factory.
‎When I finished my studies in Germany,
‎I left with a sense of deep respect
‎for Jehovah’s Witnesses.
‎The influence of my friends
‎led me to go into the military,
‎and there I saw a huge amount of corruption.
‎The hope I had that we humans
‎would be able to succeed
‎without external help
‎—without God—
‎began to collapse,
‎and then the things I had heard
‎from Jehovah’s Witnesses
‎suddenly came to my mind.
‎The same afternoon,
‎I sought out a family friend,
‎the mother of a childhood friend, named Lily.
‎I said to her, “Please give me a Bible
‎and some Bible study publications
‎because I want to study them.”
‎I read everywhere,
‎and anything that I didn’t understand,
‎I wrote down in a notebook.
‎I got to the point, in just a few days,
‎where I had written down 80 to 90 questions.
‎Harry impressed me
‎because every time I asked him a question,
‎he gave me the answer from the Bible.
‎That convinced me that I’d found the truth.
‎So in that moment,
‎I decided to leave the military
‎and to quit smoking.
‎A few months passed by,
‎where I was occupied mostly with the factory,
‎until I recognized
‎that for me to make progress in the truth,
‎I had to sell my shares in the factory.
‎And on July 7, 1984, I was baptized.
‎The authorities
‎—the police, the mayor,
‎the health inspectors—
‎began to demand money
‎so that I could keep the bar open.
‎I refused all the things they asked of me,
‎and so the war became harder
‎until one night when I went
‎to open the door to enter my home;
‎I heard a tramping from behind,
‎I tried to turn and see,
‎and as I turned,
‎I was hit in the face.
‎During that time,
‎when all of this was happening,
‎my brother Dimitris arrived.
‎As brothers,
‎we never really had a relationship.
‎When he came to Santorini
‎and began to talk to me
‎and help me understand
‎what was happening to me,
‎I realized that this was a different Dimitris.
‎I said to him, “I want us
‎to start studying the Bible together.”
‎I had the Bible with me
‎almost everywhere I went
‎so that I could read it.
‎I realized that Jehovah was helping me
‎to understand what I was living for.
‎He was helping me to understand
‎that I could have a real goal, a purpose,
‎and a hope.
‎On the day of my baptism,
‎I felt that I was drawing closer to Jehovah.
‎I felt like my smile went from ear to ear.
‎And now with Lydia,
‎I have the great joy of serving
‎in the Romany territory.
‎We enjoy very nice Bible studies.
‎It is truly something
‎that shows you Jehovah’s love,
‎interest, and affection
‎—things that I had felt
‎many years ago
‎when I studied with my brother.
‎Today, my brother and I
‎love each other very much.
‎It is a relationship characterized
‎by brotherly love
‎as it is expressed in the Bible.
‎We are very close to each other.
‎This is really a change.
‎Now we are truly brothers!
‎Today, both Dimitris
‎and Agis serve as elders
‎and have spent many years
‎in the full-time ministry.
‎Have you noticed the many ways
‎we have seen the good conquer
‎the evil in this month’s broadcast?
‎Our brothers in Korea
‎were able to endure unjust imprisonment
‎with the support of their fellow believers.
‎Viktor Winter,
‎who was also imprisoned,
‎conquered the evil
‎by maintaining a theocratic routine.
‎Our music video helped us appreciate
‎the value of our true friends
‎in the congregation,
‎who will help us fulfill our ministry
‎in this wicked world.
‎Also, Brother Jackson
‎shared principles to help us
‎overcome negative feelings
‎we may have about others
‎as a result of our imperfection.
‎Over time,
‎Emma learned to apply those principles
‎in dealing
‎with her unbelieving husband, Thomas.
‎And finally,
‎the truth conquered the evil
‎when the Sotiropoulos brothers
‎were able to clean up their lives.
‎Before we conclude,
‎we have an announcement to make.
‎You will be happy to know
‎that the next installment
‎of the video series Was it Designed?
‎entitled The Seahorse’s Tail
‎is available on Video on Demand
‎and jw.org starting this month.
‎Perhaps you can watch it
‎during your next Family Worship evening.
‎Let’s also briefly visit
‎our brothers and sisters in Portugal.
‎As the most western country
‎in continental Europe,
‎Portugal is known
‎as the place where the land ends
‎and the sea begins.
‎Mainland Portugal
‎has over 800 kilometers,
‎or over 500 miles, of Atlantic Coast.
‎In the southern part of the country,
‎they have over 3,000 hours
‎of sunshine per year.
‎Portugal became world renowned
‎as a seafaring nation
‎with colonies around the world.
‎In the 15th century,
‎navigators and explorers
‎from Portugal
‎traveled to distant places
‎such as Brazil, India,
‎and many parts of Africa.
‎The good news reached Portugal in 1925,
‎but the work was either restricted
‎or under ban from 1926 to 1974.
‎However, the brothers
‎and sisters were good examples
‎of “conquering the evil with the good.”
‎Despite the restrictions and persecution,
‎they continued to preach
‎and gather together to worship Jehovah.
‎When the Witnesses
‎gained legal recognition in 1974,
‎the country reported
‎about 13,500 publishers
‎and almost 40,000 attended
‎the first public meeting.
‎Today, the country reports
‎some 49,500 publishers
‎and a ratio of 1 publisher
‎to about 200 people
‎—one of the lowest ratios in Europe.
‎The ratio is even lower in Almada,
‎which is across the Tagus River
‎from the capital city, Lisbon.
‎In Almada, there are 16 congregations
‎with almost 1,400 publishers in total
‎with a ratio of 1 publisher
‎to about 100 residents.
‎Many of the brothers and sisters
‎in Almada are older
‎and endured faithfully during the ban,
‎setting an example to the younger ones.
‎In addition to theocratic activities,
‎our brothers in Almada
‎regularly come together to associate,
‎which can include
‎a game of soccer or singing songs.
‎They all send their love and greetings
‎to the worldwide brotherhood.
‎This is JW Broadcasting
‎from the world headquarters
‎of Jehovah’s Witnesses.