Imagine for a moment
that you’re going on a trip.
The tickets are a gift;
a friend has paid the price.
All you have to do is pack your bags
and get to the airport.
Now as you know, packing isn’t easy,
and dragging heavy bags
around the airport is exhausting.
Remember the days
before luggage had wheels?
How did we do that?
Heavy baggage can make even a vacation
seem like a burden.
Well, the point is this:
You and I have set out on an exciting journey
—a journey to God’s new world.
The trip is free; the ransom paid the price.
All we have to do is get there.
And that’s the hard part, right?
And why?
Because each one of us is carrying
some type of heavy baggage on this journey.
Now, it’s true our life is blessed.
As Isaiah 65:13 says, figuratively,
we’re eating and drinking
while the world goes hungry and thirsty.
Still, Acts 14:22 says:
“We must enter into the Kingdom of God
through many tribulations.”
We have anxieties.
And Proverbs 12:25 says:
‘Anxiety in the heart can weigh it down.’
The heavy baggage we carry
can make even the journey to God’s new world
seem like a burden.
Well, the good news is that we have help.
Open your Bible to 1 Kings 8:38, 39.
Here Solomon prayed
on behalf of Jehovah’s people
at the inauguration of the temple.
And what he said in that prayer
can help us put wheels on our baggage
so it’s easier for us to carry.
At 1 Kings 8, beginning with verse 38,
Solomon says to Jehovah:
“Whatever prayer, whatever request for favor
“may be made by any man
or by all your people Israel
“(for each one knows the plague
of his own heart)
“when they spread out their hands
toward this house,
“then may you hear from the heavens,
your dwelling place,
and may you forgive and take action.”
Now let’s stop there.
Notice that phrase
“each one knows the plague of his own heart.”
In stating that, Solomon wasn’t referring
to the nation as a whole.
He was referring to private suffering
—the baggage each person had to carry,
the problems no one else might know about.
And although Solomon evidently had
a specific type of plague in mind
—one that required forgiveness—
by extension his words can apply
to any anxiety that weighs us down.
For example,
chapter 2 of the “God’s Love” book
applies Solomon’s words
to a personal weakness
we might struggle with.
The May 1, 2010, Watchtower applies it
to the grief a person feels
after losing a mate.
The point is:
Any anxiety that weighs us down
can be considered a plague of the heart.
What is the plague of your heart?
What anxiety weighs you down
on your journey to God’s new world?
Whatever baggage we carry,
the scripture we just read
confirms that we have help.
Notice, Solomon prayed that Jehovah
would not only “hear from the heavens”
but also “take action”
—if not to eliminate our load
then at least to help us carry it.
For the rest of this discussion,
we’ll see how Jehovah can do that
in three situations:
(1) when circumstances discourage us,
(2) when people upset us,
and (3) when negative emotions
overwhelm us.
In all situations,
Jehovah can help us cope
with the plague of our heart.
Let’s see how.
First, when circumstances discourage us.
Now, when it comes to circumstances,
life is unpredictable.
In this system,
things can change just like that
with one phone call,
one accident,
one diagnosis.
Let me tell you about Anny,
who was diagnosed at age 19
with pulmonary fibrosis,
and at first she felt
this was completely unfair.
Anny says: “Pulmonary fibrosis
affects heavy smokers,
“and I had never had a cigarette in my life!
“I was depressed, I wouldn’t eat,
“and I wouldn’t talk to people.
“I would just lie in bed
and think about how miserable my life was.”
Now, Anny is one of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
and she was one when she got sick.
She understood the real cause of her illness,
and she knew about the new world.
Still, this discouraging circumstance
threw Anny off course.
She says, “I prayed and prayed
and prayed about it,
but it felt like I was just talking
to the wall.”
Now, regardless of our age,
we may relate to Anny’s comment.
When any of us face
a discouraging circumstance,
we pray about it repeatedly.
And if nothing changes,
we may wonder whether Jehovah cares about
or even sees what we’re going through.
A discouraging circumstance
can become a plague of our heart.
How can we cope with it?
Well, let’s look at 2 Corinthians 12:7-9.
Here the apostle Paul
faced a discouraging circumstance
—one that he calls “a thorn in the flesh.”
Now, as you realize,
we don’t know what that thorn was.
It might have been a physical affliction.
Whatever it was, as we read these verses,
try to detect two things:
(1) what Paul could not control
and (2) what he could control.
Second Corinthians 12,
beginning with verse 7:
“To keep me from becoming overly exalted,
“I was given a thorn in the flesh,
an angel of Satan,
“to keep slapping me,
so that I might not be overly exalted.
“Three times I begged the Lord about this,
that it would depart from me.
“But he said to me:
“‘My undeserved kindness
is sufficient for you,
for my power is being
made perfect in weakness.’”
Now let’s stop there
and look at our two components.
First, what couldn’t Paul control?
The answer is obvious
—the circumstance itself—
his “thorn in the flesh.”
Paul even prayed about it three times,
but nothing changed.
The circumstance was beyond his control.
What could Paul control?
His response.
And part of that response
was to accept the reality
of his situation
to the point that he says in verse 9:
“Most gladly, . . .
I will boast about my weaknesses.”
Once Paul realized
that his thorn would not be removed,
he didn’t waste time doubting God’s love
or asking ‘Why me?’
or comparing himself to others
who seemed to have an easier life.
No, Paul accepted reality.
He viewed his thorn as “an angel of Satan,”
and he got about the business of endurance.
Now, Paul’s experience gives us a key
to coping with any discouraging circumstance.
First, break it down into two components:
(1) what we can’t control
and (2) what we can.
And often, like Paul,
what we can control is our response.
That is a choice.
When we face a discouraging circumstance,
we could choose to become bitter about life,
angry at God.
We could even let it stumble us as some have.
Or we can choose a better response.
And like Paul,
a better response usually involves
first accepting the reality of the situation.
Now, at first that might sound cold,
but accepting reality is vital.
Why?
Page 7 of the April 2014 Awake! says this:
“By learning to accept
what you cannot change,
“. . . you are also more likely to look
for ways to cope with the situation . . .
“You start to take a measure of control
of what seems to be
an uncontrollable situation.”
Now, Harold King is an example of that.
As you know, he was imprisoned for his faith,
confined to a four-and-a-half
by nine-foot cell.
Brother King certainly couldn’t control
his circumstance,
but he could control his response.
Once Brother King
accepted the reality of his situation,
he thought of things that he could control
—things that even prison walls
could not prevent him from doing.
For example: He prayed;
he memorized scriptures;
he wrote Kingdom songs;
he celebrated the Memorial
right there in his cell alone;
he even went out in service
by creating imaginary householders.
Once Brother King accepted reality,
he was able to take a measure of control
of what seemed to be
an uncontrollable situation.
A brother whose wife
was diagnosed with cancer
relates how they did something similar.
They couldn’t control the disease.
But what could they do?
Quoted in the August 2011 Awake!
the husband says:
“We decided that at regular intervals
“we would not talk
about the cancer for a whole day.
“Instead, we focused
on the positive aspects of our life.
“It was like taking a vacation
from the disease.
Regularly we had a cancer-free day.”
Now, that’s how this couple
took a measure of control.
Others might choose a different method,
but again the point is this:
Once we accept reality,
we’re more likely to find ways
to cope with the situation
and to even take a measure
of control over it.
But is accepting reality all we can do?
No, there’s something more.
The article
“Learning to Live with the Unchangeable”
in the March 15, 1978, Watchtower
suggests this:
“In whatever state or condition
you might find yourself,
look for its compensations or mercies.”
That’s exactly what Paul did
in connection with his thorn.
For example, look back at 2 Corinthians 12.
In verse 7, twice Paul says
that his thorn kept him
“from becoming overly exalted.”
Humility—that’s one compensation.
In verse 9, Paul says God’s power
is “made perfect in weakness.”
Increased reliance on Jehovah
—that’s a second compensation.
Here’s a third.
Let’s look at Philippians 4:11.
Now, Philippians was written
about five or six years
after Paul wrote to the Corinthians
about his thorn in the flesh.
So that thorn may have been
one of the things on Paul’s mind
as he wrote what we’re about to read.
At Philippians 4:11,
the second part of the verse,
Paul says:
“I have learned to be self-sufficient
“[or according to the footnote, “content”]
regardless of my circumstances.”
Now, with these words,
Paul expresses a vital truth
that contentment, even happiness,
does not depend
on having ideal circumstances.
You know, sometimes we talk as if it does.
We say things like:
‘I’ll be happy
when I get a better work assignment’
or ‘I’ll be happy when I get married.’
‘I’ll be happy when I get a better room.’
‘I’ll be happy when I get a better roommate.’
The idea is: ‘I’ll only be happy
when my circumstances change.’
It’s been said that people who think that way
strive and strive but never arrive
because as soon as they get that circumstance
that was supposed to make them happy,
another obstacle looms up
and they’re discontent again.
Paul chose to be content,
despite his circumstances.
And notice, he says in verse 11:
“I have learned” this.
Contentment might not have been
his default position.
Perhaps like many of us,
Paul had a tendency
to veer towards negativity
when confronted with a trial.
But Paul learned to be content
even when his repeated prayers for relief
were not answered
the way he would have liked.
In fact, we could summarize
the lesson Paul learned this way:
Don’t let the blessing you’re praying for
blind you to the compensations
and mercies you have.
You know, sometimes
when we’re going through a trial,
we tend to narrow the focus
of our prayers by, in effect,
telling Jehovah how we expect to be blessed.
And yet, Jehovah may already be giving us
compensations and mercies
that we haven’t considered.
That’s what Anny, the sister
with pulmonary fibrosis, came to learn.
Remember how she said,
“I prayed and prayed and prayed,
but it felt like I was just talking
to the wall”?
Anny also admits,
“At first, I was even mad at Jehovah
for not helping me
in the way I wanted to be helped.”
How did Anny come to see
compensations and mercies
even in the midst of a serious illness?
Here’s what she says:
“My dad opened my eyes.
“While I was so upset at Jehovah,
“my dad wouldn’t stop
praying to him and thanking him
“and talking about
how good Jehovah had been to me.
“I had just been through
the worst months of my life,
“and my dad was thanking Jehovah.
“‘For what?’ I asked him.
“He told me:
“‘You have no idea
how expensive your medicine was,
“‘and I wasn’t even working.
“‘Somehow we managed
to get everything we needed.
“‘There was always food in the house.
“‘Brothers kept coming
to make sure we were eating.
Jehovah gave us the strength
to keep going and not give up.’”
And then Anny’s dad told her this:
“Just because Jehovah didn’t help you
the way you wanted to be helped
doesn’t mean he didn’t do it.”
In essence, her dad was saying,
‘Don’t let the blessing you’re praying for
blind you to the compensations
and mercies you have.’
Anny now says:
“Jehovah helps us
in ways we can’t see at first
“because we’re so overwhelmed
by what we’re going through.
“But I’ve learned that Jehovah
has a way of doing things,
and his way is always better than my way.”
We can adopt a similar viewpoint.
If we can see the compensations
and mercies in our situation,
then we’ll be better able
to cope with a circumstance
that has become a plague of our heart.
So to review:
How can the apostle Paul’s example
lighten our load
when a discouraging circumstance
is weighing us down?
First, accept the reality of the situation.
That may open our minds
to practical ways to deal with it.
Second, look for compensations and mercies.
Don’t let the blessing you’re praying for
blind you to the blessings you have.
Those two suggestions can help us cope
with a discouraging circumstance
that has become a plague of our heart.
Now let’s move on to our second point:
when people upset us.
A sister we’ll call Helen
has been pioneering for six years.
She serves as a construction volunteer.
She helped out for an extended period
on the Warwick project.
Needless to say,
Helen has been around a lot of people
—Jehovah’s people—
and that’s a blessing.
But Helen admits that at times
it’s also been a test.
Why?
She says:
“One of my greatest weaknesses
“is a critical eye toward others.
“Rarely do I have
a good first impression of a person;
“it’s always tainted
by some negative observation.
“At first, even the best of people
seem too quick to laugh,
“too popular, even too spiritual.
It’s a terrible, ugly weakness I have.”
Now, perhaps we can relate
to Helen’s comment.
We might tend to get annoyed
or even hold a grudge
when someone says or does the wrong thing.
And we think that tendency will change
when we come to Bethel, right?
‘Finally, I’ll be around people
who are easy to get along with.’
And then at some point
—whether it’s after a few months
or a few minutes—
the bubble bursts,
and now we’re not sure
whether the brotherhood is a blessing
from Jehovah or a test from Satan.
How can we cope with that
when people upset us?
Well, let’s look at Romans 12:18.
And as we read Romans 12:18,
try to detect two things:
(1) what we can’t control
and (2) what we can control.
Romans 12:18 says:
“If possible, as far as it depends on you,
be peaceable with all men.”
Now let’s look at our two components.
First, what can’t we control?
What others say or do;
that part depends on them.
What can we control?
Again, it’s our response
—that is a choice.
When someone upsets us,
we can choose to let it grow
or we can choose to let it go.
We can choose to “be peaceable with all men.”
That part, Romans 12:18 says,
depends on each one of us.
So how can we choose to be peaceable
when someone upsets us?
Well, let’s look at Judges 8:2.
This shows us one thing we can do,
Judges 8:2.
Here Gideon avoided
what could have turned out
to be a messy conflict.
You remember the story.
Gideon and his army
had just won a battle against Midian.
And at that point,
the tribe of Ephraim starts complaining.
Now, even though they
were eventually called into the battle
and even though they captured
two Midianite princes,
the Ephraimites felt that they
should have been called in sooner
and they blamed this all on Gideon.
Judges 8:1 says that “they quarreled
bitterly with him” about this.
So now there’s a conflict.
How did Gideon handle it?
Notice what he says
to the tribe of Ephraim at Judges 8:2:
“What have I done compared with you?
Are not the gleanings of Ephraim
better than the grape harvest of Abiezer?”
What does that last question mean?
Well, Gideon was from the family of Abiezer.
So, what he’s saying to the Ephraimites is:
‘The grapes that your tribe leaves behind
are better than the best grapes
my family can grow.’
And then he reminds the Ephraimites
that they had an important role
in the battle,
and again he asks them:
“What have I done compared with you?”
Verse 3 says that after that
the Ephraimites “calmed down.”
Problem solved—and how?
What did Gideon do here?
In the face of a conflict
with the Ephraimites,
he did not put them down.
He raised them up.
He found something good about them
—in this case, their grape harvest,
something totally unrelated to the conflict—
and for the sake of peace,
he praised them for it.
Now, we can take a similar approach.
When someone upsets us,
look for the “grape harvest.”
Even if it’s just to ourselves,
we can find something good
about the person,
perhaps something totally unrelated
to the conflict we’re having.
Now, that’s what Helen,
the sister I quoted earlier, is trying to do.
She says: “For every bad thought
I have toward a person,
“I try to make myself
find something good about them.
“When I take that step back,
it’s easier for me to get to know a person
from a loving standpoint.”
We can do the same thing.
When someone upsets us,
take that step back;
look for the “grape harvest.”
Find the good in that person.
That’s the first thing we can do.
Now, a second thing we can do
is identified in Galatians chapter 2.
Let’s look at that.
And before we read from this chapter,
Galatians 2,
consider this question:
Who are we most likely to get upset at?
Probably someone who wrongs us,
wouldn’t you think?
But you know, there’s one type of person
we might be even more prone to get upset at.
You know who it is?
Not someone who wrongs us,
but someone who “rights” us
by giving us correction when we need it.
And in Galatians 2,
we’re going to see an example of that.
Here Peter was given correction,
and he needed it.
But notice how the correction was given,
and then we’ll see why, in this case,
it might have been exceptionally hard
for Peter to accept it.
At Galatians 2:11,
Paul writes: “However, when Cephas
[that’s Peter] came to Antioch,
“I resisted him face-to-face,
because he was clearly in the wrong.”
Paul is upset at Peter, and why?
In verse 12, he tells us:
“For before certain men from James arrived
[those who were Jewish Christians],
“[Peter] used to eat
with people of the nations;
“but when they arrived, he stopped doing this
and separated himself,
fearing those of the circumcised class.”
Now, what’s Paul saying here?
That Peter would change how he acted
depending on who was watching,
and Paul called him out on this.
He says: “I resisted [Peter] face-to-face.”
And then in verse 14,
Paul really gives it to Peter.
He tells him straight out:
‘You act one way
when the Jewish Christians are watching
and another way
when their backs are turned.’
In verse 13, Paul calls this a “pretense,”
or as the footnote renders it “hypocrisy.”
Imagine: Paul is calling Peter a hypocrite.
And he does this not privately
but “before them all,” verse 14 says.
Can this get any worse?
Yes, and it did.
Under inspiration,
Paul wrote about this incident
in his letter to the Galatians,
which we just read from.
Now, to make a comparison:
Today, Internet messages spread
from one person to the next.
And when a message
circulates rapidly and widely,
people say it went viral.
Now, they didn’t have the Internet
in the first century, of course,
but they did have letters
—and letters circulated.
And this one, Galatians,
did more than just circulate
from one person to the next
or even one congregation to the next.
No, under Jehovah’s supervision,
this one ended up in the Bible
—billions of copies down
through the centuries still being printed,
translated into thousands of languages.
Now the whole world can read
about Peter’s hypocrisy, as we just did.
Now, the Bible doesn’t tell us
Peter’s immediate reaction.
Initially, he may have been upset
at Paul, for all we know.
But in the end,
Peter chose to be peaceable.
How do we know that?
Well, in his second letter,
which was written about 12 to 14 years later,
Peter called Paul “our beloved brother,”
and he even said
that Paul had God-given wisdom.
That’s at 2 Peter 3:15.
So in the end,
Peter looked up to Paul,
and for good reason.
As he acknowledged,
Paul had God-given wisdom
to see not only into Scripture
but also into people.
He could even see into Peter.
And instead of viewing that as a threat,
Peter saw it as a benefit.
And that’s because he chose to be peaceable.
Now, you and I can do the same.
In fact, we need to.
Why?
Because from time to time
each one of us will encounter a “Paul”
—someone who gives us correction
that we need to hear,
but it comes to us in blunt terms,
perhaps at a most inappropriate time,
and it stings.
And sometimes the counsel
that stings the most
is also the counsel we need the most.
If, like Peter, we choose to be peaceable,
we’ll be able to take it
not only when someone wrongs us
but also when someone “rights” us
by giving us needed correction.
Let’s be honest, though,
it’s tough to do that.
We can be so hypersensitive at times,
and no wonder.
We live in a world where it’s just common
to blame someone else for our mistakes.
If someone breaks something,
it’s the manufacturer’s fault
for not making it unbreakable.
A speeding ticket
—that’s the policeman’s fault
because he had to meet a quota.
If a child fails English,
it’s the teacher’s fault
for not teaching English
good enough, or well enough.
In this world,
correction is largely viewed as an insult,
not as a teaching tool.
But God’s Word
does not support the world’s view.
The Bible tells us of people
that stayed in or went out of God’s favor
depending on how they responded to counsel.
So if we choose to remain bitter
at the person who corrected us,
we need to remember this:
We are letting our upset emotions
have far too much power over us.
Resentment is heavy baggage
that will only add to our load
on our journey to God’s new world,
and who needs that?
Instead, we need to be peaceable,
not only when we’re wronged
but also when we’re righted
through correction.
So to review:
How can we lighten our load
when someone upsets us?
First, like Gideon,
look for the “grape harvest”
—find something good about the person.
Second, like Peter,
be willing to accept correction
regardless of the manner in which it’s given.
Those two suggestions
can lighten our load when people upset us.
Now, let’s move
on to our third and final point:
when negative emotions overwhelm us.
As imperfect humans,
we are prone to have
a distorted view of ourselves.
A few might ‘think more
of themselves than necessary,’
as Romans 12:3 says.
But others have the opposite problem
—thinking too little of themselves,
plagued with feelings of worthlessness.
When they look at themselves,
what they see
is a gross misrepresentation of reality,
as if viewing themselves
in a distorted fun house mirror.
For example, one Witness
quoted in the September 15, 2014,
Watchtower said this:
“When I think
about everything I’ve done wrong,
“it can make me feel as if there’s no way
anyone can ever love me, not even Jehovah.”
Another, quoted
in the January 2006, Awake! said this:
“I knew that Jehovah
had forgiven me for my mistakes,
“but I did not want him to.
“I wanted to suffer
because I hated myself so much.
“While I knew that Jehovah
could never have conceived
“of a place . . . like Christendom’s hell,
I wanted him to invent one just for me.”
Now, as these examples illustrate,
our emotions
—which ironically Jehovah created
to enhance our love and our worship—
can sometimes turn against us
and make us feel condemned.
And that does more than just hinder our joy;
it also hinders our ability
to give Jehovah full glory
for the magnitude of his love.
So how can we cope with negative emotions
that at times overwhelm us?
Well, let’s look at Romans 7:22-25.
Now, here the apostle Paul
describes negative emotions
that at times overwhelmed him.
And as we read these verses,
try to detect two things:
(1) what Paul could not control
and (2) what he could control.
Romans 7, beginning with verse 22:
“I really delight in the law of God
according to the man I am within,
“but I see in my body another law
warring against the law of my mind
“and leading me captive
to sin’s law that is in my body.
“Miserable man that I am!
“Who will rescue me
from the body undergoing this death?
Thanks to God through Jesus Christ our Lord!”
Now, let’s identify our two components.
First, what couldn’t Paul control?
Occasional feelings of self-doubt
which Paul said made him feel miserable.
What could he control?
Once again, it’s his response.
And Paul’s response
is right there in verse 25:
“Thanks to God
through Jesus Christ our Lord!”
Here Paul gives us the first key
to coping with negative emotions:
meditate on the ransom.
Make it a personal study project
if necessary.
Collect scriptures from the Bible
and material from our publications
that build up appreciation
for what Jesus’ death means
not just to the world of mankind in general
but to each one of us as an individual.
Meditating on the ransom
can help us cope with negative emotions,
and why?
Because as the April 1, 1995,
Watchtower says:
“Christ’s ransom sacrifice
is the most potent answer
to the satanic lie
that we are worthless or unlovable.”
Let’s think about that statement.
Why does it call the idea
that we are worthless or unlovable
not just a lie but a “satanic lie”?
Well, who really profits when we believe
that we’re unlovable to Jehovah?
Who really benefits when we wallow
in thoughts of self-condemnation?
Whose purpose is really served
when our emotions plague us
to the extent that we feel like giving up?
Obviously, it’s Satan.
And consider the irony of that.
Who really has proved himself
unworthy of Jehovah’s love?
Him!
Who really is beyond Jehovah’s forgiveness?
Who really does the ransom not apply to?
Him!
And yet now,
in one of his greatest “crafty acts,”
as Ephesians 6:11 calls it,
Satan tries to throw
all those feelings of condemnation
that he deserves on you and on me.
The ransom gives us permission
to throw off that heavy baggage.
Evidently, that’s what Paul did.
Yes, at times
he felt miserable about himself,
as we read at Romans 7:24.
But he also wrote at Galatians 2:20:
“I live by faith in the Son of God,
who loved me
and handed himself over for me.”
Now, in stating that,
Paul wasn’t being egotistical
or thinking more of himself than necessary.
He simply understood
a basic Scriptural truth
—that Christ died for sinners,
not for perfect people.
The fact that Paul was so keenly aware
of his imperfections was evidence
that he was the very kind of person
that Jesus gave his life for.
The ransom helped Paul
refute any feelings of self-doubt,
and it can do the same for us.
Again, the April 1, 1995, Watchtower
expresses that thought beautifully.
It says: “If life in this system
has taught you to see yourself
“as an obstacle too daunting
“even for God’s immense love to surmount,
“. . . or your sins as too vast
“even for the death
of his precious Son to cover,
“you have been taught a lie.
Reject such lies
with all the repugnance that they deserve!”
Isn’t that what we do
with all of Satan’s other lies?
Do we accept the doctrine of the Trinity? No!
Do we believe in hellfire? No!
Do we believe that life evolved? No!
Do we believe that we are unlovable
and worthless to Jehovah?
Our answer to that question should be no,
and it should be just as decisive
as our no to the other questions.
And why?
Because the idea that we are worthless
or unlovable to Jehovah is a false doctrine,
and we need to reject it just as firmly
as we would reject
any of Satan’s other God-dishonoring lies.
Meditating on the ransom can help us do that.
But besides meditating on the ransom,
there’s something else we can do
to cope with negative emotions.
Let’s look at Psalm 61:2.
What David prayed for
in this verse presents us
with another key to dealing
with negative emotions,
including feelings of worthlessness.
At Psalm 61:2,
David says to Jehovah:
“From the ends of the earth
I will cry out to you
“when my heart is in despair.
Lead me onto a rock
that is higher than I am.”
Here, David is asking Jehovah
for a different view,
an elevated one.
And that’s what we need
when negative emotions plague us.
As David wrote,
we need to be placed on a rock
that is higher than ourselves,
higher than our imperfect
and distorted reasoning.
Now, Scriptural truths
can help us do that.
For example,
when the heart is in despair,
as David wrote,
we may feel that no one can love us,
not even Jehovah.
But the elevated view from the rock
reveals a Scriptural truth
—Romans 8:38, 39—
nothing can “separate us from God’s love.”
When the heart is in despair,
we feel that our mistakes
are too great for Jehovah to forgive.
But the elevated view from the rock
reveals a Scriptural truth—Romans 5:8:
“While we were yet sinners,
Christ died for us.”
As we mentioned before,
Jesus died for sinners,
not for perfect people.
When the heart is in despair,
we can’t picture ourselves in Paradise
because in our heart we feel condemned.
But the elevated view from the rock
reveals a Scriptural truth
—1 John 3:20:
“God is greater than our hearts
and [he] knows all things,”
including the reasons why we tend to think
so negatively of ourselves.
The point is: Gradually we can replace
lowly negative thoughts
with elevated Scriptural truths.
Now, we just mentioned three of those truths.
Here’s one more.
Let’s look at Malachi 3:17.
Now, in its application,
Malachi 3 is talking
about Jehovah’s spiritual temple.
But in principle, this verse
shows us the high value
that Jehovah places on his people.
Malachi 3:17 says:
“‘And they will be mine,’
says Jehovah of armies,
‘in the day
when I produce a special property’”
or, as the footnote renders it,
“a treasured possession.”
Let’s stop there.
Notice how proudly
Jehovah talks about his people.
He says: “They will be mine.”
He even calls his people
“a special property.”
And make no mistake,
that term isn’t thrown into the Bible
just to make us feel good
or to give us empty praise.
No, Jehovah’s people are special to him.
And why?
Because he produced
this property that we just read.
In other words,
Jehovah is cultivating in each one of us
the very spiritual qualities
that make us special to him.
So again, going back to Psalm 61:2,
when the “heart is in despair,”
as David wrote, we may only see
our failings and imperfections.
But the elevated view from the rock
reveals a Scriptural truth
—Malachi 3:17—
we are “a special property” to Jehovah
despite our flaws.
And if it’s difficult for us to accept that,
then we need to remember
that Jehovah is the one
who sets the standard
for what’s special here, not us.
One sister who had
an extremely negative view of herself
was helped to reason on that.
She says:
“A spiritually mature sister helped me
“to look at myself realistically
as an imperfect human
“with strengths and weaknesses,
“no better or worse
than any other brother or sister
“struggling with imperfection.
“An elder greatly helped me too
“by telling me
that no one comes to Jehovah
“without being drawn by His spirit
(that’s John 6:44).
“So Jehovah must see
something lovable in me,
and who was I
to despise what Jehovah loves?”
And notice how this sister
is slowly moving away
from that distorted mirror
and coming to see herself
the way Jehovah does.
We can do the same.
Is it easy? Absolutely not.
Second Corinthians 10:4
talks about “strongly entrenched things”
that we need to overturn,
and it lists “reasonings”
as one of those things.
Now, that could include
our imperfect and distorted reasoning
about our value to Jehovah.
That reasoning might be
so strongly entrenched
that we need
to keep praying about it, keep studying,
(or as we mentioned earlier)
keep meditating on the ransom.
But as we gradually replace
lowly negative emotions
with elevated Scriptural truths,
we’ll be better able to move away
from that distorted mirror
and see ourselves the way Jehovah does.
So to review:
How can we cope with negative emotions
that at times overwhelm us?
First, meditate on the ransom.
It is the most potent answer
to the satanic lie
that we are worthless
or unlovable to Jehovah.
Second, gradually replace
lowly negative thoughts
with elevated Scriptural truths
—truths that will help us
see ourselves the way Jehovah does.
Those two suggestions
can help us cope with negative emotions
that have become a plague of our heart.
Now in conclusion, a final thought:
Whatever plagues our heart,
even if it’s a situation
that we haven’t touched on this evening,
remaining spiritually active
will lighten our load.
Now, we at Bethel are blessed
because we have plenty to do
in Jehovah’s work.
And really, wherever we serve,
theocratic activity
will balance our thinking
and help us to put
the principles we discussed into practice.
But our strongest means of coping
with any plague of our heart
is identified at Psalm 62:1, 2.
Let’s read those verses.
What David says in Psalm 62
can lighten our load
and make it easier for us to carry.
Psalm 62, beginning with verse 1:
“Indeed, I wait silently for God.
“My salvation comes from him.
“Indeed, he is my rock and my salvation,
“my secure refuge;
I will never be greatly shaken.”
Let’s think about that last phrase
“I will never be greatly shaken.”
What does that mean,
and how can it help us cope
with the plague of our heart?
Well, to illustrate it,
last year my wife and I were on a flight
from El Paso to New York
when the plane hit turbulence.
And this wasn’t ordinary turbulence;
this turbulence was so bad
that the pilot told the flight attendants
to sit down and fasten their seat belts.
It was a nerve-racking experience.
Obviously, we survived.
But a day or two later, I did some research
and I found out something about turbulence
that many passengers don’t know.
You know what it is?
It’s that planes are built
to handle turbulence,
even the really bad kind.
In fact, when the pilot says
he’s searching for smoother air,
he’s not doing it so much for our safety
as he is just for our comfort
and to keep the coffee in our cups.
Turbulence might shake a plane,
but the plane will not be greatly shaken.
To cope with the plague of our heart,
we need to understand something similar
about the turbulence going on in our life.
When we face a trial,
our tendency might be to panic,
to grip the armrests (so to speak),
to worry about what
the next moment will bring,
to fear that we are going to crash.
But we can have confidence that,
as David said,
we will never be greatly shaken.
We can handle the turbulence
of any trial that comes our way.
And why?
Not because of our own strength,
but because we feel
as David expresses in verse 2:
“[Jehovah] is my rock and my salvation,
my secure refuge.”
So yes, we may be shaken by our trial,
but with Jehovah’s help,
we will never be greatly shaken.
By all means, then,
whatever hardship we face
—whether it’s circumstances
that discourage us, people who upset us,
negative emotions that overwhelm us,
or anything else
—let us continue to make Jehovah
our secure refuge,
confident that he can help us cope
with the plague of our heart.