Jehovah God has the purpose
of gathering His people
out of Satan’s world
into His congregation.
Christ Jesus promised us
that he would be with us
until the conclusion
of this system of things.
When we see
this huge organization worldwide,
we know that Jesus
is fulfilling his promise
and Jehovah is executing
His purposes in a wonderful way.
This huge organization
has many services
or ministries
associated with it.
It can only be accomplished
by means of Jehovah.
He is the orchestrator
of this organization.
The apostle Paul,
here in 1 Corinthians chapter 12,
explains in great detail
how Jehovah
organizes His organization.
If we’d look at verse 14
of 1 Corinthians chapter 12,
it says:
“Indeed, the body is made up
not of one member
but of many.”
So Paul is using the body,
the human body,
as an analogy
of the organization.
And it has many members.
Each individual member
is assigned a ministry.
Let us read here
verses 4 through 6.
It says:
“Now there are different gifts,
“but there is the same spirit;
“and there are different ministries,
“and yet there is the same Lord;
“and there are different activities,
“and yet it is the same God
who performs them all in everyone.”
This reminds us that this organization
does not belong to any man.
No human is putting it together;
no human is moving it along.
It is Jehovah God himself.
And we are helped
by Paul in this chapter
to understand
our relationship to one another.
Let us read here
verses 17 and 19 and 21.
It says,
1 Corinthians 12:17:
“If the whole body were an eye,
“where would the sense of hearing be?
If it were all hearing,
where would the sense of smell be?”
Nineteen:
“If they were all the same member,
where would the body be?”
And 21:
“The eye cannot say to the hand,
“‘I do not need you,’
“or again,
the head cannot say to the feet,
‘I do not need you.’”
We all understand
we need each other.
We do different operations
or ministries,
but we need each other
very much.
And that’s why it says
in verse 20:
“Now they are many members,
yet one body.”
We are still one body.
We belong to the same congregation.
Now, this brings us
to the text for today in verse 22
where Paul says:
“On the contrary, the members of the body
that seem to be weaker are necessary.”
So “weaker” in this context,
what does it mean?
It does not refer
that this member is deficient
or not able
to do their work;
no, it just means
that this member may be,
from a physical point of view,
seem weaker.
Maybe we have an older brother
suffering with some illness,
and he cannot do
as much as he used to do.
Does it mean that
he is not fulfilling his assignment
or that he does not fit
into God’s arrangement
or that he
is useless to Jehovah?
Not at all.
He may seem to be weaker,
but we understand
how that works,
and we appreciate
God’s arrangement.
Look what it says in verse 23:
“And the parts of the body
“that we think to be less honorable
“we surround with greater honor,
“so our unseemly parts
are treated with greater modesty.”
And this is God’s arrangement.
Verse 24 says:
“Whereas our attractive parts
do not need anything.
“Nevertheless,
God has so composed the body,
giving greater honor
to the part that had a lack.”
So there is no division
in the body.
It cooperates.
You do not have members
looking down on others
because of their inability
or limited circumstances.
That’s why it says in verse 25:
“So that there should be
no division in the body,
but its members should have
mutual concern for one another.”
How does this work?
How has Jehovah arranged
and orchestrated this organization?
It’s beautifully described by Paul
in Ephesians 4:16.
Now in verse 15 here in Ephesians 4,
Paul says:
“Let us by love grow up in all things
into him who is the head, Christ.”
Christ Jesus is the Head.
There’s no pyramid structure.
Christ said:
“Your Leader is one.”
And then it says, from verse 16,
the first part of verse 16,
it explains how Jehovah God
organizes his people.
It says:
“From him,” from Christ,
“all the body
is harmoniously joined together
“and made to cooperate
through every joint
that gives what is needed.”
So it is harmoniously joined together.
It’s like the human hand.
The fingers are joined by the palm.
The palm is joined to the wrist.
There is a harmonious joining together,
and then it says here,
they are made to cooperate.
So they have been designed
to fit together,
to cooperate,
to work together.
This is what Jehovah God does.
But then the second part of the verse
shows what we need to do.
It says we need to give what is needed
and then it says:
“When each respective member
functions properly,
“this contributes
to the growth of the body
as it builds itself up in love.”
So that is our function
—to give what is needed,
to do what is required.
Jesus illustrated that
so beautifully for us in John 13.
Remember the time when
he washed the feet of the disciples.
We turn there to John 13,
and if we look
at verses 12 through 15,
Jesus explained what he did.
Then he explains the purpose of this.
It says:
“When, now, he had washed their feet
“and had put
his outer garments on,
“he again reclined at the table
and said to them:
“‘Do you understand
what I have done to you?
“‘You address me
as “Teacher” and “Lord,”
“‘and you are correct,
for I am such.
“‘Therefore, if I, the Lord and Teacher,
washed your feet,
“‘you also should wash
the feet of one another.
“‘For I set the pattern for you,
that just as I did to you,
you should also do.’”
So imagine, here is Jesus,
the Head of the congregation,
he got down on his knees
and washed the feet of his disciples,
and then he said
we must follow that example.
So, what is the purpose
of this arrangement?
Each of us fits
into God’s arrangement.
All of us have a function,
a beautiful function,
that is to serve one another
—give what is needed.
As stated there in Ephesians
in the final part of verse 16,
as we read:
“This contributes
to the growth of the body
as it builds itself up in love.”
So Jehovah has made
this wonderful arrangement
of gathering his people together.
He will take this organization,
this congregation of people,
through into
the righteous new system of things
where we will experience
wonderful blessings.
But right now,
it is our opportunity to cooperate
and to work together
in love and unity.
And that way,
whether we are weaker or stronger
from a physical point of view
does not matter,
we’re all part of the same body.