Greetings!
We’re so happy you could join us
for this broadcast.
And I’m very happy
because my cohost this month
is a good friend of mine
and a fellow worker, Brother Jim Mantz.
Now, Jim and I work together
in the Writing Department,
and Jim helps the Writing Department
—Jim and his team.
They help the Writing Department
to keep track of all the projects
that we have to work on.
And do you have any idea how many that is?
Two hundred and forty-one at any given time.
And Jim does a lot of other things as well.
Well, Jim,
we’ve got another project on hand this month,
and that’s to get this broadcast under way.
So why don’t you tell the folks at home
just what they have to look forward to?
Well, David, this month
we’ll get acquainted with a family
that raised their children
to put Jehovah first in their lives.
Let’s look for points
we can apply in our families.
Later, our music video
will emphasize the need
to take the time to marvel
at Jehovah’s creation.
And we’ll visit
the Writing Research Department.
The brothers and sisters there
help us to ensure that all our articles
and videos are accurate.
You’re going to enjoy this program,
and this is the November 2017 program
of JW Broadcasting!
This month I’d like to talk about the efforts
Jehovah’s organization is making
to produce literature, publications,
articles that are as accurate as possible.
We’re going to talk about accuracy
—accuracy of statement.
Now, first, what’s the responsibility
of the writer of the article?
When a writer submits
an article for publication,
he is expected to supply references
from reputable sources
to back up the facts
that he’s included in his article.
And our Research Department
will use those references
to check the accuracy of everything.
Reliable, respected sources.
What do we mean by a reliable source?
Well, first of all, we go with encyclopedias,
books, magazines, and then newspapers
—basically in that order.
We prefer encyclopedias over books,
books over magazines,
and magazines over newspapers
—generally because newspaper editors
have a hard time checking their facts.
They have a very limited time
in which to check their facts.
Even encyclopedias and books get updated,
so we have to go
with the latest edition of those.
We have to make sure
that our sources are reliable.
Now, when a writer quotes an expert,
our researchers will ask:
“Who’s this expert?
“What’s his reputation?
“Is he working for a particular organization?
“Does this organization have an agenda?
Is it a special-interest group?”
If we find that the goals
of the organization are questionable,
we won’t use the quote
—even if it’s a really good quote.
Now, suppose that a writer
wants to quote something from a book.
In the reference material,
he’ll supply a photocopy
of the quote in the book,
but very often he’ll give us
two or three pages before the quote
and two or three pages after as well.
And that way,
our researchers can examine the quote
in context to make sure
that what we’re saying in print
is really what the author
of the quote had in mind.
For example,
an evolutionist might make a statement
which on the surface
appears to confirm his support of creation.
Or perhaps an atheist will make a statement
that seems to indicate
that he believes in God.
But when you examine
the quote in context,
you realize that that isn’t what
the author had in mind at all.
We would never
deliberately distort a quotation.
We try very hard to use all
of our quotations in context.
Now, it’s important to keep up
with the very latest research.
Something that was stated years ago
as a fact may have been disproved.
And the reason why is obvious.
Someone may spend his entire life
researching a very limited point in history
—a very small point in history—
and, of course,
if he spends so much time researching,
he’s going to uncover things.
And so it’s not surprising
that from time to time
we have to adjust our view
of some historical points.
We have to check, check, check.
And later on in this discussion,
we’re going to consider some examples of it.
It’ll be fun; you’ll love it!
Now, someone might ask,
‘Why is it necessary to be so picky,
to be so fussy, about accuracy?’
And in answer,
I’d like to give an experience
that I heard about a few years ago.
In Northern Europe,
there was a man
who accepted a Bible study
from Jehovah’s Witnesses.
And when he was asked
what motivated him
to want to study, he said:
“I read an article
in your Awake! magazine on trees.
“Now, I happen to be
a bit of an expert on trees.
“And after I read the article,
I said to myself:
“‘That article was so well-documented.
“‘It was so precise.
“‘Any organization that is that careful
when writing about trees
is going to be just as careful
when teaching me the Bible.’”
And on that basis,
he accepted a Bible study.
Now, an area where great care
needs to be taken
is when we’re quoting statistics.
A newspaper may report on a disaster
in a certain country
and say that 10,000 people
were killed in the disaster.
Immediately,
our researchers are going to ask,
“Where did they get that statistic?”
They might phone the newspaper
and ask for the source.
And if the reporter
can’t confirm the statistic,
our researchers will go to another source
—a more official source—
to get the correct statistic.
Care is also taken
when quoting personalities of the past.
Now, suppose we want to quote
something that Napoleon Bonaparte said
—the French general.
Well, being French,
Napoleon spoke French.
So if we’re quoting it in English,
that means that somebody translated
the quote from French into English.
But did they translate the quote correctly?
Our researchers will probably go
to the target language
and research the quote
in French or in another language.
And more often than not,
they find that what is presented in English
doesn’t accurately represent
what the individual said at all.
Now, as we age,
our memory can play tricks on us.
And our researchers are aware of that.
Suppose that an elderly brother
writes in his life story
that he was baptized
at a circuit assembly on a certain date.
Our researchers may look at the date.
They may check the date,
and suppose they find that the date
the brother gave fell on a Tuesday.
Now, what are the chances that there was
a circuit assembly on a Tuesday?
There may have been,
but they’re going to check.
Is the brother’s memory failing him?
If they can’t confirm the date,
they may ask someone to help the brother
to remember the date
more correctly, more accurately.
Perhaps someone was baptized
at the same circuit assembly as he was,
and perhaps that person
has an accurate note of the date.
Our translators also go to great lengths
to present accurate information
to the brothers and sisters.
Some time ago,
the Awake! magazine published an article
on a very rare species of butterfly.
Now, with all animals and insects,
we provide our translators
with the Latin name
of the animal or the insect.
And so our translators had the Latin name.
But in one large country,
they were unable to find
the name in the vernacular.
So, what did they do?
They phoned the country’s leading university,
and they were transferred
to the Biology Department,
and there an expert gave them
the name in the vernacular
of that particular butterfly.
But then he said:
“Why is it that you’re worrying so much
“about the correct name of this butterfly?
“If you got it wrong,
there are only two of us
in the whole country
who would’ve known the difference.”
Well, that opened the way
to give a witness to this expert.
Well, now, how well would you do
in spotting a statement that is slightly off
and making it more accurate?
Would you like to find out?
Of course you would!
It’ll be fun.
So let’s take a quiz that I’ll call
You Be the Editor.
We’re going to put
a number of statements on the screen,
and there’s a problem
with each one of them.
Now your job
is to figure out what’s wrong,
why it is wrong,
and then suggest how to fix it.
It’s going to be fun.
Here’s the first statement:
“According
to the Smithsonian Knowledge Encyclopedia,
“the Egyptian Sphinx
was constructed around 2550 B.C.E.”
“The Egyptian Sphinx
Well, the problem
is with the date 2550 B.C.E.
The global Flood occurred
about 200 years after that date.
So, what are the chances
that the Sphinx survived the Flood?
Unless, of course, you think
that’s how the Sphinx lost his nose.
Now, these dates
are good for you school children
to keep in mind
when you’re writing reports.
Sometimes you copy something
from an encyclopedia,
and it gives a certain date.
But think about the date of the Flood,
2370 B.C.E.,
so that what you put in your report
is as accurate as possible.
Now let’s go on to the next one:
“In 29 C.E.,
“Jesus was baptized by a close relative,
John the Baptizer.”
Well, 29 C.E., that looks right.
And we know that Jesus
was baptized by John; that’s right.
So the problem must be
“close relative,” and it is.
Now, both of Jesus’ parents
were of the tribe of Judah,
and their parents were of the tribe of Judah.
But, what about John’s parents,
Zechariah and Elizabeth?
They were both of the tribe of Levi.
So Elizabeth and Mary
couldn’t have been sisters.
Could they have been cousins?
Maybe.
We can’t even confirm that.
And if they were, that would make
Jesus and John second cousins.
Well, is a second cousin a “close relative”?
Some would say yes;
some would say no.
So it’s safer just to say,
“In 29 C.E.,
Jesus was baptized by a relative,
John the Baptizer.”
Here’s one.
Let’s see if you can spot
the error in this one:
“While most of the early Christians
“were held in little esteem in the community,
“a few enjoyed an elevated social status.
For example, Luke was a respected physician.”
Well, the word we need
to look at is “respected.”
We respect our doctors today,
and our doctors have
a very, very fine education.
But was that the case in the first century?
A reference work says this
about first-century physicians:
“Many doctors were freed Greek slaves,
“hence the social standing
of doctors was quite low.
“Because recovery rates were so low,
many people were skeptical
or even scornful of doctors.”
Note this statement from the first century:
“Until recently, Diaulus was a doctor;
“now he is an undertaker.
“He is still doing as an undertaker,
what he used to do as a doctor.”
Not very flattering, is it?
Well, in this case, we’d probably have to use
a different example.
Here’s one:
“In 325 C.E.,
“the Roman Emperor Constantine
“established Christianity
“as the official religion
of the Roman Empire.”
Well, 325 C.E., that looks right.
And Constantine, that looks right.
But look at the word “official”
—“official religion.”
Constantine never established Christianity
as the official religion
of the Roman Empire.
In 313 B.C.E.,
he did make it legal to be a Christian,
but paganism was still
one of the official religions.
Apostate Christianity
didn’t become the official religion
until 391 C.E.
This one is tricky.
See how you do with this one:
“Imagine the apostle Paul
“during his first imprisonment in Rome,
“writing his letter to the Colossians
from a dark prison cell.”
Well, if you look in the back
of the New World Translation,
you’ll find that Paul did write his letter
to the Colossians while in Rome,
and he was imprisoned at the time.
So, what’s the problem?
“Dark prison cell.”
Where was Paul
during his first imprisonment?
In his own rented house.
So the statement “dark prison cell,”
it’s very dramatic, but it’s all wrong.
Here’s an old one:
“While Paul generally preached
“to people of the nations,
“Peter was sent to the Jews.
“Contrary to popular belief,
Peter was never in Rome.”
Some scholars used to make that statement,
and they made it 60 years ago:
“Peter was never in Rome.”
But can we really say that?
Can we be that dogmatic?
Can we say that he didn’t even spend
vacation time or have a short visit in Rome?
No, we cannot.
So it would be more accurate to state:
“There is no record
that Peter ever lived in Rome.”
Here’s one:
“We can have confidence in the Bible
—it is mankind’s oldest book.”
“Mankind’s oldest book.”
Years ago, some scholars believed
that texts written
by Adam, Noah, and others
survived the Flood
and became part of the Bible.
And if that were true,
then we could say that the Bible
is mankind’s oldest book.
Now, here’s a quote
from Insight on the Scriptures,
our Bible encyclopedia.
It says:
“There is no way to establish definitely
“that some of the histories
mentioned in the book of Genesis
were committed to writing
before the Flood.”
So, today we might call the Bible
one of mankind’s oldest books
or the world’s oldest modern book,
as we do in one of our videos.
Here’s the last one:
“In 1517,
“Martin Luther nailed his 95 theses
on the door of a church
in Wittenberg, Germany.”
Well, we’ve highlighted “95,”
but there are questions
about the entire statement.
Some modern scholars have done
a tremendous, exhaustive study
of the life of Martin Luther,
and they claim
that he couldn’t have compiled
all 95 of his theses by 1517.
Others go so far as to claim
that it never happened
—that he never did nail his theses
on the door of the church.
Still others are just as adamant
that it’s all true
—that it all happened.
So there’s no consensus.
We would have to modify the statement
—“some believe” or “it is believed”—
in order to make it more accurate
and to acknowledge the fact
that there are differences of opinion.
Well, how did you do on the quiz?
If you’re like me, you’ve probably made
some of those statements yourself at times.
The statements were based
on the best research we had at the time.
But this is to illustrate
the fact that times change;
research facilities improve.
A scholar does exhaustive research
on one point of history,
and he uncovers things
that were previously unknown.
So we have to keep up.
We have to check, check, check.
And when credible research
reveals that we have to adjust
or tweak a statement
that we made in the past,
we do so without hesitation.
Our goal is to provide information
that is as accurate as possible
because we know that you
brothers and sisters use this information.
You quote it in the field ministry.
You use it in your public talks.
So we want to make sure
that our brothers are fed
with the most accurate
spiritual food possible.
We’re imperfect, of course,
and we are going to make mistakes.
And when we do,
we have to correct them.
Our goal is to do the best we can
in all our imperfection.
Well, how does it make you feel?
I know how it makes me feel.
I’m grateful that Jehovah’s organization
takes accuracy so seriously.
It gives me confidence.
And, you know, I’m reminded
of the description of another researcher,
as recorded at Ecclesiastes 12:9, 10.
You know who this is.
Ecclesiastes 12:9, 10:
“Not only had the congregator become wise
“but he continually taught
the people what he knew,
“and he pondered
“and made a thorough search
“in order to compile many proverbs.
“The congregator sought
to find delightful words
and to record accurate words of truth.”
Now, let’s give our attention
to my good friend Jim.
And I think Jim is ready
to take us on a field trip
so we can meet
some of the researchers at Bethel.
Thank you, David.
And, yes, our researchers take very seriously
their task of maintaining
a high standard of accuracy.
In today’s media,
much of what’s presented as fact
is often colored by emotion
and personal opinion.
Jehovah’s Witnesses, however,
remain committed
to defending God’s Word,
the Bible, as the standard for truth.
As Jesus said at John 17:17:
“Your word is truth.”
The wide-ranging subject matter
contained in the publications
of Jehovah’s Witnesses
is painstakingly researched
by their Writing Research Department.
Their research methods are modeled
after that of Bible historians
such as Luke and Jeremiah
—reliance on reputable first-hand sources.
We’re not looking just for someone’s opinions
or what someone believes about a topic.
If the material is socially
or politically biased, for example,
we can’t rely on it.
We look for objective material.
We cover everything
from historical, scientific, geographical
to flora, fauna, space.
So before the script is even written,
we’ll provide a research package,
and we’ll follow
the project until final delivery
to make sure
that everything that is said
and everything that is shown
is solidly based on fact
and is well-researched.
There’s a lot more research than what
the viewer
or the reader will ever see.
You have a one-page article on the otter;
you end up with like 12 references
to back up every statement that’s made.
It seems very simple,
the height of Mont Blanc.
And with the height of Mont Blanc,
we found out, number one,
that it was 4,807 meters;
then we found another source
—4,810 meters;
let’s check a third one
—4,808 meters.
So, what is now real?
In that case, we had to consult
the French National Institute
of Geographic and Forest Information.
One of our main research tools
is our own library system.
We have about 65,000 books
and other research materials.
If we’re researching something
about ancient history
or archaeology,
we may consult
a specialized encyclopedia,
like an encyclopedia
of archaeological discoveries, for example.
Museum websites usually have pictures
of what they have in the museum.
And we can find these visuals and then send
those off to production teams
as well and say,
“This is a good example
of a first-century lamp.”
Things that you think are true
because they are “commonly known”
may not actually be totally accurate.
Quotes need to be verified.
We want to go to the first-hand source,
the original source, for that quote.
That’s one thing.
And secondly, context matters;
we want to quote things properly.
When Gandhi and Lord Irwin came together,
Gandhi said, ‘When your country
and mine come together
‘on the teachings of Christ
and on the Sermon on the Mount,
then we will have solved the problems
of our countries and the world.’
So we researched it.
No one could confirm
that those two men ever met.
So it’s a great quote.
Now, it doesn’t mean
that he didn’t refer to Jesus
or even the Sermon on the Mount,
but that particular one, we couldn’t use.
So the research work we’re doing,
sometimes it takes a lot of time,
a lot of effort.
Sometimes we don’t find
what we are expecting to find.
But it’s very gratifying
because we’re helping produce
accurate information
that our readers can rely on.
Reliable information will help us
make good informed decisions.
Anyone who reads our journals
and who sees our videos
can be confident that this
was thoroughly researched.
These are facts; this is the truth.
So when you consider
the printed publications
of Jehovah’s Witnesses
or peruse the jw.org website,
you can be confident that the material
is carefully researched and accurate.
Why?
Because Jehovah’s Witnesses
are a people who love and respect
the truth.
As Psalm 31:5 expresses,
we worship “Jehovah, the God of truth.”
So it would only make sense
that we try to imitate him
to the best of our ability
by being truthful
in all the materials that we publish.
He, no doubt, finds this very pleasing,
especially since throughout history,
many have tried to twist his teachings.
Although the organization makes efforts
to publish accurate information,
there are many things
that we can do as individuals.
This dramatization highlights
how our view of celebrations
can be pleasing to Jehovah.
Hey, Buddy!
How was school?
That’s my Dad, Grayson,
and my older brother, Dylan.
Hey, Bro!
We’re going to play ball.
You want to come?
No thanks.
Is he OK?
He normally loves to talk about school.
He didn’t want to talk about school today.
It wasn’t my worst day at school
—but pretty close.
It all started first thing this morning.
Everyone was signing a birthday card
for one of our classmates, Lucas.
Do you want to sign
the birthday card for Lucas?
He just got home from being
at the hospital for cancer treatments.
No thanks.
I’m a Jehovah’s Witness,
and I don’t celebrate birthdays.
What?
Hum?
That’s rude.
Come on, sign it!
You guys, you guys, Aiden—
My teacher said that Lucas
may not come back to school for a long time.
I felt so bad he was sick.
Aiden, Aiden, can you think about it?
The thing is, I did want to sign the card.
Lucas was one of the nicest people
in my class.
Maybe I can just sign it.
I mean, it’s not like I’m going
to a birthday party.
Hey, little man.
How are you doing?
Yeah?
Mom said you had a rough day today.
When Dad came in,
I told him everything that happened.
I know from the Bible
that it’s wrong to celebrate birthdays.
But is signing the card really a big deal?
Dad said my question was a good one.
Then he showed me a scripture.
Do you want to get your Bible for me?
Let’s look in Ephesians 5.
Ephesians 5:10:
“Keep on making sure
of what is acceptable to the Lord.”
He said,
“We all have to keep making sure
“of what’s acceptable to Jehovah
because Satan is a master at tricking us.”
Then he used the example of Aaron.
The Israelites asked Aaron
to make them a god.
So Aaron made a golden calf,
thinking that it could represent Jehovah.
He told the people:
“There is a festival to Jehovah tomorrow.”
But true worship
was being mixed with false worship,
and Jehovah was not happy.
And many were punished.
That example helped me a lot.
I know birthdays are wrong
because the Bible teaches
that they are not approved by Jehovah.
But we don’t want to be confused like Aaron
and try to mix true and false worship.
All right, let’s go talk to Mom.
We want to make Jehovah happy.
So Dad said,
“It’s always good to ask,
How would Jehovah feel if I did this?”
I still didn’t sign the card,
but I’m going to do something else for Lucas.
Can I go see Lucas?
Yeah.
Go ahead, Buddy.
He’s right over there.
How have you been feeling?
A little better.
And then I realized something:
Instead of celebrating one day,
I could share with Lucas our hope
of living forever
on a beautiful paradise earth.
So there will be no sickness ever again.
They will build houses and have food.
I enjoyed seeing how we can show
love and concern for others,
even if we do not share their beliefs.
The best way to do so
is by simple acts of kindness
and by sharing our hope with them,
just as Aiden did.
And did you notice
how the good training by Aiden’s parents
helped him make decisions
that were pleasing to God?
It made me think of Abilio and Ulla Amorim
from Portugal.
Both of them endured difficult childhoods,
but they did not allow that to affect
how they raised their own children.
Since I was very young,
I was religiously inclined
and my dream was to get married
to a man that worshipped God
and that together we would worship God
and live a peaceful life.
That didn’t happen with my parents.
We often had a better relationship
with the maid than with my mother.
My father was a very distant person.
He was always very busy
with his work and friends.
We wed in 1971 in Paris, France.
We were baptized in 1974.
I realized I really didn’t know
how to raise children,
and then I started applying some things
mentioned in the Bible.
If I wanted to teach them right,
I first had to understand
things better myself
so that I could explain them
in a way that God would want us to.
In 1976, we moved to Portugal
to serve where there was more need.
By then, our oldest son
was four and a half years old,
Maria was three and a half,
and Benjamin, one and a half.
I remember when we arrived;
we lived in a rural area.
It was a very small congregation,
so we really had to participate
from a very early age.
They wanted to put,
for sure, the spiritual interests
first in their life,
and they wanted not only to tell us
to put the Kingdom interests first
but they wanted to show us
how to do it.
And it was not only that we
sat down for family study
that we talked about Jehovah
and spiritual things.
I remember walking back home
from meetings
and then my parents would help us
to look for a star constellation;
it started a conversation about Jehovah.
In Deuteronomy chapter 6,
it says that we
must always talk to our children.
But it’s good to talk about God
and help them to see God as a real person
—a person that is linked
to everything around us.
So now I wanted to teach them very much,
and not that things about God
were sad or boring,
but were joyful.
Of course, we were imperfect.
Many times I did the wrong things.
I never remember, “You have to do it
because you have to do it.”
They always tried to explain the reasons
—Bible reasons.
I was brought up this way.
My parents dictated laws:
“You have to do this.
You must.
This is the way I want it to be.”
But I came to understand that God,
even in the Bible,
instead of only giving or dictating laws,
he explains them.
He gives so many reasons;
he gives reasons for everything.
By teaching my children,
I have to say that I have learned a lot too.
We never felt that we must go to meetings;
we must go in service
because you have to do it.
And we were always
motivated to do things.
I remember, for example,
when he gave me a new Bible,
and he wrote to me in that Bible,
“May this book always be
the motivating force in your life.”
Several times he told me:
“Please never,
“never give up in your service.
“Jehovah is your Father,
and you have to serve him
all your life.”
The Almighty has children
that failed to respond,
much like any other parent.
God does not force anyone.
He respects our free will very much.
So we wanted them
to build their own future.
I always felt
that my children were not my own,
but it was Jehovah
who kindly put them into our hands.
He entrusted them to us
so that we could care for them.
And then when we have done our part,
let them fly.
My parents always encouraged us
to pursue full-time service,
even if that meant
moving far away from home.
My husband and I are serving
as field missionaries in Klaipeda, Lithuania.
I know I will be grateful for all eternity
that I used my youth to serve Jehovah,
and that I didn’t waste
my years of my young age
doing things for this world.
My wife and I serve
in the Portugal branch office.
If Jehovah is happy,
if my parents are happy, I’m happy too.
I’m really sure
that they like what we’re doing.
They are happy with that.
We rejoice that our children
are giving their best
to their Creator and making him happy.
Jehovah deserves that.
Of course, we miss our children,
and we would like to have them around,
but we are very happy for them
for having the privilege
of serving Jehovah the way they are.
Yes, the truths found in the Bible
can provide practical help
in raising a family.
But although Jehovah
has given the responsibility
of raising children to the parents,
other members of the family
can also play an important role
in encouraging spiritual progress.
These three fleshly sisters
looked after one another
while learning about Jehovah.
I was the first to start studying the Bible.
After that, I started studying too.
After watching them for a year,
I began studying too.
Since our parents had stopped studying,
only three of us went to the meetings.
We saved our allowance
to take the bus to meetings.
But sometimes
when we were short of money—
My sisters let me ride the bus,
since I’m the youngest,
and they would walk.
We used to walk
an hour and a half each way.
Meetings were so important to us
that we never felt it was a burden.
May 2007.
For me, it was October 2006.
I was baptized in October 2005.
Three years later,
I spent a week
with a special pioneer
who was serving in the countryside.
We prayed together every night
and read life stories from The Watchtower.
I told Jehovah
that I wanted to be just like her.
Although my relatives
were unhappy with my decision,
with Jehovah’s help,
I decided to become a pioneer.
I followed her example,
and I became a pioneer too.
I was working six days a week
to support my family,
so I prayed to Jehovah
for the opportunity to become a pioneer.
After my boss reduced
my work to five days a week,
I started pioneering.
Pioneer service gives you the opportunity
to serve Jehovah more fully.
Working closely with Jehovah,
I really feel part of his family.
My relationship with Jehovah
has gotten stronger.
When I pray now,
it feels like I’m talking to my close friend.
It allows you to expand your ministry.
I became a special pioneer in June 2013.
I’ve served at Bethel since September 2013.
In April 2014,
I was appointed a special pioneer.
Now I can serve Jehovah more fully.
My appreciation for Jehovah has deepened.
Our mother, who had opposed us,
became a pioneer too.
Full-time service is—
—really awesome!
Whether we are parents or siblings,
applying Bible principles
helps us to create a strong family bond.
It can also help us before we have children,
even before we are married.
The world tries to tempt us
with deceptive lies
about what is important in life.
But our own careful research of the Bible
can protect and guide us
when we are planning a wedding.
Juliana and I have been friends
for a few years,
and we have been getting to know
each other better for several months.
Things were going really well between us.
I must say, when Nick asked me
to join some friends
for a little get-together at the park,
I was getting suspicious
when both our families were there.
I said, “Yes!”
I couldn’t believe she didn’t see it coming.
We were both so excited,
and word spread fast!
At the meeting the next day,
everyone was congratulating us
—my friend Natalie especially.
She was full of ideas.
I couldn’t wait to start making plans.
I never realized
how much goes into a wedding.
And everyone had
their own ideas of what we needed
—even Dad!
We had to think about who we would invite,
pick out flowers, decorations,
a suit for Nick and, of course, a dress!
This was going to be
so much fun
—or so I thought.
I soon found out there’s
a whole wedding-related industry out there.
They were trying to be helpful but,
at the same time,
this is how they make money.
It seemed like nothing they had was modest.
And the cost for something
I would only wear for one day
—I couldn’t afford that!
Everyone was so happy for me,
but inside I was really starting
to feel the pressure.
When we met back at Juliana’s home,
I was pretty confused.
She had been so happy a few days ago,
but now she was so stressed out.
It was like nobody
was listening to what we wanted.
But to be honest,
I’m not sure we knew
what we wanted either.
I thought it would be good
if maybe we could just take some time
and think about what a Christian wedding
should really be like.
We had a meeting with Brother Grey
and Brother Sharp the next day
to discuss using the Kingdom Hall
for our wedding.
They gave us some helpful reminders,
and I’m so glad they did.
First Corinthians 10:31 says:
“Whether you are eating
or drinking or doing anything else,
do all things for God’s glory.”
Brother Sharp helped us to see
that a wedding is a spiritual occasion,
and we need to keep
Jehovah’s standards in mind
when we plan for what we will
or won’t choose to include.
Brother Grey showed us 1 John 2:15, 16:
“Do not love either the world
or the things in the world.
“. . . Because everything in the world
“—the desire of the flesh
and the desire of the eyes
“and the showy display
of one’s means of life—
. . . originates with the world.”
He reminded us that what
the world views as normal
is far different from Christian standards
and that we can be a good example
by making sure our choices please Jehovah.
They even gave us a few articles
about wedding arrangements to review.
They wanted to make sure we would have
a happy occasion with nothing to regret.
I asked Brother Sharp
if he would be our director of the feast
to help keep things coordinated,
and he suggested that we talk
about it over dinner that night.
On the way there,
we passed by a photography studio.
I couldn’t believe how lavish
and showy some weddings are.
It looked more like an excuse to party
instead of something
that’s supposed to honor God.
It reminded me of the book of Galatians:
“Now the works of the flesh are . . .
drunkenness, wild parties,
and things like these.”
We didn’t want to do anything like that.
We each took the time
to prayerfully consider
the material the brothers gave us.
We saw that Scriptural principles
can even help us plan a wedding
that’s affordable,
enjoyable for everyone,
and a day that honors Jehovah.
It looked like we needed
to make some adjustments.
We couldn’t include
everything we originally thought
—some things were just too expensive.
And we wanted to make sure
that none of our choices
reflected the spirit of the world.
So we decided to start over
and make sure we
were doing things Jehovah’s way.
First Timothy 2:9 says that a Christian
“should adorn themselves
in appropriate [or “respectable”] dress,
with modesty and soundness of mind.”
It took some work,
but we were able
to find something affordable,
appropriate,
and beautiful.
I was able to find a nice suit
—something I could even wear later.
And of course, the girls came by
to make sure that everything matched.
Time went by so fast.
I called Brother Sharp
so he could help us follow through
on the day of the wedding.
Before we knew it,
we were sending out invitations
and finalizing all the details.
When my dad walked me
down the aisle that day,
I was so excited.
Juliana was so beautiful!
And the ceremony was just perfect.
After all that planning we did,
we were sure to make it legal.
When looking back at our photos,
it brings back so many good memories.
I was so happy
with how nice everything turned out.
And when we saw
what a great job our friends had done
decorating the reception,
I couldn’t believe my eyes.
It was perfect
—simple,
dignified.
Our friends all told us that it was
one of the nicest weddings they’ve been to.
Everything that day
was just what we wanted.
It even stayed on budget.
And most importantly,
we got our marriage off to a good start
with Jehovah’s help.
I’m so happy we found each other.
I’m so happy I found you too, Love.
And I know we’ll stay happy
if we keep Jehovah first.
The couple’s ability to reason
on Scriptural principles
helped them to make
the right decisions.
Good reasoning ability
is an essential quality of a true Christian.
But what does it really mean
to reason on matters?
This morning worship program
by Gary Breaux will show us.
If you’d open your Bibles to Romans 12:1,
we’ll note that the apostle Paul,
as has been commented on,
talks about reasoning on matters.
That’s Romans 12:1, it says:
“Therefore, I appeal to you
by the compassions of God, brothers,
“to present your bodies
as a living sacrifice,
“holy and acceptable to God,
a sacred service
with your power of reason.”
Ah, so Paul says reasoning has power to it.
A synonym for power is influence.
And so if you reason something out,
you’ll be influenced to make
the proper decision, basically.
Now, he also introduced
something else in our text today.
Let’s go there.
It’s 2 Thessalonians chapter 2,
and we’ll read verses 1 and 2:
“However, brothers,
“concerning the presence
of our Lord Jesus Christ
“and our being gathered together to him,
“we ask you not to be
quickly shaken from your reason
“nor to be alarmed
either by an inspired statement
“or by a spoken message
or by a letter appearing to be from us,
to the effect
that the day of Jehovah is here.”
So he introduces this aspect
of being quickly shaken
once you come to a conclusion on a matter
after reasoning it out.
Now, he says don’t be quickly shaken
once you come to a conclusion of the matter
as a result of reasoning the matter out.
And that’s what he was telling
the Thessalonica congregation here.
In the first letter,
he had talked about and warned them
that Jehovah’s day was imminent
and that it was coming,
and as a result,
some in the congregation went beyond that,
saying that it was here.
In fact, as verse 2 says,
there apparently was even a letter
that appeared to be from Paul
and saying that it’s not that it’s coming
—Jehovah’s day is here.
And so some got sidetracked
as a result of not thinking it through,
and their faith was shaken, apparently.
And then as you continue,
Paul then helped them
to reason further that no,
there are other things
that have to happen before Jehovah’s day.
So we’d like to talk about this matter
of quickly being shaken
—that is our faith.
It’s important because we spend years
developing a relationship with Jehovah God
and developing a solid faith,
and just this idea that Paul introduces
that one’s faith can be quickly shaken
is a rather disconcerting thought.
It can happen to any of us, really.
I just think about Judas Iscariot, right?
John 6:64 says
that from the beginning Jesus knew
who was the one who would betray him
—from the beginning.
From the beginning of what?
The Insight book says:
“‘From the beginning’
of when Judas started to go bad,
started to give in to imperfection
and sinful inclinations.”
Well, how long did that process take?
Well, it was less than a year
from the time he was appointed as an apostle.
Now, we know his appointment
was no mistake.
So within that short period of time,
this man went from an apostle
to an apostate.
That’s why it’s such good counsel
that Paul gave
for us not to be quickly shaken
from matters that we have established
as a result of good reasoning.
Now, there are times
that we’re more susceptible
to our faith
being quickly shaken than others.
And I’d like to talk
about that for just a moment.
What could some of those times be?
Well, it could be
when we’re going through stress,
depression, or anxiety.
The March 1, 2010, Watchtower,
makes this comment:
“Judgment may be clouded
when one is under great emotional stress.”
Now let me give you an example
—hypothetical, but here’s an example—
a brother has a deep relationship
with his parents;
his mother suddenly dies.
This is a great emotional blow to him;
he slips into a mild depression,
and as a result, his personal study
and his spiritual activities slow down.
Then a short time later,
a sibling is disfellowshipped.
This crushes him; he can’t sleep.
He wakes up; he gets to the computer;
he turns it on,
and he slips into watching
something inappropriate.
Now, what’s just happened?
Well, his good reasoning ability was shaken.
It’s of note
that the November 15, 1992, Watchtower,
puts it this way:
“Severe and prolonged mental depression
“may have worn away
“some of the person’s normally
strong emotional fiber
or may have made it extremely difficult
to make wise decisions.”
So, what could the brother have done?
Well, when he first recognized
this mild depression
or slipping from the spiritual activities,
it would have been good for him to get
someone to help him identify the cause.
Now, what is another circumstance
that could quickly shake our faith
if we’re not on guard?
Well, it has to do with the apostates.
Now, there is something
that the apostates are talking about
and trying to put forward.
The media has picked it up;
others have also picked it up.
And that is our Scriptural position
of having a two-witnesses requirement
for judicial action
if there is no confession.
Now, if you open your Bibles
to Deuteronomy 19:15,
our good reasoning is pretty solid on this.
At Deuteronomy 19:15,
the scripture is very, very clear.
It says:
“No single witness may convict another
“for any error or any sin that he may commit.
“On the testimony of two witnesses
“or on the testimony of three witnesses
the matter should be established.”
It’s very clear, isn’t it?
You cannot establish
a judicial committee based on one witness.
But now, listen,
here’s what they say:
“Well now, look,
the Old Testament
“also says that adulteresses
should be stoned.
“Now, since you’re not doing that,
why do you stick
to this two-witness rule?”
You see, if you’re not careful,
that can do some tricks on your mind
because you have to think it through.
Well, how might we do that?
Well, we go to Matthew 18:16
because obviously Christ Jesus
established the Christian arrangement,
and notice what he said.
Matthew 18:16, he says:
“But if he does not listen,
take along with you one or two more,
“so that on the testimony
of two or three witnesses
every matter may be established.”
So Christ Jesus establishes the fact
that there has to be two witnesses.
Now, it doesn’t mean
that if there is only one witness
that there are no consequences.
There might be,
depending upon the situation,
but the Scriptures are very clear.
Before a judicial committee can be convened,
there has to be a confession
or two witnesses,
so we will never change
our Scriptural position on that subject.
Jehovah has given us the ability
to reason things out, to think it through.
So let’s do our part
and not allow our faith
to be quickly shaken.
Then we can have
the confidence that Paul spoke of
at 2 Thessalonians 3:5 when he said:
“May the Lord continue to guide
your hearts successfully
to the love of God
and to the endurance for the Christ.”
Even when difficult circumstances arise,
such as judicial matters,
we cling to our accurate understanding
of the Bible.
Yes, Jehovah is the God of truth.
And our desire for accurate knowledge
motivates us to draw
ever closer to Jehovah
and to learn more
about his perfect qualities.
Just think of everything
we can learn about him
when we take the time
to study his works of creation.
Psalm 104:24 reads:
“How many your works are, O Jehovah!
“You have made all of them in wisdom.
The earth is full of what you have made.”
In harmony with that,
our music video for this month
is entitled Inspired by Your Wonders.
I hear the birds singing out
to the sunrise.
I see the stars fading away
in the morning light.
Golden sun shines on down
through the treetops,
Where there is a summer breeze
that whispers so soft.
And I sing,
“O Jah, Jehovah my God,
The work of your hands
fills us with awe.”
I stare at the stars,
Wondering how you care who we are.
I see your wonders,
and I sing to you.
I sing to you.
These wondrous, moving,
breathing creations—
Oh, in the night, in the day—
can you hear what they say?
From mountaintops
to the bottoms of oceans,
Let ev’ry living thing
sing out to your praise.
And I sing,
“O Jah, Jehovah my God,
The work of your hands
fills us with awe.”
I stare at the stars,
Wondering how you care who we are.
I see your wonders,
and I sing to you.
I sing to you.
Looking past what we
can see with our eyes,
We will come to know more
about the One who gave us life.
And I sing,
“O Jah, Jehovah my God,
The work of your hands
fills us with awe.”
I stare at the stars,
Wondering how you care who we are.
I see your wonders,
and I sing to you.
and I—I sing to you.
I see your wonders,
I sing to you.
When we take time to reflect
on the beauties of creation,
it becomes clear
that there is a higher intelligence
who made all these things.
Well, David, it’s hard to imagine
that we’ve already come to the end
of another monthly broadcast.
And, Jim, I want to thank you very much
for all your help with this program.
I really, really appreciate it.
Now, before we conclude,
we’d like to visit the city of Cuzco in Peru,
where we have
a Remote Translation Office, or RTO.
The city of Cuzco is a stopover
for travelers to Machu Picchu,
a historic sanctuary
of the former Inca Empire,
located high up in the mountains.
Machu Picchu is an architectural marvel.
The design is earthquake resistant.
Giant stones were cut so precisely
that in many places a piece of paper
cannot fit in between them.
At such high altitudes,
you can also see llamas,
which are raised
in the Andes Mountains.
The Inca people spoke Quechua,
a language that is spoken
by millions of Peruvians today.
There has been a translation office in Cuzco
since 2004,
but as the work grew,
so did the need for more office space.
So in 2016, a new RTO was dedicated.
The blessings of the translation work
have been evident.
Since the Bible Teach book
was released in Quechua in 2007,
the number of publishers increased
from about 700
to nearly 1,700 last year.
In addition to The Watchtower
and the Life and Ministry Meeting Workbook,
videos are translated at this office,
ranging from JW Broadcasting
monthly programs
to episodes of Become Jehovah’s Friend.
There are several regions in Peru
where Quechua is spoken,
all with slightly different dialects
and expressions.
Hence,
each translation team
has representatives from these areas
in order to ensure that the translation
is universally understood
among Quechua speakers.
Approximately 40 brothers
and sisters work at the RTO,
of which 15 are full-time.
In the Cuzco area,
there are 28 congregations and 38 groups,
with about 2,000 publishers.
We love our brothers and sisters
in Cuzco very much indeed.
And they want you to know
how much they love you.
Well, until next time,
this is JW Broadcasting
from the world headquarters
of Jehovah’s Witnesses.