This month, we’re going to discuss the theme
“Pray Continually,
So That You May Not Enter Into Temptation.”
Those words of Jesus
are recorded at Matthew 26:41.
In this discussion,
we’ll answer three important questions:
(1) Why did Jesus pray?
(2) What temptations did he face?
and (3) What lessons can we learn
from Jesus’ example?
Let’s start by reading that verse together.
That’s Matthew 26:41:
“Keep on the watch and pray continually,
“so that you may not enter into temptation.
“The spirit, of course,
is eager [or, “willing,” ftn.],
but the flesh is weak.”
Why did Jesus pray?
Jesus uttered these words
on the final night before his execution.
No doubt this was the most difficult evening
that Jesus had ever faced.
The surrounding verses tell us
that “he began to feel grieved
and to be greatly troubled.”
It’s hard for us to comprehend fully
the stress and pressure
Jesus was facing on that night.
He knew that Satan was about to throw
everything he could at him.
Jesus also knew that he’d soon die
an agonizing death.
But something else
was even harder for him to handle.
He realized
that he was about to be falsely charged
and convicted of the despicable crime
of blasphemy against Jehovah’s holy name.
The study note on Matthew 26:39 says:
“Jesus no doubt felt great concern
“over the reproach that his death
“as one charged with blasphemy and sedition
“could bring on God,
“moving him to pray
that this ‘cup’ pass away from him.”
In the face of all that pressure,
would Jesus remain faithful until death?
The lives of countless people
hung in the balance.
Even more important,
his Father’s reputation was involved.
Under all that intense emotional stress,
what did Jesus do?
He prayed, not just once,
but three times!
Notice how Luke describes what happened,
as recorded at Luke 22:44:
“But he was in such agony
“that he kept praying more earnestly;
“and his sweat became as drops of blood
falling to the ground.”
What’s the lesson for us?
Well, think about it.
Jesus knew Satan well.
Jesus had observed from heaven
all the temptations that Satan uses
in his efforts to ensnare God’s servants.
Yet, Jesus did not feel
that he could easily handle
whatever “the Tempter”
might place before him.
So this is a clear lesson for us:
If the perfect Son of God
felt the need to pray
for divine help and strength,
how much more so should we.
How appropriate then is the admonition:
“Pray continually,
so that you may not enter into temptation.”
But what does it mean
to “enter into temptation”?
The Watchtower  back in 1951 explained:
“We ourselves under Satan’s influence
“create the temptation
by thinking how nice it would be
“to do or to have something
contrary to God’s will,
“and then not dismissing
the desire created by this improper thinking,
“but considering it more and more.
“In this way we are drawn out
“and led to ignore God’s counsel and warning.
We enter into temptation.”
Prayer helps us when we face temptation.
It helps us to focus
on what Jehovah wants us to do
and to ask him for the strength
not to enter into temptation.
Our second question:
What temptations did Jesus face
while here on earth?
We probably immediately think
of the occasion shortly after Jesus’ baptism
when he was tempted three times by the Devil.
Let’s quickly summarize
those three temptations.
First, Jesus was asked
to turn stones into bread
at a time when he was extremely hungry.
Basically, Satan appealed
to Jesus’ desire for food.
However, Jesus immediately rejected
the temptation
to satisfy that desire
in an inappropriate way.
Second, Satan challenged Jesus
to throw himself off the temple battlement.
Jesus rejected this temptation as well.
Why?
Because he knew
that such a spectacular display
would amount
to a prideful testing of Jehovah.
Finally,
Satan offered Jesus
“all the kingdoms of the world
and their glory.”
But at what price?
Satan demanded that Jesus offer him in return
an act of worship.
What was Jesus’ answer?
He flatly refused, saying: “Go away, Satan!”
Have you had to face similar temptations?
Well, you might quickly answer:
‘No one has asked me
to turn stones into bread
‘or to jump off a tall building.
‘And certainly no one has offered me
the rulership
of all the governments in the world!’
But notice, please, we said “similar,”
not “the same.”
So have you faced similar temptations?
No doubt you have.
Most of us have faced temptations
involving fleshly desires.
It may have been temptations
to commit immorality
or temptations that appealed to greed
or an unbalanced concern
about material things.
Other temptations may have appealed
to our pride or tested our humility
or our desire to impress others.
And who of us hasn’t been tempted
by opportunities
offered to us by Satan’s world
for wealth, power, or position?
No matter what temptation
comes our way, though,
remember Jesus’ words:
“Pray continually,
so that you may not enter into temptation.”
But were those the only temptations
that Jesus faced?
No.
How do we know?
Well, notice Luke’s words
found at Luke 4:13:
“So the Devil,
having finished all the temptation,
departed from him
until another convenient time.”
Did Satan ever come back again
to tempt Jesus?
He must have because of what we’re told
at Hebrews 4:15.
Let’s read that:
“For we do not have a high priest
“who cannot sympathize with our weaknesses,
“but we have one who has been tested
“in all respects as we have,
but without sin.”
Have you ever wondered
what other “convenient time”
Satan selected to test Jesus?
Well, let’s consider some possibilities.
One example occurred in 32 C.E.,
about two and a half years
after the initial temptations.
Please turn to John 6:15:
“Then Jesus, knowing
that they were about to come
“and seize him to make him king,
withdrew again to the mountain all alone.”
This seems like a similar temptation
to what Jesus had already faced.
But this time, the setting was different.
Satan didn’t directly offer
the kingship to Jesus.
There was no demand
for Jesus to worship the Devil.
Rather, those following Jesus
wanted to make him their king.
This temptation was going to be
by popular demand.
How did Jesus react?
Well, even before they could make their move,
Jesus withdrew from them to a mountain,
just by himself.
And what did he do on the mountain?
We find the answer in a detail
added in the parallel account
recorded by Matthew.
Let’s read it together.
It’s Matthew 14:23:
“After sending the crowds away,
he went up on the mountain
by himself to pray.”
Yes, Jesus went there
not just to avoid the crowds
but to pray.
The third question:
What lessons can we learn
from Jesus’ example?
Even though we may have passed a test,
or avoided entering into temptation,
in the past,
we shouldn’t be surprised
if a similar temptation may arise again
but in a different form or situation
and at a convenient time.
For whom?
For Satan, not us.
Another occasion occurred
when Jesus and his apostles
were in the vicinity of Mount Hermon,
near Caesarea Philippi.
Jesus’ apostles had just acknowledged him
as “the Christ, the Son of the living God.”
So Jesus took the opportunity
to expand their thinking further.
Notice what’s recorded
at Matthew 16:21:
“From that time forward,
“Jesus began explaining to his disciples
“that he must go to Jerusalem
“and suffer many things
“from the elders and chief priests
and scribes and be killed,
and on the third day be raised up.”
What was the reaction of his apostles
to this information?
Let’s read on in verse 22:
“At this Peter took him aside
“and began to rebuke him, saying:
“‘Be kind to yourself, Lord;
you will not have this happen
to you at all.’”
Although these words were uttered
by a close friend,
Jesus immediately recognized
that they reflected Satan’s wishes,
not Jehovah’s.
So he firmly responded:
“Get behind me, Satan!
“You are a stumbling block to me,
“because you think, not God’s thoughts,
but those of men.”
Although this account
doesn’t specifically refer
to Jesus praying at that time,
we know that Jesus was a man of prayer.
The apostle Paul tells us at Hebrews 5:7:
“During his life on earth,
“Christ offered up
supplications and also petitions,
with strong outcries and tears.”
So no doubt those prayers helped Jesus
to focus on the reason why he came to earth.
That clear focus helped him to see
that Peter’s misguided counsel
would only help to further
the Tempter’s cause.
What does this teach us?
This shows us that temptations
don’t always come
from those who are Jehovah’s enemies.
Some who are close to us
may even serve Satan’s ends unintentionally,
as was the case with Peter.
It could be an employer,
a workmate, a schoolmate,
a friend, a relative, a parent,
a brother, or a marriage mate.
Let’s examine another example
of how Satan returned to Jesus.
This time, it was
by means of the religious leaders.
They attacked Jesus verbally,
misquoting Scripture
and hurling senseless accusations at him.
But Jesus understood what they were up to
and frankly told them:
“You are from your father the Devil.”
We shouldn’t be surprised
if apostates and other opposers
use similar tactics today.
Just as Jesus was accused of blasphemy
and political sedition,
so too God’s people
have been labeled as “extremists”
and have been the victims
of all sorts of false accusations.
Like Jesus, we remember
who really is behind all these attacks
—Satan, the great Tempter!
What will help us to avoid the temptation
of giving up because of discouragement?
How can we successfully handle
all these types of attacks?
Paul tells us what to do.
We read at Ephesians 6:11:
“Put on the complete suit of armor from God
“so that you may be able to stand firm
against the crafty acts of the Devil.”
After speaking about the importance
of putting on the spiritual suit of armor,
Paul goes on to say in verse 18
that this should be done together
“with every form of prayer
“and supplication
[as we] carry on prayer
on every occasion in spirit.”
So, what have we learned from our discussion?
It seems that Satan didn’t try again
to tempt Jesus directly,
but he was persistent.
He kept coming back in different guises.
He used others to give Jesus wrong advice,
to oppose and ridicule him,
as well as to try to make him a king.
Perhaps we’ve rejected
some serious temptations in the past,
but remember, Satan doesn’t give up on us
just because he failed in the past.
At a time convenient to him,
he may come back to tempt us
with something completely different
or the same temptation
dressed up in a different form.
So, what’s the key
to not entering into temptation?
We need to remember and apply
Jesus’ admonition:
“Pray continually,
so that you may not enter into temptation.”