“They.”
“They gathered them together
“to the place that is called in Hebrew
Armageddon.”
Who are “they”?
Who is being “gathered”?
And what is the significance of that to us
as we go about our sacred service today?
The answers can be found in the context.
I invite you to find Revelation chapter 16,
and let’s begin reading in verse 13,
which says:
“And I saw three
“unclean inspired expressions
“that looked like frogs
“come out of the mouth of the dragon
“and out of the mouth of the wild beast
“and out of the mouth of the false prophet.
“They are, in fact,
expressions inspired by demons
“and they perform signs,
“and they go out to the kings
of the entire inhabited earth,
to gather them together to the war
of the great day of God the Almighty.”
And verse 16 says:
“And they [these “expressions”]
“gathered them
[“the kings of the entire inhabited earth”]
to the place that is called
in Hebrew Armageddon.”
“Expressions.”
Now, these must be
very persuasive expressions
because they compel
not just a few isolated kings here and there
but “the kings of the entire inhabited earth”
to this situation called Armageddon.
Now, these expressions,
you notice, are unclean,
so they cannot originate with Jehovah.
And yet, they are inspired
—“inspired by demons.”
And yet,
they have their ultimate source
in “the mouth of the dragon,”
Satan the Devil
—“the father of the lie.”
But, now,
who actually gives voice
to these expressions?
Well, notice in verse 13 that the expressions
also ‘come out of the mouths
of the wild beast and the false prophet’
—political entities of Satan’s world.
So here we have
unclean expressions inspired by demons
—originating with Satan but voiced, repeated,
parroted, and echoed by people
who constitute Satan’s wicked world.
But, now, just what are these expressions
that are so persuasive
that they compel kings?
What concept would be so compelling?
Since 1914,
Satan has been stepping up his efforts
to mislead “the entire inhabited earth.”
And one of his goals
is to deceive mankind
into thinking that humans
—that Satan’s way of ruling is the best—
that humans can actually achieve
peace and security
through their own systems and governments.
Moreover,
according to 1 Thessalonians 5:1-3,
they will soon be saying
that they have actually achieved
“peace and security.”
Now, adding to the power
of these inspired expressions
are the signs.
The signs make it seem
as if these expressions
are actually coming true
and perhaps that they
even have the backing of God.
But the only god backing
these particular inspired expressions
is “the god of this system of things.”
Is it unprecedented
that Satan the Devil would use miracles
in an attempt to lend credibility
to his ideas, his wicked lies?
At Exodus 7:10-12,
Jehovah empowers Aaron’s rod
to become a snake,
but Pharaoh’s magic-practicing priests
mimicked that very sign.
Likewise, they mimicked the first
and the second of the Ten Plagues.
OK, but what about after the Christian
congregation came into existence?
Paul indicated at 2 Thessalonians 2:3-12
that the apostate movement,
which eventually gave birth
to the clergy of Christendom,
would be backed
“by the operation of Satan
“with every powerful work
and lying signs and wonders.”
—2 Thessalonians 2:9.
Moreover, Mark 13:22 says—
In the prophecy of the last days, Jesus said:
“False Christs and false prophets
“will arise and will perform signs
“and wonders to lead astray, if possible,
[even] the chosen ones.”
So, clearly, demons teach.
And it is not beyond Satan and the demons
to back up their false claims
with wonders at times,
although, obviously,
their power in that regard is limited.
A subtle reminder of that fact
is found at Revelation 16:16,
which says that they are ‘gathered together
to the place called Armageddon,’
“to the war of the great day
of God the Almighty.”
“The Almighty”
—only Jehovah can hold that title.
And that very word
is a guarantee that Jehovah’s will
will ultimately prevail.
Still, is it possible
that some professed Christians
could start to believe
“expressions inspired by demons”
that “perform signs”?
If it weren’t possible,
at least for individuals,
then why would
Revelation chapter 16 contain this warning
right in the middle of the discussion
about Armageddon that we just read?
The verse that we skipped, verse 15,
contains a very relevant reminder
for each and every one of us.
Now, sometimes we skip it
because we keep all the verses
about Armageddon together.
But, this is not an afterthought, a sidebar,
just a wise saying
plunked in for no apparent reason.
It’s totally relevant.
Let’s read it:
“Look! [verse 15]
“I am coming as a thief.
“Happy is the one who stays awake
and keeps his outer garments,
“so that he may not walk naked
and people look upon his shamefulness.”
So here we are, right on the cusp
of the outbreak of the great tribulation.
You have an identity
—“garments”—
an identity
as a faithful witness of Jehovah God.
Keep your identity.
How?
By keeping awake spiritually.
The article from which our text is taken,
entitled
“‘Your Deliverance Is Getting Near’!”
in the July 15, 2015, issue
of The Watchtower, points out
—in harmony with the Scriptures,
boiling down a number of Scriptural facts—
that Babylon the Great will be destroyed.
Then, the initial part
of the great tribulation will be cut short.
There will be a brief respite,
during which the majority of mankind
will seek refuge in human organizations.
Our message of good news
will change to one of judgment.
Then, the coalition of nations
referred to as Gog of Magog
will be bent on attacking
Jehovah’s anointed ones
and their associates.
Now, only loyal love for Jehovah
and obedient support
of his anointed ones will get us through.
That will mean everything!
So, what must we do now?
Stay awake.
You have an identity
—not just a Bethelite or Gilead graduate.
No.
You’ve worked hard, with Jehovah’s help,
to establish an identity
as a Christian worshipper of Jehovah
—keep it.
Perform “holy acts of conduct.”
We could say,
things we don’t do
—things we don’t watch,
things we don’t read,
things we don’t think about,
things we don’t say.
Don’t let the demons tamper
with your identity as a Christian
with their “unclean inspired expressions.”
Perform “deeds of godly devotion,”
we could say,
things we do
—preaching, lingering in prayer,
continuing in your personal study.
Much is covered in Gilead,
yes, but not everything.
The online Study Bible is amazing,
and it just keeps getting
better day after day,
helping us to forge a closer bond,
a close personal attachment,
with Jehovah.
Continue devoting time
to such “deeds of godly devotion” now
and you will succeed then.
You will not be duped by the expressions
that perform signs,
as others are.
No, you will survive
“the great day of God the Almighty,”
now so very near at hand.