Welcome to our program.
Here’s a preview
of what we can look forward to.
This brother began
his ministry in the Congo
when his fellow Witnesses
were few in number.
How did Jehovah bless his hard work
to preach and shepherd?
It’s a joy when we come together
at Assembly Halls for spiritual programs.
But how much work goes into caring
for these places of pure worship?
We also work to maintain
peaceful relationships
with our brothers and sisters.
What lesson does this sister learn
that lets her see
the beautiful qualities in others?
And we’ll consider the privilege we have
to be fellow workers with God.
You’re watching the October 2017 edition
of JW Broadcasting.
We begin with a report
from the United States branch
in Wallkill, New York.
Any Bethel assignment is a joy
and sometimes a challenge.
Proper training is therefore
an important part of every job.
How does the Maintenance Department
train hundreds of volunteers
to work efficiently and safely?
And how do the students feel
about the practical training they receive?
There were a few factors
that created the need at Bethel
for a more structured training program.
One of those factors included
the regular changeover in personnel.
The brothers have to be more versatile
in their assignments.
They may have to do tasks they
previously weren’t trained on.
Printing equipment became
more technologically advanced;
our building systems
became more complicated;
computer systems were now starting
to be used to control virtually everything.
Well, I feel like Bethel has definitely
always been good about training,
but especially now.
I think everyone sees
the need to continue investing
in the brothers and sisters
that are currently at Bethel.
I don’t think it’s possible for someone
to know less about the trades
than I did when I started.
I remember my first reaction
when I was invited to help
in electrical was fear.
So when I received my assignment,
I found out that it involved
running the heavy equipment.
So I called my parents.
I was really excited about it.
I said, “Mom and Dad,
guess what I get to do?”
And Dad said, “OK, Son.
Well, did you tell them
that you don’t know how to drive?”
It was decided to pull a group
of highly experienced,
highly skilled brothers
to concentrate
on developing and teaching
repeatable, consistent classes
that could bring people’s skill levels
up to what was needed.
We teach well over 100 different classes
in 12 major categories.
Here at Bethel,
I’ve probably been
a part of over 30 different classes,
so it’s been a variety,
depending on
the needs at the time
of the assignment.
I would estimate
that I’ve taken about 15
or 20 different courses
from safety and training
over the course of my 13 years
in learning a trade.
I’ve become certified
in at least these
seven different licensed requirements.
We teach people technical skills,
but that’s not the sole purpose
of the training.
If you aren’t skilled in safety,
you can’t be skilled
in your trade and vice versa.
The objective in all of our safety courses
is to get them to view safety
the same way Jehovah views it
—as a reflection of their spirituality.
So training in safety is essential.
So our goal is to take them
into the classroom
and give them some time
to consider the theoretical.
And then we take them out
where there is a lab set up,
and we have them do some tests on it.
Typically, they will tell us
that they’ve been able to learn
more in a week
than what they have learned
in a year of trade school.
We’ve done over 60,000 instances of training.
And so now receiving this training,
it provides an area or an aspect
in which I can give
my 100 percent to Jehovah.
You see it in their eyes.
They’re just so happy
that they now have maybe a new skill
or a new understanding
that they can use to benefit Jehovah.
I love the fact that I came
into Bethel with virtually no experience.
And not only did I
receive a trade that I could use
to carry out a work
that glorifies Jehovah
but I was trained well enough
that I can share that with others,
and they can be trained too.
Helping someone else
to go from that feeling
of not knowing anything
to feeling productive
and feeling like they’re
contributing is a real joy for me.
And they can take what they learn
wherever they go.
The confidence that people
leave with once they’ve received
that investment
—it’s confidence that they can carry out
whatever assignment
Jehovah has given them,
and the confidence that Jehovah
is going to train them
for whatever is being asked of them.
I think if younger brothers and sisters
are trying to learn a skill
so that they can come to Bethel,
that’s commendable,
but more important is spirituality.
Let Jehovah “finish your training.”
In regard to training,
we’re really only getting started.
The training that we are getting
in this system of things by Jehovah,
and especially related to safety,
is absolutely going
to be vital in the new world.
I can imagine the idea
of being able to use
some of the things I’ve learned
to figure out how
we can use the natural resources
in a way without using them up.
We know that we serve a God
who is known as the “Grand Instructor.”
So the things that we’re
teaching and training right now,
it can only expand in the future.
And as long as you let him train you,
you’re going to be all right.
Good training gives us confidence
to do our best for Jehovah.
That’s true at Bethel
but also true in the field.
Have you, though,
ever felt alone in your assignment,
even if for just a few hours
in the ministry?
Brother Pontien Mukanga may have felt
that way early in his assignment.
He was the first circuit overseer
for all of what is now
the Democratic Republic of Congo
and the Republic of Congo.
He traveled great distances to visit
the few brothers throughout the territory.
Listen to what encouraged him
the most to keep going.
In 1960,
I was made a circuit overseer
for the whole of Congo.
I was so happy to receive this privilege.
But I was shocked and scared.
The assignment was huge.
Congo is a vast country.
I was afraid to go to places I didn’t know.
I felt overwhelmed,
so I turned to Jehovah.
Sometimes I had to go through
savannahs and across the jungle.
There were wild animals.
One day, I climbed up a tree
to find a place to sleep.
I tied myself to a branch with my belt.
I was afraid I would be taken by a boa snake.
I was afraid of getting lost in the forest.
Visiting the brothers was very difficult.
Sometimes the journey took many days.
I remember one day,
I left my house
to visit the brothers to encourage them.
I left at 5:30 in the morning,
and I arrived at 7:30 that night.
I had to push my bicycle through sand
for up to 13 miles (21 km) or even more.
Other times, we traveled by truck.
That was not easy.
You had to climb on top of the truck.
I had to hold on tight so as not to fall.
Congregations, isolated groups
were far away from one another.
There were no phones at that time either.
Even though they did not know I was coming,
they made me feel so welcome.
The brothers were really very hospitable.
When I arrived,
I was exhausted
but so happy to see the brothers.
The Kitawala was a religion.
They sent many letters
to the Belgium branch
asking to be recognized
as Jehovah’s Witnesses.
These people used
our publications
and used the name Watch Tower.
It created a lot of confusion.
To clarify the matter,
the organization prepared a booklet.
My mission was to check whether
there were any genuine
Jehovah’s Witnesses in Kisangani.
We found out that these people were
not Jehovah’s Witnesses.
In all the confusion,
people even tried to kill me
during the trip.
Fortunately, I managed to escape.
Since it was Jehovah
who assigned me this privilege,
I was confident
that he would always help me.
And today, I am very happy
to have at my side my children,
my grandchildren,
and my great-grandchildren
—all Jehovah’s Witnesses.
Jehovah has given me many blessings.
I am truly grateful.
What a joy to be used by Almighty God.
Through all these years,
I have never lacked anything.
Jehovah has given me the strength
to serve him up until now—to the age of 86.
In everything and for everything,
my trust really is in Jehovah.
There were 46 publishers
in the whole of Congo.
Today, I hear there are more than
223,000 Jehovah’s Witnesses
in the Congo.
Today, when I see
the increase of Jehovah’s people,
to me it is like a miracle.
I thank Jehovah
for allowing me to see
‘the little one become a thousand’
here in the Congo.
Brother Mukanga continues to serve
as an elder at nearly 88 years old.
Can you imagine yourself
experiencing both the joys
and difficulties he had
as a circuit overseer?
He courageously visited
the Kitawala religious groups
who claimed to serve Jehovah,
only to find some were violent
and practiced immorality.
But it was his reliance on Jehovah
and watching Him turn
the small group of brothers
into more than 200,000
that has kept him going.
He personally experienced
our theme for this program:
“The Privilege and Blessing
of Being God’s Fellow Worker.”
As Jehovah’s people,
we enjoy many undeserved
and precious privileges.
Among them, we bear Jehovah’s name
and render him sacred service.
As we carry out his will,
he dignifies us in a very special way.
At 1 Corinthians 3:9,
the apostle Paul under inspiration
stated that “we are God’s fellow workers.”
What an honor to be a fellow worker
with the Universal Sovereign,
our loving heavenly Father!
To build appreciation for the privilege
of working with Jehovah,
we’re going to review events
in the life of Jonathan, a son of King Saul.
First Samuel 14:45
describes Jonathan when it says:
“For it was with God
that he acted this day.”
What was the background
that led to this statement?
How did Jonathan act, or work,
with Jehovah on that day?
What lessons can we learn
from their working relationship?
And what blessings result
from being a fellow worker with God?
Let us begin with some background.
First Samuel 12:20
records the encouraging words
spoken by the prophet Samuel
to the nation of Israel:
“Do not be afraid.  . . .
“Only do not turn away
from following Jehovah,
and serve Jehovah
with all your heart.”
Verse 22 adds:
“For the sake of his great name,
Jehovah will not abandon his people.”
As long as they remained faithful,
Jehovah would always be there to guide,
protect, and rescue them.
These words no doubt strengthened
Jonathan to carry out Jehovah’s directive
to subdue the enemy nations
and take possession of the Promised Land.
At  1 Samuel chapter 13,
we read that Jonathan
was assigned 1,000 men
to attack a Philistine garrison at Geba.
Although poorly equipped,
Jonathan and his men succeeded.
This victory strengthened
Jonathan’s confidence in Jehovah
and provides a valuable lesson for us:
While we gain strength and courage
from Jehovah’s reassuring
words of the Scriptures,
our confidence in Jehovah’s support
becomes even stronger
when we successfully
carry out our assignments
that may seem overwhelming.
The account then relates
how the Philistines
were infuriated over their defeat
and mounted a massive counterattack.
They sent out raiding parties
from their camp
at Michmash near Jerusalem.
Many Israelite men hid out of fear,
and some even fled
to the other side of the Jordan River.
In contrast,
Jonathan remained courageous.
Determined to put a stop to the raids,
he confronted the Philistine outpost
at the ravine pass of Michmash.
The approach was by way of a deep gorge
with nearly vertical cliffs.
This would have seemed next to impossible
to someone unfamiliar with the area,
but Jonathan grew up in this territory
and apparently knew it well.
His knowledge of the surroundings
provides another practical lesson:
Whatever theocratic assignment
we may be given,
putting forth time and effort
to get to know the terrain,
so to speak,
will contribute to our effectiveness.
When we show interest
in our assigned work,
we become even more effective
fellow workers of Jehovah.
Let’s read as Jonathan prepares
to take action against the Philistines.
First Samuel 14:6 states:
“So Jonathan said to his armor-bearer:
“‘Come and let us cross over
to the outpost of these uncircumcised men.
“‘Perhaps Jehovah will act in our behalf,
for nothing can hinder Jehovah
from saving by many or by few.’”
What contributed
to his confidence in Jehovah?
Recall that he put faith
in Jehovah’s reassuring words
through the prophet Samuel:
“Do not be afraid. . . .
For the sake of his great name,
Jehovah will not abandon his people.”
He experienced Jehovah’s support
when he struck down
the Philistine garrison at Geba.
Jonathan could also
think back on Israel’s history.
He could reflect
on how Gideon and his 300 men
were victorious over 135,000 Midianites.
He could meditate
on Samson killing 1,000 Philistines
with the jawbone of a donkey.
Such examples
would bolster his confidence
that he was working
with the Almighty God, Jehovah.
We too can meditate on fellow workers
of God recorded in the Scriptures
as well as published life stories
of modern-day faithful servants.
Such examples
reinforce our faith in Jehovah
as we rely on him for success.
Another lesson comes from the response
of Jonathan’s armor-bearer
at 1 Samuel 14:7:
“At this his armor-bearer said to him:
“‘Do whatever your heart impels you to do.
“‘Turn wherever you wish,
and I will follow you
wherever your heart impels you.’”
It is unlikely that the attendant
would have initiated
this challenging mission on his own.
Jonathan’s confident lead was a positive,
motivating influence on the man.
What happens today
when elders and overseers
take the lead and display zeal
in Jehovah’s work like Jonathan?
Others in the congregation are also
motivated to action by their fine example.
Let us now read verses 8-10:
“Then Jonathan said:
“‘We will cross over to those men
and reveal our presence to them.
“‘If they say to us,
“Stand still until we come to you!”
“‘we will stand where we are
and not go up to them.
“‘But if they say, “Come up against us!”
“‘we will go up, because Jehovah
will give them into our hand.
This will be our sign.’”
Jonathan once again demonstrated
humble reliance on Jehovah.
Later in Second Samuel,
Jonathan is described
as “swifter than the eagles”
and “mightier than the lions.”
However, these qualities
and abilities did not cause him
to be self-reliant or overconfident.
He sought Jehovah’s direction
by means of a sign.
What a powerful reminder for us!
Regardless of any natural abilities,
acquired skills,
or experience we may have,
the key to success is seeking
Jehovah’s guidance and support.
We seek his direction
through specific prayers,
Bible reading and meditation,
and applying direction
from “the faithful and discreet slave.”
We also consult
with longtime faithful brothers and sisters
who can share their rich experience
as God’s fellow workers.
One such example was Sister Joey Orrom,
who served in the Britain branch.
She shared her experiences
in an archived interview
some time before finishing
her earthly course in 2011.
Listen also to the comments
of her fellow workers in Britain
who benefited from their time together.
I had the privilege for two years
of sitting at the same table
as Sister Orrom for morning worship.
She expected nothing and appreciated
everything that you did for her.
Sister Orrom
was affectionately known as Joey.
And if you take the “e” out of Joey,
you’re left with the English word “joy,”
and that summed her up.
My impression of Joey
when I first met her
was here is this frail old lady.
But then when you
started to speak to Joey,
you were tapping
into a tremendous depth.
About the age of 20,
round about that time,
I had the heavenly calling.
That was a big battle.
I couldn’t understand why Jehovah
would use a person like me.
And when I was 21,
I got into pioneering, in 1939.
But the police were after me
because I wouldn’t join the armed forces,
and I was tried under a new act.
And they kept taking me
into a side room and saying,
“If you will say you are not connected
with Jehovah’s Witnesses,
not connected with the Watch Tower,
you’ll have a walk away.”
I said: “I am connected
with the Watch Tower.
I’m proud to be connected
with the Watch Tower.”
And they said,
“Then they are directing you.”
I said, “No, my stand of not doing
as you wish is my own personal stand.”
So this went on.
In the end, they sent me
to prison just for two months
and then let me out.
I partnered with another sister,
and she and I went to Northern Ireland
and pioneered there for 18 months.
And it was in Northern Ireland
that we had our call to Gilead.
In 1948, Joey was invited to Gilead,
and that was the 11th class.
It left an impression on me,
which I will never ever, ever forget.
You pick up that spirit
of good behavior, of love.
It’s something that leaves
its mark, or it should.
It has left its mark on me
—very, very much so.
One thing Brother Knorr impressed on us:
“You’ll be three years on your assignment
before you really love it.”
And it was true
because it was a hard assignment.
After Gilead,
she was assigned to be a missionary
in Dublin,
in the Irish Republic.
That was the time when Catholic priests
used to organize mobs against the pioneers.
She was full of joy,
but that didn’t mean to say
that she’d had an easy life.
We never went out from door to door
without being mobbed
and attacked and beaten up
and thrown around.
And you could only do
a few houses in a row,
and you’d have to get away very quickly.
But we made a very good name.
People got to know
we were completely neutral.
They chose four of us
to work the business property,
and I got some studies
going in their offices.
But one place I went into,
I walked the length of this draper shop,
and I asked if I could go
into the manager’s office.
As I went in, I didn’t say a word.
I didn’t open my mouth
and even say good morning,
but this man stood up,
and he said, “Russellite!”
And he took hold of me
by the scruff of my neck
and the seat of my pants,
and he lifted me up
and he carried me
the length of the store.
Well, like a silly one,
I should’ve gone heavy on him, you see.
But instead of that,
I let my legs paddle
and I was hanging onto my book bag,
not wanting to lose it.
And when he got
to the front door, the staff,
their eyes were absolutely aghast
at what was happening.
He opened his front door
and threw me out, literally.
And I went zoom!
just managed to go zoom!
And one of the brothers was passing,
and he caught me
—caught me steady—
and said,
“Whatever is going on?”
And I couldn’t stop laughing.
To me it was very, very funny.
The rest were so cross about it,
but I wasn’t at all cross.
I thought it was quite hilarious.
I could see myself being carried
through this shop sky-high.
Things like that happened.
These experiences
did not dampen her zeal.
She always retained that missionary spirit.
I first met Joey
when I was commuting to Bethel
in the infirmary.
She was sitting on that old-fashioned chair
with this huge Bible,
and she stayed there hours reading the Bible,
praying to Jehovah.
Often, when you came in,
she’d be in the middle of Bible reading.
And she’d be saying something like,
“Daniel has just been thrown
into the lion’s den!”
or “Oh, Jehovah is really angry.
He’s thundering from the heavens!”
And it made me think, ‘Wow!
‘She must have read
the Bible so many times,
but every time it was as if it was
happening right in front of her.’
Right up until she became incapacitated,
she was conducting Bible studies
and helping people
to come to know Jehovah.
She was looking forward
to her heavenly reward.
And for her that was the culmination
of a life of joy in Jehovah’s service
and that she was just transferring
to her next assignment.
I’m very, very grateful for work.
In fact, often in my prayers,
I’ll pray to Jehovah that I’ll have
some good work to do today.
I’m very grateful to have work to do.
Similar to what we
learned about Jonathan,
Sister Orrom demonstrated
humble reliance on Jehovah.
So sure was her trust in God
that she could face even fearful situations
with a sense of humor.
We may not be able to laugh
when enduring persecution,
but we can imitate Joey’s faith
and firm resolve.
What else can we learn
from Jonathan’s account?
Picking up at 1 Samuel 14:12,
Jonathan and his armor-bearer
advance toward the Philistines.
From their elevated location,
the Philistines shout to them:
“‘Come up to us,
and we will teach you a lesson!’
“At once Jonathan said to his armor-bearer:
“‘Follow me, for Jehovah will give them
into the hand of Israel.’”
Jonathan had requested a specific sign,
and he got it.
But it meant advancing
up a steep and treacherous incline
right into enemy hands.
Someone lacking complete trust
in Jehovah might have said,
“Before proceeding,
perhaps we should ask for another sign,”
but not Jonathan.
Without hesitation,
he told his attendant to follow him
because Jehovah would give
the enemy into their hand.
When we receive Jehovah’s direction,
we should without hesitation
put our hearts into the work,
confident of Jehovah’s backing.
What happened next?
First Samuel 14:13, 14 reports:
“And Jonathan climbed up
on his hands and feet,
“and his armor-bearer was behind him;
“and the Philistines began
to fall before Jonathan,
“and his armor-bearer was putting
them to death behind him.
“In the first attack that Jonathan
and his armor-bearer made,
they struck down about 20 men.”
Even after receiving
a clear sign from Jehovah,
it took great effort.
They had to ‘climb up
on their hands and feet,’
exerting themselves
vigorously over rugged terrain.
The lesson?
Even when we receive clear direction
and are ready to obey,
carrying out our assignments
will not always be easy.
We have to exert ourselves vigorously,
being willing to work hard
with all of our mind, heart, and strength.
How did the Philistines react to seeing
Jehovah’s support for his people?
First Samuel 14:15 reads:
“Then terror spread in the field camp
“and among all the people of the outpost,
“and even the raiding parties were terrified.
The earth began quaking,
and a terror from God ensued.”
The earthquake Jehovah caused
melted the Philistines’ hearts.
Soon, the Israelites, even those
who had previously fled in fear,
joined the victory battle
over the Philistines.
Likewise, when we put our hearts
into theocratic assignments,
Jehovah, our best Fellow Worker,
will always come through with whatever
we need to accomplish his will.
But there is another lesson to be learned
from this exciting Bible account.
During the height of the battle,
King Saul gave an unwise order saying:
“Cursed is the man who eats
any food before the evening
and until I have taken
vengeance on my enemies!”
Jonathan, however, was not aware
of his father’s order
and ate some wild honey
that he had found.
How did Saul react when he discovered
that his own son had disobeyed him?
First Samuel 14:43, 44 tells us:
“Then Saul said to Jonathan:
“‘Tell me, what have you done?’
“So Jonathan told him:
“‘I merely tasted a little honey
on the tip of the staff in my hand.
“Here I am!
I am ready to die!’
“At this Saul said:
“‘Thus may God do and may he add to it
if you do not die, Jonathan.’”
Imagine, after all that Jonathan had done
in risking his life in behalf of his people
and seeing Jehovah grant so much success,
he is now being condemned
to death by his own father.
How his heart must have sank in disbelief,
disappointment, and sadness!
Would Jehovah now abandon
his loyal fellow worker?
First Samuel 14:45 reads:
“But the people said to Saul:
“‘Should Jonathan die
“‘—the one who brought
this great victory to Israel?
“‘It is unthinkable!
“‘As surely as Jehovah is alive,
“‘not even a single hair of his head
should fall to the ground,
“for it was with God that he acted this day.’
With that the people rescued Jonathan,
and he did not die.”
Jonathan’s success
provided undeniable evidence
that he was truly Jehovah’s fellow worker.
Jehovah, who had been
at Jonathan’s side the whole time,
saw everything that had happened
and would not allow his loyal worker
to die at Saul’s hands.
How comforting to know that when we
faithfully carry out our assignments,
he will never forget our zealous efforts!
If someone as close as a father
fails to see and appreciate
the work we do in Jehovah’s service
or even turns against us,
Jehovah will never forget our work.
He will always be there to guide,
support, protect, and bless us.
What a faith-building account
we’ve considered
in 1 Samuel chapters 13 and 14!
Why not take the time
to read these chapters for yourself?
You’ll be moved to imitate
Jonathan’s excellent example of loyalty,
courage, and obedience.
We want to be described
just as Jonathan was at 1 Samuel 14:45:
“For it was with God
that he acted this day.”
By continuing
as industrious fellow workers with Jehovah,
we are assured
that ‘through faith and patience
we will inherit the promised reward.’
Let’s look at another example
of modern-day fellow workers with God.
Assembly Hall servants
care for the cleaning
and maintenance
of these places of worship,
but they don’t do this work alone.
In this report from the United States,
we’ll see how the work is organized,
and we’ll hear how
our brothers and sisters
feel about being able
to help with the work.
The Assembly Hall is an educational center.
This is a center of pure worship
for all the congregations that come.
Taking care of Jehovah’s house
is part of sacred service.
Even going back to the temple,
everyone had an assignment.
They had someone to open the doors.
So, of course, they also had
somebody maintaining things.
As of December 2016,
there are 773 Assembly Halls worldwide.
There are so many details
at an Assembly Hall;
you can’t do it all yourself.
To be overseer of an Assembly Hall—
We were excited to do it,
but it seemed real heavy at the time.
It does take,
in our particular case, a couple of hundred.
There are about 200 or so volunteers
each and every week
that really are necessary
to care for the Assembly Hall
—the grounds,
the accounting, the purchasing,
the maintenance,
and the cleaning.
Each and every one of these chairs
—the seating—
all have moving parts
and have to be maintained.
And with 4,050 seats in here,
we can say that every single one
of them has been maintained.
John 2:17 says:
“The zeal for your house will consume me.”
And I think we have
an opportunity to show Jehovah that
—that we have zeal,
we have an eagerness, a fire for his house,
and for caring for it.
So we appreciate all those
who want to work at the Assembly Hall.
So many of the dear friends,
after they just spent a whole day
doing some terribly dirty job,
they thank you for the privilege.
Well, that’s zeal for Jehovah’s house.
Nowhere else does that happen.
And if we tried to do it ourselves
or if we hired somebody,
it wouldn’t be as good as the work
that the friends do when they come in.
When the friends come on the weekend,
this is an educational facility.
So they come here
to be educated about Jehovah.
And new ones come,
and it needs to be dignified
and reflect Jehovah’s qualities.
So the cleaning that goes on
and the maintenance that goes on
—that’s what the purpose is.
At lunchtime, we do a spiritual program.
It could be a talk;
it could be a discussion.
And we, really,
generally try to cover a topic
that helps the volunteers
see the connection
between their work
at the Assembly Hall
and the Kingdom preaching work.
We are preachers.
That’s number one
—to spread the good news.
And we see the results of that here.
We’re filling this place up.
It’s a real privilege.
You learn so much
from the sacrifices that the friends make
in order to serve Jehovah
that it makes us feel very small,
and we realize
what a blessing it is for us to be
in that environment all the time.
The goal of any work in Jehovah’s service
is to help as many people as you can
to come to know him
and to take care of his interests
here on the earth.
And we all have the same goal
—trying to please him
and doing what we can.
Our goal, really, as Assembly Hall servants
is to take care of the place in such a way
—take care of the Assembly Hall
in such a way—
that not only saves and makes wise use
of dedicated funds and resources
but also makes things ready
in such a way
that on Saturday morning
when the brothers and sisters walk in
and the attendants and the sound
and the stage brothers are getting ready,
all they really have to do
is come on in and flip the switches
—lights come on, air conditioning, heat.
Everything is functioning.
All they have to do
is just focus on the program
and listen and take in instruction.
That’s what we’re asked to do
—listen and take in instruction.
And we can do that when we’re
not distracted by anything else.
So if everything
works well on an assembly day,
we know we’ve done our job.
We can remember
these hard-working brothers and sisters
in our prayers,
and we can do our part to help them.
If possible, volunteer to assist
with your congregation’s
cleaning assignment
at your next assembly.
Or ask about the arrangement
for maintaining Assembly Halls in your area.
A few are needed to take the lead,
but they need our help
to get the work done.
The same is true with the great amount
of work in the congregation.
In our discussion about Jonathan,
we mentioned
the zealous example of our elders.
Are the elders “leaders”
or do they “take the lead”?
What’s the difference?
Brother Geoffrey Jackson explains
in this Bethel morning worship.
While meditating on the text this morning,
I was reminded of an experience
I had many years ago as a missionary.
At the time,
I was studying with a young man
who was training to be a pastor
in his church.
This man had got to the point
where he started to attend all our meetings
while at the same time
still attending his church gatherings.
The church, obviously,
was very disturbed
about the fact that he was coming
to the meetings of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
and their headquarters
sent in a missionary from overseas
to try and rectify the situation.
The young man told me what happened.
He said the missionary asked him,
“What is it that impresses you
about Jehovah’s Witnesses?”
He said, “Well, one of the things is
that they do the preaching work.”
The missionary replied,
“Well, our church can do that too.”
So the next time they had a service,
the missionary conducted the service
and with great zeal and enthusiasm
demanded that everyone in the church
take part in the preaching work.
He announced the time that they
would have the group to go preaching.
The young man told me
quite a number of people came along.
But there was just one thing missing,
you guessed it, the missionary.
He felt that it was enough
just to encourage everybody else
to do it without engaging in it himself.
How different was the example
of Jesus and of our hard-working elders
who do take the lead
with regard to the preaching work.
Now let’s take our Bibles
and turn to a very interesting scripture
in Hebrews 13:7, 17.
Now, I’d like to highlight the beauty
of the New World Translation
in these two verses.
You see at the beginning of verse 7:
“Remember those
who are taking the lead among you.”
And then verse 17:
“Be obedient to those
who are taking the lead among you.”
If you look at other Bibles,
whether new or old,
most of them say “your leaders.”
Now, obviously,
the New World Translation Committee
had in mind Jesus’ comments with regard
to no one being a leader among us,
and although it’s a different
word in the Greek text,
still in English we can’t help
but be sensitive to that matter.
And so this accurate translation
of saying “taking the lead”
really summarizes, doesn’t it,
what the role is of an elder.
We’re not leaders,
but we set the right example.
Now, this accurate translation
is also portrayed
in the words of our Lord Jesus Christ
as recorded in Luke chapter 22,
and you’ll be interested to note
that this is part of the revision
of the New World Translation text.
Luke 22:26,
it now portrays accurately
the fact that both expressions in Hebrew
and this one here are the same word.
So, Luke 22:26,
it says:
“You, though, are not to be that way.
But let the one who is the greatest
among you become as the youngest.”
And then notice:
“and the one taking the lead,”
now this is the same expression
as in the Hebrews,
“as the one ministering.”
So, obviously,
to take the lead means to do the work,
to be a minister,
to be a servant, to serve others.
This also reminds me,
many years ago,
when I worked with the translation team
in the Pacific nation of Samoa.
At that point, we were trying to select
an accurate expression
to convey this thought of “taking the lead.”
And there were two words eventually
that the brothers
were trying to select between,
or choose between.
One was the word ta’ita’i
and the other ta’imua.
Now, you don’t have
to remember those words,
but as a foreigner,
I didn’t really understand
the subtleties between
the difference of the two words.
So I asked the brothers,
“How can you explain to me
what these two words mean?”
So one of the brothers was very eloquent.
He said: “Well, just imagine
a procession, a parade.
“So a ta’ita’i is the old man who sits
“on the side of the road
barking out the orders:
“‘You should do it this way;
you should do it that way.’
“The ta’imua, on the other hand,
is the one right in the front of the parade
taking the lead
and everyone’s following him.”
Which word do you think we selected?
Doesn’t that summarize nicely just exactly
what’s involved with being an elder?
It’s not a matter of sitting
on the sidelines barking out orders
but getting involved,
setting the right example,
and then others following.
And this is in harmony
with one Greek lexicon
that describes
this expression this way, it says,
“The concept of leading can be expressed
“by showing how to do something,
“demonstrating how we ought to do it,
and going ahead showing the way.”
Of course, on the other hand,
some religions even view
the expression “elder” as a title.
You’ve probably heard of them
introducing themselves,
“Good morning, I’m Elder Jackson.”
Well, of course,
none of us would want to view
being an elder as a title
in the sense of a position
that lords it over others.
And with that in mind,
another subtlety to the revision
is seen in 1 Timothy chapter 3,
so please turn there with me,
1 Timothy 3:1.
These are well-known words
—particularly when brothers are considering
the qualifications for elders—
but you may or may not have seen
the subtleties of the change
here in this revision.
It says now:
“This statement is trustworthy:
“If a man is reaching out to be an overseer,
he is desirous of a fine work.”
Do you remember before
the original New World Translation said:
‘If someone is reaching out
for the office of being an overseer?’
And that reflected
and no doubt was influenced
by the King James
and many of the older translations
that translated it that way.
But when we look at the rest of the verse,
we see that it’s not the office,
or the position,
of being an overseer
that someone reaches out for;
rather, it’s the work.
Yes, the hard work that needs
to be done by an overseer.
An overseer recognizes
that he needs to work hard
at setting the right example,
and then others will follow
—rather than just telling
everyone what they should do.
So when we look at these subtleties
in the New World Translation,
it only helps us to appreciate
it even more, doesn’t it?
So with this in mind,
what does our text this morning
help us to keep in mind?
Well, as elders, what do we need to do?
Not sit on the sidelines
barking out orders but, rather,
to take the lead,
be in the forefront, do the work,
and then others will follow our example,
just as we follow the example of Jesus.
The Bible gives us a clear understanding
of what Jehovah wants us
to do in the congregation.
Elders take the lead by doing the work,
and we follow their good example.
Applying God’s Word
contributes to our being fellow workers
under peaceful conditions.
But we could be distracted
even when our brothers
and sisters are right there with us.
What are these distractions?
Let’s see in this music video.
Think—think outside the box.
Be someone who talks.
Don’t waste away behind that tiny screen
’Cause you know
that there’s much more to life
Than friend requests and likes.
Think of all the things we haven’t seen.
Well, you—
You’ll never see them
if you’re focused on the superficial.
You need real friends,
if you know what I mean.
Look at me.
Can you see
What I see?
Around the world, this happy family.
Look at me.
Do you know
What I know?
That you belong.
Put down the phone, and look at me.
Take—take the time to see.
See what others see.
Don’t trade that plastic box
for all your friends.
You can make friends you know are true,
Who love Jehovah too,
Who’ll stand right
by your side until the end.
But, you—
You’ll never meet them
if you’re focused on the superficial.
You need real friends,
if you know what I mean.
Look at me.
Can you see
What I see?
Around the world, this happy family.
Look at me.
Do you know
What I know?
That you belong.
Put down the phone, and look at me.
Don’t let it play you for a fool.
What you’re getting
could be fact or could be fiction.
Life in the cloud can be so cruel.
Why don’t you come back down to earth,
converse, and reverse the addiction?
Put—put down your device
’Cause if you don’t think twice,
The best in life will surely pass you by.
Look, listen, taste, and touch—
The things we love so much
Have been here all along.
All you need to do is
Realize what’s in your hand
is only superficial.
You’ve got real friends,
if you know what I mean.
Look at me.
Can you see
What I see?
Around the world, this happy family.
Look at me.
Do you know
What I know?
That you belong.
Put down the phone, and look at me.
Can you see
What I see?
Around the world, this happy family.
Look at me.
Do you know
What I know?
That you belong.
Put down the phone, and look at me.
Time spent with our brothers
and sisters is precious.
Make the most of it
by setting aside anything
that could distract
from the interchange of encouragement.
Sometimes, though,
our viewpoint of ones in the congregation
hides their true beauty that Jehovah sees.
How does the sister
in this dramatization learn that lesson and,
in turn,
become more beautiful herself?
My name is Miki.
I moved here one year ago.
Everyone was so nice and friendly.
Well, that’s how I felt in the beginning.
I am not your babysitter!
Didn’t you see we were talking?
Come on!
This is not a park!
And the elders are always busy.
I’m not sure if they really want me here.
Yoko, a pioneer sister
from my former congregation, visited me.
She asked me how I was doing.
I told her how I felt
about my congregation.
Then she told me that she
had a similar experience.
And she shared with me
a Watchtower article that helped her.
I made this my next personal study project.
“What do you see when you look at others?
“Do you have the tendency
to view what they say or do
“as either black or white,
as if no other colors or shades existed?”
“Having that viewpoint
“would be like a photographer
who ignores the large variety
“of brilliant hues and shades
in an autumn landscape,
as if only black and white images existed.”
Maybe I’ve been viewing
the congregation as “black and white.”
The article then turned
my attention to Jesus’ example.
“The spirit, of course, is eager,
but the flesh is weak.”
Why was Jesus able to say such kind words
to his disciples?
Insight is the ability to put yourself
in the other’s place.
Jesus did that with his disciples.
OK, I need to do the same.
She always looks after the children at home.
She also needs time to be refreshed
by association with friends
at the Kingdom Hall.
She probably didn’t mean to be rude.
Since we looked like we were
having an enjoyable conversation,
she may have just wanted to join us.
The elders are so busy caring for the needs
of the congregation.
I know they’re doing the best they can.
I want to do what
I can to make their job easier.
Miki,
you are such a beautiful Christian.
We’re so glad to have you
in our congregation.
“The insight of a man certainly
“slows down his anger,
and it is beauty on his part
to overlook an offense.”
If you’d like to make this lesson a topic
for your personal study or family worship,
you can review
the March 15, 2008, Watchtower article
beginning on page 25.
The title asks the question:
“Do You View Others as Jehovah Does?”
When we share Jehovah’s view of others,
we’re better equipped
to be fellow workers with God
and with our brothers and sisters.
Finally, this month’s report
from fellow workers
comes to us
from the country of Georgia.
Forests, streams, and lush valleys
adorn this mountainous region
on the border of Europe and Asia.
Georgia’s capital,
Tbilisi, is a bustling city
where modern buildings
mix with historic architecture.
The Georgian people are known
for their strong family ties
and warm hospitality.
Folk music and dances
are a rich part of their culture.
Visitors are offered to try
a variety of delicious local foods,
such as this candy
made from walnuts and grape juice.
Old town Sighnaghi is a unique place
to enjoy the beautiful landscape and culture.
The congregation here has 50 publishers
who keep busy in the preaching work.
Despite being a small congregation,
they represent almost 3 percent
of the town’s population.
Remote towns and villages
create opportunities to preach
in unassigned territories
throughout the year.
We thank the congregation in Sighnaghi
and the more than 18,000 brothers
and sisters in Georgia
for this encouraging visit with them.
And we send them and all of you
our warm Christian love and greetings.
From the world headquarters
of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
this is JW Broadcasting.