‎Well, the words of today’s text
‎may have reminded you of the admonition
‎at 1 Corinthians 6:18,
‎where Paul wrote:
‎“Flee from sexual immorality!”
‎or perhaps the words
at 2 Timothy 2:22,
‎where he wrote to Timothy:
‎“Flee from youthful desires.”
‎In today’s text,
‎a father is counseling his son
‎and encouraging him to stay away
‎from sexual immorality.
‎In Proverbs chapter 7,
the counsel is strengthened
‎by means of an experience.
‎The king describes a scene
‎that he personally witnessed,
‎and we read about it
in Proverbs chapter 7,
‎beginning in verse 6.
‎So why don’t we turn there together?
‎At Proverbs 7:6,
‎you can imagine a father
‎encouraging a son
‎and he relates this experience:
‎“From the window of my house,
‎“through my lattice, I looked down,
‎“and as I observed the naive ones
‎“[or as the footnote says,
the “inexperienced” ones
‎“—like you, son,
the inexperienced ones],
‎“I discerned among the youths a young man
‎“lacking good sense
‎[or, “in want of heart,” ftn.].”
‎Now, that’s the first strike
‎against the young man, isn’t it?
‎He’s young and, as a result,
‎he’s inexperienced
—the two go together.
‎But the father proceeds to describe
‎what he observed
and the progression of events
‎that led to a tragic outcome
for the young man.
‎So it says in verse 8
‎that the young man
“passed along the street near her corner.”
‎Now, the “her”
‎is a prostitute.
‎What is he doing in the neighborhood?
‎Well, we’re told that “he marched
‎in the direction of her house.”
‎The word “march”
‎implies a sense of confidence, doesn’t it?
‎Isn’t it interesting
‎that a young person is often confident
‎even in risky situations?
‎Why?
‎Because a young person lacks experience
‎and can’t always foresee
‎the implications of a situation
‎or the outcome.
‎Another factor is highlighted in verse 9:
‎“In the twilight, in the evening,
‎at the approach of night and darkness.”
‎So now we have inexperience;
‎we have a bad neighborhood;
‎we have a young man who is confident,
‎who evidently has no intention
of committing immorality
‎and may even feel
that he’s in control of the circumstances;
‎and it’s nighttime.
‎Now, I know as a young man where I grew up,
‎everybody knew there were certain places,
‎or parts of town,
where you didn’t go after dark
‎because it was a recipe for disaster.
‎In verse 10, the inevitable happens.
‎The young man
is confronted by a prostitute,
‎and rather than turning around
‎and leaving the situation,
‎he engages with her in conversation.
‎And in verse 22,
‎we read the result
‎—the culmination—
of this progression
‎of ingredients:
‎“Suddenly he goes after her,
‎“like a bull to the slaughter,
‎like a fool to be punished in the stocks.”
‎Now, what do we learn
‎from this word “suddenly”?
‎Well, simply this:
‎In any situation, we can cross a line
‎where we no longer control
the circumstances;
‎rather, the circumstances control us.
‎And isn’t that what happened
to the young man?
‎He put himself in a situation
‎—going down a path
‎that eventuated, or culminated,
‎in his committing sexual immorality.
‎And the seriousness of the matter
‎is highlighted
in the “b” portion of verse 23,
‎where it says:
“It will cost him his life.”
‎So there’s a ripple effect.
‎Certainly, his relationship
with Jehovah was damaged.
‎His relationship
with his family would be affected.
‎And there are even physical factors
‎—illnesses that can result
‎from sexual immorality.
‎Now, note in verse 26,
‎the father says:
“She has caused many to fall down slain,
‎and those she has killed are numerous.”
‎And as our Watchtower
recently made the point,
‎thousands are disfellowshipped every year
‎from Jehovah’s family
‎because of sexual immorality.
‎Now, a question
that Brother Kittle addressed,
‎Is it only the inexperienced
‎that fall victim to this sad progression?
‎Well, let’s look at an illustration that appeared
‎in the Watchtower article.
‎You’ll probably remember this illustration.
‎And here we see two married couples
‎having supper together,
‎a seemingly innocent situation.
‎But what are the two folks sitting closest
‎to the camera doing?
‎They’re flirting, aren’t they?
‎You see the sister twirling
her hair with her finger,
‎and the brother is saying,
‎in essence, ‘I only have eyes for you.’
‎And you can see wedding rings on all four
‎of those individuals’ hands.
‎It’s a start down a slippery slope, isn’t it?
‎And as portrayed in The Watchtower,
‎this couple
would later accidentally “on purpose” bump
‎into each other
in the parking lot of the Kingdom Hall
‎after an evening meeting,
‎engage in conversation,
‎and that progressed to texting.
‎Now, the good news is,
as depicted in The Watchtower,
‎these folks realized
‎that they were headed
down a dangerous path
‎and took steps to correct it.
‎But wouldn’t it have been better
‎if they hadn’t gone
down the road to begin with?
‎It’s a good reminder for all of us,
‎whatever our age or circumstance.
‎Here at Bethel,
we interact with ones of the opposite sex
‎and many of us are married,
‎but many are not.
‎But as we were reminded,
‎we want to make sure our conduct is chaste
‎and pleasing to Jehovah.
‎The same holds true at the Kingdom Hall
‎and in our use of the Internet
‎and in our choice of entertainment.
‎We don’t want to start down a path
‎that could take us away from Jehovah.
‎I’ll never forget a pioneer sister
‎who used to counsel us young people
‎in the congregation, and we loved her.
‎But she had an expression
that she would tell us,
‎“If you’re not going to burn down the barn,
‎don’t strike the match.”
‎Now, what’s the point of her statement?
‎Why start a progression of events
‎that we know will lead
to sadness and tragedy?
‎So we don’t even go there.
‎And even if we’re inexperienced,
we can act wisely.
‎What did the psalmist say?
‎He said: ‘How can a young man
keep his path clean?
‎‘By keeping on guard
‎according to Jehovah’s word.’
‎So Jehovah has given us everything we need
‎to remain clean.
‎So talk to Jehovah about it.
‎Be alert to identify and be determined
‎to avoid dangerous situations,
‎and then we don’t have to experience
‎the sad outcome
of the young man described
‎in Proverbs chapter 7.
‎Instead, we can succeed
‎in fleeing from sexual immorality.