Welcome to the June 2019 program
of JW Broadcasting.
Earlier this year,
56 students from all over the world
gathered to attend
the Watchtower Bible School of Gilead.
They enjoyed a 20-week course that gifted them
with an in-depth study of the Bible.
The aim of Gilead schooling
is to help strengthen
the faith of each of the students
so that they in turn can strengthen
the brothers in their respective assignments.
On March 9 of this year,
the graduation program for the 146th class
was held at the Watchtower Educational Center
in Patterson, New York.
You’ll now enjoy faith-strengthening talks
that were delivered during the first part
of the Gilead graduation program.
Well, we’re happy to be here today
for this graduation of the 146th class of Gilead,
and we welcome all who are tied in with us
at our Bethel complexes in the United States,
in Canada, in Puerto Rico,
and in a number of remote translation offices.
We especially welcome our Gilead students
who are about to graduate
from this marvelous school.
And we welcome your dear family members
and friends who are joining you
on this very, very special day.
You seem excited, and you should be.
We’re happy.
We’re very, very happy for you.
Now, throughout your schooling,
you’ve been asked to draw out principles
from many different Bible accounts, haven’t you?
With that in mind,
here’s the theme of our introductory comments:
“Do You See the Point
and Remember the Purpose?”
We’re going to illustrate what we mean
by looking at Luke 5:1-11.
This is the account
where some of Jesus’ disciples
chose to leave everything behind
and follow him.
Here’s the setting:
Some of Jesus’ disciples were fishermen
who had followed Jesus for a time,
but then they went back to their fishing business.
Jesus sought to reach their hearts
and move them to follow him fully.
So, what did he do?
He used a powerful object lesson
that provided a point and a purpose.
Let’s read it at Luke 5:1-11,
and look for the point, first of all,
behind what Jesus did here.
It says: “On one occasion
when the crowd was pressing in on him
“and listening to the word of God,
“he was standing by the lake of Gennesaret.
“And he saw two boats docked at the lakeside,
“but the fishermen had got out of them
and were washing off their nets.
“Going aboard one of the boats,
which was Simon’s,
“he asked him to pull away a bit from land.
“Then he sat down,
and he began teaching the crowds from the boat.
“When he stopped speaking,
he said to Simon:
“‘Pull out to where it is deep,
and let down your nets for a catch.’
“But in reply Simon said:
“‘Instructor, we toiled all night and caught nothing,
“but at your word I will lower the nets.’
“Well, when they did this,
they caught a great number of fish.
“In fact, their nets began ripping apart.
“So they motioned to their partners
in the other boat to come and assist them,
“and they came and filled both boats,
so that these began to sink.
“Seeing this, Simon Peter
fell down at the knees of Jesus,
“saying: ‘Depart from me, Lord,
because I am a sinful man.’
“For both he and those with him
were overwhelmed with astonishment
“at the catch of fish they had taken,
“and the same was true
of both James and John, Zebedee’s sons,
“who were partners with Simon.
“But Jesus said to Simon:
“‘Stop being afraid.
“From now on you will be catching men alive.’
“So they brought the boats back to land
and abandoned everything and followed him.”
So, what was the point
behind this miracle here?
What was this?
Their needs would be cared for
if they trusted in Jesus and followed him.
Of course, to do this,
they had to believe Jesus, didn’t they?
They had to listen to him.
This was not a trick.
With their own eyes,
they could see that catch of fish
and then deduce that their needs would,
in fact, be cared for by Jesus.
That was the point.
Did they get it?
Yes, they did.
With what result?
Well, it says that they
were moved to abandon everything
and follow Jesus
—that is,
everything related to the fishing business.
They gave it all up and followed him.
Almost instantly,
their faith and trust in Jesus grew, didn’t it?
Now, let’s bring the point up to our day.
Soon you will go to your assignments.
Will you remember the point of your Gilead training?
Well, what is the point?
The point has been to build up your faith
and your trust in Jehovah
and thereby strengthen
your relationship with him.
In turn,
as you draw steadily closer to Jehovah,
you will be ready for whatever work
and whatever responsibility
he chooses to place on you.
Jehovah, by means of his Son, will care for you.
He will help you
to faithfully fulfill your assignments,
and you will add to his glory.
And in all that you do,
remember those disciples
who were humble enough to get the point
—abandon everything and follow Jesus.
Now, for the second part of the question
we mentioned at the beginning,
What was the purpose behind what Jesus did?
In other words,
Jesus’ miracle on that day
carried what deeper meaning for them?
Well, looking back at Luke chapter 5,
what happened
when the disciples listened to Jesus,
went out to where the water was deep,
and lowered their nets?
The catch was so great that it says
they filled two boats to the point of sinking.
The account doesn’t say
what the disciples did with the fish,
but they made it to shore.
A man who could walk on water
was not going to let them sink.
Now, we get, though,
to the greater purpose behind Jesus’ miracle.
Do you recall what Jesus said to the disciples
after that catch of fish
and after the disciples became filled with astonishment?
He told them: “Stop being afraid.
From now on you will be catching men alive.”
You see, by means of that miracle,
Jesus illustrated something
greater for them, didn’t he?
They would not only be cared for materially
(they got that point)
but, more importantly,
they would also become
very successful fishers of men.
In other words, the first miracle
pointed to an even greater one yet to come.
If their large catch was meant to illustrate
how successful they would be as fishers of men,
then they could look back
on that catch years later
and visualize those boats filled with fish
and be reminded
that they had much work yet to do
in being fishers of men
—“catching men alive,” so to speak,
and helping them to become disciples of Christ.
Your Gilead training
will help you to continue supporting
this vital and never-to-be-repeated work,
which is the greater purpose behind your training.
So, then, whatever you’re given to do
and wherever your training may take you,
never forget the point
and the purpose behind the blessing
that you just experienced
in being part of this class.
Trust in Jehovah and in his Son
to help you at all times,
and use your Gilead training
to support this important work
in the branches and the territories
where you will serve.
Well, we’ll say a little bit more about this
at the conclusion of our program today.
Now we’re going to enjoy
a series of very encouraging talks
that will strengthen your faith,
build up your trust,
(in fact, for all of us listening in)
and highlight God’s wonderful purpose
that we support.
To begin, we’re very happy to have with us
a member of the Governing Body,
Brother David Splane,
who is going to present the talk
“If You Look for It, You Will Find It.”
If you look for it,
you will find it.
Look for what?
Look for the good in your brothers.
And when you find it,
don’t be afraid to acknowledge it.
Now, we all know that we should do that,
but we do have to fight the tendency
to view others a bit critically at times.
Sometimes we question their motives,
maybe because we’re just a little bit jealous.
Now, think
about that brother in your congregation
who is just an excellent public speaker.
When he is scheduled to give a talk,
the hall is full.
And everybody raves about his talks,
even your wife
—yours, not so much.
‘The show-off; he doesn’t impress me.’
Or what about this:
You’re working in a department
with one of those annoying people
who is very efficient.
He’s never late,
he never misses a day’s work,
he gets a tremendous amount done in a day,
and he almost never makes a mistake.
‘That doesn’t impress me either.
Mr. Perfect, he’s trying to make
the rest of us look bad.’
Well, there we go questioning
someone’s motives.
Now, can we look for the good in Mr. Perfect?
Can we, see, give him the benefit of the doubt?
Maybe his parents trained him
to offer the very best gift he could to Jehovah.
In other words, if he could do more,
he was expected to do more,
because he wanted his gift
to be the very best gift
that he could possibly give.
Now, come to think of it,
he never criticizes your gift to Jehovah.
He just wants to give
his very best gift to Jehovah.
That’s the way
he approached the pioneer ministry,
and that’s the way
he approaches his Bethel service.
So, now, what do you do with Mr. Perfect?
Do you tell him to slow down?
“You’re making the rest of us look bad.”
Well, if he did that,
he’d be giving a substandard gift to Jehovah,
and Jehovah expects
and deserves the very best.
So, what do you do?
You acknowledge his gift.
“You really get a lot done in a day;
I wish I had your stamina.”
And what about Mr. Show-off,
the outstanding speaker?
“Jehovah has given you a wonderful gift.
You use it well.”
Now, was that hard?
Elders occasionally have to evaluate
brothers for privileges of service.
And while we’re not blind
to the shortcomings of our brothers,
we try to keep the discussion mainly positive.
Now, sometimes we have to discuss
a shortcoming—a negative.
But are we talking about one isolated incident,
or is it a pattern?
It’s true that if we make it
a habit to look on the positive side,
we’ll be disappointed sometimes.
But it’s better to be disappointed occasionally
than to develop a cynical or resentful attitude
toward our brothers.
Let’s consider a Scriptural example
where questioning the motives of a brother
could have led to disaster.
It’s in 1 Samuel chapter 17
—and a little bit of background,
a little bit of the setting—
Jesse has sent his youngest son, David,
to visit his three oldest brothers in the army,
and Israel is having a face-off with the Philistines.
And when he arrives, David hears Goliath
challenge any man of the house of Israel
to a battle to the death.
There are no volunteers.
David is a man of faith, and he can’t believe it.
He says:
“Who is this uncircumcised Philistine
that he should taunt
the battle line[s] of the living [true] God?”
Now, his oldest brother, Eliab, is listening,
and we pick up the account in verse 28.
So that’s 1 Samuel chapter 17,
and we’ll read verse 28:
“When his oldest brother Eliab
heard him speak to the men,
“he became [very] angry with David and said:
“‘Why have you come down?
“‘And with whom did you leave
those few sheep in the wilderness?
“‘I well know your presumptuousness
“‘and the bad intentions of your heart;
you came down just to see the battle.’”
Now, what did we learn
about Eliab’s personality from this verse?
Not much.
You recognize that as a trick question.
We just met the man,
we don’t know very much about him,
and we certainly aren’t going to pass
judgment on somebody
over one isolated incident, are we?
Now the question is this:
Was this a one-off for Eliab,
or was he always like that?
Was this an isolated incident, or was it a pattern?
When analyzing the situation, ask yourself this,
‘Was there ever an occasion
‘when I got so frustrated with my fleshly brother
‘that I said something awful,
something that I had to apologize for later?’
Well, did that make you a terrible person?
So the question is:
Is this a one-off?
Is it isolated, or is it a pattern?
These are things that we really need to apply
when it comes to our relations
with our brothers and sisters.
Don’t write somebody off
on the basis of one incident.
Well, we can say that on this occasion,
Eliab was wrong.
He questioned David’s motives,
and he wasn’t nice about it.
But that’s not the worst of it.
Suppose that David had listened to Eliab saying,
‘Slow down,
you’re making the rest of us look bad.’
What might have happened?
Suppose David had said: ‘You’re right, Eliab.
‘I am a bit arrogant.
Who do I think I am
that I could fight this mighty man of war?’
Well, that could have had
disastrous consequences for Israel,
at least temporarily.
So, what’s the lesson?
Don’t discourage anyone
from giving their best to Jehovah,
even if their best is better than your best.
Now, let’s take another isolated incident
from the life of Eliab
and say something positive about the man.
Let’s look for the good in Eliab.
First Samuel 22
—1 Samuel 22:1,
it says:
“So David went from there,
“escaping to the cave of Adullam.
“[So David is running away from Saul.]
“When his brothers
“and his father’s entire house heard of it,
“they went down there to him
[his brothers, including Eliab].”
So, what’s the point?
Well, when he was needed,
Eliab was there for him.
He could be counted on.
And later, one of David’s sons
married one of Eliab’s daughters.
Oh, wait a minute, say that again.
David ran away from Saul?
He didn’t run away from Goliath, did he?
But he ran away from Saul.
Jehovah’s spirit must have indicated
when David should stand and fight
and when he should run and hide.
Sounds like material for another talk.
Well, it’ll help our blood pressure
if we can learn to give a positive spin
to potentially negative situations.
Maybe you’ve run into this.
You’re walking down the hallway
following closely behind someone.
He goes through the door
and lets the door slam right in your face.
Is he self-centered or just lost in thought?
How do you choose to characterize that incident?
Is the public speaker a show-off,
or on this occasion is he simply trying
a bit too hard to be enthusiastic?
Is the brother being picky,
or is he trying to be thorough?
standoffish and proud
or just shy?
Now, one day, some of you brothers
are going to have positions of responsibility,
and you’re going to be dealing with people.
And when that happens, remember this:
Many joys are denied those
who keep looking for mistakes,
but the one who sees the good in others
will have “a feast constantly.”
Remember that!
And may Jehovah bless you richly.
We love you.
Well, we thank you very, very much
for that encouraging talk, Brother Splane.
Now we have a member
of the U.S. Branch Committee
with us to deliver the talk
“He Causes to Become.”
Brother Troy Snyder will do this for us.
Well, as Gilead graduates,
you’re being sent out
to strengthen and stabilize
Jehovah’s precious sheep.
And you’re being sent out
on the threshold of the great tribulation.
Now, what one scripture will strengthen
and stabilize you so you can help others?
Well, here’s a clue:
What truth did Jehovah
reveal to fortify the Israelites
right before they
were to be delivered from Egypt?
Let’s turn our Bibles to Exodus chapter 3,
and let’s notice what truth Jehovah revealed.
You remember the account?
Moses was asking Jehovah,
‘What can I tell the Israelites
so that they will have
confidence in your deliverance?’
In essence,
that’s what he was asking Jehovah.
Notice what Jehovah said
to fortify them in verse 14:
“So God said to Moses:
“‘I Will Become What I Choose to Become.’
“And he added:
‘This is what you are to say to the Israelites,
“I Will Become has sent me to you.”’”
That fortified the Israelites.
They understood that Jehovah was saying,
‘I’ll be whatever is necessary to carry out my will.’
And according to Appendix A
in our New World Translation,
it appears that the name also means
“He Causes to Become”
or “He Causes
His Creation (you and me) to Become”
whatever is needed to carry out his will.
And doesn’t that harmonize with who Jehovah is?
We know him as the Creator, don’t we?
He’s created us.
He brought about this universe.
He is the God who causes to become.
You see, this truth
—this extraordinary truth—
can strengthen and stabilize you
because it links you
to something that Jehovah is willing to give you.
Let’s look at what that is.
Let’s go to Jeremiah chapter 10.
You see, this aspect of Jehovah’s name
reveals something about his personality
and something that he’s willing to share with you.
Notice what it is in verse 6, Jeremiah 10:6.
It says:
“No one is like you, O Jehovah.
“You are great,
“and your name
is great and mighty.”
Yes, Jehovah’s name is linked to his power.
That’s what it reveals about Jehovah.
And Jehovah is willing to use
his power to strengthen us.
See, it was Jehovah’s power
that caused the Red Sea to part.
It was Jehovah’s power that made
the sun stand still when Joshua was in battle.
It was Jehovah’s power
that caused a bird to feed Elijah.
that took a tired prophet who was exhausted
and made him run faster than a racing chariot.
Isn’t that reassuring
—to know that Jehovah is saying,
‘I’m going to give you my power’?
Because oftentimes we’re exhausted
and we may feel like we’re unraveling.
But Jehovah is saying,
‘I love you so much
that I’m going to give you
the power you need to accomplish my will.’
You can see why Satan and Jehovah’s enemies
have tried to hide Jehovah’s name
—not just because it identified Him,
but because they wanted to obscure
the power that that name has
and what it means to us
and how it strengthens us.
But you know what else it also does?
It comforts us.
It can reassure our hearts.
It can allay our fears.
Notice how it did this
with one of Jehovah’s servants.
Let’s go back over to Jeremiah chapter 1.
Remember Jeremiah?
He was commissioned
with a very difficult assignment,
representing Jehovah.
And what did Jeremiah express to Jehovah?
He said: “I am but a boy.”
It was like he was saying:
‘Jehovah, I’m inexperienced.
‘I know I have a spiritual foundation
you’ve given me; you’ve trained me.
But I don’t know if I can handle this; I’m afraid.’
What did Jehovah say to him to fortify him?
What did Jehovah cause him to become?
Notice verse 18, Jeremiah 1:18.
It says:
“For today I have made you a fortified city,
“an iron pillar,
“and copper walls against all the land,
“toward the kings of Judah and her princes,
toward her priests and the people of the land.”
“A fortified city”
—see, Jehovah says:
‘I will strengthen you.
‘I’ll make you like that iron pillar.
I’ll give you that inner strength
you need to carry out your assignment.’
But “copper walls”
—what was significant about copper walls?
Well, it might be how Jehovah created copper.
What can copper do?
Copper at very high temperature will not buckle,
will not warp, will not lose its strength.
See, it’s as if Jehovah is saying,
‘Jeremiah, I will make it
so you can take the heat.’
And that’s what Jehovah is doing for you.
He will make it
—make you—
possible to handle any situation.
And you notice those were copper walls
—they fortified him.
They surrounded the city.
It’s as if mentally, emotionally, spiritually,
and physically Jehovah would give him
whatever was needed
to carry out his assignment.
Now, that fortified Jeremiah!
Could you imagine
how Jeremiah may have drawn upon this
as he dealt with challenges?
For example, when he was persecuted,
he was put in stocks.
Now, that’s torture; that’s a form of torture.
Could you imagine Jeremiah’s prayer,
‘Jehovah, cause me
to become what I need to become
to stay faithful to you’?
Now, did Jehovah block the pain?
We don’t know.
But what we do know is
that Jeremiah stayed faithful.
This experience did not break his will,
did not break his spirit,
nor did it break his integrity.
Or how about the time when Jeremiah
had to go in front of the temple
and in front of the priests and the leaders
and had to tell them that their precious temple
was going to be destroyed?
And he had to illustrate it
by slamming that clay vessel on the ground
and watching it shatter.
Could you imagine Jeremiah’s prayer?
‘Jehovah, help me become
‘what I need to to deliver this message.
‘Give me the poise.
‘Give me the courage.
Help me have that inner strength to do so.’
And Jehovah did.
Jehovah was with Jeremiah time and time again.
Yes, the very name of Jehovah
makes it clear that you will succeed.
You will be able to carry out his will.
And you’ve been doing that.
In your introductions to the family,
we heard how Jehovah
was causing you to become.
For example,
one of you talked about how as a young girl
you and your sister
were asked to leave the family home
because of your relationship with Jehovah.
What happened?
Jehovah caused you and others around you
—your brothers and sisters—
to become what was necessary
to keep you close to Jehovah.
One of you related how you were
on a theocratic construction expansion project
and you were assigned
to cut brick in the heat with all your gear on.
You said you maintained your joy.
Why?
Because Jehovah caused you to become.
One of you dear ones related to us
how you had thought
your service to Jehovah had no value to him.
You had lost your joy.
But what happened?
Jehovah caused someone to encourage you,
to strengthen you.
And one of you related how Jehovah
helped you serve
beyond the capacity of your heart.
Yes, Jehovah has caused all of you
to become what is necessary to carry out his will.
So whenever you feel discouraged,
whenever you feel afraid,
whenever you feel unqualified,
pray to Jehovah.
Ask him to help you become
what is necessary to carry out his will.
Ask him to help you do whatever you need
so you can glorify his name.
Consider: When did Jehovah reveal
this truth to the Israelites?
It was right before they were
about to face challenges.
When did Jehovah reveal this truth to us?
It was really with the revision
of the New World Translation.
It really helped bring it into focus
—the power of his name—
really, right before we are to be ushered
into Jehovah’s new world.
So, what trials will you face?
What challenges will you experience?
What will the great tribulation bring?
It doesn’t matter
because you worship Jehovah.
That’s his name
—the God who causes to become.
Well, we deeply appreciate
that very fine talk, Brother Snyder.
Now we have Brother Donald Gordon,
who serves as a helper
to the Publishing Committee,
with us to deliver the talk
“Live in Sync With Jehovah.”
Well, for the last five months you dear students
have been downloading a lot
of wonderful information about Jehovah.
Now that the class has finished,
the download is complete
—all synced up.
Well, it may seem that way for the moment.
Of course,  Jehovah did not create us
like simple computers
where we just store away
information in our memories.
We were created “in his image.”
So as we take in knowledge from Jehovah,
we have the ability to absorb it
and then to reflect his image
—to think like him, to feel like him.
We begin to act like him.
So he has given us
what we have here in his Word,
and he as well created us
in our human capacity to assimilate his Word
into the beautiful facets of his image,
and then we can truly be in sync with Jehovah.
But how does our being in sync with Jehovah
bring honor to him and joy to him?
Well, when we think of the various ones
who are in sync with Jehovah,
no doubt the foremost example is Jesus Christ.
Everything he did, everything he said,
every thought he had
was in full harmony with his Father.
Jesus said:
“I cannot do a single thing of my own initiative.”
Sometimes it’s like a husband and wife
who’ve been married a number of years.
With just a glance, without a word,
they know what the other one is thinking.
They’re in sync.
Or perhaps you’re thinking of two ice skaters
flowing across the ice as one, in unison.
Well, one example of Jehovah and Jesus
working in unison, in sync,
is when the woman
with the flow of blood was cured
by just touching the fringe of Jesus’ garment
—one of our favorite miracles.
Recall that scene again, recorded here
at Mark 5:29, 30
—Mark 5:29.
The woman
has made her way through the crowd;
she touches the garment, and then in verse 29:
“Immediately her flow of blood dried up,
“and she sensed
in her body that she had been healed
“of the grievous sickness.
“Immediately Jesus realized in himself
“that power had gone out of him,
“and he turned around in the crowd and asked:
‘Who touched my outer garments?’”
Well, that moment
when that woman sensed that she was cured,
Jehovah and Jesus
were working in complete harmony.
Actually, until that moment,
Jesus may have been unaware
that Jehovah was watching
this woman with a desire to heal her.
I suppose that Jehovah
could have just cured the woman on his own,
as it were, without Jesus even knowing.
But no, he chose to work through his Son,
who he knew was working in harmony with him.
So when Jesus felt the power go out from him,
he naturally wanted to know who was cured
—‘Who did my Father see that I did not see?’—
because they were working together in harmony.
And then seeing this woman,
realizing that actually she was unclean
and where she did not belong,
Jesus was still
in complete agreement with his Father.
He was in sync
with Jehovah’s view of this woman
and very happy
to have been involved in the cure of her
—leaving us, of course,
with one of our favorite accounts of Jesus’ life.
Well, what’s a lesson for us?
Whether we are at our work assignments,
in our congregations, or out in the ministry,
we want to be in sync
with how Jehovah views other people.
We often tend
to view others through our own eyes.
This can be clouded
by our own human concerns and viewpoints,
perhaps tainted by some misunderstandings
or misconceptions or wrong information
or perhaps
our need to be a little more forgiving.
You see, if any of those feelings
are tainting our judgment
or relationships even in a small way,
to that degree we are out of sync with Jehovah.
Jesus and Jehovah
were focused on this woman’s faith:
“Your faith has made you well.
Go in peace.”
Well, let us in every situation
strive to see others as Jehovah sees them.
This brings honor to Jehovah
and allows him
to use us in harmony with his will.
Now, there was another situation
where being in sync with his Father
took more time and effort.
When Jesus
chose his 12 apostles, he, of course,
wanted to be in harmony with his Father,
but this did not happen with just a glance.
Of course, Jesus had a very deep,
intimate knowledge of Jehovah.
And these men that he was considering
—he knew them well.
Still, this decision took hours of prayer
to arrive at the 12 apostles selected.
So it will be in performing your work
and making decisions in your assignments
—you cannot simply rely
on your knowledge of the Scriptures,
as deep as it may be.
To make decisions,
we must implore Jehovah in our prayers
—maybe many prayers—
and our meditations.
Don’t hold back from beseeching Jehovah
as you struggle for a decision.
But certainly, always relying,
of course, on his Word, the Bible
—knowledge from his Word—
prayers to our Father,
and then meditation on his will.
Of course, you’ve learned in your class
that the knowledge of Jehovah
is such a multifaceted gem.
There is an intriguing scripture
that sheds further light on this thought
here at Ephesians 3:19,
Ephesians 3:19.
It says “and to know the love of the Christ,
which surpasses knowledge.”
Well, now, how can knowing something
be more than the knowledge?
Well, you’ve learned here
that the Greek term rendered “to know” means
to know “practically, through experience.”
Now, of course, the Gospel accounts
teach us much about Christ’s love.
We come to know his patience,
his humility, his willingness to forgive, etc.
We read and we study that with delight.
But to really know it,
it’s like, well, a skill that we might learn
only after we actually do it.
For example,
a doctor goes to school to learn to be a doctor.
There’s lots of learning
and years of study involved,
but then when the studies are complete,
they begin their internship.
They begin making the rounds at the hospital.
They now begin taking part in this education
—what they learned from the books—
and applying it to real-life situations.
The knowledge learned from this experience
surpasses the knowledge learned in the books.
So we have studied the Christ;
we do the bookwork; we have learned.
Now, you Gilead students have had
the amazing opportunity these last five months
to read and study about his patience, his love,
his forgiveness, humility, compassion.
You cherish that knowledge; you’re in sync
—not quite yet.
You see, now we must do the internship;
now we must take that knowledge
and make the rounds, as it were.
We go around the congregation;
we interact with our workmates;
we go out in the field ministry.
You deal with a sticky, difficult situation
and put into practice
what you’ve learned from the Christ.
This is the way to get the full impact.
You’ve read and studied what he was thinking,
but now you know how he was feeling
—how it feels to unselfishly give
of oneself in behalf of others.
How does it really feel
to act with humility as Jesus did?
Or you come to know how it really feels
to forgive from the heart as Jesus did.
In this way, by experience
you come “to know the love of the Christ,”
and that ‘surpasses the knowledge.’
Now not only is what you know about God
and is treasured in your heart in sync
but now your actions, your life,
and who you are is in sync with Jehovah.
Indeed, like King David,
who expressed in the 139th Psalm,
you dear students have found in God’s Word
the precious thoughts of Jehovah.
Continue to search them out,
bring them to mind,
cherish them, and do them.
And then you
will be living your life in sync with Jehovah.
Well, we are very grateful
for that heartfelt talk, Brother Gordon.
Now we go to one
of our Gilead instructors for the next talk;
it’s Brother Mark Noumair.
And he will speak on the subject
“Offer Your Bow.”
At the age of 20, he was a natural leader,
commanding a thousand men.
His tribe was legendary
for their military prowess.
He was known as a skilled archer.
His bow never turned back from its target.
He was the firstborn, favored prince
—courageous, loyal, loved by the people.
Everything was lining up perfectly
for Jonathan to become Israel’s next king
—everything except
that he was not Jehovah’s choice.
So how would he react when he saw David
receive Jehovah’s special favor?
How would he react when David
was now transferred permanently
to the king’s house?
Would he be filled with envy, jealousy?
Would he feel threatened?
Would he work to assassinate David’s character?
After all,
David was 30 years younger than Jonathan
and came from a rather insignificant family.
So, what would Jonathan do?
This is what he did.
He did something remarkable.
And it’s found at 1 Samuel 18:3, 4.
And this is what we want you to think about:
what he did do and the application,
because this is so valuable for you.
First Samuel 18:3, 4:
“And Jonathan and David made a covenant,
because he loved him as himself.”
Now, note verse 4:
“Jonathan took off the sleeveless coat
“that he wore and gave it to David,
“along with his gear, his sword,
his bow, and his belt.”
Now, this dramatic act of deep symbolism
indicated that Jonathan would submit
his will to Jehovah’s will.
He was going to humbly support David.
But think about it.
By offering his bow to David,
Jonathan was giving up
a major part of his identity.
The Bible describes Jonathan as a manly warrior
—‘swifter than an eagle,’ ‘mightier than a lion.’
He was winning battles against the Philistines
before David was even born.
But was he worried
about losing the respect of others?
Did he say: ‘What will people think of me?
Will I lose my credibility
if I support this younger David?’
No.
Nor did he feel that Jehovah rejected him
because of the special favor upon David.
Jonathan’s bow and his other war equipment
were his trademark,
and that symbolized his military power.
But the bow did not make the man.
Love made the man
—love for Jehovah, love for Jehovah’s choices.
This is what we’re highlighting.
And once Jonathan offered his bow,
he never retracted it,
even when he knew
that David would be the next king.
He respected the divine arrangement,
and repeatedly Jonathan would support David.
He would reassure David,
‘You are Jehovah’s choice.’
Jonathan was not insecure.
He was not afraid to appear insignificant.
He was not threatened to see David rise;
nor did he view David as a rival to be eliminated.
Now, in human terms, this cost Jonathan.
He lost the prospect of being king;
he lost his close relationship with his father;
he might have lost
some stature in the eyes of men.
But in spiritual terms, he gained.
His unselfish devotion to David
received honorable mention in God’s Word,
which never would have happened
had he resisted Jehovah’s choice.
We wouldn’t even be talking about this right now
if he took a fleshly view
of Jehovah’s divine arrangement.
So this is your first big lesson:
Don’t measure your worth by your job title.
It’s your love of Jehovah
—that’s what makes you so valuable.
A spiritual person is a most powerful tool
in the hands of God, and this is what you are.
So how can you imitate Jonathan?
Offer your bow
by showing your support
of Jehovah’s organizational decisions,
even if it means giving up something you love
or want to cling to.
For example,
some of you have been given
new country assignments,
and yet you might not have planned
on moving to another country.
You were content where you were;
you were happy doing what you were doing.
Thank you.
Thank you for your unselfish support
of the decisions made
to advance Kingdom interests globally.
Thank you.
Or perhaps you’ve been trained in some capacity
—something you really enjoy.
And yet now someone else
is assigned to do that job.
Will you, like Jonathan,
put your heart into supporting and reassuring
the new person that took your job?
And how about you as a sister?
What about if a new sister comes and gets
the job assignment you love, you cherish?
You wake up every day ‘I love my job!’
and now you’re asked to train her.
What will you do?
Will you offer your bow?
Or the sister gets the office that you dreamed of
—the one with the window.
There it is.
You had your eyes set on it.
You might have seniority.
She could be younger than you,
but perhaps oversight
took other factors into consideration
that you were not aware of.
What will you do?
What will all of you do in these situations?
Will you accept the fact that supporting decisions
by the organization at times
involves sacrifices on your part?
Well, let your love for Jehovah
mean more than your cherished work assignment.
And this is a very, very big lesson
—lesson number one—
and very important for you to think about,
offering your bow in this way.
You’ve already shown this spirit.
We’re just reinforcing something
that you need to hear prior to your departure.
Now, I want you to think about this for a moment.
Compare Jonathan’s good example
with that of his brother Ish-bosheth.
When Saul died,
2 Samuel 2:8 says
that his general, Abner,
made Ish-bosheth king
—no loyalty to Jehovah’s choice.
And Ish-bosheth agreed, ‘I want that.’
Ish-bosheth craved position,
which led to a civil war, which led to problems.
Now, instead of Ish-bosheth offering his bow
and his war equipment to David,
2 Samuel chapter 2
describes how he provoked war with David,
which resulted in bloodshed
and the death of 380 men in Israel.
Ish-bosheth’s heart wasn’t with David.
That was Jehovah’s choice.
He was unlike his brother Jonathan.
But now imagine if Jonathan was still alive
when Saul died and Abner
now comes to Jonathan and says:
‘Jonathan, I want you to be king.
You’d make a great king.’
Would Jonathan have agreed?
Would he have then said,
‘Give me my bow back’ and retract it
and take it back and tell David:
‘No, I feigned loyalty to you.
This is what I really wanted.
I want to be king’?
No. No.
Jonathan wouldn’t have done that.
Why?
Because he gave not just his bow to David,
he gave not just his war equipment to David (no),
he gave his very heart to Jehovah’s choice.
And that’s the beautiful thing about him.
The difference between Jonathan,
who sees an opportunity
to support Jehovah’s cause,
and Ish-bosheth,
who never thought for a moment
about how Jehovah God
was directing David, is striking.
And the results speak for themselves.
Jonathan was loved and honored.
Ish-bosheth was hated and murdered.
When Jonathan died,
David was so deeply grieved
by the loss of his dear friend
that he was moved to do something.
And what he did is recorded
at 2 Samuel 1:17, 18.
I’d like to read this to you.
Second Samuel 1:17, 18:
“Then David chanted this dirge [or this song]
“over Saul and his son Jonathan and said
“that the people of Judah should be taught
the dirge [the song] called ‘The Bow.’”
“The Bow.”
Could David have had in mind the bow
that Jonathan gave him
at the beginning of their friendship?
Jonathan supported
the nation without demanding
that he receive high rank, or position.
Jonathan was so loyal.
It was a powerful lesson that David never forgot,
and neither did he want
the sons of Judah to forget,
because he instructed
that they all learn this song by heart.
Offering your bow
is a powerful word picture.
When you continue to work in the background
(work quietly in the background),
in loyal support of Jehovah’s choices
despite the cost,
despite the human imperfections,
despite the disappointments,
despite the perceived injustices,
you don’t worry about all of that.
That’s simply the ebb and flow of life.
Pick yourself up; keep on moving; grow mighty;
become a living example
to the brotherhood in loyalty.
That’s what you’ve been trained to do.
And you will receive
Jehovah’s attention and favor
just as Jonathan did.
Jehovah did not merely dismiss
Jonathan as a would-have-been king.
No.
Rather, he took note of Jonathan’s loyal support
and had his wonderful example embedded,
etched, into his inspired Word.
So as you go to your assignment,
what is your bow?
Everyone has one.
Is it your cherished work assignment?
Is it that privilege that you have been given
that few others enjoy?
Is it the responsibility
that requires many to consult you for direction?
Well, think about this:
The time will come
when someone is put in a leading role,
and you will be asked to support that person,
work under that person, help that person.
And when that time comes, ask yourself,
‘What will I do?’
And not just you brothers, you sisters too,
I mean, you wives, will you support?
will the wife support as well?
Single sisters, will you support the arrangement?
That’s the point.
Ask yourself: ‘Will I offer my bow like Jonathan?
‘Will I offer it freely?
‘Will I offer it generously to anyone chosen
for a role of responsibility
within God’s organization?’
And be assured
that Jehovah in turn will offer you
—offer you an unimaginable treasure.
And that treasure is his favor and approval.
Jehovah’s favor and approval
—what is better than that?—
now and life in the new world.
And when you get to the new world,
be sure to look for the one
who inspired you to offer your bow.
Well, we thank you, Brother Noumair,
very much for that encouraging talk.
In fact, we’ve enjoyed a series
of wonderful talks this morning, haven’t we?
What an encouraging program thus far!
And in the upcoming weeks,
look for Parts 2 and 3 of the graduation program.
They’ll be found under Latest Videos
or under the Video on Demand segment
of JW Broadcasting.
We’ll conclude this month’s program
by traveling to the tropical island
of Kosrae in Micronesia.
Located in the Pacific Ocean,
Kosrae is filled
with dense jungles, mangroves,
picturesque beaches,
and is surrounded by beautiful coral.
Many on the island work in the tourism,
fishing, or agricultural industries.
Although the official language
of Kosrae is English,
there’s a remote translation office here.
One brother and four sisters
assist with translating literature
into Kosraean.
There’s one congregation on Kosrae
with 2 field missionaries, 2 special pioneers,
and 2 regular pioneers,
and a total of about 15 publishers.
They preach
to the over 6,000 inhabitants of the island.
And their hard work is bearing fruit.
For example, in 2018,
there were 82 in attendance
at the Memorial celebration
and a peak of 65
attended the regional convention.
And in 2018,
the congregation reported some 60 Bible studies.
The brothers and sisters in Kosrae
send you their warm love and greetings.
And by means of this program,
we all send our love
and encouragement back to them.
This is JW Broadcasting
from the World Headquarters
of Jehovah’s Witnesses.