In a recent poll,
over 6,000 people surveyed worldwide
were asked to rank
what they felt were keys to happiness.
Of interest was that only 16 percent believed
that one’s faith or religious beliefs
had any impact or bearing on their personal happiness.
Now, the words of today’s text, as we know,
are part of Jesus’ Sermon on the Mount,
and he begins this by letting us know
what is needed in order to be truly happy.
But in his discussion,
Jesus explained something
quite different from that poll.
He explains that our happiness
is directly connected to our faith
and to our relationship with God.
I invite you to turn with me in your Bibles
—we’re going to consider portions of this account—
to Matthew chapter 5.
And let’s begin with the reading of Matthew 5:3:
“Happy are those
conscious of their spiritual need,
since the Kingdom of the heavens
belongs to them.”
Notice the start:
“Happy are those
conscious of their spiritual need.”
Or, as the footnote says,
or “those who are beggars for the spirit.”
A literal beggar is likely,
painfully aware of his need for physical food.
And isn’t that exactly how you and I
have to be conscious of our spiritual need?
You see,
we have to beg Jehovah for his holy spirit.
And you notice this point
is highlighted again if you look in verse 6
—the thought of “hungering and thirsting”
for divine guidance,
begging to be led in the right way
to allow Jehovah’s spirit
to be operative upon us and in our lives.
And, of course, we do this
by taking advantage of spiritual provisions
—so reading and meditating on God’s Word,
having a regular study program
and, of course,
constantly going to Jehovah in prayer.
When we do this, all of this shows
that we are putting our complete
dependence and reliance upon Jehovah.
And, of course, as we beg for holy spirit
and we work to apply the things that we learn,
well, obviously, now we’re happy
because it helps us to become better individuals
and we’re better able to display
various aspects of the fruitage of the spirit.
And this becomes evident in our dealings with others.
Jesus mentions some of these qualities in his sermon.
For example, if you look in verse 5,
we develop the quality of mildness.
In verse 7, we’re able to be merciful with others.
And then in verse 9,
we’re peaceable or we’re “peacemakers.”
So we’re the ones that go about working
to initiate peace with one another.
And being in such a large family,
certainly, can’t we see the benefit of this?
The more that we’re able to integrate these
qualities into our dealings with one another,
the happier we’re going to be and, of course,
the happier our Bethel family will be
as they deal with one another.
Now, next in the sermon
is our text for today, verse 8.
And here in verse 8, we’re helped
to examine our motives for serving God.
As our commenters mentioned,
being pure in heart has to do
with what we are on the inside.
So it’s our motives;
it’s our affections; it’s our desires.
And can’t we say,
‘Aren’t we happiest
when we know that we’re serving Jehovah
‘with a clean conscience
and that everything that we do
is motivated
by our sincere love and gratitude for him?’
You know, the interesting thing
about Jesus’ Sermon on the Mount
was that as he spoke with
these large crowds that gathered from all over,
likely the majority
of the people in the crowds were happy.
They were probably very excited
they were able to make this journey.
They were thrilled about the possibility
of meeting Jesus and learning about him.
Many of them had probably been healed by him
and cured of some sickness and infirmity.
But despite all of that joy and excitement,
Jesus was helping them to see that real happiness,
genuine happiness, was more than how they felt
or what they were doing at present.
Happiness was not just a joyous occasion.
It was more than just a good time with others.
It went much deeper than that.
It involved their contentment,
satisfaction, fulfillment in life.
And all of those things are directly related
to one’s relationship with God.
That’s why if we go back to chapter 6
—even if you look in verses 10 and 11—
it’s amazing how members of our brotherhood
can experience hurt, disappointment,
ridicule, even severe persecution,
and yet they’re able to remain remarkably happy.
Why?
It’s because of their relationship and service to Jehovah.
Now, this Sermon on the Mount was not
the only time that Jesus focuses on this point.
If we look at another account—
If you turn with me, please, to Luke chapter 11,
and here we’ll see another account
where Jesus shows the connection
between happiness
and one’s relationship with Jehovah.
Luke chapter 11,
and we’ll look at verse 27.
It says: “Now as he was saying these things,
a woman from the crowd called out to him:
‘Happy is the womb that carried you
and the breasts that nursed you!’”
Well, Jewish women desired
the privilege of being the mother of a prophet
and particularly the Messiah.
So this woman must have thought:
‘What a privilege for Mary.
‘How happy she must have been
to be the mother of Jesus Christ.’
And likely she was.
But yet, what did Jesus do?
Notice how he gently corrects the woman
and directs her attention
as to the true source of happiness.
Verse 28:
“But he said: ‘No, rather,
happy are those
hearing the word of God and keeping it!’”
So again, Jesus emphasizes that true happiness
is not found in any physical ties;
it’s not found in privileges;
it’s not found in accomplishments.
True happiness is found
in being a true, faithful servant of God;
because likely Jesus knew
that if we were to gauge our happiness
on any of these other things,
you see, our life
becomes one giant roller coaster of events.
It’s basically a bunch of highs and lows,
and we’re just waiting
for the next big thing in life to make us happy.
That’s a very tough way to live.
It’s a stressful way to live.
Well, Jesus and his Father
—they don’t want us to live this way.
How interesting that our Watchtower
for this week really helped to capture this point.
And didn’t we learn that we
cannot gauge happiness by what we have,
by what we do, even by where we serve.
Because isn’t it true that the reality is there
are some things that are just not in our control?
And as our Watchtower so nicely highlighted,
our circumstances can always change.
And that’s going to affect, expand, or limit
what we’re able to do in Jehovah’s service.
If we just go back for a minute
to that survey that was taken,
the top answer on the list
as far as what made one happy
was “family and relationships.”
And doesn’t that really highlight the disconnect
when a person does not view Jehovah as family
—when they don’t see him as their heavenly Father?
So don’t we rejoice in the fact
—we cherish the fact—
actually, that Jehovah is our Father?
And he’s a happy God,
and he wants us to be happy as well.
Jehovah is certainly appreciative of anything
that we’re able to do in his service
according to our circumstances and our abilities.
And we rejoice in the fact that our faith
is strong and we are happy
—genuinely happy.
Why?
Because we have a good relationship with God,
and this is the relationship
that allows us to learn about him,
that allows us to be fellow workers
with him in our Christian ministry
and, ultimately,
gives us the tremendous privilege
to bear and to carry his name.