Is it possible to survive
the attack of a roaring lion?
Well, now, I did some
—just quick—
checking on various wildlife websites,
and here’s what they say.
Basically, they all give the same advice
if you’re being attacked by a lion.
They say: “Hold your ground.
Never run or turn back.”
In fact, one website says:
“A lion can run 50 miles per hour (80 km/h).
“So stand still.
If you run, you will only die tired.”
Well, that’s true.
First Peter 5:9
gives us exactly the same advice.
It says: “Take your stand against him.”
Well, in this case
not against a literal lion,
but against that “roaring lion,”
Satan the Devil,
who is seeking to devour
every single one of us.
Our ability to stand firm
when facing this lion
—to be able to oppose him,
to refuse to be intimidated by him,
to refuse to run away or turn back—
requires what the apostle Peter
next mentions there in verse 9,
and Brother Crane
so nicely covered in his comment.
We have to: “Take [our] stand against him,
firm in the faith.”
To be successful,
we must have complete trust
and complete confidence in Jehovah.
Well, now, in that regard,
let’s look at an example
of someone in Bible times who had
that kind of confidence in Jehovah.
This is in the days of King Jehoshaphat,
when Judah was threatened
by the combined forces
of Moab, Ammon,
and the inhabitants
of the mountainous region of Seir.
Now let’s begin by opening our Bibles
and reading 2 Chronicles 20:12.
So here Jehoshaphat is praying to Jehovah;
he’s pouring out his heart to him,
and see what he says:
“O our God,
will you not execute judgment on them?
“For we are powerless before this large crowd
“that is coming against us;
“and we do not know what we should do,
but our eyes are toward you.”
Well, Jehoshaphat was facing the lion.
He said to Jehovah:
‘We don’t know what to do.’
But Jehoshaphat had complete and total trust;
he had firm faith in Jehovah.
Well, what did Jehovah
tell Jehoshaphat to do?
See verse 17:
“You will not need to fight this battle.
Take your position.”
Does that sound familiar?
“Take your position, stand still,
“and see the salvation of Jehovah
in your behalf.
“O Judah and Jerusalem,
“do not be afraid or be terrified.
“Tomorrow go out against them,
and Jehovah will be with you.”
Well, what did Jehovah tell them to do?
He said: ‘Take a position
in opposition to that military force,
‘stand firm, refuse to run away,
and see the salvation
that will come from Jehovah.’
Well, in order to do that,
Jehoshaphat and the people with him
would need to have strong, firm, solid faith.
Well, now, to help the people,
look at what Jehoshaphat said to them
as they were getting ready for this battle.
In verse 20, you see,
just about the middle of the verse,
it says:
“Jehoshaphat stood up and said:
“‘Listen to me, O Judah
and you inhabitants of Jerusalem!
“‘Put faith in Jehovah your God
“‘so that you may be able to stand firm.
“‘Put faith in his prophets,
and you will be successful.’”
Well, that’s exactly what happened.
See, with that kind of confidence in Jehovah,
with that firm trust in him,
with that standing firm,
what did Jehovah do?
Well, according to verses 22 and 23
—you’ll remember what happened—
the men of Ammon, Moab,
and the inhabitants
of the mountainous region of Seir,
they all went to striking down one another.
And verse 23 says:
“And the Ammonites and the Moabites
“turned against the inhabitants
of the mountainous region of Seir
“to destroy and annihilate them;
“and when they finished
with the inhabitants of Seir,
they helped to destroy one another.”
Well, Jehovah had rewarded
their firm faith in him.
The weapons that had been formed
against Jehoshaphat and his people
had no success.
Well, now,
sometimes we think, of course,
that these kinds of situations
only happened in Bible times.
But it’s amazing to see
how our brothers in our modern day
have had that same kind of faith
and have stood firm against the lion.
Here are just a couple of experiences
that really touched my heart.
Here’s one about a brother
named Pavel from Russia.
In 1958,
Pavel was arrested for religious activities.
“Accompanying me to the train,” he says,
“the officer [with me] said,
“‘Look at your wife for the last time
because you will never see her again.’”
Well, there’s the lion.
“I spent six months
in solitary confinement before my trial.
“During interrogations, . . .
the investigators did everything
“to undermine my faith.
“Sometimes violence was used.
I begged Jehovah
to give me the strength to stay firm.”
But now look what happened.
“During a routine interrogation,
“the investigator called me
into his study and [he] said:
“‘Now we will show you
what your organization is doing.
“Then you can see
if it is God’s work or not!’
“Looking at me intently, he continued:
“‘This year your convention in New York
“‘was attended by 253,000 people
“‘in two stadiums.
“The convention lasted eight days.’
“The investigator strewed
the table with photographs.
“In one of them,
I saw happy delegates
“in colorful native dress
embracing one another.
“Another photo showed
Brother Knorr giving a talk,
“and yet others showed the baptism.
“The investigator could not even imagine
“what I was feeling at that moment.
“I felt that I was attending the convention
“without ever having left the prison.
“I felt new strength flooding into me.
“[It was just what] I had needed.
“. . . And Jehovah generously
blessed me in a special way.
I was ready to endure further.”
Isn’t that amazing?
Here’s another similar experience,
1960, also in Russia,
a large publicized trial
of Jehovah’s Witnesses.
About 300 persons
were present in the courtroom,
including many of our brothers and sisters.
Well, as the evidence—
As evidence against the brothers,
the prosecutor decided to present
a letter from Nathan H. Knorr.
One of the brothers
who attended the trial said this:
“The prosecutor loudly began to read a letter
“that had been intercepted by the KGB
“from Brother Knorr
to the brothers in the Soviet Union.
“For all of us Witnesses present in the hall,
“it was a wonderful gift from Jehovah.
“This letter warmed our hearts!
“We heard wise counsel from the Bible
“and encouragement to serve
our fellow believers lovingly
“and to stay faithful [even] under trials.
“The prosecutor read the letter
“from the beginning to the very end.
“We listened with rapt attention.
It seemed to us that we were
attending a convention!”
Well, now, brothers, what additional lessons
do we learn from these two experiences?
When we stand our ground against Satan,
firm in the faith,
then Jehovah will do just what he promised
at 1 Peter 5:10.
Do you see what it says there?
“But after you have suffered a little while,
“the God of all undeserved kindness,
“who called you to his everlasting glory
in union with Christ,
“will himself finish your training.
“He will make you firm,
“he will make you strong,
he will firmly ground you.”
So, brothers,
can we survive the attack of a roaring lion?
Absolutely!
With firm faith, let’s stand fast
and see the salvation from Jehovah.