Our text today is highlighting the fact
that we do not want
to be trapped by the Devil.
And that’s what the apostle Paul
was concerned about with the Christians
in Colossae.
If we go to Colossians
where our text is found,
notice his words
and his recommendations to them
in chapter 2 and verses 6 and 7.
He says:
“Therefore, just as you have accepted
“Christ Jesus the Lord,
“go on walking in union with him,
“being rooted and built up in him
“and being stabilized in the faith,
“just as you were taught,
and overflowing with thanksgiving.”
So Paul was encouraging them:
‘Be strong Christians.
‘Have this deep,
‘spiritual taproot,
so to speak.
Have your faith solid
in Christ Jesus.’
I was in Louisiana last week,
and I tried to pull up a pecan seedling
—a little plant of a pecan.
Have you ever tried that?
You cannot pull it up with your hands
because the taproot goes so deep;
you have to have a shovel.
And so that’s what Paul was saying
—be sure that your spiritual strength
is solid and that it goes deep.
Well, why did he say that?
If you notice in verse 4, he says:
“I am saying this so that no one
may delude you
with persuasive arguments.”
See, he was concerned
that even those
with a strong spiritual foundation
may be deceived
by persuasive arguments
and, as a result,
destabilize their faith, so to speak.
So, what were some
of the persuasive arguments?
Well, our text for today
talks about them in verse 8.
He says:
“Look out that no one takes you captive
“by means of the philosophy
and empty deception
“according to human tradition,
“according to the elementary things
of the world
and not according to Christ.”
So, what were the philosophies
and empty deception?
Well, in Paul’s time,
it included the Greek philosophies of Plato,
and that could affect
the spirituality of individuals
in the congregation.
Also, that term
“philosophy” was expanded;
it referred to more
than just the Greek philosophers;
it also had reference
to many, many groups,
many schools of thought
—even religious thoughts.
And Paul didn’t want them to become
—their faith to become destabilized
because of following
those improper thoughts.
And notice,
he said in verse 8,
so that you’re not made captive.
He didn’t want them
to be captive to such thinking.
But is there something else
besides the philosophies?
Well, verse 8 says also
“elementary things of the world.”
Now what is that?
In answering that question,
The Watchtower
of August 15, 2008,
page 28,
referred to 1 John 2:15, 16.
So let’s go there.
What’s included
in “the elementary things of the world”?
First John 2:15, 16,
it says:
“Do not love either the world
or the things in the world.
“If anyone loves the world,
the love of the Father is not in him;
“because everything in the world
“—the desire of the flesh
and the desire of the eyes
“and the showy display
of one’s means of life—
does not originate with the Father,
but originates with the world.”
So The Watchtower introduces this
as not just religious thinking
that could destabilize your faith;
it could be desires of the flesh.
The immoral thinking of the world
could affect us spiritually.
Over the years,
over the thousands of years,
Satan really has carefully crafted
the environment around us
as a trap,
and so he uses that effectively.
In fact, he maneuvers circumstances
around each one of us
in order to try to work
on our personal inclinations.
So that’s why the second sentence
of our Watchtower summary says this:
“We can avert disaster
“if we quickly identify tendencies
that could lead us into temptation.”
Disaster
—well, what’s that referring to?
Well, remember,
Paul said in the scripture up there,
Colossians 2:8,
don’t be captive.
Captive.
That’s what Satan wants to do.
He wants to capture us.
We’ve heard of the poster
“Wanted Dead or Alive.”
He doesn’t want us dead;
he wants us alive.
Because why?
Well,
it’s an interesting verse in 2 Timothy;
it tells us why the Devil
would prefer to have us alive.
Second Timothy 2:26:
“And they may come to their senses
and escape from the snare of the Devil,
seeing that they have been caught alive
by him to do his will.”
If you’re dead,
you can’t do Satan’s will.
So he wants to trap us alive
—or make us captive—
alive to do his will.
So, what do we need to do to keep
from being trapped by Satan? is the question.
Well, we read that one sentence
in our comments
to quickly identify tendencies.
OK.
Now, where do the tendencies start?
This is an August 1, 1996, Watchtower,
page 12, paragraph 12,
and here’s what it says:
“Unholy actions are not just spontaneous
“or without prior basis.
“They are the result of defiling thoughts
that have been lurking in the heart.”
That’s what happened to Judas Iscariot.
Here was an individual that had
a very deep spiritual taproot,
so to speak.
And apparently,
Jesus didn’t know
that Judas would be
the one betraying Him
when he was appointed
as an apostle.
Sometime in 32 C.E.,
Jesus told his apostles:
“One of you is a slanderer.”
Apparently, by that time,
he had identified Judas as that one.
Possibly by his actions,
a perfect man, Jesus,
could identify it early.
And the Scriptures say
as a result of Judas
acting on his thoughts,
Satan entered into Judas.
In other words,
now he was going
to do the will of Satan.
But before that all happened,
there had to have been some wrong thinking
lurking in the heart of Judas.
What could it have been?
Well, it could have involved malice,
maybe greed, pride,
hypocrisy, scheming.
Somewhere in there was
something that wasn’t right;
it was going to offend Jehovah God.
And he didn’t rip it out;
he didn’t take care of it,
and look what happened to Judas.
So, what about us?
What’s lurking in our heart?
Now we all may be individuals
with this deep spiritual taproot.
We’ve been in the truth many years;
we’ve been at Bethel many years.
Or we may be young people,
and we’re serving Jehovah well right now,
but all of us
have these improper thoughts
that we have to deal with.
Perhaps it could be something like this:
Maybe there is some scheming
going on in our heart and mind,
maybe scheming of where we’re going
to get the next drink of alcohol.
Maybe it’s an evil thought against someone
that’s lurking in our heart.
Maybe it is a plan of action
of how we can see pornography
or perhaps an unhealthy attraction
to someone of the opposite sex.
If that’s the case,
what can we do?
Remember Isaiah 30:21.
It says to hear Jehovah’s voice
“behind you saying, ‘This is the way.’”
Don’t give in to Satan’s way,
but listen to Jehovah God.
Jehovah God has given us so many things
that can help us to address
the wrong thinking
that’s lurking in our hearts.
In fact, he gives us guidance
in his Word, the Bible.
Just think of all the scriptures
that we can use,
no matter what tendency we may have,
that can address those tendencies.
He gives us the holy spirit.
Jesus conveys the voice of Jehovah God.
He does so by means of the congregation
through the direction
of “the faithful and discreet slave.”
So if we are unable
to remove an improper tendency,
then get help
before Satan captures us to do his will.