“He was at ease
“with sophisticated intellectuals
“and with humble tentmakers.
“He was persuasive to Roman dignitaries
“and to Phrygian peasants.
“His writings were motivating
to liberal Greeks
and to conservative Jews.”
That’s how the December 1, 2005,
issue of The Watchtower
described the inspired writer
of today’s text.
Certainly,
the apostle Paul was a master
of becoming
“all things to people of all sorts.”
Please open your Bibles to Acts chapter 20.
We’re going to read verse 21.
With these words,
Paul describes his commission as an apostle.
As we read Acts 20:21,
notice the broad scope of his territory
and also the purpose of his ministry.
He said:
“But I thoroughly bore witness
“both to Jews and to Greeks
“about repentance toward God
and faith in our Lord Jesus.”
Like the apostle Paul,
we too have a commission
to preach to people of all sorts.
But is it too much to ask us
to imitate Paul’s example?
Think about it.
Paul had the advantage
of being well-educated.
He was part of the privileged class
of Roman citizens.
He held a powerful position as a Pharisee.
None of us have those qualifications.
But are these the things that qualified Paul
as a minister of the good news?
It’s true,
his being a distinguished lawyer
no doubt helped him to defend
and legally establish the good news.
But on the other hand,
Paul’s background created obstacles
that he had to overcome.
Only then could he preach
to people of all sorts.
Paul was a Jewish Pharisee
and that name Pharisee
means “Separated Ones.”
This may refer to the fact
that the Pharisees
maintained a very strict separation
from Gentiles.
Then Jehovah picked Paul to be an apostle.
And to whom?
To the Gentiles.
No doubt,
Paul had to do a lot of soul-searching
to overcome his former prejudices
in order to carry out
his commission to preach.
Paul’s need to make major changes
reminds me of a man
in North Carolina some years ago.
He served as the minister
of a large Methodist church
for over 25 years;
then he came into the truth.
This man had preached hundreds,
if not thousands, of sermons.
With such a background,
you would think
that public speaking
would be easy for him.
And yet, he said
one of the hardest things he ever had to do
was to stand up in front
of the congregation in the Kingdom Hall
and deliver a five-minute Bible reading.
No doubt,
the apostle Paul’s example
was a source of encouragement
to this humble brother.
Truly,
the Kingdom good news
is a message for all peoples.
But when it comes
to preaching the good news,
unlike many baseball caps,
one size does not fit all.
Like Paul, to be effective,
we have to be adaptable in the way
that we present the good news.
So let’s consider three key qualities
that helped to make Paul
an effective minister.
Paul was attentive,
he was flexible,
and he was resourceful.
Consider how he was attentive.
Paul understood the background
and the beliefs of his audience.
Consider what happened when he was asked
to appear before King Agrippa II.
Please open your Bibles to Acts chapter 26.
We’re going to read verses 2 and 3,
and we notice from these verses
that Paul first commended Agrippa
on his being well-versed
in the background
of the people he was ruling.
Acts 26:2,3,
it says:
“Concerning all the things
of which I am accused
“by the Jews, King Agrippa,
“I consider myself happy
that it is before you
“I am to make my defense this day,
“especially because you are
an expert on all the customs
“as well as the controversies
among the Jews.
Therefore,
I beg you to hear me patiently.”
Paul was not trying to flatter the king.
He was simply using
his knowledge of his audience
to establish a common ground
on which he could begin to preach.
Paul was flexible.
Consider what happened
when he and Barnabas
entered the city of Lystra to preach.
The account is recorded
in Acts chapter 14.
The audience that they met there in Lystra
was totally different
from that of King Agrippa
and the one hundred dignitaries
who may have been in the group with him.
This crowd in Lystra
was made up of a less educated
and more superstitious part
of the population.
When they healed a man
who had been lame from birth,
the crowd cried out:
“The gods have become
like humans and have come down to us!”
They even wanted to offer up
sacrifices to Paul and Barnabas.
Obviously,
Paul could not reason with those people
on the basis of their superstitions.
Rather,
he told the crowd that he and Barnabas
were imperfect humans just like them.
And then he turned
their attention away from puny humans
and directed it
to the grand creation and our living God,
the one “who made the heaven and the earth
and the sea and all the things in them.”
And that was enough to restrain the crowd
from offering those sacrifices.
A third quality of Paul
was that he was resourceful.
If Paul had had the Ministry School book
back there in the first century,
we would probably say
that he did well on point number 46,
“Illustrations From Familiar Situations.”
Paul used common,
easily understood illustrations
to clarify complex spiritual matters.
For example,
the Romans were familiar with slavery.
In fact,
many recipients of his letter to the Romans
may have themselves been slaves.
So Paul used slavery to illustrate
the great change in ownership
that had taken place
when these individuals became Christians.
Romans 6:18 says:
“Yes, since you were set free from sin,
you became slaves to righteousness.”
Our brothers around the world
are showing themselves
to be attentive, flexible,
and resourceful as they preach
to people of every background imaginable.
For example,
many people in the Far East are concerned
about things that affect them personally,
such as health,
child training, and education.
So our brothers there
effectively use those subjects
to begin conversations.
However,
that may not work as well
in certain cities
in the United States
where people may be
more concerned with corruption,
traffic congestion, and crime.
But no matter what topic
we use to introduce the truth,
to be effective Bible teachers,
it is important for us
to remain positive and encouraging
and to stress the practical value
of applying Bible principles.
With the help of God’s holy spirit,
the apostle Paul was able to overcome
personal obstacles and prejudices
to become
an outstanding minister of the good news.
It’s true,
we may not meet a Roman dignitary
or a Phrygian peasant
as we go about our territory,
but with Jehovah’s help,
we can imitate Paul’s example
of an effective minister
by being attentive,
flexible, and resourceful.
Why do we make this effort?
We do it because we want
to “become all things to people of all sorts,
so that [we]
might by all possible means save some.”