Now, when you think of it,
the apostle Paul was a very humble man.
He was flexible.
He says: “To the Jews I became as a Jew,”
and “to those under law
I became as under law.”
But there were limits to Paul’s flexibility,
and we’re going to talk
about that in just a few moments.
First of all, though,
when Paul came down to Jerusalem,
the elders explained that thousands of Jews
had become believers
and they were all zealous for the Law.
Now, they’d heard a rumor about Paul.
They’d heard the rumor
that Paul was telling the Jews
not to circumcise their children,
and the elders were worried about it.
They had a plan.
We read about that plan in Acts chapter 21,
if you would like to turn there,
Acts 21:23, 24.
Here’s their plan:
“So do what we tell you:
“We have four men
who have put themselves under a vow.
“Take these men with you
“and cleanse yourself ceremonially
together with them
“and take care of their expenses,
“so that they may have
their heads shaved.
“Then everyone will know
that there is nothing
“to the rumors
they were told about you,
“but that you are walking orderly
and you are also keeping the Law.”
Now, it says they have heard
a rumor about you,
that you were telling Jews
not to circumcise their children.
Paul was probably not telling Jews
As has already been mentioned,
Paul took Timothy and circumcised him
so as not to stumble the Jews.
Paul realized that there was nothing wrong
with circumcision per se.
It was when people
proclaimed that circumcision
was necessary in order to gain salvation
that the problem arose.
So this was a rumor.
But some brothers and sisters
were willing to believe a rumor
about a faithful brother
rather than to trust Paul.
Just as today, some believe
everything they read in the newspaper
and they don’t even ask any questions.
So now here’s the question:
What were they going to do about it?
The elders had a suggestion.
They said: “We have four men
who have put themselves under a vow.”
And they wanted Paul
to take these men to the temple
and pay their expenses.
Paul agreed.
Now, that took humility.
We all know how strongly Paul felt
about keeping the Law,
and yet Paul was willing
to see the bigger picture.
He had strong feelings,
but at the same time,
these Jews were probably new in the truth,
and Paul wanted to go as far as he could go
so as not to stumble those new in the truth.
Now the vow.
What was the vow?
Most scholars agree that the vow
was probably a Nazarite vow.
And if it was,
that was going to be tricky for Paul.
Because, you see, Nazarites
were required to offer a sin offering
when their vow came to a completion.
Now, Paul would never have agreed to that.
It would have showed—
It would have shown disrespect
for the sacrifice of Christ.
So Paul and those four men
were going to have to be very careful
about how far they would go
in the completion of this vow.
And we can be sure
that they would never do anything
that would go against their conscience.
Now, we can see that on this occasion
Paul went a long way
so as not to stumble the Jews.
But on another occasion,
he refused to cater to the Jews.
We read about that in Galatians chapter 2.
Let’s turn there.
Galatians chapter 2,
and we’ll read verses 11-14.
Galatians 2:11-14:
“However, when Cephas came to Antioch,
“I resisted him face-to-face,
“because he was clearly in the wrong.
“For before certain men from James arrived,
“he used to eat with people of the nations;
“but when they arrived, he stopped doing this
and separated himself,
“fearing those of the circumcised class.
“The rest of the Jews also joined him
“in putting on this pretense,
“so that even Barnabas
was led along with them in their pretense.
“But when I saw
that they were not walking in step
“with the truth of the good news,
“I said to Cephas before them all:
“‘If you, though you are a Jew,
live as the nations do and not as Jews do,
how can you compel people of the nations
to live according to Jewish practice?’”
So we see what was happening here.
Up till the time when men from James
came down to Antioch,
Peter and Barnabas
and the other Jewish Christians
were happily eating with the Gentiles.
But now men from James came down,
and suddenly Peter
starts to separate himself from the Gentiles.
And, following his lead,
other Jewish Christians
begin doing the same thing.
Now, who was probably new in the truth?
In this case,
it was probably the Gentile Christians.
In Acts 21, it was probably
the Jews who were newer in the truth
and Paul didn’t want to stumble the Jews.
But at this point, Paul could not be
all things to all people.
He couldn’t please the Jews;
he couldn’t please the men from James
and also please the Gentiles.
He was either going to have to stumble
—if you will—
the men from James,
or he was going
to have to stumble the Gentiles.
He had to make a choice.
And so Paul made his choice.
And what did he do about it?
He followed the advice
that he recorded
in this same book of Galatians.
Can you think of what that was?
Galatians chapter 6
—what is it saying?
“If a man takes a false step
before he is aware of it.”
What did Paul say about Peter?
He was not walking in step
with the good news.
So Peter was taking a false step.
“You who have spiritual qualifications,”
that would be Paul,
“try to readjust such a man
in a spirit of mildness.”
And that’s what the apostle Paul did.
Now, we love to pick on Peter.
But let’s give the poor man a break.
Let’s give him credit
for what he was doing right.
This was Antioch.
Now, what do we know about Antioch?
It was in Antioch when the whole matter
of keeping the Law blew up
in the first place.
And who was it
who were stirring things up in Antioch?
It was men from Jerusalem
—men from James.
Now, up until this point
—Peter and Barnabas and the others—
they’re happily eating with the Gentiles
until men from Jerusalem come down
and start stirring up trouble.
You kind of think
that if they’d stayed home once in a while
there would have been a lot less trouble
in the Christian congregation.
So Peter was doing the right thing
up until the men from James came down.
Now, Peter knew
how critical men from James could be
—or men from Jerusalem could be.
You might say,
he’d seen that movie before
in 36 C.E.,
just after the conversion of Cornelius.
Notice a detail at Acts 11:2, 3,
and this might help us
to at least understand Peter’s concern,
and perhaps misguided effort,
not to stumble the men from James.
Acts 11:2, 3:
“So when Peter came up to Jerusalem,”
this is in 33 C.E.,
“the supporters of circumcision
began to criticize him, saying:
“‘You went into the house of men
who were not circumcised
and ate with them.’”
Well, Peter knew how sensitive Jews were
about eating with the Gentiles,
but he was moved by the fear of man.
And the apostle Paul did right
to reprove him because, after all,
he was going to have to make a choice:
You stumble the Jews
or you stumble the Gentiles.
The lesson to take away:
There are times
when you can’t please everyone.
There are times when you
cannot be all things to all people.
Our young people have to realize that.
You have to take a stand for what is right
and let the chips fall where they may.
Now, you have to appreciate the wisdom
that Jesus used in selecting Paul
as an apostle to the nations.
A note to the elders:
Paul was flexible.
He didn’t insist on his own ideas
even when he felt strongly about a matter,
and he didn’t create unnecessary issues.
Paul looked at the big picture.
What a marvelous example for us.
And we can say that humble Paul
was the right man for the job.