‎We warmly welcome all of you
‎to this month’s broadcast.
‎Here is just a taste
‎of what we can look forward to on the program.
‎A life spent in the full-time ministry
‎is both exciting and challenging.
‎We’ll meet a brother and his wife
‎who have spent decades
in various forms of this service.
‎What lessons can we learn from their experiences?
‎Then we’ll hear the story of a woman
‎who struggled for years
with severe drug addiction.
‎What would help her eventually break free?
‎And our new music video
‎will help us feel the brotherly love we enjoy
‎as a part of Jehovah’s organization.
‎There’s certainly plenty to enjoy
‎on this August 2018 edition
‎of JW Broadcasting.
‎The theme for this month’s program is
‎“Appreciating Our ‘Gifts in Men.’”
‎Who of us does not enjoy being given
‎a fine, well-chosen gift?
‎For example, you brothers,
‎do you not take pleasure in receiving
‎a colorful but tasteful,
‎100 percent silk tie?
‎Or, you sisters,
do you not delight in being given
‎an exquisite, charming silk scarf?
‎But what if you took that silk tie
‎or silk scarf
‎and used it to polish your shoes?
‎How do you think
the giver of your gift would feel
‎if he saw you using his gift in that way?
‎Obviously, it would be misuse
‎and disrespect for the gift
and would insult the giver.
‎What is the point of our illustration?
‎Well, Jehovah and Jesus have given us
‎a fine, well-chosen gift
in the form of the elders.
‎But as we will discuss,
‎all of us must make sure
‎that we always show appreciation and respect
‎for this divine provision.
‎Please turn to Ephesians 4:8,
‎and let’s read about this gift
‎that Jehovah and Jesus have given us.
‎It reads:
‎“For it says:
‎“‘When he ascended on high
‎“‘he carried away captives;
‎he gave gifts in men.’”
‎You notice, by means
of Jesus’ perfect integrity,
‎Jesus conquered Satan and his world.
‎As a world conqueror,
‎figuratively He has plundered captives
‎and has given them
as gifts to the congregations.
‎How useful are these “gifts in men”?
‎Well, please look
at verses 11 and 12 for the answer:
‎“And he gave some as apostles,
‎“some as prophets,
‎“some as evangelizers,
‎“some as shepherds and teachers,
‎“with a view
to the readjustment of the holy ones,
‎“for ministerial work,
‎to build up the body of the Christ.”
‎Notice, they would be “evangelizers”
‎—taking the lead
‎in the all-important preaching
and disciple-making work.
‎They do not simply say to the publishers,
‎“Go in the preaching work.”
‎They say: “Come.
Come with us.
‎Let’s work together
in this never-to-be-repeated work.”
‎They’re also “shepherds”
‎—protecting the flock from Satan
‎the “murderer,”
“serpent,” “dragon,” and “lion.”
‎Additionally, they are “teachers”
‎—feeding the flock
with nourishing spiritual food.
‎But now we ask,
‎How does Jehovah tell us
‎that we should feel
about these hardworking “gifts in men”?
‎Let’s go to 1 Thessalonians chapter 5,
‎and let’s get the answer.
‎At 1 Thessalonians chapter 5,
‎beginning in verse number 12,
‎notice what Jehovah says:
‎“Now we request you, brothers,
‎“to show respect
‎“for those who are working hard among you
‎“and presiding over you in the Lord
‎“and admonishing you;
‎“and to give them extraordinary consideration
‎“in love because of their work.
‎Be peaceable with one another.”
‎Notice, we’re told to “show respect”
‎for these dear brothers.
‎But now, let’s move to a vital question,
‎How can we show, demonstrate,
‎that we do deeply respect
‎and appreciate these dear brothers?
‎The first way:
‎by wholeheartedly cooperating with them.
‎Please turn to Hebrews 13:17,
‎and this scripture describes how deep
‎our cooperation should be, verse 17:
‎“Be obedient
‎“to those who are taking the lead among you
‎“and be submissive,
‎“for they are keeping watch over you
‎“as those who will render an account,
‎“so that they may do this
with joy and not with sighing,
‎for this would be damaging to you.”
‎Notice, we are told to “be obedient.”
‎Clearly, this means
that we’re supposed to comply with,
‎or obey, what they tell us.
‎Of course, that would be with the proviso:
‎unless they tell us to do
something that is unscriptural.
‎And, of course, that would be extremely rare.
‎We’re also told to “be submissive.”
‎This includes the attitude
‎with which we’re to be obedient
‎—doing so with a yielding, positive attitude.
‎Would it be possible to be obedient
‎but not submissive?
‎Well, what if we said:
‎“OK. I’ll do what the elders suggest.
‎I don’t want to do it, but I’ll do it.”
‎We would be obedient but not submissive.
‎However, Jehovah tells us
‎to display both of these qualities.
‎We should be obedient and submissive
‎even if what the elders are asking us to do
‎is not the best,
most efficient way to do something.
‎Permit me to illustrate this point.
‎Admittedly, the illustration
is somewhat exaggerated,
‎but hopefully it will make the point.
‎Please imagine that the elders decide
‎that the outside of the Kingdom Hall
‎needs to be painted
and that all the publishers
‎will be given
a small two-inch (5 cm) paintbrush
‎with which to paint.
‎Now, what could happen?
‎The publishers could get all upset
‎concerning this request of the elders,
‎saying, “It is ridiculous
that the elders want us
‎to paint
with a small two-inch (5 cm) paintbrush!”
‎Consequently, some could start campaigning
‎for the right for everyone
to use a six-inch (15 cm) paintbrush.
‎Others might campaign for using paint rollers
‎to roll the paint on the Kingdom Hall.
‎Still others
might start trying to build support
‎for renting and using a paint sprayer
‎to spray the paint on the Kingdom Hall.
‎In another camp,
ones might champion the idea
‎of hiring out to a contractor
‎the painting of the Kingdom Hall,
‎while another group is promoting the idea
‎that the Kingdom Hall
doesn’t even need to be painted.
‎Now, what would be the outcome?
‎The congregation would be divided,
‎the Kingdom Hall would never get painted,
‎publishers could end up
stumbled right out of the truth,
‎the elders would be very discouraged,
‎Jehovah would be sad,
‎and Satan would be made very happy.
‎On the other hand,
‎what if everyone humbly supported
the elders, perhaps thinking:
‎‘There’s no scripture
‎‘that says we can’t paint
with a two-inch (5 cm) paintbrush.
‎‘In fact, Hebrews 13:17 tells us
‎‘to “be obedient”
and “submissive” to the elders.
‎So why don’t we go ahead
and support the elders?’
‎Now what would be the outcome?
‎The Kingdom Hall would get painted,
‎the publishers would get to enjoy
‎a lot of good association
‎because they’d be working together
for a long time,
‎the elders would be very encouraged,
‎Satan would be sad,
‎and Jehovah’s heart would be made glad.
‎Well, what is the point
of this hyperbole illustration?
‎Being obedient and submissive
to those taking the lead
‎is much more important
than how something is done.
‎That is the attitude
‎that Jehovah will richly bless.
‎But, now, a second way we can demonstrate
‎that we deeply appreciate these dear brothers
‎is to pray for them.
‎Please note what the elder Paul urged
‎the brothers to do for him
‎at Romans 15:30.
‎Here Paul said:
‎“Now I urge you, brothers,
‎“through our Lord Jesus Christ
‎“and through the love of the spirit,
‎“that you exert yourselves with me
‎in prayers to God for me.”
‎Paul recognized
‎the power that he would derive
‎as a result of others praying for him,
‎and your local elders feel the same way.
‎But the question is,
‎In your personal, private prayers,
‎do you regularly thank Jehovah
‎for your “gifts in men” and entreat Jehovah
‎to richly supply them
with his powerful holy spirit?
‎Our answer to that question can reveal much
‎about our appreciation
for these hardworking elders.
‎Now let’s move to a third way
‎that we can demonstrate deep appreciation:
‎We can do so by commending the elders.
‎Here is a soul-searching question:
‎Do you periodically go up
‎to various elders and say something like,
‎“Brother Elder,
‎“we just want
to thank you for your hard work.
‎Please be assured that we appreciate it”?
‎However, it seems
‎that some publishers
never ever commend the elders
‎or express appreciation.
‎Might this not indicate
that we are taking them
‎and their hard work for granted?
‎Of course, they will not quit
if you do not give them commendation;
‎they primarily do their work for Jehovah.
‎But if you do express appreciation,
‎believe me,
it will be most encouraging to them.
‎And even though
it may really surprise the elder
‎the very first time you do this,
‎please do not hold back
‎this “good from those to whom it is owing.”
‎Appropriately,
‎Jehovah tells us at Proverbs 3:27:
‎“Do not withhold good
from those to whom you should give it
‎if it is within your power to help.”
‎And one thing
that will move us to be more aware
‎of commending the elders is to remember
all the good work they are doing.
‎Many elders are family men
‎who must work secularly
to provide for their families.
‎If he has children,
‎these young ones need time
and attention from their father.
‎He may need to help
them with their schoolwork
‎as well as schedule time for them
‎to enjoy wholesome recreation.
‎Most important, he cares
for the spiritual needs of his family
‎—regularly conducting family worship,
‎working with them in the ministry,
‎and taking them to meetings.
‎But in addition
to these numerous responsibilities
‎common to many of us,
‎they have voluminous additional responsibilities
‎as elders.
‎And much of the elders’ hard work
‎in our behalf
is not seen by the congregation.
‎For example, you may see
‎an elder giving a part on the meeting.
‎What you didn’t see
‎are the hours he spent preparing that part.
‎How long does it take you
‎to prepare a student assignment
‎on the midweek meeting?
‎Some elders have a part every week,
‎sometimes more than one.
‎While gaining experience
in speaking is certainly helpful,
‎the fact remains
‎that good talks require hard work.
‎But that is not all that the elders do.
‎They have shepherding calls to make
‎and judicial cases to handle.
‎Some elders are also busy
helping to build Kingdom Halls
‎and branch facilities,
‎serving on Hospital Liaison Committees,
‎volunteering at assemblies and conventions
‎—and elders do many other things
‎that are too numerous to recount.
‎What we see
is often only the tip of the iceberg
‎—90 percent of an iceberg
‎is unseen underwater.
‎At 2 Timothy 4:6,
‎the apostle Paul referred to himself
‎as “being poured out like a drink offering.”
‎A drink offering
‎was poured on the altar
and went up in smoke.
‎That well describes how the elders likewise
‎expend themselves.
‎Remembering all of this should move us
‎to regularly offer sincere commendation
‎to our hardworking elders.
‎Now we have discussed ways
‎that we can demonstrate
‎that we deeply appreciate our “gifts in men.”
‎We should
(1) wholeheartedly cooperate with them,
‎(2) pray for them,
‎and (3) commend them.
‎Thereby we will prove
‎that we are not even slightly like
‎an unappreciative recipient
of a silk tie or a silk scarf,
‎who uses that gift to polish his shoes.
‎To the contrary,
‎we will prove to Jehovah and Jesus
‎that we love, respect,
‎and appreciate
‎the divine gifts
—our “gifts in men”—
‎that they have so generously given to us!
‎But, now, what effect
can these “gifts in men”
‎have on individuals
who have strayed from Jehovah
‎and his organization?
‎What actions show
that they are loving shepherds
‎who want to assist
these ones to return to Jehovah
‎despite serious struggles or even addictions?
‎Let’s look for those answers
in the following story.
‎‘Turn your life around,
‎‘so that seasons of refreshing
‎may come from Jehovah himself.’
‎Those words changed my life,
‎and they saved the life of my little girl.
‎I was raised in a Witness family.
‎But I chose
‎a dark underworld
‎of practically everything
that Jehovah hates.
‎After about 15 years,
‎although financially secure,
‎I was confronted with the failure
that my life had become.
‎I was trying to raise a child
while addicted to drugs.
‎I just didn’t want
to live like that anymore,
‎and I wanted to be a good mother.
‎So for the first time in years,
‎I prayed to Jehovah.
‎The knock came on my door
the very next day.
‎I began studying with a vengeance.
‎I had 15 years to catch up on.
‎I had a lot of help.
‎I progressively changed my lifestyle,
‎I changed my associates,
‎and I conquered my addiction.
‎I slowly began to overcome
‎feelings of worthlessness.
‎So none of these changes were easy to make,
‎but it made me feel
‎clean and happy
‎knowing that Jehovah was pleased.
‎My burning desire at that point
really was to begin sharing
‎with other people what I was learning,
‎but I didn’t qualify
to engage in the public ministry
‎because I was still living
with my boyfriend at the time.
‎And he didn’t understand
some of the changes I was making.
‎I was determined
‎to turn my life around
and overcome this last hurdle
‎that was preventing me
from serving Jehovah fully.
‎Two weeks later,
‎I found out I was pregnant.
‎I was devastated.
‎I didn’t know what all those people
who had helped me would think
‎and how Jehovah
felt about what was happening.
‎I was so ashamed.
‎I actually blamed Jehovah
for letting it happen.
‎I was so confused.
‎My first inclination
‎was just to get an abortion.
‎But deep down,
I knew that was wrong.
‎I thought, ‘Now everyone will know
‎‘that I’m still the worthless person
‎that I always knew I was.’
‎At that point,
I just felt like giving up.
‎I told my aunt and uncle,
‎who are Jehovah’s Witnesses,
about my situation.
‎They didn’t judge me at all,
‎but they did offer a curious suggestion:
‎They invited me up to Bethel for a visit.
‎They introduced me to an elder
who was very kind,
‎and I talked to him
about my situation.
‎I was shocked
‎by how loving he was.
‎So he shared with me Acts 3:19.
‎“Repent, therefore, and turn around
‎“so as to get your sins blotted out,
‎“that seasons of refreshing
‎may come from the person of Jehovah.”
‎Well, he told me
‎I had already sinned,
but why should I sin a second time?
‎Why should this innocent child pay
‎for what I had done wrong?
‎He suggested I teach my baby
‎about Jehovah and raise the child up
‎to know Him and have a friendship with Him.
‎I loved that he took something that was
‎sad and depressing for me
‎and turned it into something beautiful.
‎Well, I had a new plan now.
‎I was really determined
to do everything I had to do
‎to turn my life around
in order to please Jehovah.
‎So eventually I qualified to become
an unbaptized publisher,
‎and later I was baptized in 2010.
‎I gave birth to a healthy baby girl.
‎I already dedicated my life to Jehovah.
‎So two of my goals
are to get baptized and pioneer.
‎I’m as determined as ever
to raise Jolie up to love Jehovah
‎and to avoid the traps
that almost cost us our lives.
‎Describing our elders,
‎Isaiah 32:2 reads:
‎“And each one will be like
a hiding place from the wind,
‎“a place of concealment from the rainstorm,
‎“like streams of water in a waterless land,
‎“like the shadow of a massive crag
‎in a parched land.”
‎Did you note two key ways
our “gifts in men” did that?
‎One, the elder she met at Bethel
‎was kind and approachable.
‎He made her feel
comfortable to express herself.
‎Two, he lovingly used the Bible
‎to help her make a wise decision
and avoid further calamity.
‎This is an excellent example
‎of how elders can help ones
who are struggling spiritually.
‎But in what other ways
can elders be an example?
‎In their zeal for the ministry.
‎But what if weather conditions
in our territory make this difficult?
‎When the elders take the lead,
‎the rest of the congregation
responds in the same way.
‎The example of those preaching
in the Faroe Islands
‎will offer some encouraging tips.
‎The Faroe Islands are
also called the Land of Maybe.
‎The weather is very diverse
and can rapidly change.
‎So when you begin in the ministry,
the weather can be sunny.
‎And then ten minutes later,
you find yourself
‎in a massive rain shower
and everything gets wet.
‎Wind is another challenge.
‎We have some severe winter storms.
‎So you have to be careful
that your service partner or the car door
‎doesn’t blow away
while you’re getting out of the car.
‎We make sure to wear clothes
appropriate for the weather.
‎And also to stay updated
on the weather situation
‎and see where in our territory
the weather is most suitable, and then adapt.
‎If the weather is nice,
then we try to go from house to house.
‎And if the weather is bad,
‎then you can go on calls
where you can go inside,
‎meaning where they will invite you in
‎or where the entrance is covered.
‎And you can plan your ministry
so that if the weather gets bad,
‎you can make visits that you know
will be at home that time of day.
‎When the weather is poor,
it’s good to adjust.
‎Maybe you can do
some telephone witnessing or letter writing.
‎At a meeting for pioneers,
‎an elder reminded us
that when the weather is bad,
‎try not to think:
‘The weather is bad again,’
‎but instead,
‘Yay! Now people are actually at home.’
‎It is a good idea to have a plan
for whom you’d like to visit
‎and what you’d like
to talk to them about
‎because then when it rains
or the weather isn’t ideal,
‎you focus on your plan
‎instead of thinking
that now I have been out preaching
‎for five hours in stormy weather.
‎I think Ecclesiastes 11:4
applies quite well to our territory:
‎“The one who watches the wind
will not sow seed,
‎and the one who looks at the clouds
will not reap.”
‎If we have to wait
for the perfect weather conditions to preach,
‎then we wouldn’t be out that often.
‎Something else
that helps us to endure bad weather
‎is to think of the first publishers
in the Faroe Islands.
‎They fought with seasickness, bad weather,
‎and they had to hike over the mountains
to visit remote settlements.
‎They overcame these obstacles,
‎and it motivates me to overcome
the challenges I am facing today.
‎I remember when we came
to the Faroe Islands,
‎I looked out the window
and thought,‘Is it even possible
‎to go out in the ministry
in this kind of weather?’
‎And then we arrived
at the meeting for field service,
‎and the friends
with children and strollers were there
‎and were positive
and ready for field service.
‎It made me think
that if they can do it, then I can too.
‎So we are a team of publishers,
and we have the weather as our challenge.
‎And especially when the weather is bad,
we encourage one another.
‎We really like the song
“The Life of a Pioneer.”
‎It’s an amazing song.
‎It says: “In the work we endure,
whether sunshine or rain.”
‎It’s because we love Jehovah.
‎We really want people
to get to know Jehovah.
‎They need to know the truth.
‎When Jesus said that we should preach,
‎I think that he
also would have put on a raincoat
‎and gone out to preach the good news.
‎We experience how Jehovah blesses
our efforts when we go in the ministry.
‎And you especially feel it
when you persist in your efforts
‎to preach when the weather isn’t good.
‎It may be that one day
you have a really nice conversation
‎with a person about the Bible.
‎I also feel it gives me great joy.
‎Paul said that the one who “sows bountifully
will also reap bountifully.”
‎So if you want to sow bountifully
in the Faroe Islands,
‎you need to preach
also when the weather is bad.
‎And we feel
that we have reaped bountifully
‎with nice return visits and Bible studies.
‎I feel it’s worth all the effort
‎because we see that people in the territory
‎really appreciate what they are learning.
‎All that we do in our ministry
‎is motivated by love for Jehovah
‎and the people in the territory,
and it won’t be changed by bad weather.
‎It’s an opportunity to show
that our worship is wholehearted.
‎You don’t just go
in the ministry when everything is good
‎and the sun is shining.
‎I think we have become more enduring
‎and flexible in our ministry.
‎We saw that the publishers
were fully supporting
‎the spirit that the elders showed
‎in sharing the good news
‎despite inclement weather.
‎Around the world,
‎many of our brothers face severe opposition
‎because of remaining loyal to Jehovah
‎and maintaining their Christian neutrality.
‎Let’s travel to Spain
‎and hear how some of our brothers
‎have dealt with these challenges firsthand.
‎Spain is a land of castles.
‎From the mountains of central Spain
‎to the Mediterranean coast,
castles dominate the landscape.
‎But there is one castle
—the Castle of Santa Catalina—
‎that played a unique part in the history
of Jehovah’s Witnesses in Spain.
‎This castle that guards the entrance
‎to the harbor of Cádiz,
in southern Spain,
‎became a military prison
over two centuries ago.
‎And this fortress
‎tested the faith
of around 300 Spanish Witnesses.
‎The battle began
in the 1960’s when Spain was ruled
‎by General Franco, a military dictator.
‎Franco wanted all Spanish men
to serve the fatherland,
‎and this meant military service.
‎But in Spain, there were Jehovah’s Witnesses
‎whose conscience said no.
‎So this castle became a battleground
‎where Franco’s military regime fought
‎to stamp out the Christian consciences
of those young Witnesses.
‎But times have changed in Spain.
‎The city of Cádiz has organized an exhibition
‎to salute the sacrifice made
by those valiant Witnesses.
‎Over 40 years after their release,
‎some of those conscientious objectors
have returned to Cádiz
‎to attend this exhibition.
‎At the inauguration,
‎the mayor described them
as citizens who spoke up
‎and who presented arguments
against the injustice
‎—arguments based on peace, freedom,
‎and, above all, their conscience.
‎Those who spent years
of their lives behind bars
‎have vivid memories
‎of the times
when this castle was their prison.
‎I think one of the greatest challenges
‎was never knowing
‎if we would be granted our freedom.
‎Our first sentence
‎was for three years.
‎And since we still refused
to enlist in the military,
‎we were then sentenced again
for another lengthy period.
‎So it seemed as if we had a life sentence.
‎We organized daily activities
‎to keep us busy.
‎Mornings, we worked at our trades
‎to earn a little money.
‎Afternoons, we set aside
for spiritual activities.
‎Our preaching
was done mainly by writing letters.
‎And in this way,
some of us could even pioneer.
‎A few people did reply to our letters,
‎and we were thrilled to hear
that some of them accepted the truth.
‎Of course,
we also preached to other prisoners,
‎and a few of them
became baptized Witnesses.
‎We also studied the Bible thoroughly,
‎both individually and as a group,
‎which proved vital
in building us up spiritually.
‎At first,
we had to study our literature secretly,
‎but later the guards
‎allowed us to have
the Bible and other publications.
‎As our numbers grew,
‎all the Witnesses
were kept together
‎in the same place
—in the same barracks—
‎so we could organize meetings.
‎We even held assemblies,
including the Biblical dramas.
‎And we loved
‎singing Kingdom songs.
‎These songs really
lifted up our spirits.
‎We really felt Jehovah’s loving care
when the brothers came to visit us.
‎We even had a special visit
from Brother Grant Suiter
‎of the Governing Body,
‎but there were also other visits
that we really looked forward to.
‎Many of the brothers endured
years of separation from their families
‎and fiancées.
‎This was a real test.
‎But these faithful sisters
‎wholeheartedly supported their neutral stand.
‎Those were years that molded me spiritually.
‎I studied the Bible
as I had never done before.
‎I developed skills
as a public speaker and as an overseer.
‎Above all, it was a time in my life
‎when I learned to rely totally on Jehovah.
‎Thanks to my fervent prayers,
he became my closest friend
‎and he never let me down.
‎That was priceless.
‎The firm stand of those Witnesses
‎gave a powerful testimony
in Cádiz and throughout Spain.
‎The run-down military prison
‎that once tested their faith
‎has been restored.
‎It is now a tourist attraction
‎and a cultural center.
‎But while the castle has changed,
‎the faith of those valiant Witnesses has not.
‎The castle certainly tested them,
‎but they fought a fine fight for the faith.
‎And with Jehovah’s help, they won the battle.
‎Forty years later,
‎their victory is still giving a witness
‎to Jehovah’s name.
‎As we noted earlier,
‎the apostle Paul said
‎that he was “being poured out
like a drink offering.”
‎Similarly, by remaining neutral,
‎these brothers offered up a great sacrifice
‎of praise to Jehovah despite resistance.
‎And as we learned, by loyal endurance,
‎they went on to be “gifts in men”
‎to those in the congregations
and circuits that they later served.
‎Other examples of “gifts in men”
‎are those who serve
as headquarters representatives
‎visiting branch offices
‎and encouraging members
of the Bethel families.
‎Brother Daniel Molchan had the privilege
‎to visit the countries of Haiti
and the Dominican Republic.
‎They have had
some exciting spiritual developments
‎in those lands.
‎On Sunday, February the 26th,
‎I traveled
to Port-au-Prince for the branch visit
‎and was warmly welcomed
by many of the Bethel family of 54 members.
‎The branch office
supervises the preaching work
‎for more than 20,000 publishers.
‎Although Haiti has faced economic challenges
‎and suffered recent natural disasters,
‎our brothers are positive
‎and focus their attention on helping
others to identify our Scriptural hope.
‎The Haitian people show
a keen interest in the Word of God.
‎Our brothers average
more than 42,000 Bible studies each month,
‎and Haiti enjoyed a Memorial attendance
‎of more than 86,000 in 2016.
‎This was four times more than the number
of publishers in the branch territory.
‎The brothers love to use
the videos in the ministry.
‎This is made possible
by the Haiti audio/video team
‎translating the videos
into their native language.
‎While many in Haiti speak French,
‎the common language
of the people in general is Haitian Creole.
‎Creole is said to be
‎an expressive language
that combines French words
‎with the grammar
of West African languages.
‎The number of publishers in Haiti
has quadrupled since the start
‎of Creole translation back in 1987.
‎The complete New World Translation Bible
‎was released in Creole in 2015.
‎We met with the translation team
to commend them for the good work they do.
‎We reminded them of the many positive results
‎in the field ministry that have taken place
‎since translating the Bible
and our literature into Creole.
‎As an example, Mirlène is a vendor
of fruits and vegetables who was asked
‎if she would supply
some of her produce to Bethel.
‎Although she was very impressed
‎the first time
she arrived at the Bethel property,
‎she said she found
the large steel gate to be intimidating.
‎So she prayed to God to protect her
‎while in the yard at Bethel.
‎The brothers dealt kindly
with her when she made
‎her deliveries on Monday each week.
‎One of the brothers from the kitchen
told her that maybe someday
‎she too would become
one of Jehovah’s Witnesses.
‎She accepted an invitation to the Memorial,
‎and despite some personal challenges,
such as not being able to read well,
‎she began to attend
some congregation meetings.
‎Mirlène could see the difference
‎between Jehovah’s loving people
and those in her church.
‎A study was started with her,
‎and she progressed
to the point of baptism in 2009.
‎Since then, she has worked diligently
‎to teach the truth
to her children with good results.
‎Her oldest son graduated
from the School for Kingdom Evangelizers
‎and serves as an elder
and temporary special pioneer.
‎Recently, another of her sons
was appointed a ministerial servant,
‎and the four other children
are unbaptized publishers.
‎Having our literature in Creole
‎and with the help of her children,
she has improved her reading.
‎She now benefits
from reading the Bible in Creole,
‎the language of her heart.
‎Good results are beginning to be seen
‎in the field of American Sign Language,
which is now used in Haiti.
‎There are now 87 deaf publishers
‎in 4 ASL congregations and 8 groups.
‎The congregation here
is singing praises to Jehovah.
‎Even our little sister
is learning to do this.
‎This brother showed us
the effort he puts forth
‎to prepare for a Bible reading.
‎A special program for Haiti was held
‎on Saturday morning
at the open-air Assembly Hall
‎on the branch property.
‎A total of 1,405 were in attendance.
‎We were very encouraged to see
‎the group of our brothers
who benefited from the program
‎in American Sign Language.
‎The program was recorded and presented
at Kingdom Halls throughout the country
‎later that same day and also on Sunday
‎to a combined audience of 34,812.
‎We felt a little sad to leave
the brothers on Sunday morning
‎for a drive of about six hours or so
‎to the Dominican Republic
‎for the second branch visit.
‎En route, we traveled
through some semiarid areas
‎to the border between the two countries.
‎The terrain varied greatly
as we drove through small mountains,
‎rich agricultural regions,
and along the Caribbean Sea.
‎We took the opportunity
to witness to some individuals at the border
‎and at various checkpoints,
leaving literature along the way.
‎Upon entering the city of Santo Domingo,
‎we quickly identified
the large JW.ORG sign at the branch office.
‎We were enthusiastically greeted
‎by many of the 73 Bethel family members.
‎Although the preaching work
is done primarily in Spanish,
‎our brothers are expanding their ministry
‎to reach the language of the hearts
of many peoples and cultures.
‎There are now 5 Haitian Creole
circuits in the branch territory,
‎26 American Sign Language congregations,
‎and other congregations or groups
‎in Russian, Chinese, Italian and French.
‎We joined a group of brothers
and sisters in the field ministry
‎in the Chinatown district of Santo Domingo.
‎Our group gave a witness to both Spanish-
‎and Chinese-speaking people on the streets
‎—most of whom
respectfully listened to our message.
‎A Bethel brother, Evan,
told us of the challenge
‎he faced when learning the truth.
‎I was finishing medical school
‎while serving in the Dominican army.
‎By then I had been serving for six years.
‎At my aunt’s home,
I found the Revelation book.
‎It made such an impact on me,
‎that I stole it and read it all on my own.
‎There’s a vision in chapter 6 of Revelation,
‎where the sixth seal is opened
‎and the skies darken
and the army commanders hide in caves.
‎That vision impressed me so much
‎that I decided to serve Jehovah.
‎That meant that I
would have to leave the army
‎because Witnesses are neutral.
‎I quickly decided to talk
to my immediate commander
‎to ask him
to please discharge me from the army.
‎However, he rejected my request and said:
‎“No, you have served
in the army for six years.
‎You have to stay in the army.”
‎I was not concerned
because I could still appeal
‎to the colonel in charge of personnel.
‎However, my request
for resignation was rejected again.
‎I left and went into the hallway.
‎I prayed to Jehovah:
‎“I want to serve you.
‎“What should I do?
‎Help me find a way out of this!”
‎When I opened my eyes,
another army officer approached
‎and greeted me using my name.
‎I still don’t know who he was.
‎He asked me,
“What do you need?”
‎I explained that I wanted to resign
in order to become a Jehovah’s Witness.
‎He said: “Don’t worry,
give me your papers.
‎I’m the colonel’s assistant.”
‎Within 20 minutes, my discharge papers
were ready and approved.
‎In a short period of time,
I became a publisher
‎and I got baptized
as one of Jehovah’s Witnesses.
‎At this time,
I have been serving happily in Bethel
‎for over 11 years with my wife, Jael.
‎Without a doubt, Jehovah helps
those who put their complete trust in him.
‎The branch is blessed
to have as part of their Bethel family
‎some who had been longtime missionaries.
‎I enjoyed a very pleasant visit
‎with five of the senior members of this group
‎—three of whom are 98 years of age.
‎Brother William Dingman
is of the first class of Gilead.
‎His wife, Estelle, attended the 12th class.
‎Thelma Critz is also of the 12th class.
‎Barbara Parker is of the 42nd class,
‎and Helen Ferrari
attended the 2nd class of Gilead.
‎To illustrate the length
of their full-time service
‎is the fact that Sister Ferrari
‎is among those
who stood up to identify themselves
‎as part of the great multitude
‎at the 1935 convention in Washington, D.C.
‎The average age of this group is 94.
‎Even more impressive
‎is that their average years
of full-time service is 73.
‎These faithful ones set a fine example
‎continuing to be active in the ministry
‎—taking into account
their ages and health limitations.
‎Such loyal servants of Jehovah are considered
‎spiritual treasures wherever they may serve.
‎I still have one study so far,
‎although my eyesight doesn’t allow
‎me to do too much.
‎But I try.
‎My legs aren’t so good for walking,
‎so they wheel me around.
‎In all of my life, I would consider
‎the life that I have spent as a missionary
‎and in Dominican Republic as well
‎—it’s a wonderful life.
‎I couldn’t have chosen
‎a better companion
‎and also a better life
‎than to be preaching
‎the message of the good news of the Kingdom.
‎The Dominican Republic Bethel family
‎considers it a privilege
to have a share in providing
‎care for such faithful ones.
‎On Sunday, March the 12th,
a special program was held
‎at the open-air Assembly Hall
adjacent to the branch office.
‎A total of 3,050 benefited
‎from the spiritual program
and Christian association.
‎The visits to the Dominican Republic
and Haiti branches
‎proved to be
an encouragement and a spiritual blessing
‎to all who participated in them.
‎We thank Brother Molchan for that report
‎and for sharing those motivating experiences
‎of longtime servants of Jehovah.
‎Another example of this
are Richard and Peggy Kelsey.
‎How has he,
with the support of his dear wife,
‎proved to be one of the “gifts in men”
‎throughout his decades of full-time service?
‎I was born in a little town
‎called Adair, Iowa
‎—actually out on the farm​—
‎and that was in 1930.
‎I was born in 1931,
‎also in a small town in Iowa.
‎My father wanted to be a farmer.
‎So we moved to a farm,
and I grew up on a farm.
‎And then the Watchtower Study
of a little group,
‎and then a little congregation
was in our home.
‎And happily, when Peggy’s father
came into the truth,
‎the family came to our place
to the Watchtower Study.
‎I was—I guess at that time—
eight or nine,
‎and Peggy was one year younger.
‎But the thing was,
they moved away just after about one year.
‎Well, I started pioneering
in September 1948.
‎Gilead was what I wanted.
‎I didn’t apply for Bethel
‎because I liked the field service,
‎and I thought South America, Africa,
‎countries where there is still so much to do
‎—that’s what I wanted.
‎I was called to Gilead
‎in 1951, in February.
‎The assignment after attending Gilead
‎was a great surprise.
‎Brother Schroeder, one of the instructors,
‎he said: “You will have
‎“a very wonderful opportunity,
‎“being assigned to the German Bethel.
‎“There are brothers there
‎“who have been in concentration camps
for up to nine years,
‎and you can learn very much
from these brothers.”
‎And that was very true.
‎In 1953,
at the convention in New York,
‎I saw a beautiful young sister
‎standing in the cafeteria line
next to my cafeteria line.
‎And I looked twice,
‎and it was Peggy.
‎So we were together
for the rest of the convention
‎and decided that we would correspond
and think about serving together.
‎In 1955 we married.
‎I had received
the assignment to circuit work.
‎We were assigned to northern Germany.
‎When we began circuit work, I was 24.
‎I felt completely inadequate
‎because I’d been serving in Bethel
‎and had no training
‎that would qualify me
to serve as a circuit overseer
‎—that was my feeling.
‎In the first place,
the sisters with me always got nervous
‎with me not being able to speak correctly.
‎So they would take over the conversation,
‎and I stood there
and didn’t understand anything.
‎But with time, you pick it up.
‎After two years,
I could understand everything
‎in the theocratic language,
‎but in the kitchen I was still lost.
‎It was nine years for circuit work
and, at the conclusion, district work.
‎And then we were called back into Bethel.
‎The biggest shock for me
‎was when Brother Knorr asked me
‎if I would be branch overseer.
‎And that was at the convention
‎of 1969 in Nuremberg.
‎And despite different arguments
that I presented,
‎I got a letter later saying
that I’d have that assignment.
‎For about 40 years,
‎we had the wonderful privilege
of doing zone work or,
‎as it’s now stated,
being representative of headquarters.
‎So it was wonderful to visit
‎somewhat over 90 different countries.
‎We became acquainted
with Jehovah’s lovely family
‎—the worldwide brotherhood, the unity,
‎and seeing how the brothers everywhere
‎are devoted to Jehovah
‎and want to serve him faithfully
‎under sometimes very difficult conditions.
‎I would say,
sometimes we benefited more
‎from the visit
than the brothers we were visiting
‎because it was so faith-strengthening.
‎When we got this privilege
‎of traveling
to many branches in the zone work,
‎we were able to engage in the field ministry
‎in numerous countries,
‎which I never would have had, of course,
‎if I would have just gone
into missionary service.
‎So I said to myself,
‎‘Accept every assignment
Jehovah gives you
‎and you’ll find that you have
the greatest blessings possible.’
‎Since the 1st of January 1952,
‎I’ve been able to keep
full-time service as my career.
‎And it’s something
I certainly wouldn’t have changed
‎for anything else.
‎We have often said,
‎“Where would we be today
if we hadn’t taken up full-time service?”
‎Certainly, we would not have enjoyed
‎so many things as we have in our lifetime.
‎There are so many young,
talented brothers and sisters
‎who are working and helping.
‎We encourage them to make full-time service
‎in Jehovah’s organization their goal in life.
‎Are you one
of those young, talented brothers or sisters
‎who Brother Kelsey mentioned
could make full-time service a goal?
‎If so, keep it in your prayers.
‎Yes, as we look back at our program
‎and the examples of various “gifts in men,”
‎their wives,
‎and numerous others
doing all they can for Jehovah,
‎what is it that motivates them
‎to live such self-sacrificing lives?
‎Love.
‎And that’s the theme
of this month’s music video
‎entitled Brotherly Love.
‎Wherever you go,
you will have fam’ly near.
‎Because wherever you go,
Jehovah’s people are there.
‎And you’ll feel love.
‎You’ll feel love,
A brotherly love.
‎So feel the love.
‎Brothers and sisters all over the world
Unite with Jehovah and follow his Son
‎To bring you love—
A nation of,
‎Of brotherly love.
So feel the love.
‎Our Father provides for us all—
No one left over.
‎Deep in the jungle
or on mountains high,
‎In big, modern cities
or on islands afar,
‎You belong.
You belong to the people of God.
‎So feel the love.
‎Our Father provides for us all—
No, no one left over.
‎But in the world, it can be cold—
A scary place, truth to be told.
‎So how wonderful it is to know
The one true God and his people!
‎Jesus, he taught
his disciples to love.
‎So millions of people,
as a nation, they show
‎Jehovah’s love—
And you belong among all of them.
‎So feel the love.
‎What a beautiful song
‎and a good reminder that one way
‎we can show our love to Jehovah and Jesus
‎is by showing love,
respect, and appreciation
‎for the “gifts in men”
they have generously given us.
‎Now, before we end the program,
‎we have a special treat.
‎Our postcard this month
comes from right here
‎at our JW Broadcasting studio.
‎Yes, you get
a sneak peek behind the scenes
‎of how our broadcast is produced.
‎First, a group of brothers and sisters
‎set aside their regular Bethel work
for parts of three days.
‎Early on the first day,
‎the director reviews
the “shot list” with crew members.
‎The “shot list” is a series of photographs
‎showing how the cameras
will record each scene.
‎In the control room,
media is prepared for display
‎on the studio’s video screen.
‎The microphones and cameras
are all properly adjusted.
‎Then the crew rehearses
the entire program several times
‎while a stand-in substitutes
for the program host.
‎This allows the real host
to concentrate on his other work
‎during these technical rehearsals.
‎On the third day,
the actual host reports
‎to the studio’s makeup room,
‎where wardrobe makes sure
that he looks his best.
‎Before recording begins,
‎the crew assembles for a brief meeting.
‎The host often gives a few brief comments,
‎and the floor director gives
any final instruction to the crew.
‎After a prayer,
everyone takes their positions.
‎Within a few hours,
‎the entire recording
for that month’s program is completed.
‎Yes, our hardworking brothers
and sisters that work in the studio
‎happily send you
their warm love and greetings.
‎This is JW Broadcasting
‎from the world headquarters
‎of Jehovah’s Witnesses.