But now, let me ask you this:
Do you know what OPI stands for?
You’ll find that out and a lot more
in the following report,
which will be given by Brother Paul Gillies,
who serves as the overseer of OPI.
Ecclesiastes 12:10 says:
“The congregator sought to find
“delightful words and to record
accurate words of truth.”
In harmony with this principle,
the Office of Public Information, OPI,
at world headquarters has, over the years,
been assigned by the Governing Body
to convey accurate information
to the news media and academics.
But as Satan intensifies
his slanderous attacks
on Jehovah’s people
and opposers feed authorities
with twisted
and distorted statements about us,
OPI’s assignment now includes
conveying accurate words of truth
to government officials.
So in this report, we’d like to explain to you
how and why this work is done
and also relate a few experiences.
There are Scriptural precedents
for contacting government officials.
Jehovah positioned
his servants before rulers
in order to protect his people
and to further his purposes.
Examples include Joseph before Pharaoh,
Nehemiah before King Artaxerxes,
Esther and Mordecai before King Ahasuerus,
and Paul before Felix.
Of course, we do not need
the permission of governments
to meet and to preach.
But we do recognize
that having religious freedom
and the cooperation of officials
is conducive to spreading
the Kingdom message.
While remaining politically neutral,
we provide accurate information
to ‘kings and all those in high positions
so that we may go on leading
a calm and quiet life,’
as 1 Timothy 2:2 states.
Recently, brothers
from OPI met with officials
to address specific issues
hindering our work
in Azerbaijan, Belarus,
Russia, and Central Asia.
In July, a meeting
was held with the prime minister
of one African country to explain
the reasons for our Christian neutrality.
Reports such as these
that document incidents of injustice
are provided to officials.
Many express appreciation
for this information.
At a recent meeting
held in Congo (Kinshasa),
an embassy official
commenting on the quality
of these reports stated,
“They remain objective and moderate
despite the seriousness of the facts.”
So if we don’t take the initiative
to provide accurate information,
government officials
may receive misinformation
from opposers trying
to influence them to act against us.
Now, while it takes time and effort
to counteract lies and misinformation,
we have often experienced the truthfulness
of what Proverbs 25:15 tells us:
“By patience a commander is won over,
and a gentle tongue can break a bone.”
Well, let’s now share
with you some experiences
that demonstrate the benefit
of contacting both government officials
and the media.
Regarding Russia,
OPI keeps various officials
around the world informed
of the ongoing harassment
and unjust detentions of our brothers.
As a result, many of these authorities
have issued strongly worded statements
condemning the ban in Russia,
some of which you can find
on the jw.org “Newsroom.”
Meanwhile, OPI communicated
with journalists about Russia,
one of whom wrote a very interesting article
for the international edition of Newsweek.
This article appeared on the front cover.
And this one outlet alone has published
about 30 articles about the oppression
of Jehovah’s Witnesses
not just in Russia but other countries.
Each year in Uzbekistan,
our brothers experience police raids,
detentions, fines,
and sadly,
in some occasions, severe beatings.
This is just
for carrying out their Christian ministry.
Now, often the reason for that
is because we have been consistently
denied registration.
This photograph shows
some brothers and sisters
who are maintaining
their joy despite all of them
having been fined exorbitant amounts.
Now interestingly, on May 14, 2018,
the ambassador from Uzbekistan
to the United States
said this in Washington D.C.,
“Jehovah’s Witnesses
will be able to register much easier.”
So seizing this opportunity,
a delegation of brothers was approved
to travel to Uzbekistan last month
and held preliminary discussions
with government representatives.
If it be Jehovah’s will,
we certainly pray that these efforts will lead
to national registration
and some relief for our brothers
who have endured persecution.
Where appropriate,
OPI also helps branches
to organize public events
in areas where our work
is often misrepresented.
For instance, in Kazakhstan,
where there have been some obstacles,
local officials and communities
have recently demonstrated a willingness
to learn more about Jehovah’s people.
Therefore, the branch hosted
a series of open house events
in Kingdom Halls in select locations.
A number of officials, media representatives,
and other professionals
attended these events.
A government ministry
wrote to the brothers stating,
“These events will provide
the citizens of our country
“an opportunity
to learn more about the activities
“and the history of Jehovah’s Witnesses
in Kazakhstan and worldwide.”
In Sri Lanka,
the cardinal of the Catholic Church
wrote to the president
and other representatives of the government
demanding that they cancel
the special convention
that was scheduled for just last July.
Not only did the cardinal not get his way
but favorable government ministers
actually invited the branch
to hold a press conference
to publicize the convention.
After OPI prepared
the Sri Lanka branch for the event,
approximately 45 media representatives
attended the press conference held at Bethel.
Some of the journalists
who attended this press conference
also attended the special convention
and published positive news stories.
So instead of the clergy
successfully influencing
government officials
to cancel the convention,
these officials
actually assisted us in publicizing it.
One of the tools that we use
for conveying accurate information
to the media and government officials
is the “Newsroom” section of jw.org.
However, seeing the need
for our brotherhood
to have a source of reliable reports
about current events
involving Jehovah’s people,
the majority of articles are now written
with you in mind.
Quite a few have expressed appreciation
for the “Imprisoned for Their Faith” feature,
which is now updated monthly
and allows us to mention
imprisoned brothers by name in our prayers.
Just as an example, these are the faces
of some of our young brothers in Turkmenistan
who have been imprisoned
as conscientious objectors
during 2018.
Jesus foretold:
“You will be hated by all the nations
on account of my name.”
So we recognize that no amount of effort
to educate government officials
is going to change that.
Like Pharaoh, some of the world’s dictators
‘harden their hearts’ against Jehovah.
However, Jesus also foretold:
“You will be brought
before governors and kings
“for my sake, for a witness
to them and the nations.”
It’s not just OPI that is giving
a witness to the governments,
it is every brother and sister
that officials come in contact with.
We’ve often heard
a government official say
that they know either
a schoolmate, a former workmate,
or a relative
who is one of Jehovah’s Witnesses.
Additionally, each and every brother
in prison is giving a witness.
For example, on July 15, 2018,
during a press interview,
the prime minister of Armenia
commented on his contact
with Jehovah’s Witnesses
when he was a political prisoner.
He said:
“There were prisoners, Jehovah’s Witnesses,
“who were there for not serving in the army.
“These people were convinced
about their beliefs.”
Then he added,
“You don’t have to agree with them,
but you could feel it was their conviction.”
So who knows if someone
who observes your conduct
or who you talk to
in field service or on public transport
may be the very person
who one day is in a government position
and knows something
about Jehovah’s Witnesses
because of what you did or said.
Indeed, we couldn’t do the work at OPI
without you brothers and sisters
setting such a fine example.
Those who work
in the Office of Public Information
under the direction
of the Coordinators’ Committee
consider it a real privilege
to support all of you
by communicating
with government officials
and representatives
of the media and academia
—by conveying our beliefs and practices
with “accurate words of truth.”
Thank you kindly, Brother Gillies,
for that thought-provoking update
on the important work being done
in the Office of Public Information.
Notice how quickly I learned
the meaning of that acronym.
And if you remember
from a previous annual meeting,
Brother Herd especially likes acronyms.
Brother Gillies,
we know Britain misses having you,
but we’re very happy to have you
with us here at headquarters.
But you will have to learn how
to correctly say, “schedule.”
But we love you anyway.
But now, let me ask you this:
Does it seem like
our brothers and sisters around the globe
are being pummeled
with more and more natural disasters?
Well, you’ll find out.
Brother John Ekrann,
who serves as a helper
to the Coordinators’ Committee,
will give us the facts.
You’ll find it very interesting.
Brother Ekrann, please.
Two thousand seventeen and 2018
were certainly record years for disasters.
Just look at a few of the headlines
from the news in 2017 and 2018.
There were earthquakes in Mexico,
plague in Madagascar,
food shortages in Venezuela
—disasters are going to get worse—
war in Congo,
deadly Nipah virus in India,
a volcano erupts in Guatemala,
violence in Cameroon,
and Ebola in the DRC.
Now, we are not surprised
because we see
the increased frequency
and intensity of disasters
as fulfillment of Bible prophecy.
If we look at Luke chapter 21
and look at verses 10 and 11,
Jesus said:
“Then he said to them:
‘Nation will rise against nation,
“‘and kingdom against kingdom.
“‘There will be great earthquakes,
“‘and in one place after another
food shortages and pestilences.’”
We are actually witnessing
and can see
the fulfillment of Jesus’ words.
We are seeing ‘earthquakes
in one place after another’
—and truly great earthquakes
as Jesus described.
Volcanoes dump huge amounts
of ash and smoke into the air.
Tornadoes, hurricanes,
and typhoon winds
destroy buildings and property.
Rain and flooding
from these huge storms
cause rivers to overflow
and damage large areas
of lands and property,
causing mud and debris
to flow into buildings
like this expandable Kingdom Hall.
Wildfires engulf both forests
and communities in flames and smoke,
leaving only behind the charred remains
of what was once called home.
Now, when there is a disaster,
all of us are keenly interested to know,
‘How are our brothers
and sisters doing?’
The “JW News” section of jw.org
is regularly updated with news
of how our brothers and sisters
are affected by a certain disaster.
Just here, we see some
of the headlines
that are on “JW News” lately,
and we encourage you
to read this section regularly
to stay up-to-date.
Now, to show you the size and scale
of disasters lately, look at this map
as we plot on it the disasters that have occurred
in just the last service year.
And do you notice the number of brothers
that are affected?
Did you notice
close to half a million of our brothers
were directly affected by these disasters
in just the last couple of years?
Now, it’s sad to say that 22
of our brothers and sisters
died in these disasters
and 84 were seriously injured.
Tens of thousands of our brothers
have had to find new homes.
And of these, 14,000 had to
completely flee their homeland.
Now, we want all of you to know
that have been affected
by many of these disasters
just in the last couple of years
that we love and pray for you.
You are not lost or forgotten.
Jehovah says at Isaiah 49:15:
“I would never forget you.”
Now, proof that Jehovah
has not forgotten you
is the love of your brotherhood.
Now, Acts chapter 2
describes in the first century
how the brothers then
took care of one another.
Acts chapter 2 describes
how our brothers
were willing to sell
properties and possessions
to help one another out.
And in Acts chapter 11,
the brothers sent relief aid
to those who were facing
a very great famine.
Well, how has
our united brotherhood responded
to these disasters today?
Well, there’s a fine phrase
in Philippians 1:27
that can show, really,
how our brothers and sisters
—all of us—
are helping one another.
Philippians 1:27, it says:
“Only behave in a manner worthy
of the good news about the Christ,
“so that whether
I come and see you or I am absent,
“I may hear about you and learn
“that you are standing firm in one spirit,
“with one soul,
(and here’s the phrase)
“striving side by side
for the faith of the good news.”
Well, one very big way
that we can ‘strive side by side’
in helping one another
is by our donations
to the worldwide work.
This chart gives you an idea
of the cost of disasters
and how they’ve jumped in 2018.
As you can see, we spent on an average
between five and seven million dollars
on disaster relief in past service years.
But look, though, what has happened in 2018.
Just in 2018, it has climbed
to over 33 million dollars.
Now, what will happen in 2019?
What will we see?
Well, it’s already off
to a big start in September.
The Governing Body asked
that I pass along to all of you
thanks and appreciation
for your generous donations.
We would like to assure you
that your donations
are being put to good use
in helping in one disaster after another.
Now, another way
that we as a brotherhood
work side by side
is volunteering to assist in a disaster.
Thousands of our brothers and sisters
have willingly volunteered
to reconstruct or repair Kingdom Halls
or our brothers’ and sisters’ homes.
Others carry and deliver food, water,
and many other items needed
after a disaster
to help our brothers
by using any transportation means possible:
horses, boats, trucks.
Some volunteer
with paint rollers and brushes.
Others show up with shovels
to clean up after a disaster,
prepare meals for the workers,
put supply packages together,
and sort, bag,
and deliver them
—all with a smile.
Just look at all these happy faces!
We want to thank all of you
that have worked so hard
on disaster relief,
especially the last couple of years.
We also want to thank
the departments at headquarters,
the Branch Committees,
the branch departments,
the circuit overseers, LDCs,
disaster relief committees,
and all of you elders worldwide
that have really pitched in
and helped so much
with disaster relief efforts
the past couple of years.
Thank you.
Well, how do
our brothers and sisters feel
about your love and support?
Well, as you watch this next video,
I’m going to read
to you a sentence or two
from different letters
of appreciation
that our brothers
have sent in following a disaster:
“Jehovah knows
when we’re in need, and he spoils us
“by giving us
even more than we ask for.
“Your deep concern
as well as the spiritual, emotional,
“and material support you’ve provided
and that we’re still receiving
“is a real soothing ointment
that can help us to endure.
“When we see our belongings
covered with mud brought outside
“and thrown as garbage,
“we feel very heartbroken.
“But the brothers and sisters saw them,
“not as a lump of garbage,
“but as a mass of our feelings.
“The day the construction brothers
arrived at my home, I burst into tears.
“I’d like to clarify that I didn’t cry
because I was going to get a new house
“but because I saw
Jehovah’s hand in my life.
“The transformation
was not limited to my house.
“This experience has changed me.
“I’ve not only seen
but also felt Jehovah’s tender care.
“They not only repaired our house;
they also repaired our heart.
“We were able to see Jehovah
in this beautiful work
“of strengthening help.
“Even though
we lost our possessions, being busy
“in the construction and preaching work
helped us to maintain
“our emotional and spiritual balance.
“We felt a lump
in our throats at being witnesses
to the tender care
of our protective God.”
We can expect that disasters
are going to intensify
as we get closer
to the end of this system.
The study note on Mark 13:8
on the phrase
“pangs of distress” says this:
‘It may suggest that like birth pains
the foretold troubles and suffering
‘will increase in frequency,
intensity, and duration
in the time period
before a great tribulation.’
Who knows?
You may be next
to need help from your brothers.
Be prepared, but at the same time,
don’t put trust
in money or your belongings.
All can be gone instantly.
While nothing
of our possessions will last forever,
the love of Jehovah
and the love of our brothers will.
As we face increasing disasters,
let’s continue side by side
to help everyone
—each one of us—
to survive this old system.
We appreciate very much, Brother Ekrann,
that enlightening report that you gave us.
Now, those were
some necessary announcements
you needed to know about,
but we have two more
very exciting announcements.
And we thought it would be better
if you were seated for these.
Here’s the first one:
The Governing Body has approved
a significant redesign
of the jw.org® website
to include the features
of JW Broadcasting®
and Watchtower ONLINE LIBRARY™.
Additionally, the JW Library® app
will be redesigned and will incorporate
the content and features
of Watchtower Library.
As a result, the overall appearance
of the new website and app will be unified
and become more user-friendly.
Planning and design work
have already begun
on this very large project.
You should see certain improvements
within a few months.
Now this time,
less than six months does apply.
But what do you think of that?
Here’s one more very exciting announcement
—especially for our field missionaries,
some of whom may be here in attendance,
you’ll be happy you were seated:
For nearly 75 years,
Gilead-trained missionaries
have been serving in the worldwide field,
opening up new territories
as well as strengthening the brotherhood.
The majority
of these missionaries continue to serve
in field assignments
and have gained valuable experience.
We are pleased to inform you
that the Governing Body has given approval
for all field missionaries
with an FMF enrollment
who have been serving
for at least five years to attend
the School of Kingdom Evangelizers—SKE.
This provision will reinforce
the spirituality of these dear ones.
They will be mixed into the SKE classes
along with new students
to allow others to benefit from their experience.
Approved missionaries will attend SKE
in the location of the school of the country
to which they are assigned.
We’re all very happy
for you hard-working field missionaries.
But now, Brother Herd
has a couple more acronyms
as a result of this announcement
—the FMF enrollment
and SKE classes.
So Brother Herd,
I hope you took note of that.
But now, for the next one hour
and twenty minutes,
we’re going to get to enjoy
some very exciting, fast-moving,
enlightening talks
given by five different members
of the Governing Body.
You notice, I highlighted
that word “enlightening.”
Our leadoff speaker
is Brother Kenneth Cook
who will present the talk,
“We Should Be Teachers.”
Brother Cook.
After a convention, we often say
that the teaching
was better than ever.
But even the best teachers
at this convention
or your convention
or on today’s program
are no match
for the Great Teacher.
Jesus was an exceptional teacher.
Imagine what it would have been like
to hear Jesus teach.
What made him so effective?
We don’t have to guess.
Consider a few of the methods
that he used in the Sermon on the Mount.
For example, his introduction
aroused interest and introduced his subject.
At Matthew chapter 5, for example,
and verse 3, Jesus simply said:
“Happy are those conscious
of their spiritual need.”
That simple statement
provided the interest for his listeners.
They would want to know,
‘How would this make me happy?’
He then added:
“. . . since the Kingdom
of the heavens belongs to them.”
And there is the subject
that he consistently used
to mark his teaching.
Jesus also used effective questions
to reason with his listeners.
He crafted simple
but powerful illustrations.
And if birds and lilies were on hand,
perhaps he was actually using visual aids
during that Sermon on the Mount.
Finally, his conclusion was simple;
it was brief and motivating.
No wonder Jesus’ listeners
were astounded!
Did Jesus expect us
to be merely astounded
at his teaching, though?
No.
He commissioned his disciples
to ‘go preaching and teaching.’
Paul later plainly told
the Hebrew Christians:
“You should be teachers.”
Why was effective teaching
so necessary then and now?
Because lives are involved.
Parents, Satan is waging war
for the hearts of your children,
so it’s never been more important
to inculcate the truth in them.
It means their life.
Elders, our fellow worshippers
are battered by this system,
so it’s never been more important
to encourage
and strengthen them to endure.
It means their life.
And publishers, that’s all of us here,
the end is rapidly drawing near,
so it’s never been more important
to teach Bible truth
in a simple,
appealing, and motivating way.
It means life to those who listen to us.
Because teaching is so important,
Jehovah has motivated skilled teachers
to pass on their methods to others.
For this reason, the Bible tells us
that Paul imparted to Timothy
not only what to teach
but also his methods,
or how to teach.
Those methods, it says,
were valid everywhere
in every congregation,
so Timothy passed
those methods on to others.
Today, Jehovah’s organization
has endeavored
to follow the same pattern.
Teaching teachers has a long history
in Jehovah’s organization.
Let’s look at some modern examples
of how Jehovah has trained us to be teachers.
In 1922, The School of the Prophets
was used by some groups of Bible students
to develop the art
of public teaching and speaking.
One suggestion in the booklet
was to practice a figure-eight gesture,
yes, so that speakers would learn
to move their arms and hands in curves.
Those schools were later discontinued.
Nineteen forty-two
—even before the Theocratic Ministry School
was introduced to the congregations—
a series of articles in Consolation magazine
appeared until 1945 under the heading
“Presenting ‘This Gospel of the Kingdom.’”
The first article stated the series’ purpose.
It said: “To give
helpful instruction and practical hints
“to such ones as would publish God’s kingdom
“after the example of Christ himself . . .
“Study and apply this instruction,
and note your improvement
as a Kingdom publisher.”
Nineteen forty-three
—the booklet Course in Theocratic Ministry
featured 52 lessons,
one for each week of the year,
in conjunction with the newly formed
Theocratic Ministry School.
Nineteen forty-five
—the book
Theocratic Aid to Kingdom Publishers
expanded that course to 90 lessons.
Nineteen fifty-five
—the book Qualified to Be Ministers
was described in The Watchtower
as the “best yet” book
for the Theocratic Ministry School
until it was revised
into an even better qualified book
in 1967.
Nineteen seventy-one
—the Theocratic Ministry School Guidebook
was released.
And then in 2002, we received
Benefit From Theocratic
Ministry School Education,
which included
new study points, exercises,
and a counsel form right in the book.
Clearly, as needs change, Jehovah provides us
with new tools to improve our teaching.
Is it time for a new tool
to improve our skills as teachers?
Consider the following
regarding our Ministry School textbook:
(1) Terminology:
The contents
and even the title of that book
refer to the Theocratic Ministry School,
and that, as such, is no longer in place.
(2) Simplicity:
Many find it difficult
to quickly find key ideas
in the book’s 53 study points.
An elder from Georgia, U.S.A., wrote,
“In the short time available
to direct the congregation
“to specific locations in the book,
“it makes it very difficult for the brothers
to find where the chairman is.”
(3) Translation:
It isn’t easy
to translate a book this big.
In fact, in over 200 languages
around the globe,
congregations have
the Meeting Workbook
but lack the Ministry School book.
For all of these reasons and more,
we are pleased to announce a release
that addresses those concerns
and that will help more
of God’s people
to improve their teaching.
It is a 28-page brochure entitled
Apply Yourself to Reading and Teaching.
The chairman will let you know
how you can access a copy
for your personal use
—no doubt in less than six months.
In addition, the instructions
for Our Christian Life and Ministry Meeting
will soon be revised
and made available to the public.
Now this brochure will be used
at our midweek meetings worldwide
beginning January 7, 2019.
Don’t discard
your Ministry School book, though.
Although we won’t be using it
at our weekly meetings,
it is still a very valuable reference.
Would you like to know more about some
of this new brochure’s features?
We begin with brevity.
There are only 20 study points,
and each study point is only one page long.
Does this mean important points
have been omitted?
No.
In many cases, similar points
have been combined.
For example,
“Study 5—Accurate Reading,”
incorporates key ideas from three points
in the Ministry School book.
They are accurate reading,
words clearly spoken,
and correct pronunciation.
After all, reading accurately
includes pronouncing
each word correctly and clearly.
Oh, and by the way,
the brochure does not suggest
using that figure-eight gesture,
so you don’t have to worry about that.
Another feature is clarity.
Each study features
two or three main points
with simple, direct instructions,
and some study points
also include practical tips
that relate to the main point.
In addition, you will find
that many of the study points
include a box entitled “In the Ministry.”
Why?
Because while most
of the points in the brochure
apply both to the field ministry
and to teaching from the platform,
suggestions that are specific
to the field ministry
appear in this separate box.
Next is a feature
that you will really find of interest:
“Record Your Progress.”
One of the last pages
of the brochure
is for you to record the date
you consider each study point.
More about that in a moment.
So there are some features.
But how will the new brochure
address the three needs
that we mentioned earlier,
namely terminology,
simplicity, and translation?
We begin with terminology.
The brochure uses updated expressions,
but it does not refer
to specific meetings or meeting parts.
Therefore, it will not need
to be frequently revised.
Next, simplicity: Fewer study points
and a simple easy-to-use layout
will allow the chairman
to isolate main points quickly
and will help the audience
to follow along closely
with the chairman.
Also, and you elders
are going to love this,
more is being done
to simplify the work
of the chairman
and the Life and Ministry Meeting overseer.
Beginning January 7, 2019,
the instructions in the Meeting Workbook
for each student assignment
will include in parentheses
the specific study point
that the student should work on.
As an example,
for the week of January 7th,
all brothers worldwide
who are assigned the Bible reading
will consider
“Study 5—Accurate Reading.”
We thought you would like that.
Life and Ministry Meeting
overseers and chairmen
will no longer need to worry
about assigning study points
or keeping track
of what each student is working on.
Would you like to see a chairman use
the new brochure to assist a student?
Please watch.
“. . . and Abednego over the administration
of the province of Babylon,
but Daniel served in the king’s court.”
Thank you, Brother Gomez.
That was an excellent reading.
You were accurate, fluent,
and we could tell that you prepared well.
You were working
on study point number 10, “Modulation.”
The summary tells us that we have
two goals when modulating our voice.
One goal is to stir emotion.
You stirred our emotions
when you read Daniel 2:47:
“Truly your God is a God of gods.”
By raising your pitch, you conveyed
Nebuchadnezzar’s intensity and surprise.
That’s the way to do it.
A second goal is to convey ideas clearly.
One way to do it is to increase our volume.
For example,
what is the main point of verse 44?
Isn’t it that Jehovah will set up a Kingdom?
So instead of emphasizing the word “kings,”
you might increase your volume
when reading “God of heaven.”
“In the days of those kings
the God of heaven will set up a kingdom.”
So that’s something you might try
when preparing to read a scripture.
Look for the main point in each verse,
and then try varying your pitch, pace,
or volume to make that idea stand out.
Thank you, Brother Gomez. Well done!
For our next part, we’ll consider . . .
That was a very good example
of concise and helpful
one-minute comments
and counsel by the chairman.
But where does the chairman write
whether the student
completed the assigned point?
He doesn’t write anything.
But on the page
“Record Your Progress” mentioned earlier,
who will write the dates
that the student considered each point?
The student, not the chairman.
When should a student
record a date on this page?
Well that’s up to you, the student.
Many will likely record the date
that they are assigned
to consider a specific point
for a student assignment.
Others, including elders,
who may not handle
student assignments regularly,
may want to consider
each of these points on their own.
Each brother and sister
can decide when and how
to use this page
to record their progress.
This “Record Your Progress” page
is for your personal use.
Now, so far, we’ve looked at the need
for updated terminology
and greater simplicity.
Now let’s consider
that third point: translation.
You will be thrilled to know
that the Governing Body
has already approved for this brochure
to be translated
into over 350 languages
—more than twice
the number of languages
that produce the current textbook.
But the same brevity that allows us
to expand the translation also means
that there are few real-life examples
in the brochure
that show how to apply the study points.
So wouldn’t it be helpful to see
how to put the study points into action,
both from the platform
and in the field ministry?
Indeed it would.
For this reason, the Governing Body
has approved the production of 20 videos
—one for each study point—
to depict the application of these points.
Let’s watch the video
for “Study 1—Effective Introduction.”
You’re at the Kingdom Hall
about to give a public talk.
Will the audience listen
to what you have to say?
Much depends on how
you introduce your subject.
An effective introduction arouses interest,
identifies your subject,
and shows why the subject
is important to your listeners.
Let’s give our brother
an opportunity to introduce his subject.
As the meeting chairman mentioned,
we’re going to talk about death
and what it means to you and me.
Let’s read a scripture
at Ecclesiastes 9:5.
So, what do you think?
Did the speaker identify his subject?
Yes.
Did he arouse interest?
Not so much.
Did he show why the subject is important?
No.
So how might he approach
the subject differently?
Let’s watch.
Throughout all of human history,
not one person has escaped death.
The lives of some people
are cut short suddenly
by unexpected events or illness.
Have you ever lost a loved one in death?
If so, you know how painful that is.
Yet how can something
that causes so much pain
be a normal, natural part of life?
The Bible is the key
to understanding why we die,
where we go when we die,
and how death will be reversed.
Let’s consider each of those points.
You can apply this principle
to any subject when giving a talk.
But how can you effectively introduce
a subject in the ministry?
Remember, of course,
that in most cases
you’re a complete stranger
to the householder.
Try not to startle the person.
Identify yourself early in the conversation.
To determine what
a person might be interested in,
observe his activities or surroundings.
You might begin by asking a question
or making a brief comment
about those things.
Let’s consider one example.
Hi, my name is Jill.
I’m here to talk
about God’s purpose for the future.
The Bible says here—
Sorry, but I don’t have time to talk.
Was the introduction effective?
The householder didn’t want
to continue the conversation,
so apparently the introduction
didn’t arouse interest.
How might the publisher
have handled the situation better?
Good morning.
You have a beautiful garden.
It must take a lot of work.
It sure does!
Well, your work is certainly paying off.
Thank you.
By the way, my name is Jill,
and this is Tammy.
I’m Emily.
Emily, you work so hard
to care for the garden you planted.
Do you think that God cares the same way
about this planet that he created?
Because the publisher took into account
the interests of the householder,
she increased the chances
of starting a conversation
and sharing the Kingdom message.
This can also be done in urban areas
where people expect you
to get right to the point.
In such settings, try to include
a thought-provoking statement
or question in your introduction.
Effective introductions are the first step
toward productive conversations
and presentations of the good news.
Jesus foretold
that the ‘preaching of the good news
of the Kingdom
will stop when the end comes.’
So our work is urgent.
However, the work of teaching
has only just begun.
Isaiah 26:9 says of Jehovah
that “when there are judgments
from you for the earth,
the inhabitants of the land
learn about righteousness.”
And that will certainly prove
to be true in the new world.
The great crowd will soon be invited
to teach vast numbers
of resurrected ones.
You may study with someone
who lived 3,000 years ago or more.
Imagine how helpful it will be
to have learned
how to explain unfamiliar terms
in “Study 17—Understandable to Others.”
Your student may have lived
during the Middle Ages
when people were taught
to fear the clergy
rather than to love God.
But you will have already
learned from Study 19
how to “Reach the Heart” of your student.
And when you’re asked to summarize
all that Jehovah did
for his people during the last days,
you’ll need to keep things simple,
something you learned
in “Study 14—Main Points Made to Stand Out.”
Even today, however, we must be teachers.
So use this new brochure
to ‘continue applying yourself
to reading and teaching.’
By doing this, the Bible tells us:
“You will save both yourself
and those who listen to you.”
Thank you so much, Brother Cook,
and thank you also
for joining us on the Governing Body.
To borrow words from Brother Sydlik:
“The Lord knew we needed your help.”
I’m still working on that too.
But we have the following announcement
regarding our wonderful new brochure
—and I double checked;
I got the right announcement this time:
The Teaching brochure
in all available languages
will be released on jw.org,
Watchtower ONLINE LIBRARY™,
and JW Library®
on Monday October 8, 2018.
Now, in addition to that,
if you will be making use
of a hard copy of this publication,
one copy of the printed edition
will be available after the program
at the various annual meeting locations,
including the main lobby of your complex
for those watching from their personal rooms.
Additional printed copies
may be requested through the congregations.
So Monday
—in two days—
you get this one electronically.
But now, moving to our next talk.
We’re privileged to listen
to Brother Anthony Morris,
and he’s going to deliver the gripping talk,
“This Is It!”
I hope that I rendered justice
to announcing that title, Brother Morris.
I’ll talk to you later on.
It ruined my introduction, but that’s all right.
But I think all of you would agree
how much we enjoyed the museum video
and hearing Brother Fred Franz
—his voice—
talking about after the assassination
of the archduke
that the brothers said, ‘Aha!
‘There it is!
There it is!
What we’ve been waiting for.’
Well, that’s very stirring,
and then we would have critics saying,
‘Yeah, but you people had other expectations
that were not realized,’
and etcetera, you know.
But it’s amazing that even the world
recognized that this was unique—1914.
See?
In fact, I’ve had this for many years.
I want to show it to you.
It’s The New World Magazine.
And it was widely read at the time,
and I guess about 1931,
they went out of business.
But here,
“End of All Kingdoms in 1914
—‘Millennial Dawners’ 25 Year Prophecy,”
widely read; other newspapers covered it.
They made comments here:
“The terrific war outbreak in Europe
“has fulfilled an extraordinary prophecy.
“For a quarter of a century past,
“through preachers and through press,
“the ‘International Bible Students,’
best known as ‘Millennial Dawners,’
“have been proclaiming
to the world that the Day of Wrath
“prophesied in the Bible would dawn in 1914.
“‘Look out for 1914!’
has been the cry
of the hundreds of traveling evangelists.”
And I appreciate very much how
the Yearbook in 1975
considering our modern-day history
made this beautiful quote:
“Disappointments about going to heaven
“in 1914 really were very minor,
“compared with the great expectations realized
in connection with that year.”
And it’s amazing.
During the first six months
of 1914, nothing happened.
They were being ridiculed.
And then the archduke is assassinated.
This one was particularly released
on August 30, 1914.
Millions died in World War I.
So it’s Brother Franz’s statement
that really gave
the idea for the theme here:
“This Is It!”
The question arises, Will we have
one or more times
—in the future or even now—
when we can say, “This is it”
and have that same exciting fervor
because of Bible prophecy?
Well, let’s begin with this one here.
Find Daniel chapter 11,
Daniel chapter 11.
And we’re going to read here verse 40,
or half of it:
“In the time of the end the king of the south
(here at Daniel 11:40)
will engage with him in a pushing.”
So the Governing Body
has been prayerfully considering recent events.
And we know that in 1991,
the Soviet Union came to an end.
So who is “the king of the north”?
Well, after prayerfully considering it
and the matter of the pushing,
we’re assuring you that what we see,
after prayerfully considering it,
is that it’s Russia
and its allies
—the king of the north.
Now, here’s some reasoning.
The Soviet Union disbanded;
Russia came up from the rubble
of the Soviet Union, along with its allies.
And here are some of the facts.
Two things have become apparent.
Russia and its allies
are continuing to engage
in a pushing with the king of the south.
We’ll get to that “pushing” point shortly.
And the second, they are taking the lead
in persecuting and opposing God’s people.
Now, notice what the pushing includes:
electronic espionage,
computer attacks,
trade wars
(and that’s what they call them),
and the hostile flooding
into surrounding territory.
These are recurring features
of the news headlines.
You’re aware of them.
So someone asks if the king
of the north has been inactive.
Well, no.
It appears he’s never been this busy
with pushing the king of the south.
So this is it!
At this point, we’re confident
to share with you that Russia
and its allies are the king of the north,
and they’re engaged in this pushing.
In fact, last month,
they had the largest war games
—Russia did—
since the Soviet Union
was in existence way back in the ’80’s.
And they had their allies
with them in the war game.
So we’re confident this is it.
This is the king of the north,
and that’s what’s involved at this time
with the pushing—
locking horns with each other.
So is there going to be another time
related to Bible prophecy
where the faithful slave
will be able to say to you, “This is it”?
Well, one that we’re all very familiar with
—and especially
this audience here in Newburgh,
you’ve been in the truth for decades—
notice the very familiar thoughts
from 1 Thessalonians chapter 5,
and we’re going to read verse 2
and verse 3,
5:2, 3:
“For you yourselves know very well
“that Jehovah’s day is coming exactly
“as a thief in the night.
“Whenever it is that they are saying,
“‘Peace and security!’
“then sudden destruction
is to be instantly on them,
“just like birth pains on a pregnant woman,
and they will by no means escape.”
Now, so that we have clear thinking
on the published comments regarding
these two verses
that we read, we’ll take you back
to the September 15, 2012, Watchtower:
“As used here, ‘Jehovah’s day’
“refers to the period
that will start with the destruction
“of false religion and will culminate
“in the war of Armageddon.
“However, just before
that day of Jehovah begins,
“world leaders will be saying,
‘Peace and security!’
“This may refer to one event
“or to a series of events.
“Nations may think they are close
to solving some of their big problems.”
So here’s the question, and it’s understood
that it would be asked,
Will the faithful slave
be able to at a certain time
say to the brotherhood: “This is it!
“This is what we’ve been waiting for.
This is the ‘peace and security’ prophecy”?
Well, keep this comment in mind
from The Watchtower, 2004,
February 1, page 21:
“Since Bible prophecies
are often fully understood
“only after they are fulfilled
or are in the process of fulfillment . . .”
Isn’t that interesting?
So keep that in mind.
We’ll come back to it,
and that happens
to be the case when
the prophecy is fulfilled.
“Oh, OK.”
But, see, we’ll come back
to that statement
from The Watchtower shortly.
But just consider
(especially those of you here,
many of you are aged,
and you’ll remember,
many of you who were
in the truth at the time),
What about the year 1986?
The United Nations
was proclaiming prior
to January of 1986 that,
you know, ‘Get ready.’
They wanted
the governments to put their arms down
for at least a year,
the International Year of Peace.
Whoa!
And if you were in the truth back then,
you were like, “OK.”
So they were all big.
In fact, the pope at that time
gathered all these religious leaders
over there to Assisi, Italy,
and they were all over there
praying to who they pray to
and having this fervor
for peace for the earth.
Well, how did
the faithful slave handle all that?
So this honors
Jehovah’s faithful slave serving at that time.
Here’s what was published
in the ’85 Watchtower,
October 1, page 18.
Now, this is some months
before that all started in 1986.
Here’s what was stated:
“Christians cannot say in advance exactly
“when the great tribulation will strike.
(Period.)
“Jehovah has not revealed
‘that day or the hour.’
“Thus when, for example, the United Nations
“declares the year 1986
“an ‘International Year of Peace,’
“Christians watch the event with interest.
“But they cannot say in advance
whether this will prove
to be the fulfillment of Paul’s words.”
Nonetheless, we kept on the watch,
but God’s spirit was guiding his people,
particularly the faithful slave.
They were not only faithful,
they were discreet.
And they did not say:
“This is it!
“This is the fulfillment
of 1 Thessalonians chapter 5.”
No.
But if you are still there,
go back to 1 Thessalonians chapter 5
—just something to keep in mind here—
sometimes we’ll read
verses 2 and 3 and leave out verse 4.
He writes: “But you, brothers,
“you are not in darkness,
so that the day should overtake
you as it would thieves.”
So thieves are doing their thievery
when it’s dark, but we’re sons of light.
So that’s not going to catch us,
the faithful ones worshipping the true God,
obedient to this
earthly part of his organization.
So the question comes up—
If you go back to that quote
from the 2004 Watchtower,
‘Prophecies are only fully understood
only after they are fulfilled,’
but we also said, ‘or are in the process
of fulfillment.’
So will
the faithful slave be able to say
in the process of the fulfillment
of this prophecy from 1 Thessalonians:
“This is it!
That’s what we’ve been waiting for”?
We’ll have to wait and see.
But there’s a word of caution here
we want to pass on to you
because we’re all human.
We must keep on the watch,
but please, just don’t be gullible.
You hear a world leader
say something about peace.
And then you
start e-mailing or something else
with a social network.
“This is it!”
Leave the channel to handle such matters.
If the faithful slave is moved by God’s spirit
to say that to the brotherhood,
and that’s His will, fine.
But please don’t be gullible.
Stick with the way
Jehovah wants this to operate,
and he’ll bless your obedience.
Now, you’ll remember
Jehovah’s day begins
as they’re saying,
“Peace and security!”
Turn to Revelation chapter 17.
My, what stirring words!
They are familiar,
but it does nourish our figurative hearts
when we read these,
chapter 17,
verses 15, 16, and 17:
“He said to me: ‘The waters
that you saw, where the prostitute
“‘(the world empire of false religion) is sitting,
“‘mean peoples and crowds
and nations and tongues.
“‘And the ten horns
that you saw and the wild beast,
“‘these will hate the prostitute
“‘and will make her devastated and naked,
“‘and they will eat up her flesh
and completely burn her with fire.
“‘For God put it
into their hearts to carry out his thought,
“‘yes, to carry out their one thought
“‘by giving their kingdom to the wild beast,
until the words of God
will have been accomplished.’”
Now, this is what’s going to happen.
And when you think about it,
this is just mind-boggling.
They have no plans as such
—the governments—
at this point.
So Jehovah forces
one part of Satan’s system
to destroy another part.
Only the Almighty God can do that.
So when they do destroy Babylon the Great
and all of this is taking place on the earth,
you brothers are not going
to need a breaking news update.
Around the globe you’re going to say:
“This is it!
The great tribulation has started.”
And, frankly,
for those who worry sometimes,
during the great tribulation
as these events unfold,
you’re not going to be terrified.
No.
You’re going to stand up straight,
lift your heads up, and say:
“This is it!
Our deliverance is here.”
Thank you very much, Brother Morris,
for heightening our eagerness
for what lies ahead in the near future.
And thank you for removing the veil
from “the king of the north.”