We’d like for you to picture this scene:
You’re with thousands
of your brothers and sisters at a convention.
You’re riveted with the brother who’s giving,
delivering, this beautiful talk.
He’s actually giving some instruction
about the great tribulation
and what we need to do now
to go through that great tribulation loyally.
But then a man steps up to the platform
and addresses the speaker and says:
“My brother is the executor
of my father’s will,
“and he’s cutting me out.
“I deserve more.
“I’d like for you to step down
from the platform,
come over and talk some sense
into my brother.”
Well, as ridiculous as that sounds,
this really did happen 2,000 years ago.
And as was brought up by our commenter,
in Luke chapter 12,
Jesus was speaking to a large crowd.
In fact, at Luke 12:1,
it says that there was “a crowd of so many
thousands [that] had gathered together
that they were stepping on one another.”
So try to imagine the scene.
All were trying to crowd closer to Jesus.
They wanted to listen to what he had to say.
There were some that were sitting;
some were standing.
They were on the ground;
they were on rocks;
they were trying to go under a shade tree.
Maybe it was sunny.
Maybe the sun was in their eyes.
Babies were crying.
So all kinds of distractions
were taking place.
But yet, Jesus continued
focusing on his message.
Yes, Jesus was speaking
to some of those followers
about important spiritual matters.
Some of those spiritual matters
were designed to prepare them
for opposition that lay ahead
and how they could tap
into Jehovah’s holy spirit and be successful.
And just then,
we read at Luke 12:13,
the man has his request.
He says: “Teacher, tell my brother
to divide the inheritance with me.”
What was the man thinking?
It had nothing to do with what Jesus
was trying to talk about to those
who were gathered.
Really, we can see that he was
weighed down with a distraction
—anxieties over personal issues
with his brother.
Rather than focusing in on what Jesus
had prepared for them
that would really prepare them
for the future,
he was distracted
with these mundane things.
And likely, he really didn’t hear
anything that Jesus had to say.
Not only was this man distracted
but he single-handedly
distracted thousands of others.
And no doubt those that were gathered
had their own anxieties
that they were thinking about.
But did the distractions from this man
become Jesus’ distractions?
No.
Rather, Jesus refused to be
drawn into this dispute
over some material things.
His response is found in our Scriptural theme
for today, Luke 12:14.
And you can imagine Jesus
looking out at the crowd,
finding that man and saying:
“Man, who appointed me judge
or arbitrator between you two?”
Jesus could have ruled on it.
He was perfect.
He could’ve stepped down
away from his area
that he was speaking from
and addressed the man.
But he did not.
It was not the time;
it was not the place.
And it really wasn’t Jesus’ place
to get involved.
Jesus did not allow this man
to break his focus—his spiritual focus—
and his real purpose
for coming to the earth.
And what is that?
John 3:17 says:
“For God did not send his Son into the world
for him to judge the world,
but for the world
to be saved through him.”
So Jesus knew that it was
the time and the place
to give instructions to his followers,
prepare them for the future,
point them towards
Jehovah and the Kingdom.
Knowing that we are imperfect
and easily distracted,
Jesus reminds us in verse 15
of chapter 12 what is needed.
He said to them, not just to the man,
but to all those gathered:
“Keep your eyes open
and guard against every sort of greed,
[or the footnote says, “covetousness”]
because even when a [man]
has an abundance,
his life does not result
from the things he possesses.”
So, what was Jesus trying to get across?
Yes, they had anxieties,
they had distractions,
but they needed to keep focused.
Their eyes needed to be looking
at what lay ahead
and how they could serve
Jehovah acceptably.
But he also warned against
allowing anxieties
to turn into distractions.
Note verse 29 of chapter 12.
He said:
“Stop seeking [or focusing on]
“what you will eat
and what you will drink,
and stop being in anxious suspense.”
And verse 30 goes on to say
that’s what happens in the world.
That’s what people are pursuing today.
But he said: “Stop.
Stop focusing; stop seeking.”
And we think about the word “anxious.”
Jesus used this quite a bit
within this chapter
and in other discussions
he had with his listeners.
What does the word “anxious” mean?
The Greek verb rendered “to be anxious”
means “to have the mind distracted.”
The word “distract,”
where does that come from?
It’s interesting to note that “distract”
comes from the Latin word tractus
meaning “to be pulled or dragged,”
and this gives us the root word “tract.”
So to “attract” would be
drawing toward something.
And to “distract” means to pull someone’s
attention away from something.
So this is what’s happening
every day of our lives.
We could be attracted to something
or distracted from something.
And, really, distractions
come in all shapes and sizes.
In fact, my little illustration here
will help us to appreciate
that they come in various colors,
various shades, and sizes.
Now, what happens with distractions?
We know that they
come in from external means
and sometimes from ourselves.
We cause some of our anxieties,
some of our distractions.
But if we do not keep our focus,
what eventually happens to distractions?
They become our main focus.
We’re not able to see past them.
We need to continually keep
our eyes open
so that we can continue
to serve Jehovah.
Well, distractions for all of us
come in various shapes and sizes.
It could be
the health concerns of our mate,
ourselves, our aging parents.
It could be the loss of a loved one
or how we can provide for our family.
It could be
the responsibilities that we have
—the assignments—
that could be weighing us down.
Or it could be our goal
to have more responsibilities.
We see other brothers
that are gaining responsibilities,
and we would wish to have those.
Well, all of these could become
the center of our life
and distract us from our service.
But we want to remember
that when anxieties
and distractions threaten us,
there’s something that we can do about it.
A quote that I found
that I thought was appropriate said,
“Starve your distractions;
feed your focus.”
Well, how do we starve our distractions
and feed our focus?
We go to something
that Jesus said 2,000 years ago
that has been the key
to faithful servants ever since,
and that is in chapter 12
in verse 31 of Luke.
He says: ‘Keep seeking
[or focusing on] the Kingdom,
and all these other things
will be added to you.’
And then in verse 34:
‘For where your treasure is,
that is where your heart will be also.’
So as we seek the Kingdom
and we treasure what Jehovah
has within that Kingdom,
we know that’s where our heart
will be and we can lessen our anxieties.
We think about faithful servants
in the past before Jesus, like David.
They had anxieties like you and me.
He was a king.
He had many opportunities
to be surrounded with spiritual people,
but even he faced times
that he needed help.
He treasured drawing close
to Jehovah with prayer.
In fact, one of my go-to scriptures,
and it may be one of yours,
is what he said at Psalm 94:19,
that’s Psalm 94:19:
“When anxieties [or the footnote says,
“disquieting thoughts”] overwhelmed me,
you comforted [me] and soothed me.”
That really helps us when we’re
going through anxieties and distractions.
Along with asking Jehovah for help,
calmness of heart,
and calmness of mind,
we do our best to apply
what Paul said at Hebrews 2:1:
“To pay more than the usual attention
to the things we have heard,
so that we never drift away.”
That’s what happened to the man
that raised the objection to Jesus.
His mind wandered,
he drifted away,
and he allowed others
to be distracted as well.
We want to copy Jesus Christ
who always had
that spiritual focus well in mind.
And we want to have
our service to Jehovah,
to the best of our ability,
to be focused without
allowing any distractions
to take us out of the race for life.