In the printed comments on today’s text,
a reference is made to Matthew 25
and Luke 19.
In Matthew 25,
we have the illustration of the talents
—three slaves who received talents.
One slave receives five, another two,
and a third slave receives one talent.
And in Luke 19,
the illustration is about ten slaves
with each slave receiving one mina.
These were all sums of money,
you could say, talents or the minas.
Both illustrations were given
some days before Jesus died,
and they were given in different places.
The illustration about the minas
was given in Jericho.
The illustration about the talents
that Jesus gave to his apostles
was on the Mount of Olives.
But there’s a key point
in each illustration that we’ll focus on:
The slave in each account
who did nothing with his talent or his mina
is described as “wicked.”
That’s a powerful denunciation
for someone to be called “wicked,”
particularly by the Master.
But to see how powerful it is,
at Matthew 6:13,
Jesus refers to Satan as “the wicked one.”
And Proverbs 10:7 says:
“The name of the wicked will rot.”
So that is a very strong term
to apply to any human.
But why?
Why are these two slaves
described as “wicked”?
Jesus didn’t say they broke
any of the Ten Commandments.
No, but they did something
that was extremely serious:
They failed to do something
with the talents or the minas
that they were given;
they were guilty of sins of omission.
In Jesus’ parable,
just to give you an example,
of the sheep and the goats
at Matthew 25:41-46,
you remember in the account
how the goats are condemned
to “everlasting cutting-off”
—not for doing something bad,
but because the scripture says
that they didn’t help Christ’s brothers.
Again, it was a sin of omission
—not doing something
that they should have done.
It’s also interesting to note
that in Matthew’s account,
the talents were given to the slaves
“according to [their] ability.”
So one received five, one received two,
and the third one, one talent.
Was the master being partial?
No, not at all.
The account explains clearly
that the talents were given to the slaves
“according to [their] ability.”
So that was really being considerate
on the part of the master
—the way he apportioned
the responsibilities
to work for his interests,
to increase his belongings.
And, you know,
that’s a very comforting thought
for all of us:
to realize that Jehovah
takes into account what we can do
—not comparing us
with others in the congregation.
We have to be careful
about feeling worthless
or devaluing our own worth,
because that can happen.
We can feel we just can’t ever do enough
to please Jehovah God,
or there’s just too much going on.
No, we just have to do
whatever we are able to do
and give our best to Jehovah God.
We never want to fall into the trap
that the sluggish and wicked slave fell into.
If you recall the account,
he started to criticize the master:
“I know that you reap
what you haven’t sowed.
“I know that you do this or that.
You’re harsh.”
He was really placing the blame
on the master
for his own inactivity
—for what he didn’t do.
But the master turned the tables on him,
and he said:
“You say that I’m that way.
Well, now ‘wicked slave.’ . . .”
And then he told him
that he wasn’t going to receive anything.
He was categorized as “wicked”!
So as long as we give our best
—we give from the heart—
Jehovah is going to bless us.
And there’s another interesting thing too
with the slaves
—the one slave who received five talents
and the one who received two talents.
The one who received two talents
gained two talents.
The one who received five gained five.
But the one who had two
and gained only two
didn’t look at the one
who gained five and say:
“I can’t do what he did.
I only received two talents.”
No, he was just happy with what he had.
Isn’t that a good lesson for us?
Be happy with you
and with what you’re able to do.
If you can reach out
and do more, wonderful!
Do it.
But we don’t want to start comparing,
“I can’t keep up with him or with her.”
That’s just a bad, bad idea,
and it will not benefit anyone.
What did the master say
to the slave who gained five talents
—a total of ten talents?
And that was a fortune in those days.
Well, let’s see what the scripture says,
Matthew 25
—Matthew 25:21.
And these are the words of the master
to the slave who gained five talents,
verse 21:
“His master said to him:
‘Well done, good and faithful slave!
“‘You were faithful over a few things.
“‘I will appoint you over many things.
Enter into the joy of your master.’”
What a reward from the master!
But what did he say to the slave
who gained only two talents?
Verse 23:
“His master said to him:
“‘Well done, good and faithful slave!
“‘You were faithful over a few things.
“‘I will appoint you over many things.
Enter into the joy of your master.’”
Same, same
—isn’t that what it is?
It was according to each one’s ability.
The reward in each case was the same:
the approval of the master and,
undoubtedly, additional responsibilities.
Put simply, the Master is Jesus Christ.
The talents refer to the responsibility
that Jehovah gives to his anointed servants;
they have to preach and make disciples.
That commission was given to the anointed.
We of the other sheep,
we have the responsibility
to do the same thing,
but that illustration was directed,
truly, to the anointed.
But there is a scripture that helps us
to appreciate what we need to do,
and it’s in Revelation chapter 22
—Revelation 22:17.
It’s not directly connected to the talents,
but it does give us direction
on what we all should do
—whether we’re of the anointed
or of the other sheep.
Revelation 22:17 says:
“And the spirit and the bride
keep on saying, ‘Come!’
and let anyone hearing
say, ‘Come!’”
Well, that would be “anyone hearing”
—we of the other sheep.
Because the bride—
We know who the bride is.
The bride is the anointed brothers of Christ.
And then it says:
“And let anyone thirsting come;
let anyone who wishes
take life’s water free.”
Well, “the spirit” says “Come!”
Yes, indeed!
At Pentecost, holy spirit
was poured out upon 120 disciples.
They could go out
and speak other languages.
They were sharing the good news
—the hope—
with Jews in Jerusalem at that time.
The holy spirit inspired men
to write the Scriptures;
holy spirit is behind the prophecies
that we read in the Bible.
And the holy spirit is saying “Come!”
—isn’t it?—
when you read a scripture to someone
about the time of the end
(2 Timothy 3 or other scriptures)
and they say,
“That’s what’s taking place today!”
“Come on, ‘Come!’”
The holy spirit is nudging,
urging people when they read God’s Word
and they understand it
and they accept what it says.
It says “Come!”
What about the bride?
Well, the bride’s been saying “Come!”
for a long time.
One hundred and twenty disciples
at Pentecost went down,
they preached in different languages,
and they were saying
to the Jews there, “Come!”
And then down through the centuries,
we know that the few there
who may have been of the bride class
did their best to serve Jehovah
and honor him.
But in these last days
is when it
has really expanded tremendously,
with the bride saying “Come!”
Think about it.
From 120 disciples at Pentecost
and preaching in one city
—in this case, Jerusalem—
the work of the bride
has increased
to 8,220,105 disciples
in 240 lands.
Has the bride been saying “Come!”?
Absolutely!
From one congregation at Pentecost
—you could call
the 120 disciples a congregation—
to 118,016 congregations worldwide.
The Master, Jesus,
must be very happy, joyful,
to see that his obedient slaves
have truly covered the earth
with the Kingdom message.
What a privilege we have
to share in that work!