‎Welcome to JW Broadcasting.
‎What do we have for you
on this month’s program?
‎We’ll hear the story of Cecil Goff,
‎an elder and regular pioneer
with over 80 years in Jehovah’s service.
‎What valuable lessons from his experience
‎can you apply to your life and ministry?
‎Whether we are young or old,
‎how can we make good decisions
when choosing entertainment?
‎In this dramatization,
we’ll see how a young brother named Danny
‎learns the value of sowing
‎what is wholesome in his mind.
‎Has a challenge in your life
ever been so severe
‎that you felt overwhelmed?
‎When anxiety stirs within us,
‎this new music video
‎can reassure us
of Jehovah’s loving support.
‎This is JW Broadcasting for September 2018.
‎We start this month
with the story of Brother Cecil Goff.
‎Cecil is 99 years old
‎and has served Jehovah for over 80 years.
‎He’s spent many of those years
in full-time service.
‎He had the privilege
to serve at Brooklyn Bethel,
‎as a circuit overseer,
as a Gilead-trained missionary,
‎and as a branch overseer in Cuba.
‎As you watch his interview,
‎try to determine why he’s convinced
‎that his life
in Jehovah’s service was more rewarding
‎than anything the world had to offer.
‎My name is Cecil Joseph Goff.
‎I began to lose eyesight in the ’70’s.
‎I can’t see to read or anything.
‎I see only peripheral vision.
‎I was playing in a country band
at a very young age.
‎Well, I played the tenor banjo,
tenor guitar, and I played the mandolin.
‎It was my life.
‎And yet, when I began reading and studying,
‎really, I wanted to stick with that,
‎and I left the band.
‎I started pioneering,
‎and then they assigned me
to Texarkana, Texas.
‎Another brother and I were stopped
‎as we were holding the phonograph up,
‎and I was playing it for a lady at the door.
‎Why, here about 15 or 20 men surrounded me.
‎I asked him, “How did you enjoy it?”
‎And he said: “That’s not the question.
‎My question is, Do you salute the flag?”
‎And I said, “Let me explain it.”
‎He said: “I don’t want an explanation.
‎I just want to know yes or no;
do you or do you not?”
‎I said, “I do not.”
‎He threw me up in the air.
‎I fell on my back in the street there,
‎and then about three of them
got on top of me.
‎He said: “You’re going
to salute the flag or eat it.
‎Bring me that flag over there.”
‎I was praying to Jehovah
to remember me in the resurrection.
‎About that time, several women
ran out of the houses on both sides of us:
‎“Leave those men alone.
They didn’t bother you.
‎Leave them alone.
Let them go.”
‎So they got off of me, and they left us
like a bunch of beaten kittens.
‎I was asked to go to Brooklyn Bethel
and become a member of the Bethel home.
‎Brother Knorr asked me,
“Do you know how to use the typewriter?”
‎I said, “Yes, I can type.”
‎He said: “Well, I’m going
to put you on a machine.
‎“It’s called a Linotype.
‎It has three keyboards.”
‎And he said: “And it will take you
about two years to learn it.
‎Are you willing to accept it?”
‎And I said, “Yes, I will.”
‎So I was put on the Linotype.
‎I got married
in the fall of 1945 and left Bethel.
‎Well, we were invited in 1949
‎to go into the circuit work.
‎We were in the 21st class of Gilead.
‎We enjoyed that course very much.
‎We received an assignment for Cuba,
‎and I was assigned as branch overseer.
‎And in ’63,
‎the police car came
‎up to the branch
at about ten o’clock at night.
‎I was told to take my papers,
‎and we went
over to the police station, and so forth.
‎And sure enough,
soon thereafter, here comes an official.
‎He said, “You have to leave Cuba
‎because you’re not in favor
of the Cuban government.”
‎A person asked
a policeman standing close by, he said,
‎“Who are these people
that are being sent out of the country?”
‎And they said: “Over there,”
‎talking about me,
‎“see that gangster man over there?
‎He’s the head of it.”
‎So then we got on the plane
and headed back.
‎I got in contact with Brooklyn Bethel,
‎talked to Brother Knorr, and he said,
‎“As soon as you can,
in the next day or two, come back to Bethel.”
‎And Brother Knorr said,
“You got back just in time
‎“to get back on the Linotype machine
‎to set up a new book we have in Spanish.”
‎So I did that and got on the Linotype.
‎And then Brother Knorr told me, he said,
‎“In 1964, we’re going to have
a ten-month course in Gilead
‎for all branch people
who have branch experience.”
‎Oh, it was very, very good.
‎We studied a lot, not only the Bible
‎(we studied a lot on the Bible,
discourse and everything)
‎but we studied a lot of branch material too.
‎Above everything else,
our love for Jehovah should continue to grow.
‎He knows our thoughts, our mind, our heart.
‎He goes far beyond what man can do.
‎And whatever his decision is,
‎I’ve learned to understand
that it’s the best decision.
‎I have learned that if we obey
what the organization says
‎and what the Bible says,
then we’re doing Jehovah’s will;
‎and that’s my concern
‎—no regrets whatsoever, none.
‎Maybe I could’ve done more at times,
‎but I’m certainly glad
that I have taken advantage of it
‎as much as I have up until now.
‎And it’s been a happy life.
‎And I have seen Jehovah’s hand
‎time and again.
‎Brother Goff has led
a full, happy life in theocratic service.
‎But do you wonder,
‎‘How was he
able to persevere for so many years
‎and through so many different assignments?’
‎Cecil learned the value
‎of letting Jehovah and his organization
‎shape his thinking.
‎But he had to make
a choice as a young man,
‎a choice all of Jehovah’s servants
have to make.
‎And that’s the basis
for our discussion this month.
‎The theme is
‎“Stop Being Molded
by This System of Things.”
‎In describing godly wisdom,
‎the ancient man Job
‎recognized it as priceless.
‎At Job 28:17, he said:
‎“Gold and glass cannot be compared to it.”
‎Glass
—it has been around for centuries,
‎even back in Job’s day.
‎However,
what revolutionized glass production
‎was the invention of glassblowing.
‎By blowing through a hollow tube,
‎a glassblower can quickly mold
superheated molten glass
‎into a specific shape.
‎Satan’s system has developed the art
‎of shaping the minds of people
‎into fragile glass vessels
with little useful purpose.
‎In fact,
Romans 9:22 refers to such ones
‎as “vessels of wrath made fit for destruction.”
‎Find with me Romans 12:2.
‎What is responsible for molding and shaping
‎the inclinations of the people of the world?
‎Romans 12:2:
‎“And stop being molded
by this system of things,
‎“but be transformed
by making your mind over,
‎“so that you
may prove to yourselves
‎the good and acceptable
and perfect will of God.”
‎To counteract “being molded,”
the verse said:
‎“But be transformed
by making your mind over.”
‎So the molding of this system
is related to our thinking
‎—the shaping of our minds.
‎Well, what evil air
is blown down the hollow tube?
‎It’s identified quite clearly for us
at Ephesians 2:2, 3.
‎Concerning a Christian’s previous
unclean thinking and behavior,
‎verse 2 says:
‎“In which you at one time walked
‎“according to the system
of things of this world,
‎“according to the ruler
of the authority of the air,
‎the spirit that is now at work
in the sons of disobedience.”
‎The verse makes clear
that this “system of things” has a ruler.
‎Satan is called
“the ruler of the authority of the air.”
‎The verse indicates
that “the air” is “the spirit” of the world.
‎Well, with such a mind-set,
‎what kind of behavior
does the thinking of the world lead to?
‎Verse 3:
‎“Yes, among them
we all at one time conducted ourselves
‎“in harmony with the desires of our flesh,
‎“carrying out the will
of the flesh and of our thoughts,
‎and we were naturally children
of wrath just as the rest.”
‎For this reason, they become
‎“vessels of wrath made fit for destruction.”
‎Glassblowers often work
in groups known as “shops.”
‎An apprentice dips
a hollow blowpipe into the liquid glass.
‎By twirling it,
he gathers a blob of molten glass.
‎He shapes the blob by rolling it
‎on a smooth surface called a marver.
‎He then passes the tube
to the gaffer, or shop master.
‎He blows air into the tube
and fashions the glass into a globe.
‎If a wine glass is being made,
‎the tube is then passed to the stem-maker
‎and another gather of glass is attached.
‎It is then shaped
by means of long-pointed tongs
‎to form the stem.
‎Then, another gather of hot glass
is added to the stem.
‎The craftsman rolls the tube
on the arm of his chair.
‎He forms the base of the glass.
‎We will briefly consider four ways
‎that this system subtly tries to shape
‎our mind into Satan’s designs.
‎The first is harmful peer pressure.
‎Now, often this is just an apprentice
in Satan’s shop
‎—maybe fellow students in school,
fellow workers on the job.
‎Don’t you think Satan will try to capitalize
‎on these circumstantial relationships?
‎Absolutely!
‎Peer pressure
—it can have an influence on our mind.
‎They may make fun
of our wholesome morals,
‎our clean speech, our dignified dress.
‎That is pressure.
‎Possibly, they invite us to do things
that we know will lead to no good.
‎They are twirling us
‎with their thinking, with their taunts,
‎or maybe with their flattery and temptation.
‎They are rolling things
over and over in our mind.
‎Turn to 2 Peter 2:18, 19.
‎And as you read this,
‎can you pick out a word
that is equivalent to peer pressure?
‎Let’s read
‎2 Peter 2:18, 19:
‎“They make high-sounding statements
that are empty [like air].
‎“By appealing to the desires of the flesh
and with acts of brazen conduct,
‎“they entice [that’s peer pressure] people
‎“who have just escaped
from those who live in error.
‎“While they are promising them freedom,
‎“they themselves are slaves of corruption;
‎“for if anyone is overcome by someone,
‎he is his slave.”
‎The verse says that if we are overcome
by peer pressure—enticed—
‎we actually become a “slave” of that person.
‎That is scary!
‎It’s dangerous!
‎Peer pressure is deceptively strong.
‎Well, what is another way
that the spirit of this system
‎can shape our thinking?
‎You recall that the apprentice
passed the glassblowing tube
‎to the gaffer who blew air
into the glass, giving it shape.
‎What does Satan and this system
next use to mold our thinking?
‎Enticing advertisements.
‎Like the air of a glassblower,
‎advertisements often have little substance.
‎For example,
that product we decided to buy
‎when we last went shopping.
‎Maybe it was a brand of clothing
‎or a brand of dry cereal
we bought for breakfast.
‎Is that always purely a personal,
rational decision on our part?
‎Or did advertising
‎subtly but powerfully affect our choice?
‎Now, it’s not that all advertising
is bad or misleading.
‎But the more
we allow ourselves to be influenced by it,
‎the more we are in danger
of being led into a materialistic way of life.
‎For example,
instead of dry cereal,
‎are we now influenced
to buy that flashy-looking sports car?
‎Turn to 1 John 2:15-17.
‎This system inflates our thinking
by means of “things.”
‎First John 2:15, 16:
‎“Do not love either the world
or the things in the world.
‎“If anyone loves the world,
the love of the Father is not in him;
‎“because everything in the world
‎“—the desire of the flesh
and the desire of the eyes
‎“and the showy display
of one’s means of life—
‎“does not originate with the Father,
‎but originates with the world.”
‎Why do we need to resist catering
‎to advertisements
that feed the spirit of the world?
‎Verse 17:
‎“Furthermore, the world is passing away
‎“and so is its desire,
‎but the one who does
the will of God remains forever.”
‎Remember Eve!
‎Satan advertised the forbidden fruit.
‎The scripture says
it was “desirable to the eyes,
‎. . . the tree was pleasing to look at.”
‎She succumbed to the advertisement
‎with disastrous results.
‎Similarly, Satan used advertisements
to try to reshape Jesus’ focus.
‎Matthew chapter 4 says that Satan
‎“showed him all the kingdoms of the world,”
‎offering them
in exchange for one act of worship.
‎Jesus simply turned him off.
‎Don’t be overly influenced by advertisements.
‎What’s the next aspect of this system
that can distort our minds?
‎Bad associations.
‎It is as if the gaffer
has now passed the glassblowing tube
‎ to the stem-maker.
‎He takes another gather of molten glass
‎and attaches it to our globe.
‎Then he stretches that associated blob
‎into the form of a stem.
‎Well, we already talked about peer pressure,
‎but that often comes
from those who are not necessarily
‎our close associates.
‎What we’re discussing now is our decisions
‎about whom we spend a lot of time with.
‎People who don’t love Jehovah
can stretch and misshape our minds,
‎providing a stem or a handle
for the world to hold us by.
‎Turn to 1 Corinthians 15:33.
‎Sometimes we hear the phrase
that some of the kids in school
‎are nicer than some of the kids
in the congregation.
‎But usually, nicer actually means more fun
‎rather than more wholesome.
‎But let’s look
at 1 Corinthians 15:33 in its context.
‎What did the apostle Paul mean
‎when he said to the Corinthians
“bad associations”?
‎First Corinthians 15:33:
‎“Do not be misled.
‎Bad associations spoil useful habits.”
‎But what made these ones bad association?
‎Let’s see it in context.
‎Look at 1 Corinthians 15:12:
‎“Now if it is being preached
that Christ has been raised from the dead,
‎how is it that some among you say
there is no resurrection of the dead?”
‎Well, what was the initial problem
with these associates?
‎They did not believe the same way.
‎Why would that make them bad associations?
‎Because what an associate believes
‎will eventually affect our thinking,
‎and our thinking affects our behavior.
‎Notice how Paul describes this.
‎Look at 1 Corinthians 15:32.
‎What good is it to endure
the rigors of the Christian race for life
‎if there is no resurrection,
no future, no hope?
‎Verse 32:
‎“If like other men,
I have fought with wild beasts at Ephesus,
‎“of what good is it to me?
‎“If the dead are not to be raised up,
‎‘let us eat and drink,
for tomorrow we are to die.’”
‎May all of us avoid bad association
‎whether in person,
on TV, or on the Internet.
‎What’s a fourth means by which Satan
‎attempts to fashion us,
reshaping our thinking?
‎Higher education.
‎Most of us remember
the January 2015 JW Broadcasting program
‎hosted by Brother Morris
of the Governing Body.
‎He focused on the value of divine education.
‎But he also reaffirmed
‎the dangers
of pursuing higher secular education.
‎Its whole purpose is for learning
—influencing one’s thinking.
‎And while a person’s intention
might be just to create
‎a stable base for his secular future,
‎his decision could expose him
‎to unscriptural ideas and practices.
‎Back to the glass shop.
‎Recall that another gather of hot glass
‎is added to the end of the stem.
‎The craftsman then rolls the tube
backward and forward.
‎He forms the base for the glass.
‎Well, we will say no more about this topic
‎other than what Brother Morris
has already shared.
‎You might want to go back
and review that broadcast.
‎However,
we would like to read 1 Timothy 6:20, 21:
‎“Timothy, guard what
has been entrusted to you
‎“[that’s divine education],
‎“turning away from the empty speeches
that violate what is holy
‎“and from the contradictions
‎“of the falsely called ‘knowledge.’
‎“By making a show of such knowledge,
‎some have deviated from the faith.”
‎Unfortunately, in an effort to make
‎a stable base for one’s financial future,
‎many “have deviated from the faith.”
‎In the visuals of a glassblowing shop,
‎we observed the skill of the workers involved.
‎And that shop obviously produces
‎beautiful, useful glass vessels.
‎Satan’s glass shop
is also skilled at shaping one’s thinking.
‎But what does it produce?
‎Instead of a person becoming
a valuable vessel that Jehovah can use,
‎Satan is actually mass-producing
‎worthless vessels that Jehovah cannot use.
‎What could you do
with this misshaped creation?
‎Nothing
—it is useless.
‎At the outset,
Romans 9:22 was quoted.
‎Those who conform
to Satan’s system are referred to
‎as “vessels of wrath
made fit for destruction.”
‎Jehovah has paid a high price for us.
‎Gold and glass cannot be compared to it.
‎May we make over our minds
by applying godly wisdom.
‎Glorify Jehovah
as a vessel that he can use.
‎First Corinthians 6:20
concludes this discussion nicely, saying:
‎“For you were bought with a price.
‎By all means, glorify God in your body.”
‎How else may the world try to mold us?
‎Another way
is through the entertainment it produces.
‎How can we choose
entertainment that will enhance
‎and not taint our sacrifice to Jehovah?
‎In the following dramatization,
‎notice how a fellow Christian
‎helps a young brother to make better choices.
‎I promised Akil I’d go out
in service with him after school.
‎Hey, we’re just waiting in the car.
‎And I kept my word,
‎but my head just wasn’t in it.
‎Akil could tell, so he tried
to see if everything was OK.
‎Honestly, at the time,
‎I would have rather been playing
video games,
‎but I couldn’t tell him that.
‎I mean,
he’s a pioneer, a ministerial servant.
‎He wouldn’t understand.
‎Later that week,
‎Akil invited me
to go mountain biking with some friends.
‎It was actually really fun.
‎. . . and your croissant.
‎Great, thanks.
‎Please let me know
if there’s anything else, OK?
‎All right. Thanks.
‎So, Danny,
you’re obviously good at biking.
‎What else do you like to do for fun?
‎OK, so I have this game and it’s called . . .
‎Soon I was showing him my video games.
‎And surprisingly,
he liked video games too.
‎But he said he chose to be selective.
‎He began to describe
the gladiators in ancient Rome.
‎People would come from all over
‎to watch them fight to the death.
‎And while the spectators
weren’t in any physical danger,
‎the real danger came over time.
‎Repeatedly watching
the bloodshed and the killing,
‎it was dulling their senses,
and they wanted more of it.
‎This was a big test
for the Christians who lived back then.
‎Akil helped me to reason on the scripture
‎at Romans 12:9:
‎“Abhor what is wicked;
cling to what is good.”
‎So, Danny,
‎the games may have changed over time,
‎but the violence is still the same.
‎I like video games,
‎but I avoid the ones
that promote what Jehovah hates.
‎Jehovah’s people can still have fun.
‎And, yeah,
we can even play video games.
‎I just want to make wise choices.
‎I want to show Jehovah
that I hate wickedness
‎and make his heart glad.
‎This video is part of a series of videos.
‎We’re pleased to announce
‎that all 17 episodes
will be made available
‎under a new
“Principles for Daily Living” category.
‎It can be found in both the “Family”
and “Our Meetings and Ministry” sections.
‎As we saw in this episode,
‎our choice of entertainment
can affect our worship.
‎We could be exposing
ourselves to Satan’s thinking.
‎If you’re enticed
by entertainment that displeases Jehovah,
‎what Bible principles will help you?
‎Chapter 6 of the “God’s Love” book
‎features a box entitled
‎“What Entertainment Should I Choose?”
‎Make the scriptures in this feature
‎a matter of prayer
and discussion in family worship.
‎They will help you “cling to what is good.”
‎But at times ‘clinging to the good’
‎includes receiving discipline,
‎which can be painful.
‎How can we look beyond any pain
‎to the benefits of divine correction?
‎At a Bethel morning worship,
‎Brother Anthony Morris,
a member of the Governing Body,
‎discussed how a proper view of discipline
‎brings us closer to Jehovah.
‎This morning
‎I thought I’d discuss the matter
‎of how a proper view of discipline
‎keeps us close to Jehovah.
‎Now, in the context of today’s text
‎about Jehovah correcting
‎to the proper degree,
‎he’s talking to his people
about being brought back to their land.
‎He was not going to exterminate them
or leave them,
‎and it helps us to appreciate
that he wanted them
‎to keep their relationship with him.
‎Now, today we receive
discipline in various ways.
‎It might be from personal Bible study.
‎And I was excited this morning
‎(I don’t know when it happened,
maybe last night)
‎to see that we have in JW Library®
‎where we can put our personal notes,
‎and I got started with some already.
‎So that’ll be like thoughts
or discipline from Jehovah
‎that is just between him and ourselves
‎—a very beneficial and wise way
to go when it comes to discipline.
‎It keeps us from veering off
in our relationship with him.
‎It might be something
we read in a publication;
‎might hear in a talk at a meeting,
at an assembly,
‎or convention;
something in a JW Broadcast
‎—various ways, any number of ways
Jehovah will discipline us.
‎And we need to remember
‎that he does it
so that we remain close to him.
‎The problem is discipline
is not easy to take.
‎It requires humility.
‎And the proper view of discipline
is found here in Proverbs chapter 3,
‎and this gives us the Scriptural basis
‎to have this proper view of discipline
‎that’ll keep us close to Jehovah God.
‎Now, notice verses 11 and 12
of Proverbs chapter 3:
‎“My son, do not reject
the discipline of Jehovah,
‎“and do not loathe his reproof,
‎“for those whom Jehovah loves
he reproves,
‎just as a father does a son
in whom he delights.”
‎So how might we reject
the discipline of Jehovah?
‎Well, put yourself
in a position of being counseled.
‎It’s come to the point
where overseers and elders
‎have had to sit down with you.
‎Now, for some,
as soon as the counsel begins to flow,
‎there’s this quickness to be upset,
‎to justify, to feel picked on.
‎Well, Jehovah is saying, ‘Don’t reject this.’
‎If they’re using the Scriptures
and thoughts from publications,
‎view it as coming from Jehovah
so that we can stay close to him.
‎Now, to give you an idea,
‎sometimes reading something
will bring us close to Jehovah,
‎especially if we veered off
and didn’t even realize it.
‎I’m going to go way back
to some examples
‎of Jehovah’s sheep
reading something in The Watchtower,
‎and it just disciplined them
so that they could get close to Jehovah.
‎And it goes way back to 1982,
‎and it had to do with TV serials,
or soap operas.
‎Some are saying,
“Well, that’s a long time ago.”
‎Well, the fact is nothing has changed.
‎Some of these soap operas
are still on that had the name
‎that they had in 1982.
‎They still have it.
‎So many readers
personally benefited from the counsel.
‎The counsel still applies
that was found there.
‎But I think it’s very touching
and commendable
‎for the ones who read that
that they recognized it.
‎It impacted their relationship with Jehovah,
‎and they wanted to get close to him.
‎Now, the cover on The Watchtower was
‎“TV Serials—Can They Corrupt the Heart?”
‎And in the opening article, we did say:
‎“Millions of women and men of all ages,
‎races and backgrounds
will rarely miss a show.”
‎Well, now you can record them
and have them anytime that you like.
‎It’s still an ongoing problem
and an issue for a true Christian,
‎a worshipper of Jehovah,
to make sure we’re not being corrupted
‎by soap operas, or TV serials.
‎Now, after the articles came out,
‎we had some write in
to explain what happened to them.
‎And so months later,
after this 1982 issue of The Watchtower
‎(that was December 1),
‎we went
to the ’83 Watchtower, December 1,
‎and here’s the response
from some of the readers.
‎And I found it very commendable.
‎I think you’ll appreciate the humility
because it takes humility
‎to accept and have
the proper view of discipline.
‎So one of the dangers
‎that the brothers
were warned about is that
‎you can get emotionally attached
to the characters in the show.
‎So here’s what one wrote:
‎“I had grown up
watching this one soap opera
‎“and the character ‘Julie’
was just like my ‘friend.’ . . .
‎“One day ‘Julie’ had an accident
‎“that left her beautiful face
badly scarred . . .
‎“I was in front of the TV set every day
‎“to make sure
she was going to pull through.
‎“That night as I was saying my prayers,
‎“before I even thought
what I was saying,
‎I prayed,
‘And Jehovah, please bless Julie.’”
‎Well, she admits:
“‘I was shocked.
‎“‘[She should’ve been.]
‎“‘This plea to Jehovah for Julie
had come from my heart!’
‎“Realizing how involved
she had become,
‎“she stopped watching these programs.
‎“She wrote: ‘If all readers
‎“‘will take your article
on TV serials to heart,
‎“‘they will feel a real sense of freedom,
‎since our own everyday problems
are enough to cope with.’”
‎So, you see, our sister
had the proper view of discipline,
‎and she was able
to keep close to Jehovah.
‎Now, another one,
after expressing appreciation, wrote:
‎“I realized that I was ‘addicted’
to soap operas,
‎“and that I had to do something about it.
‎“I wondered, too, if my relationship
with Jehovah could be affected.
‎“How could I have ‘them’ as friends
‎“and also be a friend to Jehovah?
‎“I had to quit all at once
‎—it was the only way,
and how hard it was!” she admits.
‎So, what did she
have to do to break free?
‎She had to unplug her TV.
‎She’d go outdoors
and work in the garden, call somebody
‎—anything to stay busy
so that she wouldn’t go back
‎to watching those soap operas.
‎She took time for personal Bible study
‎—that’ll keep you close to Jehovah—
‎preparing for her meetings,
and other spiritual things.
‎And then she confesses:
“How much better I felt!
‎“It has been over two years now
[from this last writing]
‎“since I have seen
those so-called friends.
‎“I must admit
that at times I still wonder
‎“what is going on with them,
but I fight it. . . .
‎Perhaps many others
who have not yet broken free will now.”
‎She says:
‘Thank you, Jehovah and you brothers,
‎for exposing
this “good-for-nothing thing.”’
‎Then, finally, this third one says:
‎“I cried when I read the articles,
‎“for I discovered that my heart
was no longer complete toward Jehovah.
‎“I promised my God
‎“that I would no longer be
a slave to these serials
‎“and asked him to help me
to get out of my home
‎“on the day of the program. . . .
‎“Two days later,
I was invited to attend a Bible study
‎“on the very day and time of ‘my’ serial.
‎“I happily accepted. . . .
‎“[and notice] I now feel
closer to Jehovah,
‎“and my relationship with him
is more intimate.
‎How good Jehovah is
to discipline us through his Word!”
‎Yes, she had
the proper view of discipline.
‎Now, finally,
let’s look in Hebrews chapter 12,
‎and we appreciate
these sincere comments
‎and the counsel there certainly applies.
‎Any kind of entertainment
‎that has that corrupting influence
‎would be avoided by a true Christian.
‎So here at Hebrews chapter 12,
‎notice verse 11:
‎“True, no discipline seems
for the present to be joyous,
‎“but it is painful;
‎“yet afterward, it yields
the peaceable fruit of righteousness
‎to those who have been trained by it.”
‎So discipline is painful,
‎but “the peaceable fruit
of righteousness”
‎makes it worth it
to have a proper view of the discipline
‎and to accept it humbly
‎so that we can remain close
to our precious Father, Jehovah.
‎Discipline helps us
reshape our thinking and actions,
‎drawing us closer to our Grand Creator.
‎It may come from God’s Word,
‎publications produced
by “the faithful and discreet slave,”
‎a parent, or mature fellow Christians.
‎No matter how we receive discipline,
‎always remember what Proverbs 3:12 says:
‎“Those whom Jehovah loves he reproves,
‎just as a father does a son
in whom he delights.”
‎But what if the world’s thinking
has molded you,
‎not by choice, but by circumstance?
‎You’ll appreciate the story
of sister Guzel Gainanshina,
‎who was not raised
as one of Jehovah’s Witnesses.
‎In her youth,
Guzel searched for fulfillment
‎through competitive sports.
‎Even though she achieved
some level of success,
‎what helped her
to find a true purpose in life?
‎I lived in the north,
with the glorious dark, starlit sky
‎and the beauty of fir trees.
‎I thought it was
the most wonderful place in the world.
‎My mom was always drawing
my attention to the beauty of creation.
‎And she always told me,
‎“My daughter, it’s so important
to live your life in the right way.”
‎And the questions
that stayed with me were:
‎‘So why are we alive?
‎Why is there so much
suffering, injustice, pain?’
‎When I was 18,
I took up a form of karate
‎known as Kyokushinkai.
‎Just imagine a large number
of people in kimonos, standing in rows
‎bravely and without a shadow of fear,
‎working on improving their blows
and striving to progress.
‎I thought: ‘This is it!
This is what I’ve been looking for!’
‎I set the goal of reaching
the next world championships,
‎winning a high place,
‎and immortalizing myself
so that my name would remain
‎and generations would remember me.
‎Among those sportsmen, although I saw
a lot of nice words and slogans,
‎not everything was as pure as I’d hoped for.
‎And then on one occasion,
I was sitting down
‎and feelings of emptiness
‎just wouldn’t leave me alone.
‎And for the first time in my life,
‎I talked to God.
‎And then I prayed:
‎“I don’t understand you.
‎“Why is there so much beauty in the world
‎“and yet so much suffering?
‎“Is that really what you want
‎—for us to live like this?”
‎I prayed, I guess, for about four hours.
‎You know, the strongest feeling
of emptiness and loneliness
‎is that of a creation
‎without its Creator.
‎And I was so lonely at that time.
‎And a while afterwards,
there was a knock at my door.
‎It was Jehovah’s Witnesses.
‎I started studying the Bible.
‎It was so wonderful!
‎On one occasion,
the sister who studied with me
‎looked up at me,
and when she looked at those bruises
‎and those beaten-up knuckles,
‎she took a deep breath and shook her head.
‎I said, “Is there something wrong?”
‎She said, “You know, I’m in great pain.”
‎I said, “Why are you in pain?”
‎She said: “Well,
‎“I’m looking at your hands,
your elbows, your battered legs, all of that.
‎Doesn’t it hurt?”
‎I said, “Well, yes.”
‎And she said, “You know,
it hurts me to see you in pain.”
‎And I started to understand
that Jehovah is the true God
‎and that this really was the truth.
‎It was difficult.
‎The pressure from relatives
and friends was very strong.
‎But the most difficult thing
‎that I had to battle with
was my strong attachment to karate.
‎Just a year remained
until the world championships.
‎I had prepared for them.
‎I had been working
toward that goal for five years.
‎Glory can seem really sweet
‎when you are the victor,
when your opponents fall to the ground.
‎So I flew to the world championships.
‎When I made it to the last four winners
‎and I had to fight for third place,
‎I wanted to ask my trainer
to let me stop. Why?
‎Because I couldn’t feel
a single place on my body
‎—everything was beaten up.
‎But he said:
‎“You know, we love you so much.
Go for it!”
‎And at that moment,
it felt as though I was weighing love
‎—the world’s love
‎and the love of Jehovah’s organization.
‎It seemed to me
that the world was saying:
‎“We love you.
Now just go and die!”
‎But the love in the organization says,
‎“It hurts me to see you in pain.”
‎I realized that the world
can’t give you what it doesn’t have.
‎It doesn’t know how to love.
‎But, nevertheless, I went to the fight
‎and became the bronze medalist.
‎And when I stood on the podium of glory,
‎I understood that glory
among people who don’t love you
‎weighs no more than emptiness.
‎If a person dedicates his life
‎to glorifying himself,
he will always meet
‎with disappointment and emptiness.
‎So I made the firm decision
to escape from karate.
‎I started preaching,
and I was baptized in 2005
‎at the summer convention in Kurgan.
‎Later, I started full-time service.
‎I learned the Tatar language
so that I could serve in that territory.
‎Now, when in the evenings
‎I look up at the starry sky,
I feel not hopelessness,
‎but tremendous joy
‎because I know who is behind it all:
‎our loving Creator, Jehovah God.
‎Guzel had been “molded
by this system of things,”
‎but she was “transformed
by making [her] mind over.”
‎The literal cuts and bruises
Guzel suffered healed with time,
‎but she found true comfort
from the One described at Psalm 147:3,
‎who “heals the brokenhearted”
‎and who “binds up” the emotional “wounds”
‎inflicted by this system of things.
‎Her example shows that no matter
our situation or background,
‎the beautiful truths of God’s Word
can change us.
‎It may feel like a leap of faith
‎to leave behind secular pursuits
to reach spiritual goals.
‎Some have made
this leap after investing years
‎of training, education, and financial resources
‎toward a career in the world.
‎If that’s true for you,
‎rest assured that you are not alone.
‎Our next segment
will introduce you to young ones
‎who resisted the pressure to conform
‎to the world’s view of success.
‎Right now I am serving
in the Central America branch,
‎and I have the opportunity to work
with extraordinary brothers and sisters
‎—both here and in other parts of the world.
‎My name is Rogelio.
‎I’m part of the Art Department,
‎and I’m a digital illustrator.
‎Music really means the world to me.
‎I am Joyce; I’m a pioneer,
‎and I sing alto in the Bethel chorus.
‎My name is Lou-Len,
‎and I serve as a regular pioneer
in a congregation where there’s a need.
‎I love doing that.
‎My life is wonderful.
‎Seeing people’s faces light up
when you teach them God’s name
‎or when you tell them
of Jehovah’s promises for us
‎fills me with great joy.
‎My name is Josué Martell.
‎I serve as a regular pioneer
‎and as an elder in the congregation.
‎Ever since I was little,
‎I’ve always loved playing soccer,
and that was my biggest dream.
‎My goal was to become
a professional soccer player.
‎The truth is, setting goals
was always difficult for me
‎because I always had two passions,
‎‘Am I a servant of Jehovah or an artist?’
‎My goal was to become
the best gymnast in the world.
‎At that moment,
‎gymnastics were number one in my life.
‎I played at big festivals.
‎Standing ovations
‎—that was amazing.
‎I was surrounded by non-Witnesses
‎who were using drugs,
smoking, and swearing.
‎My trainer had mapped out
a complete training program
‎with the Olympics as a goal.
‎This made me feel trapped.
‎I started thinking,
‘What do I want to do with my life?’
‎More importantly,
‘What does Jehovah want?’
‎When I was studying design,
I was already a regular pioneer.
‎It wasn’t easy for me
to come to the understanding
‎that the one
who really matters is Jehovah.
‎When I was 16 years old,
‎different teams started offering me
high-paying contracts.
‎I felt a lot of pressure,
and it was a temptation
‎because they would constantly
call me and come to my house.
‎I noticed that when the players
played the sport,
‎they were happy,
but afterwards they weren’t.
‎My mother was in the full-time service,
and I saw her happiness.
‎That motivated me because I too wanted
‎to experience that lasting happiness.
‎I felt a little guilty
when I thought of how much of myself
‎I was giving to design
and art and all of that.
‎So that’s when I made my decision.
‎I decided to leave university
and focus on my service.
‎I realized that for a long time
I hadn’t been growing spiritually.
‎I prayed intensely to Jehovah.
‎I asked: “Do I know you?
‎Do I live the way you would want?”
‎And after that,
‎I stopped performing with non-Witnesses.
‎I prayed to Jehovah.
‎And then, at the convention,
‎we received the DVD Young People Ask
—What Will I Do With My Life?
‎That really was Jehovah’s answer
‎to my prayer.
‎In the Bible it says
‎that “the truth will set you free.”
‎That freedom is something
I never used to feel.
‎I love working together
with other sisters in the ministry
‎and seeing how they share
my enthusiasm for making return visits
‎and conducting Bible studies.
‎It’s just wonderful to see!
‎To wake up each day knowing
‎that I am going to do something new
for Jehovah is extraordinary.
‎It’s an unbelievable blessing;
it’s like living a dream.
‎I feel that I belong
to a global organization
‎and we are all going
in the same direction.
‎It’s something really wonderful for me.
‎To sing for Jehovah
is the most beautiful privilege
‎I could ever imagine.
‎One of the biggest blessings
‎is that I have a real friendship
with Jehovah
‎and friendships with my brothers and sisters
—young or old.
‎It doesn’t matter.
‎I am really happy
that when Jehovah looks at me,
‎I feel his approval.
‎That makes me happy.
‎My trust in Jehovah has grown stronger.
‎The way I communicate with him
continues to improve.
‎And I also love my assignment
‎of being a regular pioneer,
an elder, and being able to support
‎the brothers and sisters.
‎To continue to be among Jehovah’s people,
‎that’s the joy I was looking for
‎—and I found it!
‎The world tries to pass off the thrill
of recognition or fame as fulfillment,
‎but do not be deceived.
‎These fine examples show
that doing your best for Jehovah
‎leads to real contentment.
‎His smile of approval is worth
‎more than any accolade
this system of things could ever bestow.
‎Satan works tirelessly
‎to wear us down physically and emotionally.
‎How can we have the courage
‎to stand up to challenges
and pressures to give up?
‎The loving support
true Christians give to one another
‎is illustrated in this month’s music video,
‎entitled Do Not Be Afraid.
‎It’s hard to see clear
when challenges appear.
‎We get lost inside
the emotions we feel.
‎When adversity
strikes us down,
‎No need to stay
on the ground.
‎Look up;
Reach out.
‎Do not be afraid,
for He is with us,
‎Saving us with His right hand
of righteousness.
‎So when it gets
hard sometimes,
‎We need to remember
we’re not alone.
‎No, we’re never alone.
‎Just pray;
Do not be afraid.
‎He gives us friends
who stick by our side.
‎Their prayers of faith and love
are always right on time.
‎And each day
when we read His Word,
‎It gives us
the strength to endure.
‎When we’re down,
We’ll reach out.
‎Do not be afraid,
for He is with us,
‎Saving us with His right hand
of righteousness.
‎So when it gets
hard sometimes,
‎We need to remember
we’re not alone.
‎No, we’re never alone.
Just pray.
‎So when those dark clouds
come rolling in,
‎Hold your head high.
It’ll be all right.
‎Do not be afraid,
for He is with us,
‎Saving us with His right hand
of righteousness.
‎So when it gets
hard sometimes,
‎We need to remember
we’re not alone.
‎No, we’re never alone.
‎Just pray;
Do not be afraid.
‎The heartfelt appeal of that song
‎brings to mind the words of Isaiah 41:10,
‎where we’re encouraged:
‎“Do not be afraid, for I am with you.
‎“Do not be anxious, for I am your God.
‎“I will fortify you, yes, I will help you,
‎I will really hold on to you
with my right hand of righteousness.”
‎Be assured that you will receive help
‎from our heavenly Father, Jehovah,
‎and from fellow believers
‎to resist being molded by this system.
‎To conclude,
we bring you greetings
‎from Maraã,
in the state of Amazonas
‎in northern Brazil.
‎Nestled in the Amazon rain forest
along the Japurá River,
‎there are no roads leading to this city;
‎it can only be reached by river.
‎For most travelers,
reaching the city is a three-day journey,
‎which involves sleeping
in hammocks along the way.
‎Around 18,000 people inhabit the area,
‎but because of its remote location,
‎many people have never had
the opportunity to hear the good news.
‎With that in mind,
along with several other cities,
‎Maraã was included
in the Amazonas national preaching campaign.
‎The goal of this special campaign
was to reach the thousands of people
‎who live in some
of Amazon’s most isolated areas.
‎As a result,
many willing brothers and sisters
‎moved here to serve
where the need is greater.
‎Since the city
is completely surrounded by rivers,
‎publishers reach interested ones by boat.
‎Special pioneers have played
a large part in cultivating interest
‎by using this method of preaching.
‎One of the 23 congregations that was formed
‎as a result of the special campaign
‎is located here.
‎Today,
more than 20 publishers in the congregation
‎are conducting at least 100 Bible studies.
‎And we’re happy to report that in 2017
‎the first local family was baptized.
‎Our dear brothers and sisters
are working hard to help
‎those in the Amazon region
to learn about Jehovah,
‎and they send their warm love
‎and greetings to all of us
‎around the globe.
‎Thank you for joining us this month.
‎As always, this is JW Broadcasting
‎from the world headquarters
of Jehovah’s Witnesses.