Modesty is absolutely essential
to having a good relationship
with our heavenly Father, Jehovah.
We remember what Micah 6:8 tells us:
“He has told you, O man, what is good.
“And what is Jehovah requiring of you?
“Only to exercise justice,
“to cherish loyalty,
and to walk in modesty with your God!”
Well now, what does modesty mean to you?
You probably, when you listened
to the comments this morning,
heard a variety of different definitions.
All of them had a common theme,
but each one had a slightly different sense.
The Watchtower  of 2000 made
some very interesting comments
about the definition of modesty.
It said:
“Modesty can mean a number of things,
“such as a lack of conceit, or vanity,
“and a reluctance to boast
about one’s abilities,
“achievements, and possessions.
“According to one reference work,
“modesty also means ‘keeping within bounds.’
“A modest person
“stays within the bounds of good behavior.
“He also acknowledges
that there are limits
“to what he ought to do
and is able to do.
“He knows that there are things
to which he is not entitled.”
That’s a very interesting definition,
isn’t it?
And it kind of helps us to see
that there are many shades of meaning
involved with this word.
But let’s center our discussion this morning
on that last thought.
A modest person “acknowledges
that there are limits
to what he ought to do
and is able to do.”
Well now, to be modest,
we understand,
involves recognizing
our own personal limitations.
And sometimes it’s easier
to be able to see our physical limitations.
For example, if you’re not a strong swimmer,
probably when you go to the beach,
you won’t swim right out
into the ocean, will you?
You’ll recognize your limitations.
Or if you’re not in good shape,
you probably won’t sign up
for the New York marathon.
You see, we are able to see
that we’re not able to do
some of these physical tasks.
But modesty goes far beyond
just simply acknowledging
our own physical limitations.
Now let’s look
at an example from the Scriptures
that can help us to see this,
perhaps more clearly.
Let’s go to 1 Samuel chapter 26,
and we’re going to start reading
here at verse 7,
so 1 Samuel 26:7.
Now, just to set the context for you here,
you’ll remember that David
had been hiding from King Saul,
who was seeking to kill him.
Now, a golden opportunity came for David
to be able to put an end to Saul
and to all of this hiding
that David had had to be doing for so long.
Now, let’s read what it says,
verse 7:
“So David and Abishai made their way
to the troops by night,
“and they found Saul lying asleep
in the camp enclosure
“with his spear stuck to the ground
next to his head;
“Abner and the troops
were lying all around him.
“Abishai now said to David:
“‘Today God has surrendered
your enemy into your hand.
“‘And now, please,
let me pin him to the ground
“‘with the spear just once,
“and I will not need to do it twice.’
“However, David said to Abishai:
“‘Do not harm him,
“‘for who can lift his hand
against the anointed of Jehovah
“and remain innocent?’
“David continued:
“‘As surely as Jehovah is living,
“‘Jehovah himself will strike him down,
“‘or his day will come and he will die,
“‘or he will go down into battle and perish.
“‘It is unthinkable from Jehovah’s standpoint
“‘for me to lift my hand
against the anointed of Jehovah!
“‘So now take, please,
the spear next to his head and the water jug,
and let us be on our way.’”
Well now, it would have been so easy
for David to kill Saul, right?
But what helped David
to act modestly in this situation?
Well, let’s consider the first factor:
David had to consider his own position,
or his own authority.
Now, had Jehovah
instructed David to kill Saul?
No.
Jehovah had never assigned David
to carry out that task.
After all, Saul was anointed by Jehovah
to be the king of Israel,
so David acknowledged
that he simply did not have
the authority to kill Saul.
It was not his place.
But now, let’s consider a second factor.
Notice verse 10.
Do you remember what David said?
He said:
“As surely as Jehovah is living,
“Jehovah himself will strike him down,
“or his day will come and he will die,
or he will go down into battle and perish.”
Well, what’s the point?
You see, David had
complete confidence in Jehovah.
You see, instead of taking matters
into his own hands,
he had the total confidence
that Jehovah was going
to handle this situation
in his own way and in his own time
David modestly trusted in Jehovah.
Well, David acted modestly on that occasion.
But perhaps you can think
of a few other occasions later in his life
when he didn’t act so modestly.
What’s the lesson?
Modesty is a quality
that we must work hard to develop,
but we must also work hard
to maintain our modesty.
Otherwise, our minds can begin to focus
on our strengths, on our talents,
and on our abilities
to such an extent
that we begin to get
a very distorted view of self.
When that happens,
our modesty can begin to disappear,
and we can begin to behave presumptuously.
Now, who is one of the greatest examples
of this in the Bible?
Well, perhaps right away
you think of the example of Uzziah.
And if you go in your Bible
to 2 Chronicles chapter 26,
let’s just review for a minute
what we know about Uzziah
and what happened to him.
You see in 2 Chronicles 26:4—
Do you see what it says?
“He [speaking of Uzziah]
“continued to do what was right
in Jehovah’s eyes,
“just as his father Amaziah had done.
“And [you notice this]
he kept searching for God
“in the days of Zechariah,
who taught him to fear the true God.
“During the time
he was searching for Jehovah,
the true God made him prosper.”
Now, do you hear the modesty there?
Did you hear it?
Well, you see, it says Uzziah
was not a self-satisfied person
at that point in his life.
He was searching for Jehovah.
He felt the need for Jehovah’s guidance
and wisdom and blessing in his life.
But what happened?
If you go down to verse 16,
do you see?
“However, as soon as he was strong,
“his heart became haughty
to his own ruin,
“and he acted unfaithfully
against Jehovah his God
“by entering the temple of Jehovah
to burn incense on the altar of incense.”
Can you imagine?
He became so emboldened
that he actually went into Jehovah’s temple
and burned incense on the altar of incense.
Well, the priests came running.
And what did they say to him?
Do you see verse 18?
“It is not proper for you, Uzziah,
to burn incense to Jehovah!
“It is only the priest
who should burn incense,
“for they are the descendants of Aaron,
those who have been sanctified.
“Go out from the sanctuary,
“for you have acted unfaithfully
and you will receive no glory
from Jehovah God for this.”
Well, Uzziah started out fearing God.
He started out searching for Jehovah,
but when he became powerful,
what happened?
He quickly lost his modesty.
Well now, brothers,
why is this an important discussion,
really, for all of us?
Well, all of us face
trying situations in life.
And when we face those situations,
we may be tempted
to want to rush in and handle them.
We may be tempted
to ignore Bible principles
and even published direction that we have
from “the faithful and discreet slave.”
How wise we are in those moments,
in those situations,
to step back for a moment,
take a deep breath, count to ten,
and say to ourselves:
‘Do I really have the authority
to do what I’m about to do?
‘Is it really my place to say
what I’m about to say?
‘Instead, would it be better
to wait on Jehovah
to correct this situation?’
You see, by having a proper view of self,
by sticking closely to the direction
that we have from Jehovah
and from “the faithful and discreet slave,”
and by maintaining our full
and complete confidence
that Jehovah will correct any matters
that need to be rectified,
we can have the privilege to walk
—not just for a short time
but to walk eternally—
in modesty with our magnificent,
our wonderful God, Jehovah.