This morning we’re talking
about the clever strategy of Satan,
designed to lure people away from Jehovah God.
And so we’re going to examine two approaches:
One he used
with the youngest intelligent creature
in the universe,
and the other he used
on the oldest intelligent creature
in the universe.
Let’s take the youngest first.
Of course, that was Eve.
So taking advantage of her inexperience,
his purpose was to trick this woman
and to seduce her.
Now, how would he do it?
Well, as we know, he was behind a serpent.
He didn’t want to show her who he really was
—what his aim really was.
His choice of words also reveal a lot.
And our text is Genesis chapter 3.
Let’s go there if you would.
I’d like to just read his question again,
Genesis 3:1:
“Did God really say
that you must not eat
from every tree of the garden?”
Now, what was his motive in asking this question?
Well, as was stated by one of the commenters,
what he was trying to do
was to seed a doubt in her mind,
implying that Jehovah God
was holding something back from her.
‘He was too restrictive on you.’
Well, it’s interesting concerning questions.
The be book, Benefit From Theocratic
Ministry School Education,
on page 66 says:
“Some questions are like icebergs.
“The most substantial part
lies hidden beneath the surface.
An underlying issue
is often more important than the question itself.”
And in the case of Eve,
when the question was asked,
she didn’t see
the underlying purpose of the question.
Her answer in verses 2 and 3 indicate this.
She said: “We may eat
of the fruit of the trees of the garden.
“But God has said about the fruit of the tree
that is in the middle of the garden:
‘You must not eat from it, no,
you must not touch it; otherwise you will die.’”
Her answer was truthful,
and it was an honest, innocent answer.
But Satan had her exactly where he wanted her.
You see, he was banking
on her self-interest,
that she would be more interested in herself
—her own needs—
than the love she had
for the God that gave
her everything that she had.
Read his words again in verses 4 and 5.
Satan said:
“You certainly will not die.
“For God knows
that in the very day you eat from it,
“your eyes will be opened
and you will be like God,
knowing good and bad.”
Tragically, his gamble worked.
She had not cultivated
the kind of love
and appreciation for Jehovah God
that she should have.
So, what can we learn from this example?
Well, if a perfect human can succumb
to this kind of reasoning
—irrational reasoning, really—
it can happen to any one of us.
Jehovah God created us as free moral agents.
That’s the way he made Eve.
He doesn’t want robots.
He wants us to be able to think things through,
make the right choices,
decide between right and wrong.
Satan is counting on us
to make the wrong choices.
Now, what can we do
to counter that attack from Satan?
Well, we have to know what is in our hearts.
If you go to Hebrews 12:15, 16,
the apostle Paul
gives a warning to his fellow Christians
against becoming people
who do not appreciate sacred things.
And that’s sort of the context
of verses 15 and 16.
He says: “Carefully watch that no one
“fails to obtain the undeserved kindness of God,
“so that no poisonous root springs up
“to cause trouble and many are defiled by it;
“and watch that among you
there is no one who is sexually immoral
nor anyone
who does not appreciate sacred things.”
So there is a need,
as he said here in verse 15,
to: “Carefully watch.”
‘Carefully watch that no poisonous root
will spring up and contaminate the congregation.’
The expression “poisonous root”
refers to a few that may be in a congregation
who may find fault
with the way things are done,
maybe even find fault
with the direction Jehovah has given on matters
—maybe the sacredness of marriage
or the need for moral cleanness.
So we don’t want to be those kind of people
—obviously.
But tell me,
what’s necessary before a root can appear?
Well, a seed has to be planted,
and then it germinates,
and then it grows into a root.
So it’s at the seed level
that we have to give special attention.
We have to learn to identify
these improper seeds, as it were.
No one can do that for us
because they can’t read our heart.
The seed may even—
We’ve never even voiced what the seed is,
but it could be
in our thinking and in our heart.
And these internal weaknesses
have to be addressed
for fear we find ourselves in a circumstance
maneuvered by Satan
to accentuate that particular weakness.
Now, James 1:14, 15
really describes the process well.
James 1:14, 15, where he says:
“Each one is tried
by being drawn out and enticed
“by his own desire [own desire].
“Then the desire [the seed],
“when it has become fertile [starts to grow],
“gives birth to sin; in turn sin,
when it has been carried out, brings forth death.”
So, being “enticed by his own desire.”
Does that sound familiar?
It’s a powerful force.
It’s one that happened to Eve,
the self-interests
—they’re similar.
So, what do we need to do?
Well, as we said earlier,
identify the seed or seeds
if that may be the case.
Don’t let them germinate;
don’t let them start to grow.
Rid ourselves of that thinking.
And if a “poisonous root”
may happen to be in us
or starting to grow,
then we need to rip it out.
And you may need to have help to do it.
It may be impossible
to remove a “poisonous root” by yourself.
Now, let’s spend a few moments
on the approach Satan used
for the oldest intelligent creature in the universe,
of course, Christ Jesus.
Now, in this case, he didn’t try to hide himself.
He realized there was no need to do that.
Jesus knew exactly who he was.
He understood the motive.
And so he just went overtly right to Jesus.
And as you know, in the account of Matthew 4,
he said, ‘Look, just fall down
and do an act of worship to me.’
Now, what does this tell us about Satan?
Well, he has long been driven by jealousy
over the worship that goes to Jehovah God.
And he’s going to go to any length possible
to try to violate our worship to Jehovah God.
He wants to pervert our worship to Jehovah God.
And so if he has enough boldness
to approach Jesus Christ,
then we know he will approach any one of us.
And it makes no difference
how spiritually strong we look on the outside;
he will try to break our integrity.
Clearly, the Bible reveals that Satan
is a deadly strategist in seeking his aims.
Happily, though, we don’t have to be like Eve,
because we know
the designs of Satan the Devil.
May each of us cultivate
the kind of love Jesus had for Jehovah God,
so we too can stand firm in our integrity.