Thank you for joining us,
and welcome to the program!
It’s our privilege
to spend the next hour
with you dear brothers
and sisters.
Please join us
on a field trip to Ethiopia
where we will meet
Brother Stephanos Demsas.
Brother Demsas and his wife
served faithfully for many years
while the preaching work
was under ban.
You will enjoy their experiences.
Have you ever participated
in a preaching campaign?
Our team was present
when one was arranged in Armenia.
A preaching campaign
is uplifting and encouraging
to everyone involved
as this segment will show.
How would you react
if one of your loved ones decides
to leave the truth?
It truly is heartbreaking,
to say the least,
but what Bible principles
can help us endure
such a challenge?
This dramatization will help us.
This is the November program
of JW Broadcasting!
We have selected the theme
“Be a Champion of Truth!”
You may have heard
of the word “champion”
used in the context of sports.
What is a champion?
The word
can have different meanings.
The word is related
to the French word champ,
meaning “field.”
That word has its origin
in the Latin word campus,
also meaning “field”
or “battlefield.”
The Bible speaks of
a champion on a battlefield
in 1 Samuel 17:4:
“Then a champion came out
from the camps of the Philistines;
his name was Goliath.”
Goliath was a champion
for a wrong cause,
namely,
to take the lead in defeating
the ancient Israelites in battle.
In our modern time,
according to one definition,
a champion
is “an ardent defender
“or supporter of a cause
or another person.”
Christians today
are ardent defenders
and supporters of the truth.
The Watchtower
of January 15, 2012,
said on page 8:
“Other champions
of Bible truth rose up
in the centuries that followed.”
Years before,
The Watchtower said:
“This magazine
will never shrink in fear
from championing the truth!”
“The Watchtower
has been championing
‘the cause of Kingdom truth.’”
So, are you a champion?
In a sports competition,
only one individual
gets to be the champion.
But in the case
of true Christians,
all can be champions
of the truth.
All Christians
are to defend the truth
and become conquerors
—winners.
It’s necessary
to defend the truth
because in today’s world
truth is being attacked
and distorted.
We are surrounded
by a sea of lies
and misrepresentations.
How did such lies get started?
They started in the garden of Eden
when Satan told Eve lies.
Satan,
through his deceptive statements,
became “the father of the lie.”
All the problems in the world
—all calamities
(also your personal calamities),
all wars,
all diseases, all crimes,
all unhappiness,
sorrow, and death
—started with the original lies
in the garden of Eden.
Satan is “the father of the lie.”
But today there are
many “children” of the lie.
Every one of us is affected.
We are surrounded
by a sea of lies.
A lie is “a false statement
“deliberately presented
as being true;
a falsehood.”
A lie is the opposite
of the truth.
Lying involves
saying something incorrect
to a person who is entitled to know
the truth about a matter.
But there is also something
that is called a half-truth.
The Bible tells Christians
to be honest with each other.
“Now that you
have put away deceit,
. . . speak truth,”
wrote the apostle Paul
at Ephesians 4:25.
Lies and half-truths
undermine trust.
A German proverb says,
“Who lies once is not believed,
even if he says the truth.”
So we need to speak openly
and honestly with each other,
not withholding
bits of information
that could change
the perception of the listener
or mislead him.
As to lies,
there are different types.
Some politicians
have lied about matters
they wanted to keep secret.
Companies sometimes lie
in advertisements
regarding their products.
What about the news media?
Many try to report events truthfully.
But we should not be gullible
and believe
everything newspapers write
or everything we hear on radio
or see on television.
Then there are religious lies.
If Satan is called
“the father of the lie,”
then Babylon the Great,
the global empire of false religion,
can be called
the “mother” of the lie.
Individual false religions
could be called
“daughters” of the lie.
Some lie by saying that sinners
will get tormented in hell forever.
Others lie by saying,
“Once saved, always saved.”
Again, others lie
by saying that the earth
will be burned up
on Judgment Day
and all good people
will go to heaven.
Some worship idols.
Paul wrote at Romans 1:25:
“They exchanged
the truth of God for the lie
“and venerated
and rendered sacred service
to the creation
rather than the Creator.”
Then there are many lies
of a personal nature
that people express
in everyday life.
A businessman
may get a phone call
but tell his secretary
to answer the caller
by saying he is not in.
This may be considered
a small lie.
There are small lies,
big lies,
and malicious lies.
A child may have broken something
but when asked initially,
out of fear of punishment,
denies having done it.
This does not make the child
a malicious liar.
In contrast,
what if an entrepreneur
tells his bookkeeper
to falsify the entries
in the books
in order to save on taxes?
This lying to the tax office
is certainly a serious lie.
It is a deliberate attempt
to mislead somebody
that has the right to know.
It also robs the government
of what they have established
as legal income.
We can see
that not all lies are the same;
there are small lies, big lies,
and malicious lies.
Satan is a malicious liar.
He is the champion of the lie.
Since Jehovah hates liars,
we should avoid all lies,
not just big or malicious lies.
But can we find the truth?
Some say, “Truth is relative.”
It is like saying,
“This is truth for you,
and this is truth for me.”
This claim is not logical
when it comes to religious truth.
Either God is a Trinity
or he’s not.
Either the soul is mortal
or it is not.
Either there is a future paradise
on earth or there is not.
Either homosexuality
is acceptable to God or it is not.
Either participating in wars
is permissible or it is not.
Truth is definite, not relative,
because Jehovah conveyed
the truth to his servants.
Psalm 43:3 says:
“Send out your light and your truth.”
Jehovah is a Revealer of truth.
One of several reasons
why Jesus came into the world
was to “witness to the truth.”
At John 18:37b,
he said:
“For this I have been born,
“and for this
I have come into the world,
“that I should bear witness
to the truth.
Everyone who is on the side
of the truth listens to my voice.”
So if we listen to Jesus,
or read in the Bible
what he taught,
we can learn the truth.
Jesus was the personification
of the truth.
He said: “I am the way
and the truth and the life.”
We can find out what the truth is
by diligently studying the Bible.
Truth is that which is a fact.
For true Christians,
the entire text
of the Hebrew
and Christian Greek Scriptures
constitutes the truth.
Psalm 119:160
says of Jehovah:
‘The essence
of your word is truth.’
That is why
it is good to do
daily Bible reading
with meditation
and weekly family worship.
At Matthew 24:45-47, we read
that for the time of the end,
Jesus would appoint
a “faithful and discreet slave,”
or Governing Body,
to explain the Bible
to His followers
and help them to grow
in understanding of the truth.
Whereas Jesus’ teachings
and the written Word of God
are inspired,
“the faithful and discreet slave”
is not inspired,
although it champions the truth.
Nevertheless, the faithful slave
provides spiritual food.
Whereas in the first century
there was supernatural knowledge
available for apostles
and Bible writers,
in the time of the end,
Jehovah does not bestow
this miraculous gift anymore,
as explained
at 1 Corinthians 13:8.
Although there is
no divine inspiration today,
still Jesus leads
his people progressively
through the services
of the faithful slave.
Jesus trusts
that the imperfect faithful slave
will do its best
to convey spiritual food.
Do you also trust the slave?
Whereas the truth
of God’s Word does not change,
our understanding
of the truth does change
because we
are not perfect yet.
We understand more
about the truth today
than Christians
in the first century.
Do we keep up with the progressive
understanding of truth?
Daniel was told:
“Many will rove about,
and the true knowledge
will become abundant.”
This is a gradual process.
We are still roving about.
During the Millennium,
Jehovah will reveal
additional truths to mankind.
At Revelation 20:12,
it mentions scrolls
that will be opened.
The apostle John reports
that the dead are to be “judged
“out of those things
written in the scrolls
according to their deeds.”
Evidently, then,
these scrolls will contain
additional information for mankind
during the thousand years.
It stands to reason
that after the end of the Millennium,
there will be
additional truths to learn.
Still,
according to Ecclesiastes
chapter 3, verse 11:
“Mankind will never find out
the work
that the true God has made.”
But how do we know
we have the truth?
At Pentecost 33
of our Common Era,
true Christians
numbered only about 3,000.
Today, we are millions.
And on average,
every weekend
more than 5,000
are getting baptized.
But this in itself
is not proof
that we have the truth.
Truth is not measured
in numbers.
Why do we know
we have the truth?
For one,
because we remain
in Jesus’ teaching,
John 8:31.
Second,
we know we have the truth
because of the deep bond of love
for each other, John 13:35.
Third, we know we have the truth
because our conduct
adheres
to the high moral standards of truth,
John 15:10.
Fourth,
we know we have the truth
because we remain neutral
in the controversies of the world,
as Jesus advised
at John 17:14.
Fifth,
we know we have the truth
because we are
God’s name people.
Acts 15:14 speaks
of “a people for his name.”
Jesus said:
“The truth will set you free.”
It sets us free from fears
—like the fear of death,
fear of the future,
and an exaggerated fear of man.
It also sets us free
from false teachings,
from spiritism,
and from astrology and magic.
It frees us from immorality
and its consequences.
There are
no other people on earth
that are
as spiritually free as we are.
Do we appreciate that freedom?
Truth leads to freedom.
Second Corinthians 3:17 says:
“Where the spirit of Jehovah is,
there is freedom.”
The truth penetrates schools.
How so?
By means of our children
who preach the truth
to classmates and to teachers.
Do you go to school?
Do you champion
the truth at school?
How can you do this?
You do this not only by preaching
but also by your conduct,
by your dress and grooming,
and by taking a stand for the truth
when others want you
to participate
in unchristian practices.
You also champion the truth
by remaining honest
and not cheating
on your exams.
And Jehovah
will love you for that.
The truth
also penetrates prisons.
Reports have come in
from many countries
telling of the good work
brothers are doing
in contacting prisoners
in various prisons,
helping some to rehabilitate
their lives spiritually.
In a number of such institutions,
regular meetings are being held
and several prisoners
have studied to the point
of dedication and baptism.
The truth penetrates
even walls of monasteries.
In Mexico, in 2009,
a nun was baptized who,
because of the truth,
had left
her monastery and order,
although she was
the mother superior.
The world
is in utter confusion.
What a blessing
to know the truth!
We rejoice in it!
We have the truth on our lips.
We have the truth around our hips.
Ephesians chapter 6
says that “the belt of truth”
is fastened around our waists.
We are ready to teach it.
We talk the truth,
and we walk in the truth.
Those who continue to walk
in the truth
will walk in it forever.
Help your students
to love the truth
and to live the truth but,
if necessary,
to be willing to die
for the truth and for Jehovah.
The truth is invincible
and will conquer
this wicked world.
In some countries,
we may have many enemies
who may want to silence us.
But the apostle Paul said
at 2 Corinthians 13:8:
“For we can do nothing
against the truth.”
Neither can our enemies
suppress the truth.
Do we appreciate
that we have the truth
—the only truth?
Is this arrogant to say?
By no means!
It would be a sin
if we would not say so.
Jesus was not arrogant
when he said:
‘I am the truth.’
To know the truth
is not enough.
We need to champion it.
There are still
many lovers of truth out there;
search for them.
Who will help you
in the search?
According to John 4:23,
Jesus said that Jehovah
is searching for ones
that want to worship in truth.
The majority
will not listen to the truth
because ‘they love the darkness
rather than the light.’
The truth may expose
their sinful conduct,
and they
may not have the humility
to want
to repent and change.
We still have to preach to them
—to warn them.
Ezekiel was told:
“You must warn them from me.”
The principle applies to us as well.
Paul speaks of “the sword
of . . . God’s word.”
Use it well
to champion the truth.
Train your students
to be good defenders of it as well.
The time will come
in Paradise after the final test
when it will not be necessary
to champion,
or defend, the truth,
because nobody
will attack it anymore.
Right now,
whether we are adults,
teenagers, or children,
let us follow and imitate Jesus
—the greatest Champion of truth!
To that end,
keep studying the truth.
Keep spreading the truth.
Keep loving the truth
and Jehovah, the God of truth.
Hold fast to the truth
as to a lifeline
—as this is what it is!
By staying faithful,
whether you survive Armageddon
or are resurrected in Paradise,
you will be a victorious
champion of the truth!
Let’s now look at some examples
of how our brothers and sisters
around the world
faithfully champion the truth.
Chris?
Thank you, Brother Lösch.
When a dear friend or perhaps
even a family member leaves the truth,
it can be a very challenging situation.
It can truly be a test of our faith
when we see something
like that take place.
While watching
this dramatization,
pay attention to how the mother
was able to champion the truth
by remaining
loyal to Jehovah.
My name is Gabriella.
Ben and I have always enjoyed
attending the meetings.
But lately,
it’s been difficult.
Something was missing
—our son.
It was like watching a movie
of someone else’s family.
I couldn’t believe
this was happening to us.
Our son, Levi,
was no longer
one of Jehovah’s Witnesses.
The elders and friends
in the congregation
were so supportive
and understanding.
Many of them
watched Levi grow up,
give his first talk,
get baptized.
I was so torn.
I was disappointed in Levi
for leaving Jehovah,
but I was
more disappointed in myself.
I felt like we
failed him somehow.
I kept wondering
how he was doing.
Was he OK?
Then, as hard
as the past few weeks had been,
it just got harder.
I knew what the Bible said
about “quit mixing in company
with anyone”
who is not living
according to Christian standards.
But I never thought that scripture
would one day apply to me.
Later that evening,
a brother was talking
about the example
of Korah’s sons.
Jehovah confirmed that He
was using Moses
to lead His people,
not Korah.
When the people were told
to move away
from the rebels’ tents,
what would Korah’s sons do?
Would they put loyalty to family
ahead of loyalty to Jehovah?
The Bible tells us
that his sons remained loyal
to Jehovah
and were blessed for it.
That night,
after the meeting,
I told Ben about the text
I received from Levi.
I told him everything
—how I missed Levi so much,
but that I also wanted to be loyal
to Jehovah like Korah’s sons.
Ben admitted that he too
had been struggling
with feelings like mine.
But then he said something
that I hadn’t thought of.
If we were to stand between Levi
and the discipline he needs,
we would, in effect,
be blocking
an expression of Jehovah’s love
from reaching him.
In fact,
it’s our very loyalty
to Jehovah
that could save his life.
We agreed to continue
to put our trust
in Jehovah
and stay loyal to him.
It’s been five years now,
and while Levi
still hasn’t returned to Jehovah,
I haven’t given up hope on him.
Until that day,
I’m staying busy as a regular pioneer
and focusing my energies
on helping others
learn about Jehovah.
I’ve come to experience firsthand
the truth of Psalm 97:10.
Jehovah really does guard
his loyal ones.
What helped Gabriella overcome
this difficult challenge?
For example,
when she received
a text message from her son,
she applied Scriptural counsel
to her personal circumstances.
The good example of Korah’s sons
gave her added motivation
so as not to allow
her feelings for her son
to dictate her actions.
Instead, she was firm
in her loyalty to Jehovah.
Also, her husband, Ben,
had found an article
that helped
the two of them appreciate
that they should make sure
not to stand
between Jehovah
and their son, Levi.
Instead, they wanted
Jehovah’s expression of love
to reach Levi.
Whenever we
are faced with a trial,
we need to remember
to pray constantly
to Jehovah for guidance
and to look for Jehovah’s counsel
in our literature
and during our meetings.
The apostle Paul faced
many challenges in his ministry.
In 2 Corinthians chapter 11,
starting in verse 23,
he enumerates
over 20 hardships
that he experienced
in his ministry.
What helped Paul
to keep his motivation strong
despite everything he faced?
In this morning worship
from Bethel,
Brother John Ekrann highlights
what Paul himself said
kept him going.
When you look
at the words in the way
that the apostle Paul worded things,
he said: “I live by faith
in the Son of God,
who loved me
and handed himself over for me.”
And we can really see
the very personal nature
of the ransom to the apostle Paul.
And it’s important for us to do
—as our commenters
pointed out nicely—
it is important for us
to personalize the ransom.
The apostle Paul, in Hebrews 6:5,
showed the very personal nature;
he understood the personal nature
of the Bible and the ransom.
In Hebrews 6:5,
he uses this expression:
“And who have tasted
the fine word of God
and powers
of the coming system of things.”
Well, it’s interesting
he used the word “taste.”
Taste is something very personal.
Somebody can’t taste
something for you.
You have to put it
in your mouth in order
to really know
what it’s going to taste like.
So, too, with the ransom.
And what practical ways
can we “taste,”
or personalize,
the ransom for us?
Let’s just consider
a couple this morning.
One is personal fears.
‘Does God really love me?
Am I worthy of love?’
Sometimes the “what-ifs”
and their cousins, the “could-bes,”
they come to live and never leave.
You know, if bad things
or trials or difficulties happen to us,
we begin to reason,
‘Well, Jehovah God maybe doesn’t love me.’
There’s really strong reason for us
to somehow believe
in cause and effect.
We see the cause of things and effect,
and so after a while,
everything that happens to us,
we begin to look at some cause
and even begin to think
that maybe Jehovah
doesn’t love us.
Even if we’re a good person
and bad things happen to us,
we begin to wonder,
‘Others my age are healthy.’
Some leaving
or changing assignments,
you hear everything
falls into place
for them within a few weeks.
‘I’m still looking for a job.
I’m still looking for work.’
In other words,
do not try to reason
that just because things
don’t work out perfectly
that Jehovah doesn’t love us.
It’s not true.
We can still be doing very,
very good things,
and yet some difficulties
can face us.
For example,
you’re driving down the road,
obeying all the traffic laws.
You pull up to a red light,
you stop,
it turns green, you go through it,
and you get broadsided
by some knucklehead who went
through the red light on the other side.
Well, that’s not your fault.
Are you going to say:
“Well, you know what?
I’m not going to obey traffic laws anymore.
See, it doesn’t pay!”
Well, no!
It was his fault for running
through the traffic light.
And sometimes bad, or difficult,
things can happen to us.
It’s not our fault
or it’s not any sign
that Jehovah doesn’t love us.
So how can reflecting
on the ransom help us
when we have these kinds
of personal fears?
Well, we could start with,
Why do we have the ransom?
Well, because some very bad things
were happening
to some good people
—us—
Adam and Eve’s descendants.
I mean,
Adam sinned and Eve sinned,
yet we suffer.
The ransom is Jehovah’s solution
for those who appreciate it.
It’s his way of telling us,
‘I know bad things are happening,
and I’m working to fix it.’
Yes, when we reflect
on the reason
why Jehovah God
gave us the ransom,
it helps us to know
that Jehovah knows we suffer
from cancer and old age
and the sins and mistakes of others
and even our own imperfections.
See, tasting of the ransom in this way
means we’ll not get the feeling
that Jehovah doesn’t love us
when trials befall us.
To the contrary, the ransom
is the greatest expression
of Jehovah’s and Jesus’ love for us
and their desire to fix
the current mess we live in now.
How about,
let’s consider a second way
that we could reflect
on the ransom,
and that is the death
of someone close to us.
Anyone who’s had someone
very close to them die
knows the very helpless feeling
that you have,
knowing that there’s
really nothing you can do.
In that instant when they die,
your hope
—your faith in the resurrection
based on the ransom—
becomes more real to you
than any time in your entire life.
In Acts 17:31,
in a beautiful speech
that the apostle Paul gave,
he highlights
that Jesus’ death
and resurrection and the ransom
was really a guarantee
that we have.
Here in Acts 17:31,
he says: “Because he has set a day
on which he purposes
“to judge the inhabited earth
in righteousness
“by a man
whom he has appointed,
“and he has provided
a guarantee
“to all men
by resurrecting him
from the dead.”
So personalizing the ransom
and all that it makes possible
helps us to know that the resurrection is,
not just possible,
but that Jehovah
and Jesus want to resurrect
our mother, our father,
our beloved husband or a wife.
They care about each person
that has ever lived or died
and know them
so intimately and so completely
that they can resurrect them completely
with all their memories
and personality completely
as we knew them.
I mean, how much more personal
could God’s love for us
become than that?
You know, to bring our loved ones
back from the dead
is the ultimate statement
of Jehovah’s personal interest
in each and every human being.
We are not just collateral damage
in Satan’s war on Jehovah.
The ransom is the way
that Jehovah plans
to undo all the harm
that Satan has caused
since the death of Adam and Eve.
In fact, the resurrection
is really Jehovah’s way
of proving all of Satan’s lies
completely false.
When you think about it today,
Satan can perpetrate
all kinds of lies about what happens
to people after they die.
‘They’re going to go here,
they’re going to go there,
‘they’re going to go to some afterlife,
they’re going to go to some paradise,
they’re going to come back
as some animal.’
But in the new world,
when the vast majority of people
have been resurrected,
that lie isn’t going
to be sold anymore.
Each one can tell everyone
what happened to them
when they died
—nothing,
no afterlife.
Everyone will know
that it’s nonexistence.
That lie won’t work.
See, Jehovah knew
that we would hurt terribly
at the death of loved ones,
so he gave us the ransom
as his way of telling us,
‘I know it hurts,
but please know
that I have
the perfect solution in mind.’
Now, we’ve just considered two ways
to reflect and meditate on the ransom,
like the apostle Paul did,
to really personalize it.
We just talked about personal fears
and the resurrection,
the death of someone close to us.
Imagine how many more ways
we can benefit today
from meditating on the ransom
and how it affects us personally.
As ministers of Jehovah,
we take part in preaching
the good news.
That good news includes
the wonderful provision
of the ransom
Brother Ekrann highlighted.
Have you ever participated
in a preaching campaign?
I’m sure you
have enjoyed campaigns
such as inviting
our neighbors to the Memorial
or the regional convention.
On occasion,
other campaigns are approved
by the Service Committee
of the Governing Body
when there is a specific need
in an area or language group.
We bring you a report
on a special campaign
in Armenia.
Armenia is an ancient country
with rich history,
situated in the lands
of Mount Ararat.
In the Caucasus region,
Lake Sevan
is considered to be
a prized jewel.
Diversity of its flora and fauna
contribute to the unique
and beautiful countryside.
Yerevan, the capital,
is a modern metropolis
with picturesque views
that remind many of Paris
with its trees, cafés,
and beautiful water fountains.
Recently, a special three-week
preaching campaign took place.
Groups of Armenian-speaking
Jehovah’s Witnesses
from six different countries
wholeheartedly responded
to the invitation.
The main purpose of the campaign
was to cover as many
of the 512 unassigned territories
as possible
with the Kingdom good news.
Thus, an opportunity
for an interchange
of encouragement was created
for both the local friends
and the campaign participants.
They were warmly greeted
at the airport
by local brothers and sisters.
The Witnesses made good use
of their tablets and smartphones to show
videos from the jw.org website.
Armenia is also currently home
to over 11,000 Western-Armenian refugees.
A special effort was made
to share with these individuals
the positive message of hope
and peace from the Bible
in their native tongue,
West Armenian.
Metropolitan witnessing
served as an effective way
to reach these ones.
It was the first time in my life
that I participated in public witnessing,
and it was very encouraging.
When individuals would approach us
and show interest,
I could explain to them
the truth in their own language.
It was amazing.
It’s been very heartwarming.
People have really responded well.
They were in need of comfort
and the good news, especially those that
we came for,
the Western Armenians.
Pretty much every door invited us in,
and they were very hospitable
and receptive.
After we heard the announcement
about the special campaign
in the Western language
that’s going to take place in Armenia,
we said: “We cannot miss this.
“We have to be there
and bring our share
in this very joyful
preaching campaign.”
During the three-week campaign,
over 15,000 pieces
of Bible-based literature
were left with interested ones,
and over 200 Bible studies
were started.
We were very happy to see
how many brothers and sisters
were ready to come
for the campaign in Armenia
from different countries
around the world.
That response showed
that Jehovah has blessed our efforts.
Those who came from far and wide
greatly appreciated the share
they had in this special event.
Everyone was so happy to see us.
And when we were giving them a Bible,
they were so excited to find answers
from their own Bible.
I’m so blessed to be here.
This has been the best vacation
that we have had as a family.
The first time I came to Armenia,
it was in 1982.
And I looked for the Witnesses,
and I hardly found just a few.
But now that I came
for this campaign,
we have 11,000 Witnesses!
I’m really so happy!
I really want to come back!
It is our hope that Jehovah God
continues to help
all sorts of people to be saved
and come
to an accurate knowledge of truth.
While we
enjoy relative freedom
in many countries
around the world,
at times governments
impose bans
or restrictions
on the preaching work.
Brother Stephanos Demsas
serves as a special pioneer
in Addis Ababa, Ethiopia,
along with his wife, Leteberhan.
Their faith was tested
during many years of adversity.
What helped them
champion the truth?
Their story began
in what is today Eritrea.
I come from a family
of nine children.
I joined the navy in 1956.
That was during the time
when Eritrea was part of Ethiopia.
My brother Gebrehiwot
asked me to come to Asmara.
He was studying the Bible
with Jehovah’s Witnesses.
I was so impressed
with what he shared with me
that for the rest of my vacation,
Bible study became my priority.
In time,
I was discharged from the navy
and started working
in Addis Ababa,
so I was able to continue studying
the Bible and get baptized.
Leti was also doing the same.
In 1960,
I was attending a nursing college.
There, a nurse shared
some interesting thoughts
with me from the Bible.
Ten other student nurses
also showed interest.
But the college
threatened us with dismissal
because there was a ban
on Jehovah’s Witnesses.
When we were shown from the Bible
why true Christians are persecuted,
we renewed our determination.
Eventually,
five of us were baptized.
In time, I met Stephanos,
and we were married in 1964.
Because of the ban,
the brothers were meeting
in small groups.
Our trust was in Jehovah,
and we made the preaching work
a matter of prayer,
confident that he would help us.
We saw evidence of this
with the underground production
of The Watchtower.
Our brothers were of modest means,
but they used what they had to buy
a hand-operated duplicating machine
which was used in our home.
After returning
from our secular work,
Leti and I would get busy
making copies of The Watchtower.
We would play music
so our neighbors
wouldn’t hear the sound
of the duplicator.
In 1974,
Emperor Haile Selassie was deposed.
This Communist government quickly began
a campaign called “Red Terror”
against any supposed political opposer.
Now, just having a typewriter
or a duplicating machine
could put you in prison
or even have you killed.
Picking up a paper
from the street
with something printed on it
against the government
could put one’s life in danger.
It was common
for people to disappear.
Sadly, my youngest brother,
Eyob, was a victim.
He disappeared on his way home
and was never seen again.
With the situation
being very dangerous,
we were quite concerned
raising our daughter, Janet.
But as we fully trusted in Jehovah,
we felt his loving protection.
From time to time,
sections of the city
were suddenly blockaded.
This happened one morning
as a translator
was heading to our home
to deliver stencils for printing.
Urgently, he telephoned
informing us
that a house-to-house search
was under way.
Our house was full of publications
along with a duplicator
and typewriters!
Just after the phone call,
three soldiers
entered our compound to search.
At that moment,
I prayed silently
that Jehovah would blind them.
Entering the room
where the duplicator
and stacks
of freshly printed literature were,
one soldier asked,
“What is all this?”
“Oh, this is a duplicator that we use
to print these Bible materials.”
Completing his search,
he went outside
to the commander,
who asked him,
“What did you find?”
To our utter amazement,
after seeing everything,
he answered:
“Nothing!
We won’t find anything here.”
In the late 1970’s
and into the early 80’s,
another wave
of vicious persecution occurred.
A number of faithful brothers
were imprisoned,
tortured, and murdered.
I was taken from my work place
because of my neutral stand
and put in prison.
When I think about living through
those difficult times,
I am reminded of Isaiah 54:17
where Jehovah promised us:
“No weapon formed against you
will have any success.”
Finally, in 1991,
a liberal government came to power.
They gave us legal recognition
and freedom of worship.
With these difficult,
dangerous years
now behind us,
we were assigned to the circuit work
in Eritrea and Ethiopia.
By now, Eritrea was becoming
an independent country,
and this brought about
new challenges for the brothers.
Some young brothers
were arrested and imprisoned
because of their Christian stand.
Paul wrote at Hebrews 13:3:
“Keep in mind those in prison,
as though you were imprisoned with them.”
After enjoying the circuit work
for 15 years,
we faced another change.
We were invited to serve at Bethel
as full-time commuters.
What has helped us to endure
through the ban years
and to adjust to the many changes
is our spiritual study program.
We’re in full agreement
with Jeremiah 17:7:
“Blessed is the man
who puts his trust in Jehovah.”
It also brings us much happiness
to know that our daughter, Janet,
has been serving
as a regular pioneer
for 20 years now.
Each assignment
has had its challenges
but many rewards and blessings.
I’m not young anymore;
I’m 77 years old.
And I’m 74 years old.
We are now serving
as special pioneers.
When we think about all the changes
that we’ve been through,
we realize
that the words at Isaiah 6:8:
“Here I am! Send me!”
are, not just for young people,
but for all of us.
It is very encouraging to see
Stephanos
and Leteberhan’s determination
to stay faithful to Jehovah,
come what may.
We know that Jehovah
looks with delight
on their many years of service.
Some of our brothers in Canada
underwent similar persecution.
How did Jehovah help them?
Pay special attention
to the numerous acts of courage
displayed by these
champions of truth.
Preaching in the province of Quebec
was a real challenge.
The Catholic Church
was present
in every sphere of public life.
In the early ’40s,
the persecution
took on quite a bit
of emphasis.
Many Witnesses were being arrested.
Any excuse was used.
Peddling without a license
—this was a favorite excuse.
Jehovah’s Witnesses were put in prison
whenever they were seen
with religious literature.
It had got so bad in Quebec
that it was decided to circulate a petition,
and this petition was circulated
throughout Canada.
And it called
on the government of Quebec
to put an end
to this persecution.
And interestingly,
some 600,000 people
signed the petition.
The Witnesses distributed
a very fiery tract
called the Burning Hate of Quebec.
And in this tract,
they showed
what was really happening
—the actions of the policemen,
the illegal arrests,
the mob action.
Within four months,
there were 800 new court cases.
So here,
for 400 Jehovah’s Witnesses,
you had 1,600 court cases.
The seriousness
of the court cases increased,
in that now
they were accusing
the brothers of sedition.
If convicted,
it was more than 10
—maybe 12 or 15—
years in prison.
We had one brother,
Aimé Boucher,
who was arrested
and charged with sedition.
Aimé Boucher
was a very poor brother,
who lived
in a rural part of Quebec.
And he actually
went to court
with his ox and buggy.
And on the way to court,
he was preaching,
so he was arrested again.
They had the court hearing,
and he was condemned.
He was found guilty of sedition.
And his case went up
to the Court of Appeal
—and at that time, the Court of Appeal
of Quebec was very hostile—
and he lost on appeal,
so it went up
to the Supreme Court of Canada.
And by this time,
there were several
other brothers and sisters
also charged on sedition,
which meant that if he lost his case,
we had several going to prison
for very lengthy prison terms.
When Brother Boucher’s case
came before the Supreme Court,
he lost by a majority of one.
The Catholic judges
all ruled against him,
and they found that the tract
the Burning Hate of Quebec
was seditious.
Our lawyers looked at the situation,
prayed about it, and thought:
‘What can we do?
We can’t lose this battle.’
And they realized that in Canada
there was a very rarely used provision
of asking the Supreme Court
for a rehearing.
At the rehearing,
one of the Catholic judges
was willing to discuss further
the issue of sedition.
And to be guilty of sedition,
you have to incite to violence.
So our attorney asked them:
“Please, look at the record.
“Show the court
where Jehovah’s Witnesses
incited to violence.”
And finally, they were able
to convince a court they were wrong.
And so they overturned
their initial decision,
and Brother Boucher’s case
was victorious.
This dealt with all
the accusations of sedition
and really brought to an end
the vicious opposition,
because that case
was the one the government
was hoping would work out for them.
There is one case
that’s quite noteworthy in Quebec.
And it’s a case of the priest
calling up the federal police
to come and interrupt
a meeting of Jehovah’s Witnesses
and expel the speaker
from the province of Quebec.
The police obeyed the priest.
They went to the meeting,
they took the brother,
and they escorted him
out of the province into Ontario.
And to disrupt a religious meeting
was a criminal act.
For the first time
—and it’s at the level of the Supreme Court—
they found that the three policemen
had to pay moral damages
to the brothers
for intercepting,
or interrupting, the meeting.
This has never happened before.
And when it came up
to the Supreme Court,
they unanimously ruled
against the province of Quebec.
The section on religious freedom
is the result of these court cases.
Every lawyer in Canada
(whether in Quebec or in English Canada),
when he studies law,
must review these cases.
They are the fundamentals
of religious freedom.
And they represent
the different areas
—police action, government action,
criminal action—
and they lay a very nice basis
for our freedoms today.
Our purpose is to be able
to preach the good news
and to direct people’s attention
toward the Bible.
But our court cases
have helped governments,
courts, judges,
and officials
to have the right point of view
on the issue of religious freedom.
The endurance and hard work
of our brothers in Quebec
truly resulted in a witness
to the nations.
While the hope
for a positive outcome
can at times provide us
with needed motivation,
we can’t always expect support
from the authorities
in this system of things.
The same applies
in many areas of life,
whatever trials we may face.
Perhaps you have lost
a loved one in death.
Looking forward to a time
just around the corner
can help us endure.
That’s also the title
of this month’s music video,
Just Around the Corner.
You can hear the songbirds singing,
And you watch the clouds roll by.
Then you’re walking in the valley
As the sun shines in a clear blue sky.
You’re welcoming your loved ones,
And you can’t believe your eyes.
Yes, this earthly Paradise
Was just around the corner.
There’s a house down in the valley
And a house high on the hill.
There is singing by the river
As the water flows and turns the mill.
The golden fields are waiting.
Let the harvesting begin.
Once the world we’re living in
Was just around the corner.
It’s great to share with friends who care
The things that we looked forward to.
Now every tear has disappeared.
The world is young, and life is new.
There’s the sound of happy voices
And the scent of new mown hay.
Now you’re calling to your loved ones
As you start another perfect day.
Then we thank our God, Jehovah,
For his tender loving care.
Yes, the blessings we all share
Were just around the corner.
And evʹry day I smile and say,
“How good to see your happy face!”
ʹCause once, it seemed, I only dreamed
That you’d be in my warm embrace.
Waiting ʹround the corner
Is a world I long to see.
It’s a promise from Jehovah.
It’s a guaranteed reality.
And it’s hard to get downhearted
When I think of what’s in store.
It’s the day I’m waiting for,
And it’s just around the corner.
What a beautiful song!
Personally, I lost my father
when I was two years old.
He was a soldier in World War II
and was killed in battle.
I never had an opportunity
to get to know him.
Growing up,
I missed having a father
because I saw
everyone else had one.
So I look forward to observing
the earthly resurrection
and seeing my physical father,
and I hope that both he
and my mother
will want to worship
Jehovah in Paradise.
Thank you for sharing that,
Brother Lösch.
When my father comes back
in the resurrection,
I look forward to welcoming him
with open arms.
He was a keen student
of history and the Bible,
and so he will want to know
all about what took place
during this time of the end.
So my family and I
will have a good time
filling him in on what took place.
This music video
and some of the videos we’ve seen
the past few years
at regional conventions
have painted such a clear picture
of the hope we have for the future.
And if we work hard
as champions of the truth,
that hope will become
a reality very soon.
Well said.
And speaking of champions
of the truth,
we would like
to conclude this program
with greetings from our brothers
and sisters in Romania,
a country situated
in the southeast of Europe.
Some of you may know Romania
for its traditional instrument
called the nai, or pan flute.
It’s made of wood
and has around 20 pipes,
arranged in a curved array.
The pitch is adjusted
with beeswax,
which is introduced
in the pipes.
The brothers and sisters
in the Certeze North Congregation,
in the north of Romania,
send us their love.
The congregation is located
near the Ukrainian border,
an area known
for its brightly colored folk costumes.
The congregation
is made up of families
with many generations
of Witnesses,
so they have been
champions of truth
for a long time.
The truth reached this area
about 80 years ago,
and now the congregation
is made up of 126 publishers.
They conduct
about 90 Bible studies,
of which many
attend the meetings.
Because there is
a large concentration
of Witnesses in the area,
the congregation territory
is only five kilometers,
or a little over three miles,
from the one end to the other.
Each territory card
has only about five houses.
Because of that,
the congregation
regularly assists
with working territory
up to 200 kilometers,
or about 124 miles away.
The brothers and sisters
of the Certeze North Congregation
send all of you
champions of the truth
their love and greetings
and so do all of us
at world headquarters.
This is JW Broadcasting
in Brooklyn, New York.