We extend a warm welcome to all of you
to the December 2019 edition
of JW Broadcasting®.
The Watchtower Bible School of Gilead
began on February 1, 1943.
Since then,
thousands of students have benefited
from the school’s in-depth course
of Bible study.
After months of intense study,
graduation day is a highlight for the class.
In this month’s program,
you’ll enjoy Part 1 of the graduation
of the 147th class of Gilead.
Pay close attention
to these encouraging Scriptural talks
delivered to the graduates
on Saturday, September 14, 2019.
Well, this is a very happy day
for those
who are very soon to graduate
from this 147th class of Gilead.
I wanted to begin by asking them a question,
and that is, How far will you go?
Well now,
when people ask that question,
How far will you go?
(normally in connection
with secular education)
the meaning of the question is,
Are you going to get your bachelor’s degree
or are you going to go for your master’s
or are you going to go for a PhD
and get your doctorate?
And so, in that sense,
often going far in secular education
is solely a means of self-fulfillment
and not necessarily to help others.
Some study what’s called pure science,
meant just to advance
mankind’s understanding of science
but with no practical benefit;
some study dead languages;
some study bacteria or insects,
which is wonderful if you like insects.
It may increase knowledge,
but it doesn’t necessarily help anyone.
Well, divine education is so different.
You see, it motivates us to ask the question,
‘How far can I go,
‘not to further myself,
but to help others?’
Now, Jehovah God and Christ Jesus
really set the example for us here.
Would you join me?
Let’s read together Psalm 113,
and let’s look here at verse 6.
Speaking of our wonderful God, Jehovah,
it says:
“He stoops down
to look on heaven and earth.”
Well, now, how high
do you imagine Jehovah to be?
Well, no matter how high you imagine it,
you know it’s still higher.
Jehovah is so high as the Almighty God.
But what does it say here in verse 6?
“He stoops down.”
Well, just think.
You might think of an illustration
of a man who is perhaps very, very tall,
and he’s talking to a very, very small child.
What does he do?
Well, oftentimes he might crouch down,
get down on one knee,
and get right down onto the level
of the child to speak to him.
And as a result,
how does the little child feel?
Well, not so afraid,
not so intimidated by that large man.
The child becomes calm.
Well, think about Jehovah.
How far has Jehovah gone
to “stoop down”
so that we feel loved?
so that we feel valued?
so that we feel appreciated?
What a beautiful example Jehovah sets
in going far to make us feel
so comfortable with him!
Now, what about our Lord Jesus?
Well, think how far he went
to help each one of us.
Just look at the scripture here
in Philippians chapter 2.
Philippians chapter 2
says that Jesus, of course,
came from heaven, didn’t he?
Can you imagine how far that is?
It says in verse 5:
“Keep this mental attitude in you
“that was also in Christ Jesus,
“who, although he was existing in God’s form,
“gave no consideration to a seizure,
“namely, that he should be equal to God.
No, but he emptied himself.”
And what did he do?
He “took a slave’s form and became human.”
Well, that was pretty far to go.
And while you and I think the earth
is pretty amazing and pretty wonderful,
have you ever seen heaven?
And that’s where Jesus left
—willingly—
to come down to be among us, to serve us.
And then in the end, how far did he go?
Well, what does verse 8 say?
“More than that, when he came as a man,
“he humbled himself
and became obedient [to what?]
“to the point of death,
yes, death on a torture stake.”
Jesus was willing to go very, very far
to help people.
Well, now, you have all come to Gilead.
Why did you come to Gilead?
What was the purpose of it?
You see,
was it to increase your Bible knowledge?
Was it to give you
some grand knowledge of Bible history
or to give you
some comprehensive knowledge
of Biblical Greek or Hebrew?
No.
The purpose of your coming to Gilead
was to help you so that you could strengthen
and stabilize the field and branch territory.
That’s the purpose of Gilead.
But now,
what is the field and the branch territory?
What is that?
It’s people
—it’s people that need to be loved;
it’s people that need to be organized;
it’s people that need
to be trained and helped.
And at Gilead, you have learned
that Colossians 4:11
says to be “a source of great comfort” or,
as the footnote says,
to be “a strengthening aid” to other people.
Well, now, the question
that sits before you now is,
How far will you go?
How far will you go to be
fathers and mothers?
to be brothers and sisters
to all of these ones?
There has never been a need,
such a great need,
for this type of help.
We have now in the world
more of our brothers
facing persecution than we have ever seen,
and we expect that that is going to increase.
In some lands, we have lawlessness
on a level previously unheard of,
where kidnapping and rampant violence
occur on a daily basis.
And many of our brothers
are facing anxieties and pressures
that they have never ever
had to experience before.
They need your help;
they need to be strengthened
and comforted by you.
Well, sometimes
you’re going to feel overwhelmed.
Sometimes you’re going to wonder,
‘What should I do?’
And you won’t know exactly what to do.
Sometimes even your best efforts
of working very, very hard
won’t work out the way
that you want them to.
But remember that the brothers and sisters
that you’re working with,
the people that you’re trying to help,
are wonderful people,
and they will work with you,
and they will support you.
But most of all,
our wonderful and amazing God, Jehovah,
will be there to support you.
Here’s an experience that I just heard
that really brought this
to my mind and strengthened it.
It comes from Abaco in the Bahamas.
Now, you remember that just about a week ago,
we had this terrible Hurricane Dorian
that struck this part of the world.
The Disaster Relief Committee in the Bahamas
was working very hard to evacuate
our brothers from Abaco Island to Nassau.
Now, they had an airplane.
They worked very hard to have
an airplane ready to go in the evening.
And although almost all communication
had been cut off with Abaco Island,
they sent a message on all possible channels
for the brothers in Abaco
to make their way to the airstrip.
Now, as they were loading
the plane with all the necessary materials,
they were told that the government
would not grant permission
for the plane to land that day.
Now, the brothers tried everything.
They persisted,
but the government authorities
would not budge.
Can you imagine how they felt?
But an hour or so later,
much to their surprise,
they heard reports
that 14 brothers and sisters
from Abaco would be landing soon in Nassau.
And they wondered,
‘How could this be possible?’
Well, they made preparations immediately
at the Nassau Assembly Hall,
and 14 exhausted, hungry brothers and sisters
arrived who had just been evacuated.
There was a congregation meeting
just ending at the Assembly Hall.
The brothers all went out greeting them
and singing our new song “Unfailing Love.”
Can you imagine what the scene
must have been there at Nassau?
But, of course, the question was,
How could this have happened?
Well, the brothers explained:
“We heard the message to go to the airstrip,
“so we made our journey there.
“A plane arrived,
and we thought it was the brothers,
“but it was a company
who had a plane circling the island.
“When they saw
a group of people at the airstrip,
they landed and evacuated us.”
Everyone was in tears.
Fourteen of the brothers got the message.
They followed the direction.
They assembled to be rescued,
and the Disaster Relief Committee said,
“Jehovah made sure that his people
were evacuated to safety.”
Isn’t that wonderful?
So even when your best
doesn’t seem to be good enough,
Jehovah will make up for it.
Do your best, and Jehovah will do the rest.
If you have love for God
and you have love
for your brothers in your heart,
how far will you go?
You will go very, very far.
Well, we’re looking
forward now to our first talk
from a member of the Governing Body,
our dear Brother Samuel Herd,
and he is going to give us
a very fine warning.
His talk is entitled
“Be Careful! ‘Knowledge Puffs Up.’”
I’m looking at you.
I’m looking at you too.
But you have something that I can’t see.
It’s in your head and in your heart.
It’s knowledge.
You’ve been cramming now for five months,
stuffing things into that brain
and allowing it through meditation
to trickle down into your heart.
So you may feel that you have enough.
“I can’t get any more into the brain.”
But we know better.
There’s still room for you
to put a little more knowledge
into the brain.
And you’re going to do that,
but you may feel right now
that you are ready to explode.
Don’t you do it.
But here’s something to think about:
“Knowledge puffs up,
but love builds up.”
Now, that’s a scripture
found at 1 Corinthians 8:1.
Now, it doesn’t have to be this way,
especially with divine knowledge,
the knowledge that you receive from Jehovah.
It’s not designed to puff you up
and to make you feel better
than your neighbors
—your brothers and your sisters—
who may not have the amount
of knowledge and education
that you have
and what you have just now received.
No, that’s not the purpose
of the knowledge that you have acquired
here in Gilead School.
But there is something
we have to think about.
What is that?
Well, let’s open our Bibles.
Let’s open our Bibles to 2 Peter,
and let’s take a look
at what is stated here at 2 Peter
the first chapter, verses 5 and 6.
It says: “For this very reason,
“put forth all earnest effort
to supply to your faith virtue,
“to your virtue knowledge,
to your knowledge self-control,
“to your self-control endurance,
to your endurance godly devotion.”
You see what you must apply
to your knowledge?
Self-control.
We can’t allow our mouths to just run wild
with the information that we’ve received
—just spreading it everywhere.
It doesn’t matter who may receive it,
but you have to control
how much knowledge you permit
to flow out of your mouth at a given time.
Self-control is needed.
So that means we should not boast
over our accomplishments.
All glory must go to Jehovah God
and not to ourselves.
And it’s easy for others
to feel that we are putting them
down a little bit
because of the vast knowledge that we have.
So we have to be careful
and control it and not boast.
It reminded me of a story,
a fable, I heard years ago
about a little flea by the name of Herman.
Herman the Flea got on the back
of a giant elephant.
And he rode on that elephant
across the rickety bridge,
and the bridge just shook as if it was
going to explode and fall apart.
But they made it to the other side.
And when they made it to the other side
and the flea left the elephant
and found his friends,
he bragged about what he was able to do,
along with the elephant,
in making that bridge shake
as they crossed it.
Now, how much do you feel
that that flea contributed
to the shaking of that bridge?
Now what we’re going to do, though—
We’re going to leave the fable,
and we’re going to go to the Bible.
Let’s go to the Bible,
and we’re going to trade that flea
in for a grasshopper.
Now, here it is—Isaiah 40:22.
Take a look at it:
“There is One who dwells
above the circle of the earth,
“and its inhabitants are like grasshoppers.
“He is stretching out the heavens
like a fine gauze,
and he spreads them out
like a tent to dwell in.”
Now, what we can do is we
can apply this to ourselves.
Now, of course,
in this scripture’s context,
Jehovah is really not talking
about his people as grasshoppers
but of people with worldly knowledge
that they’ve acquired.
They are like grasshoppers
as far as Jehovah is concerned.
You see the whole context
of what he’s talking about.
But we’re going to apply it to ourselves
because we are so small
in the eyes of Jehovah
that we can be just like a grasshopper
on the back of a giant elephant.
And our accomplishments that we make
are not of our own abilities,
but it’s because of the help that we have
coming from heaven—Jehovah.
And we find that the apostle Paul
set a fine example of not being a braggart.
What did he have?
Well, he had so much knowledge.
In fact, when known
as the man Saul of Tarsus,
he was highly educated and was a Pharisee,
and that was viewed
as an impeccable Jewish pedigree
that this man had.
But when he wrote letters,
he didn’t glorify himself.
For instance,
take a look at 1 Corinthians chapter 2,
and read along with me verses 1 through 5.
And you’ll find that he did not
allow knowledge to puff him up.
This is how it reads:
“So when I came to you, brothers,
I did not come with extravagant speech
“or wisdom declaring
the sacred secret of God to you.
“For I decided not to know anything
among you except Jesus Christ,
“and him executed on the stake.
“And I came to you in weakness
and in fear and with much trembling;
“and my speech and what I preached were
“not with persuasive words of wisdom
“but with a demonstration
of spirit and power,
“so that your faith might be,
“not in men’s wisdom,
but in God’s power.”
There’s the example.
Let’s try our best to follow that example
and not be like men and women of the world
who attend these great universities.
And they come out,
and they’re able to get doctorate degrees
in science or this or that,
and they kind of show all that off.
But we’re not like that.
But we could be if we’re not careful.
Now, the Bible shows
what worldly wisdom can accomplish
and what it cannot accomplish.
For instance, in Ecclesiastes 1:16-18,
the account starts off this way.
It says: “Then I said in my heart: ‘Look!
“‘I have acquired great wisdom,
“‘more than anyone
who was before me in Jerusalem,
and my heart gained a great deal
of wisdom and knowledge.’”
It goes on:
“I applied my heart to knowing wisdom
“and to knowing madness and to knowing folly,
“and this too is a chasing after the wind.
“For an abundance of wisdom
brings an abundance of frustration,
so that whoever increases
knowledge increases pain.”
Now, if you’ve got a little whiff of that,
Know-it-all,
then blow it away.
Move away from it.
You don’t want to think that way.
Let’s never try to be a know-it-all.
Jesus doesn’t know everything
that he has been learning
from Jehovah for aeons of time.
Now, how long is an aeon?
An aeon is a really, really, superlong,
impossible-to-measure length of time.
That’s an aeon.
Only Jehovah knows everything.
Keep that in mind.
There is nothing beyond his understanding.
How do we know that?
Well, the Bible tells us.
That same chapter where he mentions
a grasshopper
—Isaiah chapter 40—
but this time verses 13 and 14 say:
“Who has taken the measurements
of the spirit of Jehovah,
“and who can instruct him as [an] adviser?
“With whom did he consult
to gain understanding,
“or who teaches him in the path of justice,
or teaches him knowledge,
or shows him the way of true understanding?”
Think about it.
We can know what we need to know
at the time we need to know it.
Now, that’s a mouthful!
Or should we say, “a headful”?
Yes, all of you graduates of Gilead School,
please share with others
what you’ve learned here at Gilead School.
Don’t walk away from this talk thinking
you should keep your mouths closed.
We’re not saying that.
But control what you say and when you say it
and to whom you tell it to.
So we know that you’ve learned
so much at this school,
but share it discreetly.
Keep in mind these words of King Solomon.
He says: “There is an appointed time
for everything, . . .
a time to be silent and a time to speak.”
Don’t point to yourselves; point heavenward.
Always glorify Jehovah; point to Jehovah.
Now, Governing Body members
—all of us—
we have to be very careful ourselves
because we get credit for things
that we are not responsible for.
Brothers will come and hug you:
“Oh, thank you, brother,
you Governing Body member
—you really, wow, whoo, how, wah!”
Now, we know we didn’t do anything.
You could have done
what we did if you’d been in our seat.
It’s Jehovah’s spirit that causes
these things to happen.
Now, it’s true that we’re tools that he uses,
but he’s the One.
Now, we’re not saying that you can’t say,
“Thank you, brother,
for what you’re doing, the work that you do.”
No, we’re not saying that.
It’s just—
Be careful that you’re not glorifying men,
but glorify God.
The Governing Body gets credit
that we don’t deserve.
It belongs to Jehovah and Jesus,
and we haven’t been able to close the mouths
of over eight million bleating sheep.
But we will keep trying.
So in conclusion,
be like the grasshopper
that rode on the back of the elephant.
Stay close to Jehovah, and enjoy the ride;
but always give Him the credit
for your accomplishments.
Well, we thank you so much, Brother Herd,
for that excellent warning for us.
Of course, the one day
I mention insects in my introduction,
Brother Herd uses insects in his talk.
I guess we do need to know about insects.
Well, now we’re looking forward to hearing
from a helper to the Service Committee
of the Governing Body,
Brother Christopher Mavor,
and Brother Mavor
is going to speak to us on the topic
“‘Count Your Days.’”
Isn’t it true that we often “count our days”
when we anticipate an exciting event?
And no doubt you Gilead students
were counting your days
in anticipation of this day.
And then, if you were,
you know that today is
the 138th day
of your Gilead School experience.
But after today,
will you continue to ‘count your days’?
Should you?
To answer that question,
please open your Bibles to the 90th Psalm,
and it’s a prayer that Moses said to Jehovah.
And notice what Moses
asked him in verse 12:
“Teach us how to count our days
so that we may acquire a heart of wisdom.”
So the answer to this question is,
Yes, we should continue to count our days.
But what does that mean—count your days?
And why will we need God’s help to do it?
The answer is this:
because we are dedicated servants
of Jehovah God.
Each and every day,
we need to make sure that we are using it
in his service to bring him glory.
Now, we’re imperfect,
so this is not always easy to do.
In fact, if we look at verse 10
of the 90th Psalm,
we notice that Moses said
that our days are few
and they are filled
with a lot of difficulties.
So we need God’s help
to fulfill our dedication.
Yes, we need to count our days,
and Jehovah promises
that he will be there to help us.
Notice this promise at Isaiah 30:21.
Jehovah says: “And your own ears
will hear a word behind you saying,
“‘This is the way.
“Walk in it,’
in case you should go to the right
or in case you should go to the left.”
So the reality is that we need Jehovah
to help us to live a dedicated life to him.
Thankfully,
we don’t need to figure it out on our own.
He’s there to guide and direct us.
But did you note what he expects of us?
Looking back at that scripture,
he says that when he tells you something,
“walk in it.”
That’s an emphatic statement, isn’t it?
It doesn’t leave any doubt.
We need to do it
and make it happen in our life.
We cannot be passive about our dedication.
You know, as Christians,
we live a very busy life.
We have various events to go to.
And especially
if you’re in full-time service,
well, you are given an assignment
and oftentimes
that assignment is spelled out for you,
and even the schedule in which
to accomplish that work is set for us.
We don’t really need
to think too much about it.
Now, if we’re not careful,
we could just get carried along
with the flow of time
and the flow of the work and not remember
why we are doing it
and who we are doing it for.
In fact, we could become like
this fine young brother on a raft.
He is enjoying himself;
he’s going with the flow of the time.
But is he really mindful
of where he is going and why?
He’s sitting down; he’s looking all around.
The oar is not in his hand.
He’s not actively steering his life;
he’s passive.
Now, being passive
in our dedication to Jehovah
is a very dangerous situation
because as Ecclesiastes 9:11 tells us:
‘Time and unexpected events overtake us.’
Now this fine brother
is about to get a rude awakening.
An unexpected rock has popped up.
A sudden storm of difficulties
has overtaken him.
Because he was passive,
he was caught off guard.
He lost his balance.
Now he’s suffering spiritual shipwreck.
He did not count his days.
He forgot to listen to Jehovah God
and to pay attention
to his dedication in his life.
He wasn’t listening.
Jesus emphasized
that it’s so important for us
not to be passive
about our dedication to God.
At Luke 13:24, Jesus made it clear
that we are to ‘exert ourselves vigorously,’
not just at a work assignment,
but in our life as a Christian
—being personally involved in what
we are doing in our Christian dedication.
The apostle Paul also gave good counsel
to the young man Timothy
that we benefit from today.
At 1 Timothy 4:7,
you’ll recall that Paul said:
“Train yourself
with godly devotion as your aim.”
Now, when we’re training ourselves,
that means we’re not finished yet;
we’re still in the competition;
we’re still in training.
Godly devotion
must be something that we personally do
for ourselves and work at it.
It just doesn’t happen on its own.
But thankfully, Jehovah helps us.
He’s given us his Word, the Bible.
He’s given us his organization, which
helps us apply Bible principles in our life
and gives us warnings
on the things to look out for.
It’s up to us to do it.
It’s as if Jehovah gives us the oar,
and he says, ‘Now pick it up,
and use it in your stream of time.’
And when we do,
then we’re like this young brother now.
He’s taking a firm hold on the oar.
He’s using it even during
peaceful times in his life,
making sure that his life is continuing on
in a faithful Christian course.
Then, when he encounters
temptations or trials,
well, he’s got his oar in his hand.
Jehovah is there to help him
and to guide and direct him,
to navigate through the difficult times.
It takes effort;
it can be distressing,
but Jehovah has given us the means
to navigate through these difficult times
and to continue on in pursuing
our dedicated Christian life.
Jesus set the perfect example in this.
Every day, Jesus relied
heavily on Jehovah’s direction.
He did not take it for granted.
But Jesus knew that when he was sent
to the earth, he had an assignment;
he was on a very strict time budget.
It was humanly impossible, really,
for a man, even a perfect man,
to accomplish what Jesus did.
He relied on Jehovah.
He did not take a casual viewpoint of it,
but every day he looked to Jehovah
to help him to apply the principles
that he learned through His Word
—the direction that he received
from Jehovah God
in going through this difficult assignment.
And Jesus knew at the end of the day
—after the things he preached
and the things he did—
He knew that that was a miracle.
He said so at John 14:10.
He said: “The Father who remains
in union with me is doing his works.”
He knew that Jehovah was backing him up,
and Jesus worked with Jehovah.
He didn’t take a casual view of it.
Now, we can have
the same kind of confidence in Jehovah.
He is there for us,
even when we are encountering something
that we feel is humanly impossible.
We have a good example of that.
There was a couple
who graduated in the 24th class of Gilead.
Their names are Malcolm and Grace Allen.
Now, their life story
is in the October 15, 2013, Watchtower,
and it’s really worthwhile reading.
We will find that in their early life
they both pioneered;
they got married; they pioneered together;
they were in the circuit work
for a number of years;
they were invited to Gilead;
and after Gilead,
they were assigned to Brooklyn Bethel.
And there Brother Allen served
in some very responsible positions,
and his wife was a housekeeper.
They loved their Bethel service.
But 25 years into their Bethel career,
their course in life took a sudden change
—a detour.
Unexpectedly,
both sets of parents
became very ill and needy,
and it became apparent that they
would have to relinquish their Bethel service
and full-time service
in order to care for them.
Now, mind you, at this point in their life,
they’re both in their late 50’s.
They used their youth in service to God,
so Brother Allen did not really have
a secular career
or a skill on which to go back to.
He needed to start in his late 50’s
to be the breadwinner of the family.
Sister Allen now needed
to take care of both sets of parents.
This was a sharp change in events for them,
but they held firm to their oar
that Jehovah God had given them.
They learned to rely on Jehovah God
and to lean on him
every inch of the way,
and they were successful.
Brother Allen found a job
as an insurance salesman,
which provided for the family.
And they kept going,
even though it was stressful times.
They were successful.
Now, eventually,
their parents died, and they thought,
‘Well, maybe
we can return to Bethel service.’
But unfortunately,
at this point in their life,
their own health and age overtook them.
And now they had to be content with being
good, local, congregation publishers.
How did they view this?
Was this a view of failure on their part?
Did they think, ‘I failed’ or ‘I’m bitter
because of things that happened’?
Well, Brother Allen makes
this very profound statement
about life in Jehovah’s service.
This is what he says:
“Life is unpredictable at times, uncertain,
“and even hard to deal with.
“But Jehovah blesses those who lean on him,
not on their own understanding.
“This is what my wife and I have experienced
over our long and rewarding life.”
They rejoiced in their life
as dedicated servants of God
by taking advantage
of every opportunity to express
their dedication to him
and pursuing and practicing
godly devotion in their life.
And they saw Jehovah’s hand
in their life in truly miraculous ways.
Now, they will experience
another miracle of God,
because both of them
are now sleeping in the grave.
But we know that Jehovah
has already calculated the days
when he will resurrect Malcolm and Grace
and bring them back to life
so that they can continue serving him
in a dedicated way
for an eternity of days to come.
This is certainly
a good lesson for all of us:
to count our days
and to be fully invested in our journey
as a dedicated Christian to Jehovah.
Therefore, you Gilead students
and really all of us,
let us continue to lean on Jehovah
and to work vigorously
at doing what Jehovah directs us to do
during these difficult last days
—living up to our dedication to God!
And by doing so, we can be assured
that we too will be blessed by Jehovah.
He will give us an eternity of days to enjoy
in his glorious new world soon to come.
Well, we thank you very much, Brother Mavor,
for that very good reminder.
Well, now we have the privilege to hear
from one of our more recently
appointed helpers to the Governing Body
—Brother Leonard Myers—
a helper to the Writing Committee.
He’s going to speak to us on the topic
“‘You Trusted in Me.’”
“You trusted in me.”
Now, you may be saying:
“Brother Myers, I don’t even know you.
How can I trust in you?”
And it’s true that we need
to have a relationship
with an individual to truly trust him.
But the “me” in our talk title
isn’t referring to any human;
it’s referring to our
trustworthy God, Jehovah.
And that phrase
“you trusted in me” was stated
by Jehovah to the faithful man Ebed-melech.
Why could Jehovah tell him that?
And how can his example help you students?
Well, turn with me, please,
to Jeremiah chapter 38.
And as we review his example,
look for ways
that Ebed-melech trusted in Jehovah.
Now, as you know,
Ebed-melech was an Ethiopian eunuch
employed in the house of King Zedekiah,
and he was a friend of the prophet Jeremiah.
At the time, Jerusalem
was under siege by the Babylonians,
and Jeremiah had repeatedly declared
that this city was doomed.
He had encouraged the people
to save themselves by surrendering.
Now, that enraged certain princes
who were Zedekiah’s advisers.
They were determined
to defend the city at all costs,
and Jeremiah was an obstacle to that defense.
Well, if you look in verse 4
of Jeremiah chapter 38,
the princes went to Zedekiah,
and they accused Jeremiah of weakening
the morale of the soldiers
and all the people.
Weak king that he was,
Zedekiah stated in verse 5:
“Look! He is in your hands,
for the king cannot do anything to stop you.”
Well, we know what that resulted in.
Those princes had Jeremiah
lowered into a miry, muddy cistern.
With the food supply
being virtually exhausted in Jerusalem,
there was no hope
of Jeremiah receiving food from anyone.
His death was just a matter of time.
Well, in stepped Ebed-melech.
He heard what those princes had done,
and trusting in Jehovah,
he approached the king,
not privately and not secretly,
but in public at one of the city gates.
And notice what he stated in verse 9:
“O my lord the king,
“what these men have done
to Jeremiah the prophet is evil!
“They have thrown him into the cistern,
“and he will die there because of the famine,
for there is no bread left in the city.”
And what was the result
of his bold action and trust in Jehovah?
The king stated in verse 10:
“Take 30 men with you from here,
and pull Jeremiah the prophet
up out of the cistern before he dies.”
Now, 30 men certainly
would have served as a protection.
Yet, Ebed-melech may still have feared
what those princes would do to him.
But his concern was outweighed
by his friendship
and respect for Jehovah’s prophet
and by his trust in Jehovah.
And as we know, verses 11-13
outline his successful rescue mission.
But why could Ebed-melech be so courageous
when he approached
the king and rescued Jeremiah?
It was because he trusted in Jehovah.
And because of that trust,
notice how Jehovah would reward him.
In chapter 39, we’ll start reading
in the B  portion of verse 16.
Notice Jehovah’s words
through Jeremiah to Ebed-melech:
“‘Here I am fulfilling my words
on this city for calamity and not for good,
“‘and in that day you will see it happen.
“But I will rescue you
in that day,’ declares Jehovah,
“‘and you will not be handed over
to the men you fear.
“‘For I will surely provide you with escape,
and you will not fall by the sword.
“‘You will have your life as a spoil,
because you trusted in me.’”
Ebed-melech didn’t need to fear.
As he had viewed Jeremiah’s life as precious,
so Jehovah viewed his life as precious
and would preserve him alive
—all because, as verse 18 says,
‘he trusted in Jehovah.’
Now, whether he was deported
to Babylon and died a natural death
or was left back in the land of Judah,
the Bible doesn’t say,
but his life would be spared,
and he could continue to worship
the God in whom he trusted.
At this point,
Ebed-melech vanishes from Bible history
but not his name nor the example
that he set for you and me
to trust in Jehovah.
Now, this thought of trusting
in Jehovah isn’t new to you students.
Trusting in Jehovah got you to Gilead.
In your assignments at Bethel or the field,
you proved your trust in God.
Trust helped you
through your studies at Gilead.
Do you remember the times
when you prayed for Jehovah’s help
with an assignment or a test
or, as one recent graduate said,
“when your brain was full and you needed
a full week off to digest all the material”?
Remember those times?
See, that took trust
that Jehovah would help you.
And as you look to the future,
trusting in Jehovah
will help you to be successful
in your assignments.
Notice these comments from graduates
of the last class of Gilead.
One brother wrote:
“We have placed our lives in Jehovah’s hands.
“We pray to Jehovah
with an intensity and trust
that never existed before.”
Another brother wrote:
“At times I have felt like, ‘What do we do?’
“Then I’m reminded that we confidently leave
the matter in Jehovah’s hands,
trusting that he will handle it
or make clear to us the course to take.”
And finally another brother wrote:
“At times we have felt quite overwhelmed
“with the new language,
responsibilities, culture, and so forth.
“However, our trust in Jehovah
“reminds us that this is his organization
“—his work—
and they are his sheep.
“If we do our part and work hard,
there is no doubt that he’ll help us.
We never have to rely on ourselves.”
Like Ebed-melech, trusting in Jehovah
will help you
to be successful in your assignments.
Here are two ways
that you can add to your trust.
(1) Trusting in Jehovah
involves trusting
in the power of holy spirit.
For example,
trusting in that spirit will help you
to deal with your brothers and sisters.
Now, your assignments
will involve close contact with them.
Will there be challenges at times?
Very likely.
We’re all imperfect.
Trust that holy spirit can help you
to cultivate the love,
peace, patience, mildness, and self-control
that you’ll need
to deal with those situations.
(2) Trusting in Jehovah means
trusting those whom he trusts.
Jehovah has arranged for
“the faithful and discreet slave”
to care for earthly Kingdom interests.
Trust in the appointment of the slave,
trust in Jehovah’s arrangement,
follow any direction that the slave provides.
Those are two ways
that you can add to your trust in Jehovah.
We encourage you to trust in Jehovah,
especially when you face
challenging situations.
During those times,
remember scriptures such as these:
Proverbs 3:5:
“Trust in Jehovah with all your heart,
and do not rely on your own understanding”;
Psalm 56:3, 4:
“When I am afraid, I put my trust in you.
“In God
—whose word I praise—
in God I put my trust”;
and Isaiah 26:3, 4:
“You will safeguard those
who fully lean on you;
“you will give them continuous peace,
“because it is in you that they trust.
Trust in Jehovah forever.”
Scriptures like those
can really help you during challenging times.
Trust got you here to Gilead,
trust helped you through your studies,
and trust in Jehovah
will help you in your assignments.
Like Ebed-melech,
continue to trust in Jehovah.
You know, one day I hope
to get to know all of you students.
Then we can truly say
that we trust one another.
Until then, continue to trust in Jehovah
so that he can say
of you dear Gilead students:
“You trusted in me.”
Well, we thank you
for that excellent advice, Brother Myers.
And now we’re looking forward to hearing
from one of the Gilead instructors,
and I’m sure all the students are going
to be interested to hear what he has to say.
Brother James Cauthon
is going to speak to us on the subject
“Shaken but Not Forsaken.”
Congratulations.
Today, you become a graduate
of the 147th class of Gilead.
It’s a day to be celebrated;
it’s a day to be enjoyed.
And you deserve it; you worked hard.
And even when you thought
you had reached your limit,
you didn’t give up.
You kept coming in;
you kept trusting in Jehovah.
As your instructors, we’re very pleased
to see your happy, smiling faces.
And if we could, we’d wish that for you
every day for the rest of your lives.
However, as much as we try,
we can’t control what happens
to us in life, isn’t that true?
A change comes for everyone.
Sooner or later, it’s inevitable.
Some changes are small.
Other changes,
however, can rock our world
and leave us shaken to the core.
And when that happens,
we may suddenly find
that we’re no longer
the person we thought we were.
It can seem as if our very identity
has been ripped away from us.
Consider Moses.
Moses grew up in one of the most
luxuriant places on earth at the time,
that is, the Egyptian royal court.
Members of the royal household
resided in opulent mansions
that were dotted along the Nile.
These homes
were decorated in precious stones,
incorporated with pools and gardens.
They housed a large staff
that prepared lavish meals.
Moses likely had a knowledge
and understanding of some
of the most amazing structures
the world has ever seen, and why?
Likely, it’s because
he was schooled from a young age
in subjects such as writing,
math, science, and architecture.
In addition,
Moses may have witnessed
Egypt’s rise to become a mighty empire
and a powerful military force.
Moses enjoyed a privileged
and extravagant upbringing,
and no doubt he became
a man of confidence and influence.
Acts 7:22 says:
“So Moses was instructed
in all the wisdom of the Egyptians.
In fact, he was powerful
in his words and deeds.”
So when he killed an Egyptian
on behalf of his fellow Hebrew brother,
he saw himself as a deliverer.
He was confident,
he was ready, but he was wrong.
We know what happened.
He fled to Midian.
He was no longer the favorite prince
and no longer in charge of anyone
except some sheep.
The confidence he knew back in Egypt
had been replaced
with confusion, loss, and fear.
Moses must have been shaken.
So often, disappointments in life
bring on feelings of sadness,
self-doubt, and worthlessness.
And those things, in effect,
strip us of our cherished identity.
And we’re especially vulnerable
if we define ourselves
by our natural skills and qualities
or by what others think of us
or even by our assignment or position.
In effect, when we do that, we’re saying:
“I am what I do”
or “I am what others think of me.”
These are deceptive filters
that cause us to lose sight
of who we really are
and, then, when change comes,
we’re shaken.
But are we forsaken?
Let’s consider Moses again.
Moses was the chosen one to—
Was Moses the chosen one
to deliver the Hebrews?
Well, the answer is yes.
Was it Jehovah’s time?
The answer is no,
and neither was he fully qualified
for the appointment
or the assignment.
You see, he needed divine training,
and that was something
that he could not get in Egypt.
It’s true that he had worldly education;
he had confidence; he had poise,
but he needed the qualities
of patience, meekness,
humility, and self-control
to be developed to a greater degree.
Jehovah saw that,
and he knew just how to accomplish it.
That would be the lowly occupation
of being a shepherd in Midian.
Now, after 40 years,
Moses sees the flaming thorn bush,
and to his surprise and shock,
Jehovah commissions him 40 years later.
Now think about how Moses
must have felt at that moment
—the realization that he wasn’t worthless
and that Jehovah still valued him.
His daily pain of heart
over the suffering of his fellow Hebrews
was now being replaced
with a keen anticipation
for what Jehovah was going to do,
and no doubt in a marvelous way.
So, you see,
Moses was never really forsaken by God.
No.
Rather, Jehovah had been with him
every step of the way
during those 40 years,
molding him and preparing him
for an incredible future assignment
that he could never have possibly imagined.
Jehovah will do the same for you.
You see, he takes a long-range view.
He sees your potential.
He knows how to accomplish it.
And remember that Jehovah
will do it at the right time
and at his time
and that his view must be our view.
So when a change comes,
whatever it may be,
it’s just the scene;
it’s not the entire movie;
it’s a chapter; it’s not the book.
You may not know
what’s coming next, but don’t worry,
Jehovah does.
Decades later, after leading
Jehovah’s people out of Egypt
and navigating through the wilderness,
it was now time for Joshua to step up.
At Deuteronomy 31:8
Moses said to Joshua:
“Jehovah . . . will neither desert you
nor abandon you.”
Those must have been
very encouraging words.
You see, Moses never forgot the lesson
he learned all those years ago.
He had been shaken, yes,
but he was not forsaken.
And perhaps that was his motivation
for writing another passage in the Bible.
See if you remember this:
“Anyone dwelling
in the secret place of the Most High
“will lodge under the shadow of the Almighty.
“I will say to Jehovah:
“‘You are my refuge and my stronghold,
my God in whom I trust.’”
Does that sound familiar?—Psalm 91.
Moses had become absolutely convinced
that Jehovah was always with him
through the good times
and through the hard times.
So like Moses,
you’ll experience joys
and some disappointments
and, sooner or later, change
—perhaps a change
away from a cherished assignment.
It may feel devastating.
You can either roll with it
or you can be rolled over by it.
How will you roll with it?
You can roll with it if you remember
that you’re not your career;
you’re not your assignment;
you’re not your privilege.
You are, however, loved by God,
you have a spiritual heritage,
and you have a wonderful, bright future.
And when you remember that,
you can gracefully
accept the changes that come.
And there’s something else you can do:
You can use your experience to help others.
In fact, your willingness
to help others even when you’re shaken
by a personal experience,
will reveal your loyalty and your maturity.
Do little things
as if they were great things.
Small tasks reveal a big heart.
It’s all a part of our training
now and for life in the new world.
And remember this too:
A change of circumstances
is rarely as important
as a change of attitude.
So it’s not your position,
but it will be your disposition
that will bring Jehovah’s blessing.
So in conclusion: Yes, change will come.
The world changes;
circumstances change; we change.
However, Jehovah does not change,
his Word does not change,
and his love for you will never change.
So while you may be shaken at times,
rest assured,
you will never ever be forsaken.
Well, I don’t know about you,
but I marked down,
“It’s not your position;
it’s your disposition.”
I’ll be using that one in the future.
Thank you very, very much, Brother Cauthon,
for those excellent thoughts.
Well, now we have the privilege to hear
from another of the Gilead instructors,
Brother Mark Noumair.
He’s going to speak to us on the topic
“Remember the Vision.”
One of the rarest privileges
a human has ever had
is to see a vision of Jehovah’s throne.
And it’s good for us now
to look on with a man
who had this privilege
and how the vision changed his life.
What were the circumstances
around this event?
And more importantly for you,
how does it affect you?
And what lessons
do we want you to take to heart?
So please open your Bibles
or listen closely to these words
recorded at Isaiah 6:1.
Isaiah 6:1:
“In the year that King Uzziah died,
“I saw Jehovah sitting
“on a lofty and elevated throne,
and the skirts of his robe
filled the temple.”
The skirts of Jehovah’s magnificent garment
filling the temple
—this is what Isaiah saw.
What does it show?
It shows that Jehovah
was figuratively present in the temple
and that he was keenly aware of everything
that was going on there,
including what had happened with King Uzziah.
Now, recall that Uzziah
was not content with his role as king.
What did he do?
He forced his way
into the holy compartment of the temple.
Why?
To burn incense like a priest.
And for that, he was struck with leprosy.
But it is of interest
that Jehovah inspired Isaiah to write,
not in the year
that Jotham (Uzziah’s son) became king,
but, rather,
“in the year that King Uzziah died.”
By directing Isaiah to pen those words
in the year that Uzziah died,
it could be said
that Jehovah was setting the stage
for teaching Isaiah what qualities he loves
and what qualities he hates.
So you see, this vision is going to be
life-changing for Isaiah,
and we want it to be
life-changing for you.
So, what happens next?
Well, verse 2 shows
that Jehovah reveals something
perhaps no other human has seen in vision
—seraphs.
Isaiah is the only Bible writer
that mentions them.
Now, the privileges these seraphs enjoy
—their high rank and serving close
to the Universal Sovereign—
move them to humbly cover their faces
with their wings
and sing Jehovah’s praises with such power
that the temple foundation shakes.
What lesson in contrast
could Jehovah have been impressing on Isaiah?
Well, consider this:
Uzziah became king at only 16 years old
and showed
tremendous potential at the outset.
When Isaiah became a prophet,
he too was a young man,
most likely in his twenties.
He was married to a supportive wife;
she’s called a prophetess.
So by showing Isaiah
the example of these humble seraphs
in the same year Uzziah died,
it was as if Jehovah was saying:
‘You know, Isaiah, you’re a fine young man.
‘You have a bright future.
‘You have a good wife.
But don’t become presumptuous like Uzziah.’
What a powerful contrast
for Isaiah to meditate on!
No doubt this affected him deeply.
And this is your first lesson:
Like Isaiah, you have a bright future.
Don’t miss the purpose
of why you’ve been called to Gilead.
Your assignment is to honor Jehovah God.
You’ve been trained
to support his organization.
We are investing in you for the future.
So remember the vision.
Imitate the seraphs.
Cover your face,
and don’t spoil your humility
by drawing undue attention to yourself.
You see, even the most subtle boasting
invites others to take
a peek at you and look in.
‘Who are you?
What are you doing?’
No, that detracts from Jehovah’s glory.
So when tempted to blow your own horn,
remember the mighty song of the seraphs.
Sing Jehovah’s praises, not your own.
Any privilege you receive
should make you
more humble like the seraphs,
not puff you up like Uzziah.
And by remaining humble,
Jehovah can use you to a greater extent.
Why?
Because he can trust you
to give him the glory.
Seraphs
—they don’t aspire to be kings;
they don’t aspire to be priests.
But they’re content
with their role as workers.
So be like the seraphs by doing your part
to advance pure worship.
What else could Isaiah learn from this song?
Well, chapter 6, verse 3b says:
“The whole earth is filled with his glory.”
Now, that’s an interesting statement.
Why may Jehovah have included
those words as part of the vision?
Well, consider this:
Isaiah was faced
with extreme apathy in his assignment.
The land of Judah was full of false worship.
The rebellious ten-tribe kingdom of Samaria
had rejected Jehovah.
To Isaiah, it could have felt
like no one was glorifying Jehovah.
‘Where’s the glory for Jehovah?’
If he focused on those trials,
it could have been so easy for him
to get discouraged, to give up.
‘What’s the use?
Why should I put up with this?
No one is listening.’
So, what would help him not to give up?
He would need to go back to the vision
and imagine a future time
of the whole earth
being filled with Jehovah’s glory.
And with eyes of faith,
Isaiah would focus on what Jehovah
was yet to accomplish as part of His purpose.
Jehovah strengthened Isaiah
with prophecies about the future
when the whole earth
would be filled with His glory
—prophecies about the Messiah
and the restoration of true worship.
Isaiah himself even witnessed
the prophecy
being fulfilled in his own lifetime
—the fall of the ten-tribe kingdom
to the Assyrians.
Then more than 40 years later
after his hard work,
imagine, he was honored to record
one of the most spectacular demonstrations
of God’s executional power in all Scripture
—the destruction
of 185,000 soldiers in one night.
An outstanding reminder:
‘Isaiah, my glory
is indeed filling the whole earth.’
It was as if Jehovah was saying:
‘Isaiah, listen;
‘I know you see badness among people,
‘but keep your focus.
‘Focus on the good things
that I’m accomplishing right now
and will accomplish in the future.’
And this is lesson number two for you:
When you find yourself
becoming consumed with trials
—the imperfections of others
(maybe some you work with two,
three, four, five here and there),
the frustrations of the work,
being passed over again for a privilege,
and you start thinking:
‘What’s the use of working hard?
‘Why am I trying so hard to apply
the good training I’ve received at Gilead?
No one here cares’
—take a deep breath.
Back away;
return to the vision;
shift the focus off yourself
and onto the big picture,
which is the whole earth
being filled with Jehovah’s glory.
Put your focus
on the 8.5 million people earth wide
who are glorifying Jehovah God
in his great spiritual temple.
Each one is playing
a small but valuable role
in accomplishing Jehovah’s purpose.
If you do that,
it will help you to cherish
your place in God’s global arrangement.
Next comes the invitation.
The invitation
—here it comes.
And that invitation in verse 8
is so real, so vivid,
to Isaiah that he’s moved to declare:
“Here I am! [Here I am!] Send me!”
No hesitation
—he didn’t ask what he would gain.
He didn’t ask what other assignments
his contemporary prophets got.
‘What about that one?
What about this one?
What’s Micah going to do?
Hosea and what—?’
No.
He just said:
“Here I am! Send me!”
Isn’t that amazing?
And the fact is he didn’t know
everything he was signing up for.
Those details would come later,
and they did
—about 17 years later.
Now Isaiah is told to take
his small son Shear-jashub
and go meet King Ahaz
—wicked King Ahaz—
and offer him help.
I mean, can you imagine?
Isaiah
—what was he thinking?
‘Now, wait a minute,
wait a minute, Jehovah.
‘Ahaz murders his own children,
‘and now you want me
to take my son along?
I said:
“Here I am! Send me—not us.”’
And what about his wife?
What about his wife?
‘Isaiah, you’re not taking my little boy.
Shear-jashub, get back here.’
I mean, you don’t know,
but it just helps you to think about this.
So both Isaiah and his wife
would need to return
to the vision for reassurance
that Jehovah’s skirts, his attention,
was indeed filling Judah.
He was aware of everything.
They would need to trust in Jehovah
—follow his direction.
Isaiah, in effect, said:
‘I’ll go; I’ll go.
I’ll be faithful even if the king is not.’
Isaiah did not let
the tests of others make him fail his.
Lesson number three:
Assignments to support the Kingdom work
are not always easy,
and you wives feel it too.
When your husband receives
an assignment perhaps no one else wants,
you play a crucial role.
How will you respond
when he tells you of the assignment?
‘Why did they pick you?
‘Can’t you tell them to find someone else?
You did it last time.’
Or will you be proud of your husband
—proud of him for being Isaiah-like,
accepting the assignments faithfully,
even volunteering for them?
You wives,
your support is priceless in God’s eyes,
and it can make all the difference.
How do you think
Isaiah remembered the vision?
No doubt he recalled
not only the images but the sounds
of Jehovah’s skirts stretching,
filling the temple;
the seraphs’ powerful wings
beating through the air;
the melodious words echoing in song.
They would no doubt be
permanently etched in his mind.
We can only imagine
that Isaiah and his wife
replayed that vision
over and over again in their minds.
And how it must have helped
them to hold on to Jehovah
and never let go for those 40 plus years.
And the vision can do the same for you.
That’s the point.
This inspired vision, this holy scripture,
can help you
to stick to Jehovah and never let go,
especially when times are hard.
When you are struggling
to keep afloat spiritually,
you have a challenge
you have to overcome,
you might even feel at times
like you’re swimming in mud,
don’t give up.
Make the vision come alive in your mind.
See the images; hear the sounds;
feel the awe Isaiah must have felt.
And then
—and then apply the lessons in your life.
Apply these wonderful Scriptural lessons
in your life.
Imitate the seraphs:
Cover your face; stay humble.
See God’s glory filling the whole earth.
Focus on the big picture.
Keep ablaze the “Here I am! Send me!” fire.
Yes, remember the vision
and let it motivate you
to keep your cherished place
in God’s great spiritual temple now
and in Jehovah’s heart for all eternity.
Well, we thank you so much, Brother Noumair,
for those excellent thoughts.
It truly was
a spiritually enriching Gilead program.
And in the coming weeks,
Parts 2 and 3 of the graduation
will be released on JW Broadcasting,
so keep on the lookout.
We’ll conclude this month’s program
by traveling to the island of Réunion,
located in the Indian Ocean
between Madagascar
and Mauritius.
It’s decorated
with beautiful volcanic sand beaches,
waterfalls,
deep valleys, rugged peaks,
and one of the most
active volcanoes on earth,
Piton de la Fournaise.
The first Kingdom publisher
arrived to Réunion in 1955.
Now more than 3,000
of our brothers and sisters
are serving there;
over 400 of them are regular pioneers.
While French
is the official language of the island,
there are 3 congregations in Malagasy
and 13 in the common tongue
of Creole of Réunion.
Because of the brothers’ evangelizing spirit,
over 6,500 people on Réunion
attended the Memorial
in 2018.
This is the Grand Bois Congregation.
They have more than 130 publishers,
with 13 regular pioneers.
And as of May 2019,
they were conducting 61 Bible studies.
And here is
the Salazie Creole Congregation,
with just 21 publishers.
But they conduct 13 Bible studies!
These warm and hospitable
brothers and sisters
in both Grand Bois and Salazie Creole
are working hard
to proclaim the Kingdom message.
We love our brothers in Réunion
and send them our greetings.
And we love all of you faithful ones
who are viewing this program.
From the World Headquarters
of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
this is JW Broadcasting!