The text and comment in today’s
Examining the Scriptures Daily
was taken from a
Watchtower study article with the theme
“How Can We Maintain ‘a Waiting Attitude’?”
That’s a timely question
for all of us to ponder
because as that Watchtower said:
“Impatience can be dangerous,
for it can cause us to behave rashly.”
What’s the antidote to impatience?
Open, please,
your Bible to the theme text
for that Watchtower study
at Micah 7:7,
and let’s read Micah 7:7 together
and consider for a few moments
how Micah’s good example
can help us to maintain a waiting attitude.
That text reads:
“But as for me,
I will keep on the lookout for Jehovah.
I will show a waiting attitude.”
Or as the footnote says:
“I will wait patiently
“for the God of my salvation.
My God will hear me.”
It’s beautiful
that in just that one verse,
three times Micah refers
to his God—our God—Jehovah.
And that’s a nice reminder
that no matter what the situation is
that may cause us to have feelings
of impatience or frustration,
whenever we put a problem
or difficulty side by side
with our God, Jehovah,
what happens to the situation?
It appears smaller
—manageable with his help.
We might conclude, as did Brother Karl Klein
as published in his life story,
that ‘if Jehovah permits it,
we can take it.’
With Jehovah’s help, we can patiently endure
any trial, circumstance, or situation
as long as necessary without losing our joy.
Micah was confident of that.
Look again at chapter 7 and verse 7.
By saying that he would
“keep on the lookout for Jehovah,”
in effect, Micah was saying
that he was determined
to become like
an active sentry on a watchtower.
So let’s try to picture that:
A wide-eyed watchman on high alert.
That was Micah, spiritually speaking.
He was determined not to get impatient
and not to get frustrated
with things that he could not change.
Was it easy for Micah
to maintain a waiting attitude?
Probably not.
Notice the context that reveals
what circumstances were like
in Israel and in Judah
in Micah’s time.
Notice as you consider
some of the thoughts there
beginning in verse 2
of Micah chapter 7.
He says: “The loyal one
has perished from the earth.”
Verse 3: “Their hands
are expert at doing what is bad.”
Verse 4: “Their best one is like thorns,
their most upright one
is worse than a thorn hedge.”
In fact, in verse 5, he says:
“Do not put faith in your companion
or trust a close friend.
Guard what you say to the one
who lies in your embrace.”
Verse 6: “For a son despises his father,
“a daughter rises up against her mother,
“and a daughter-in-law
is against her mother-in-law;
a man’s enemies
are the men of his household.”
Yes, times were difficult
when Micah was alive.
During wicked King Ahaz’ rule,
the spiritual and moral conditions in Israel
deteriorated to an appalling state.
Can you relate to Micah’s circumstances?
All of Jehovah’s people today
experience a test of endurance,
a test of patience,
because we’re living in a selfish world
where, according to the Scriptures,
people are “unthankful, disloyal,”
they have “no natural affection.”
True Christians are
“objects of hatred,” as Jesus foretold.
Some of our brothers
and sisters experience
hatred and opposition
at school and at work
nearly every day.
Sometimes that hatred
is within the family,
from unbelieving family members.
Think, too, about the hatred
that our brothers and sisters
have experienced who are imprisoned.
I can’t help but think
about the two sisters in Azerbaijan,
who we’re praying fervently for
because of their unjust persecution,
or 600 more in Eritrea,
Nagorno-Karabakh, Singapore,
South Korea, and Turkmenistan.
Those are injustices
that we long to see corrected.
We’d love to see
those situations changed today!
But are we impatient?
No.
We cultivate a waiting attitude.
Added to these circumstances
are the health problems
that many of our brothers
and sisters are facing.
These too are tests of patience,
tests of endurance.
Maybe you’re dealing with a health challenge
or a family member or a friend of yours
is battling one of these
to a greater or lesser degree.
It made me think of the broadcast
for this month, for December,
where we met
Sabina Hernandez, in Panama,
who was born with a severe handicap.
Since birth, her life
has been anything but normal.
But what an encouragement she is!
She’s come to trust in Jehovah.
Like Micah,
she’s developed a waiting attitude,
and this sister is doing her best
to serve Jehovah
despite her health challenge.
She looks forward to the day
when those circumstances will change,
and we do too.
We’d love to see it today, wouldn’t we?
Of course, those problems will end,
and likely it will happen
sooner than we think.
But whether the end of our circumstances
that are so difficult
comes today or a little later,
what can Micah’s example teach us?
Well, think a little deeper about Micah.
Micah served faithfully
for some six decades,
some sixty years.
He did live to see the fulfillment of some
of Jehovah’s judgement messages.
He did see some good fruitage
from his prophesying activity.
But did Micah live to see the fulfillment
of all of Jehovah’s promises?
No.
So, what helped him to wait patiently,
to keep active,
to be confident in Jehovah?
It was his absolute confidence
that Jehovah would in time
fulfill all of His promises.
He trusted completely in Him.
Well, by way of a reminder,
what two practical steps
could we do or do more fully
that will help us to cultivate
that same trusting,
confident waiting attitude?
The first is the text found
at 1 Thessalonians 5:17;
let’s read that together,
1 Thessalonians 5:17.
Perhaps you have it memorized.
It’s one of the easiest verses to do that
—two words.
What does it tell us to do?
“Pray constantly.”
We need to remember that prayer
is real communication with God.
We can never be charged
with talking too much to Jehovah.
When it comes
to real communication with God,
The Watchtower cited this text and said:
“He is willing to listen endlessly
to those who do his will.”
Let’s accept that invitation.
Let’s pray constantly
about the things that distress us.
Let’s cultivate the trust
in him by praying specifically
about the things that we need help with.
But what if we pray constantly
and we’re enduring a situation
and the problem persists?
What then?
Notice Luke 11:9, please.
Jesus’ words give us
every reason for confidence
when it says at Luke 11:9:
“So I say to you, keep on asking,
and it will be given you;
“keep on seeking,
and you will find;
keep on knocking,
and it will be opened to you.”
Yes, we want to do
whatever is in our power
to solve our problems,
having confidence that in time Jehovah
will give us the solution
and until then he’ll help us endure.
Remember what happens to a mountain
when it’s put next to Jehovah.
It becomes a molehill.
We need to turn mountains into molehills
by throwing our concerns
upon Jehovah in prayer.
Micah’s confidence was not misplaced.
Soon he’ll be back with us
in the resurrection
to witness the fulfillment of all
of Jehovah’s promises
that he patiently waited for.
So, like him, may we curb
our natural feelings of impatience
by keeping wide awake in faith,
always “on the lookout for Jehovah.”