Welcome to JW Broadcasting!
This month we’ll consider
ways we can get
the most benefit
from Bible principles.
Here are some highlights:
How can Bible study and meditation
prepare us for trials?
We’ll learn about the example
of Sister Gertrud Pötzinger
through an archived interview.
What principles and Bible accounts
enabled her and her husband, Martin,
to keep their integrity
in Nazi Germany?
Jehovah urges us
to seek first the Kingdom.
What can happen when a person
seeks things in the world
instead of the Kingdom?
We’ll listen to how this young sister
learned to trust Jehovah
and lead a life that brings
true happiness.
Have you ever thought
that a familiar piece of Bible counsel
didn’t apply to your situation?
Well, how can analyzing such counsel
lead to related principles
that fit your specific challenge?
We’ll see
in this encouraging dramatization.
You’re watching
JW Broadcasting for February 2017.
You and I make a lot of decisions every day.
Now, some have a little impact on our lives;
others have a very big impact.
And we can appreciate that we can make
choices and decisions for ourselves.
Think of how life would be
if you made no decisions for yourself
—someone tells you when to go to bed,
they pick out your clothes,
and they tell you what to do for work.
Well, none of us would like that!
Jehovah gave each of us free will,
and that’s the precious gift
of making choices for ourselves.
Now, have you ever thought
about why Jehovah gave us this gift?
I mean,
why trust us with free will
when he knew that we could make
bad choices or decisions?
Well, one powerful reason is love.
The only way to give us the gift of love
is also to give us the gift of free will.
The two are tied together.
You really can’t have
one without the other.
For example,
if I programmed my computer
to give me a message
every day at 2:00 p.m.:
“John, I love you.
I think you’re a wonderful guy,”
I think there’d be a little something
wrong with me if I thought:
‘Aw, isn’t that nice?
My computer, it loves me.’
Yeah, love only exists
if it comes truly
from a free-will expression.
Now, did Jehovah place
any boundaries on free will?
Yes.
They were stated in the Law
to the nation of Israel.
And Jesus later repeated them
at Matthew 22:37-40:
“He said to him:
“‘“You must love Jehovah your God
with your whole heart
“‘“and with your whole soul
and with your whole mind.”
“‘This is the greatest
and first commandment.
“‘The second, like it, is this:
“‘“You must love your
neighbor as yourself.”
“‘On these two commandments
the whole Law hangs,
and the Prophets.’”
So our use of free will
has love of God
and love of neighbor
as its boundaries.
Notice, for example,
what people are doing
in this picture,
both inside the circle boundary
and outside.
See, free will allows us to do
any of the things
we see in the picture.
But love of God
and love of neighbor
move us to reject
what’s outside the circle
and choose
to do the kinds of things
that we see inside the circle.
Now, to stay
within those boundaries,
Jehovah gave us
a marvelous brain
and a built-in conscience,
but he also knows
we need more help.
And that’s why
he also gave us Bible principles
—basic truths from the Bible
that can help us
to make good decisions.
And it can safely be said
that any decision we face
can be guided
by Bible principles.
Now, our Creator, Jehovah,
knows what’s best for us.
And he also trusts us
to make decisions
based on Bible principles
because he knows
that when we do that,
then we’re really,
truly going to be happy, content,
and at peace with him
and with others.
So in review so far:
Jehovah gave us free will
—that’s the privilege
to make choices for ourselves—
and he also gave us
Bible principles
as the boundaries
to our choices.
But making difficult decisions
requires that we train ourselves
to recognize Bible principles
and apply them.
Now let’s read Romans 12:1,
and let’s see how this verse
describes the decision-making process.
“Therefore, I appeal to you
“by the compassions of God, brothers,
“to present your bodies
as a living sacrifice,
“holy and acceptable to God,
a sacred service
with your power of reason.”
So are we using
our “power of reason”
to understand Bible principles?
For example, young children
ask lots of questions.
But has a child ever asked you:
“What happens when I drop a ball?
a pencil? a book?”
No, they don’t ask that.
They know what happens
to anything they drop.
It falls down!
See, the child doesn’t need
rules for every object
but has quickly grasped the principle.
Anything he drops falls down.
Now,
what if an 18-year-old asked you,
“What’s going to happen
when I drop this pen?”
Well, it’s obvious
he’s not been paying attention
to basic principles of life.
So by us paying attention
to Bible principles,
we can very quickly see
the pattern
of love of God
and love of neighbor
and know
the right thing to do
without a long list of rules
for every situation.
Well, how can we train
our “power of reason”?
We train it by paying attention
as we read and study the Bible.
Now, we don’t need rules
for which movies to watch,
which songs to listen to,
or what clothes we can wear.
If we’re paying attention
when we’re reading the Bible,
we train our conscience
with Bible principles
so we can make
such decisions
without needing
a long list of rules.
You know,
we could compare our training
of our “power of reason”
to a blind person
using a guide dog.
Now, an untrained dog
would be very helpful
to a blind person.
It would bark when others
were around, for example.
However,
a dog trained
in specific skills
is amazingly helpful.
The dog knows
when to stop at curbs
and walk around obstacles
that the person
might run their head into.
A guide dog
is also taught a skill called
“intelligent disobedience.”
And even if the blind person
encourages the dog forward,
it won’t obey,
but it’ll pull
the person back from danger.
Now, it can take a year or more
of training for the dog to learn
the amazing skills
that are so helpful to a blind person.
Likewise, our raw,
untrained “power of reason”
can help us to a degree.
However, it can be amazing
if we take the time to train it.
Now, here are
three skills that we can use
to train our “power of reason.”
They are illustrating,
analyzing,
and balancing.
Now, to consider our first skill,
illustrating,
let’s use the general topic
of forgiveness.
What Bible principles
could help with forgiveness?
Please think of as many principles
and scriptures as you can.
Now, if it helps,
you can pause the program now
and write down
the principles that come to mind.
Now, your list
may include principles like these:
Matthew 18:22 says
to forgive “up to 77 times”;
Proverbs 12:18 says:
“The tongue of the wise is a healing”;
and Colossians 3:13 tells us
to ‘forgive one another freely.’
Now, the skill
we want to learn is illustrating
—creating a mental picture
of an idea or principle
to see its real meaning
and impact.
Now, even if we
are not skilled artists,
all of us can and do create
pictures in our minds.
When illustrating,
pay attention to things that are similar
or like the thing
you are trying to visualize.
For example,
if sin is like debt,
then forgiveness
is like someone canceling the debt.
If a hurtful remark
is like a cut,
then forgiveness
is like seeing it heal.
If sin is like a mark
on a blackboard,
forgiveness is like erasing it.
Proverbs 12:18
is a great example
of using the “like” technique.
“Thoughtless speech
is like the stabs of a sword,
but the tongue of the wise
is a healing.”
Imagine what your skin
would look like
if you still had
every open cut, bruise,
or bleeding scratch
since childhood.
See, Jehovah
wonderfully designed our body
to heal such minor cuts
and bruises.
And we can now visualize
how the forgiveness of others
helps us to heal emotionally.
Now, learning to illustrate,
or visualize,
takes time and practice.
However, it can be one
of the most powerful skills we use
to train
our “power of reason,”
and it can also be
quite enjoyable.
You know,
try at your family worship
to take
the principles for a topic
and see
how many similarities,
or “likes,”
you can come up with.
Now, granted,
they all won’t be amazing,
but you may be surprised
by the insights
that come from seeing
something from a new perspective.
Well, let’s consider now
our second skill:
analyzing.
Now, analyzing something means
“examining it carefully in detail.”
And let’s use
the topic of wrong desires.
Now, in this case,
let’s say that we’ve already found
the principle
at Colossians 3:5:
“Deaden, therefore, your body members
that are on the earth
“as respects sexual immorality,
uncleanness,
“uncontrolled sexual passion,
“hurtful desire, and greediness,
which is idolatry.”
Now, what can we learn
from analyzing Colossians 3:5
to help when we struggle
with wrong desires?
Again, feel free
to pause the program
if you want some time
to think about it.
Look carefully
at each step outlined.
Did you notice, for example,
what appears to be
a reverse order
of the steps leading to sin?
This verse works its way
from sexual immorality
back to the very roots
of the problem.
Now, let’s take each phrase
starting with the last,
“greediness, which is idolatry.”
So, sexual immorality
starts with selfishness,
greedily putting our needs
ahead of anything else.
Next is “hurtful desire.”
Greediness leads to “hurtful desire.”
It’s like a person
hanging around a bakery,
smelling the bread and cakes
when he can’t pay for it.
Likewise,
hanging around immoral entertainment
or bad associates
can feed “hurtful desire”
for what is not ours.
Next is listed
“uncontrolled sexual passion.”
So “hurtful desire”
has now turned from an idea
into a strong emotion
of passion,
causing one
to look for an opportunity
to fulfill the desire.
Next, “uncleanness.”
The previous steps have now led
to inappropriate physical conduct
with another person.
Finally, “sexual immorality”
—serious sin.
Sexual immorality
has occurred between persons
that are not married
to one another.
So analyzing Colossians 3:5
can really help us to eliminate,
not stimulate, wrong desires.
And we can see
how important it is
to get rid
of wrong desires immediately.
It’s easier
to walk away from sin
when we’re still in the early stages,
rather than later.
So we need
to practice the skill
of not simply
just reading scriptures
but analyzing them
until we’ve learned
all that we can.
And we can use
the many research tools we have
to find valuable comments
and application.
Now, let’s consider our third
and final skill: balancing.
And to do that,
let’s use a question
on the topic of alcohol.
What Bible principles
could help a couple to decide
whether to serve alcohol
at their wedding?
What principles and scriptures
do you think would help them
make a balanced decision?
Again, you’re welcome
to pause the program
if you’d like to write down
what comes to mind
or to research something.
Now, your list probably has
some of these principles.
At John 2:9,
Jesus made wine for a wedding.
However,
1 Corinthians 6:10 says
that ‘drunkards
will not inherit the Kingdom.’
And 1 Corinthians 10:31, 32 says:
“Whether you are eating or drinking . . . ,
do all things for God’s glory”
and to “keep from becoming
causes for stumbling.”
Now,
it doesn’t seem
that any one principle
provides the answer.
The couple could simply say:
“Well, Jesus served wine at a wedding,
so we can too.”
However, there’s really more
to it than that, isn’t there?
It’s clear that a balance
of all these Bible principles
is needed.
Will relatives
or others be there
who might be prone
to overdrinking?
Would serving alcohol bother
the conscience of many present
because of local customs
and feelings about alcohol?
It’s often the case
when making decisions
that we need to balance
several Bible principles,
not taking any one principle solely
on its own merit.
Jehovah expects us
to use our “power of reason”
to balance Bible principles
and make good decisions.
Ecclesiastes 7:16-18
gives us good advice
about being balanced.
“Do not be overly righteous,
“nor show yourself excessively wise.
“Why should you bring ruin to yourself?
“Do not be excessively wicked,
nor be foolish.
“Why should you die before your time?
“It is best to grasp one warning
“without letting go of the other;
for the one who fears God
will heed them both.”
How true.
Such balance between extremes
is often necessary
when we apply
Bible principles.
We need to heed them both,
so to speak.
We need to balance
all the Bible principles
so we can come
to the decision
that would show love of God
and love of neighbor.
We could illustrate the balance
between different Bible principles
and applying them with this model bike.
It was a gift from a brother in Malawi.
Now, a bicycle has
three basic principles of operation:
the brakes, the pedals, and the steering.
Now, the brakes are really like principles
that slow us down
or stop us from doing the wrong thing.
And the pedals are really like the principles
that move us forward
in showing love for Jehovah
and our brothers and sisters.
And the steering is like our free will
to choose a direction in life
that pleases Jehovah.
So making decisions
is like riding a bicycle.
We have to balance
several Bible principles.
So in review,
Jehovah gave us free will
to use within the boundaries
of love of God and love of neighbor
and many other fine Bible principles.
Making difficult decisions requires
that we train our “power of reason”
to recognize Bible principles
and apply them.
And we discussed
how to train
our power of reason
with the three skills:
illustrating,
analyzing,
and balancing.
So no matter what decisions
you are faced with,
we encourage you:
“Let Bible principles guide you.”
Let’s use
the following dramatization
to practice the skills
we’ve just discussed.
In this video,
three Witnesses all hear
the same familiar Bible counsel
at a Christian meeting.
And at first,
it doesn’t seem to apply
to anything
they’re currently experiencing,
but it does.
Maybe that’s happened to you.
As you listen to their reasoning,
what do you think they
could do to let Bible principles
guide them
to making a good decision?
We must know Jehovah well.
That means knowing
his thinking on matters.
We should welcome
such an examination
and make any necessary changes.
For example,
let’s read
1 Corinthians 15:33 together.
Here we read:
“Do not be misled.
Bad associations spoil useful habits.”
As familiar as that principle is,
can you think of an area in your life
where it’s difficult to apply?
Hey, John.
Hey.
I know it’s not your usual,
but there’s no one to entertain
those clients tonight.
So can you do it?
Thanks.
But I have. . .
Great.
Until then,
it wasn’t my usual thing.
But I need to support my family.
And these aren’t really my friends.
I can handle it.
I think.
. . .we’re faced with bad associations
in subtle ways.
This may require us
to ask additional questions
of ourselves.
Are we letting in bad association
through social media?
Perhaps we can think
of another way bad association. . .
I don’t think so
—except for some friends
from my old congregation.
Wow!
They’re not doing so well spiritually.
But if I stay connected
and see what they’re doing,
maybe I can help them.
. . .can affect us.
Maybe it’s something very specific.
Or maybe
bad association
is coming from a place
we never expected.
I only join games
with Witness friends I know.
But sometimes
they connect
with people I don’t know
who pick games
I’m not sure we should play.
But maybe my friends know them,
so they’re probably OK.
It is vital that we avoid
bad associations.
Now,
as we resume in Psalm 26. . .
The basic principle in this story
is one we all know:
“Bad associations spoil useful habits.”
But do our three friends
find themselves in the same situation,
where they can simply apply
1 Corinthians 15:33
in exactly the same way?
No.
The family head is concerned
about supporting his family.
Our sister wants
to stay in touch with her friends
in hopes of helping them spiritually.
And our young brother
didn’t know exactly who
his associates were.
Are you already thinking of
additional principles
that would apply
to each person’s problem?
How would you illustrate, analyze,
or balance those principles
if you were in their position?
If you want to,
pause the program here.
Take the time to write down
what you’re thinking.
Then watch how they each
search for Bible principles
and train their “power of reason.”
I thought that talk
didn’t apply to me.
But can I really handle
bad association?
If I take a stand,
I may lose my job.
But that’s being anxious
about tomorrow.
Jesus said:
“So never be anxious and say,
“‘What are we to eat?’ or,
“‘What are we to drink?’ or,
‘What are we to wear?’”
Jehovah knows I need a job.
And I need
to set a good example
for when my children
face bad association.
1 Corinthians 15:33.
My friends’ posts
are getting worse
—their pictures and comments.
Hmm, 2 Timothy 2:16.
“But reject empty speeches
“that violate what is holy,
for they will lead
to more and more ungodliness.”
I’m letting them share
“empty speeches” with me online.
I will try to help
them while I still can,
but following their posts
is not the way to do it.
I told Mom what’s been happening
when I game
with my friends.
She gave me good ideas
on what to look for
in the Research Guide.
“Christian Life.”
“Association.”
“Is Your Recreation Beneficial?”
“Who Are My Companions?”
It says,
“Who are the ones I want
to share my leisure time with?”
“Does he have the same Bible-based
values and morals that I have?”
Good question.
I don’t even know
who they are sometimes.
Psalm 119:63 says:
“I am a friend of all who fear you
and of those who keep your orders.”
But if I only know them online,
I can’t know if they fear Jehovah.
Let’s turn in our Bibles
to the book
of 1 Timothy 1:5
and notice how it reads:
“Really, the objective of this instruction
“is love out of a clean heart
“and out of a good conscience
and out of faith without hypocrisy.”
We train our conscience
with Bible principles
that reveal Jehovah’s thinking.
There may be several principles needed
for our unique problem.
But when we find
and apply them,
we’ll enjoy a clean heart
and a good conscience.
How did their Bible principles
and meditation
compare to what
you were thinking?
Now, you may not have come up
with the same scriptures and thoughts,
but that’s OK.
The important thing is that by training
our “power of reason,”
we’re aligning our thoughts
with Jehovah’s thoughts.
Did you see the three skills in use?
The young brother was able
to visualize his potential friends.
He couldn’t see them literally,
but knowing they didn’t fear Jehovah
or keep His orders
painted a picture of the kind of associates
they might prove to be.
When our sister
analyzed 2 Timothy 2:16,
she saw the social media comments
were similar to “empty speeches”
that could weaken her faith.
And the family head balanced
his family responsibilities
by applying the principle
at Matthew 6:31,
where Jesus said
not to be anxious over material things.
And we can imagine him trying
to work the matter out with his boss
while trusting Jehovah
to care for him and his family,
no matter what
might happen to his job.
Think now about another principle
in Matthew chapter 6.
Jesus tells us in verse 33
to ‘seek first the Kingdom.’
Young ones especially
face temptations
—both large and small—
to seek things
in the world instead.
And sadly, some have ignored
Bible principles they have learned.
They’ve looked
for happiness in what appears
to be the exciting possibilities
of this system of things.
In this “Truth Transforms Lives” segment,
Sister Anneliese Zelina explains
what led her to a similar choice
and what drew her back to Jehovah.
Growing up in the truth,
I felt like I fit in
more with my friends at school
or people who weren’t Witnesses.
I was living a double life
and I knew it.
I was not baptized.
I had always tried to make
the truth fit in with the world.
And this time I decided
that I just want to give
the world a shot
and see what that’s like.
I came right to my parents,
and I said,
“I want to move to LA
and pursue modeling.”
I had my first job within the week.
It looked so glamorous.
There were a lot of parties
—going to the coolest houses,
getting to hang out with celebrities.
There are no rules.
You have the money
to do whatever you want.
That lifestyle was so far
from what I was raised knowing as right
that I basically had
no relationship with Jehovah.
Once all the smoke
and mirrors are gone,
you see these things
for what they are.
I remember I called my mom,
and I told her:
“It’s like Sodom and Gomorrah.
I’m literally in the middle of it all.”
And I thought, like, this is it;
this is what everyone says is the best,
and I’m not happy.
And I just felt so dull
—empty.
And I actually thought to myself:
‘I wish—
I wish I was never raised a Witness.
I wish I never even knew Jehovah existed.’
There were certain nights
where I needed him.
I was thinking,
‘Just pray; just go to him.’
And I couldn’t.
I thought I would never be able to
come back to Jehovah.
One of the jobs
I got hired to do
was to work
for this young fashion company.
In between different outfits and shoots,
you would, you know,
talk with the photographer.
So, what are you guys
going to be for Halloween?
Matt doesn’t celebrate Halloween.
He’s one of Jehovah’s Witnesses.
So am I.
It’s not a joke.
No, I’m not kidding.
I was raised as a Witness.
Yeah, I was raised as one as well.
Do you, um—
do you go to meetings?
No, I haven’t been in forever.
What about you?
No, no, I haven’t.
I got a last-minute job to New York.
I decided to walk the Brooklyn Bridge.
I knew Bethel was there,
and I’d never been to Bethel.
This sister stopped me on my tour,
and she invited me up to her office.
There were different paintings
of the resurrection.
She asked me, “Do you know why
the people are waiting on the balcony?”
And I was like,
“I—I don’t know. Why?”
And she said, “Because they’re waiting
for their loved ones to be resurrected.”
It was as if something
just went straight to my heart.
I’ve never felt something like that.
I had for the first time actually seen
the resurrection and believed it.
It wasn’t just this thing that might happen
—it was for sure.
I knew exactly
what it was going to look like.
I would be standing there
on that balcony
looking for my loved ones
to come back,
and I wanted to be there.
The resurrection was so real to me.
And the second I got out of Bethel,
I—I called my mom,
and I told her, and I said:
“Mom, Mom, I’m coming back.
“I know exactly what I need to do.
I’m coming back to Jehovah.”
I had made up my mind, you know,
I’m going to give Jehovah a chance.
But, you know,
I’m coming back to the truth.
I’m going to do it right.
There was an elder
who was doing the Watchtower,
and he just came off so kind
that I thought, you know,
when this meeting ends,
I want to talk with him, and I’m going
to explain to him why I’m here.
I knew I had so many changes to make.
Matthew 6:33 is so important to me,
‘Seek first the Kingdom.’
My entire life I sought
everything else before Jehovah.
I never put him first,
and I for the first time was saying,
“OK, Jehovah, I’m going to put you first.”
The job I have right now
isn’t necessarily my dream job,
but it allows me to do exactly
what I want to do for Jehovah
—and that’s pioneer.
I used to walk down Hollywood Boulevard
going from casting to casting
with my portfolio in hand,
and now I walk down Hollywood Boulevard
with the cart in my hand.
Out in the ministry,
I see models that I used to work with,
and I love getting to show
them that this is my new life,
and this has changed my life.
I am so happy.
I know what it’s like
to superficially feel good.
But to literally have the joy,
the happiness
—I want to share that with everybody.
Jehovah completely changed my life.
We’re so happy
that Sister Zelina returned
and dedicated
her life to Jehovah.
Even though she wanted to forget
what she knew about God,
the things she had learned about him
kept coming back to her mind.
Finally, when she saw
the picture of the resurrection,
while touring Bethel,
it was a powerful reminder
of Jehovah’s love.
Really,
Sister Zelina’s Bible-trained conscience
was at work the entire time.
Young ones, please know
that Jehovah does not want
to hold you back
from having fun,
and he doesn’t want
you to feel guilty
for the desire to use
your talents and to enjoy life.
But he does want to protect you
from spiritual dangers,
and he asks you to seek first
the Kingdom in these last days.
Proverbs 10:22 puts it well:
“It is the blessing of Jehovah
that makes one rich,
and He adds no pain with it.”
It is Satan’s system that adds
any pain we may experience.
Sister Zelina and so many others
have found that scripture to be true.
So often, young ones who choose
to give Jehovah their best
are blessed with ways to use
their talents and interests
in sacred service.
Jehovah wants you to be part
of the exciting fulfillment
of Micah 4:2,
where nations are saying:
“Come, let us go up
to the mountain of Jehovah.”
Well, that verse was the daily text
and part of a morning worship discussion
by Brother Geoffrey Jackson.
Micah’s prophecy is being fulfilled now,
and it results
in our worldwide brotherhood
and highlights the need
for Christian unity and neutrality.
So Brother Jackson asked
an interesting question,
“How important is our neutrality?”
It’s true, isn’t it?
When we look at this prophecy
in the book of Micah,
it’s very exciting
because it portrays to us
what’s actually happening
among God’s people today.
We know that although
in the new world
there will be a tremendous unity
displayed by God’s people,
chapter 4 of Micah
is actually portraying  what’s happening now,
and we’re involved with this.
We know that because
in verse 5 it says
that at the same time
that this unity would be evident:
“All the peoples will walk,
each in the name of its god.”
Well, that’s not talking
about the new world, is it?
It’s talking about the time
we are living in now.
Well, what is it that helps all
of Jehovah’s Witnesses worldwide
to be so united and not to be involved
with the wars of this world?
Well, one of the things that helps us
is our Christian neutrality.
What do we mean by neutrality?
We mean not taking sides
in political issues.
Of course, we take sides
with Jehovah and the Kingdom,
but with regard to worldly political debates
and issues that arise,
we don’t take sides.
Why is this so important?
Well, let’s turn our Bibles
to Revelation chapter 13.
Revelation 13:16, 17,
and here it tells us:
“It puts under compulsion all people
—the small and the great,
“the rich and the poor,
the free and the slaves
“—that these should be marked
on their right hand or on their forehead,
“and that nobody can buy or sell
except a person having the mark,
the name of the wild beast
or the number of its name.”
What’s the point of this verse?
Well, of course,
we will look forward to seeing
how this may
turn out in the future
and what pressure is put
on God’s people at that time.
But even now,
we see the principle here
that the political system is wanting
to put its mark on us,
mentally as well as physically.
So we see the forehead
as well as the hand being involved.
So we need to be absolutely certain
that we remain neutral
with regard to political issues
in the world,
not only by
not being involved actively
in the political issues
but also mentally not allowing
ourselves to take sides.
What are some of the things
that perhaps could erode our neutrality?
Well, maybe we could mention
three things this morning.
One is the propaganda
that the world puts forward.
Now, we have seen what the media says
about Jehovah’s Witnesses, haven’t we?
How distorted some of their reports are
and how they can paint
a negative picture with regard to us.
Well, should we expect
that they are neutral
with regard to other events
that they report on,
particularly when there are conflicts
between two nations?
The media
in one particular nation may promote
certain ideas about the other nation.
We may be affected by that.
We may be surprised perhaps
to visit some other countries
that have a different political ideology
and be surprised to see
how things perhaps are a little different
in that country to how it’s portrayed
by the media in our country.
So we need to be careful
not to be influenced
by the propaganda of this world,
particularly media reports and so on.
What’s another thing perhaps
that could cause us
to lose a measure of neutrality?
Sporting events.
Sometimes sporting events
are able to achieve
certain goals
with regard to nationalism.
We see the national anthem
being played at many of these events.
It reminds me many years ago
when I was in a different country,
a friend of mine asked me
to record a certain sporting event.
I wasn’t particularly
interested in the event,
but because he made this request,
I recorded it.
And, of course, I wanted to make sure
that I got the last ten minutes of it.
I thought our friendship
may be strained
if I didn’t get
the actual last part of the game.
When I watched it,
it was absolutely exciting
—nail-biting finish.
Well, after the brother
gave me back the videotape,
I thought maybe
some of the other brothers
who would be interested
in this sporting event
may want to have it
rather than just wipe the tape.
So I offered it to several,
and each one of them said to me:
“No thanks.
If we had won,
perhaps it would be different.”
Now, what was the problem?
As I said to them,
“Were you watching the game
or were you taking sides?”
An interesting concept,
because here
two different nations were involved.
So we have to be careful
that even sporting events
don’t stir up within us
certain nationalistic feelings,
and perhaps we could take sides
with regard to certain events.
The third area that perhaps
could erode our neutrality:
the political promises being made,
particularly at election time.
Perhaps one of the candidates
is from our ethnic background
or perhaps
is the same gender as we are.
When we look at the political situation
these days with many elections,
it seems to be more in the form
of entertainment than anything else,
with music
and very colorful characters.
But if we were
to say in our heart,
‘I hope that idiot
doesn’t get into power,’
are we neutral?
Or worse still, if we say,
‘I hope the other person
gets into power,’
well, we need
to be careful, don’t we?
I remember many years ago
as a young pioneer in Australia,
I was facing
the conscription issue
—the national call-up
for the military.
At that time,
the Vietnam War was being fought.
And then there was
an election in Australia.
And at that time, the party
that was trying to get into power
said that if they got into power,
they would abolish conscription.
So now that affected me personally.
I remember how hard it was sitting there
watching the election results,
not to say in my heart,
‘I hope they get in.’
And then, when they got in,
not to say, ‘Yes!’
You see, if we personally are affected
by some of these political promises,
we may violate our neutrality.
So brothers and sisters,
let’s work hard at remembering
that we’re no part of this world.
We support the best government
that could ever rule this earth.
And by doing so,
we will keep our neutrality,
and we will keep our unity.
When neutrality is mentioned,
isn’t it true we often think of taking
a stand during times of war?
But Brother Jackson
reminded us that neutrality
is something we do every day
in our thoughts and in our speech.
What a good example
of analyzing a Bible principle
to understand its full meaning
and application for us.
Of course,
there are times when governments
do pressure God’s people
to renounce their faith or take up arms.
This happened
to Sister Gertrud Pötzinger
and her husband, Martin,
in Nazi Germany
during World War II.
Now, later in life, Brother Pötzinger
was a member of the Governing Body,
and he finished
his earthly course in 1988;
but Sister Pötzinger continued
faithful until her death in 2003.
In an archived interview,
Sister Pötzinger described
her wartime experiences.
How did Gertrud and Martin,
like thousands
of our spiritual brothers and sisters,
keep their integrity
through brutal persecution?
I worked underground
and traveled in Silesia,
and at that time,
I visited the families
with copies of The Watchtower.
They caught me and arrested me
in Dresden.
And there, there was
the same strong interrogation,
and Jehovah helped me
in a wonderful way.
I was surprised by myself
—what kind of thoughts
came in my mind
when they asked me,
“Did you know
“that the organization
of the Watchtower
is forbidden
by the government?”
I was saying,
“Sure, I know that.”
“Why were you
working underground
against our command?”
Then I was saying:
“The German judgment,
“they acknowledge the command:
“‘You have not to steal,
not to lie, not to murder.’
“And this came from the Mosaic Law;
it’s from the Bible.
“If you acknowledge
this command,
“then you have to acknowledge
the other command too.
“The Bible is saying:
‘You have to watch
“to come together
and to encourage one another.’
“How can I do it
if I would be ashamed to meet them?
“I want to do the will of God.
This is a commandment.”
The judge was saying nothing.
He spoke with the side judge,
but he gave no answer.
I was sentenced
at first for five years.
And later on,
they made it go down
to three and a half years
because I was so young;
I was 25 years of age.
So I started
my solitary confinement.
But Jehovah’s spirit
made me real joyful.
Every day
I was thinking:
‘Now I have
to make every day
‘a special object
to think about.
‘In fact,
I want to think
about the qualities
of Jehovah.
I’ll start with wisdom.’
And so I put
my fingers in my ears
and was running
to and fro and to and fro.
I wanted
to hear nothing outside.
So, wonderful thoughts
and I was happy.
Then when that was over,
then I thought:
‘What is hope?
What is faith?’
I started to think
about the fruits of the spirit.
You have a lot.
Then I have
so much to think,
and the time runs.
After three and a half years,
the Gestapo
called me again
and gave me
a declaration.
I have to sign
that I never want
to be in connection
with the Jehovah’s Witnesses
and that I refuse
to learn more
from the Bible.
And I said:
“No! Never!”
Then he said,
“You can think for overnight.”
“No!
I want not to think overnight.”
And immediately I said:
“Never will I do it!
Never will I sign it!”
And then he was saying:
“Then you have
to take the consequences.
“You will transfer
to the concentration camp
—to Ravensbruck.”
And when I came,
they ordered that I have
to put all my dress out
and to get them away.
And then I have to stay
with other prisoners
several hours
in a big bedroom.
And we have to wait
till the doctor will see us.
And it was
so humiliating.
They wanted to humiliate,
and they wanted
to make us down.
And the old women
between the young girls,
they were  so strongly ashamed.
You saw it
—how they suffered.
I never will forget this.
And after,
we got the new dress
from the camp
and we were assigned to go
to the punishment barrack.
And then
that was a terrible night.
So many prisoners,
they were crying the night
and others were vomiting
—had to vomit.
It was a terrible night.
The next day,
we had to go for working.
We had so strong to work
from morning
—in summertime,
from 5 o’clock
we were on the roll call place
till evening, 7 o’clock.
Then the quarantine came.
We have to not go out.
They closed the door.
They gave us our meals
through the window,
and we had
a fine time to have rest.
We encouraged one another
with spiritual interests.
And the doctor came
and knocked on the window.
“Who died in your barrack?”
“Nobody.”
No one.
Our old, weak sisters
they overcame all.
Never some became sick.
So it was really a good witness
for the others in the camp.
My husband was
in the concentration camp,
at first in Dachau
and later on in Mauthausen.
They worked
in the stone quarry.
And in that group,
a brother
had the bad shoes;
they were too tight for him,
and he took them off.
And he had forgotten
to take them from the stone quarry
to the camp.
And my husband
wanted to help him,
and he was running
to pick up the shoes.
And the watchman
observed that he
ran away from the lawn,
from the group.
His punishment was to hang
for one hour on the pole.
When I asked my husband,
“How did you overcome
such a torture?”
Then he said:
“I was thinking:
“‘How was the situation
“‘when Abraham
had to kill his son?
“And this was a long way.’
“I was always thinking:
“‘What were his thoughts?
“‘How had he
overcome his feeling
and what Jehovah
wants for him?’”
And in this way,
he didn’t feel anymore.
After one hour,
when he came down,
the other brothers
were saying,
“You don’t look as you have been
on the torture stake.”
So Jehovah can help us
in all such situations.
Every situation we had some
of what was not so easy.
But in every situation,
we have a touch of wonderful help
—Jehovah’s spirit.
And we could pray.
Jehovah’s name
is the most important part in our life.
Nothing is so important
like Jehovah’s name.
Did you see the ways Jehovah blessed
Sister Pötzinger’s determination
to stay loyal under pressure?
At Matthew 10:19,
Jesus told his apostles:
“When they hand you over,
do not become anxious
“about how or what
you are to speak,
for what you are to speak
will be given you in that hour.”
She may have felt that same assurance
when arrested and interrogated.
Then, when tested in the camps,
she and Martin meditated
on Christian qualities
and the faith of Bible characters.
And finally they,
like so many Witnesses,
were helped to survive
because of the love and care
of their spiritual brothers and sisters.
Sister Pötzinger used her experience
to encourage others
in her later assignments.
For example, in the interview
with William and Sandra Malenfant,
Sister Malenfant remembered working
with Sister Pötzinger
in the Bethel Sewing Department,
and Sister Pötzinger had given her
a memorable sewing illustration.
She likened each prayer
to adding another thread
to a strong cord
that unites us with Jehovah.
You might enjoy
watching that interview again
in the “Interviews and Experiences” section,
under “Blessings of Sacred Service.”
Later this month,
you’ll also want to watch
a new original song
under the “Music” section.
In the April 2016 program,
a group of young ones explained
why they visited Bethel
and what they enjoyed seeing.
While there, they also sang
a song about their experience,
with the help of Bethelites,
at the branches they visited.
And we have a music video
to enjoy in this month’s program.
It’s called
Stop, Think, and Pray.
No matter what the problem is,
we should always take time
to think about Bible principles
and pray for Jehovah’s holy spirit.
Life’s not easy when trouble’s around
And the whole situation is getting you down.
So-called friends, they just want a reaction.
Turn to Jehovah and pray—
Silently pray.
Don’t give up; don’t give in.
Put your trust in Jehovah.
Keep it calm; we can win
If we stop, think, and pray.
When there seems no way out,
He’ll be there, always by our side.
He will be our guide, never doubt;
No, just stop, think, and pray.
Make Jehovah smile.
Let him show the way.
Ev’ry day will have troubles to share.
There are bills to be paid
with no money to spare.
Even so, we’ll be happy in giving
If we can make someone smile—
Make someone smile.
Never doubt; never fear.
Put your trust in Jehovah.
And our road will be clear
If we stop, think, and pray.
When we’re weak, we are strong.
And we’ll see he was by our side.
He has been our guide all along.
Always stop, think, and pray.
Make Jehovah smile.
Let him show the way.
Put your trust in Jehovah.
And our road will be clear
If we stop, think, and pray.
When we’re weak, we are strong.
And we’ll see he was by our side.
He has been our guide all along.
Always stop, think, and pray.
Make Jehovah smile.
Thank him ev’ry day.
Jehovah will always bless us
when we go to him
in prayer with our concerns.
Whatever the situation,
he can give us
“the power beyond what is normal.”
And as we learned
and practiced in this program,
we do our part by training
our “power of reason”
with the principles
from his written Word.
Finally,
we have greetings
from the Vesterålen islands,
in Norway.
These islands are home to 30,000 people
who enjoy the beautiful fjords, mountains,
and calm beaches.
The 53 publishers
in the Sortland Norwegian Congregation
preach in a territory that covers
1,800 square kilometers,
or 695 square miles.
Their thorough witnessing takes them
into the beautiful countryside,
as well as to the city of Sortland
for metropolitan public witnessing.
Each year, they organize trips
to unassigned territory,
where they often meet people
who show deep respect for the Bible.
One Saturday each month,
after the ministry,
they gather to watch
the JW Broadcasting program
and enjoy spending time together.
Progressive Bible studies
and a Russian group
join them each week
at their meetings.
We send our love
and greetings
and thank them
for their Christian love
and example of faith.
Thank you for watching.
From the world headquarters
of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
this is JW Broadcasting!