The theme for this month is
“In Whom Do You Trust?”
Do you trust me?
I hope so.
All of us want to be trusted.
Trust is a basic element of everyday life.
To trust others is a normal reaction.
Many of us have traveled on a train or a bus.
Did we worry whether
the conductor or driver
would bring us safely to our destination?
Normally, we do not worry.
We trust an airplane captain
to take us safely to our destination.
We trust that when we enter an elevator,
it will not crash at the bottom of the shaft,
but safely take us to the desired floor.
When we marry, we trust that
our partner will remain faithful.
In many situations in life we need trust.
What is trust?
Trust is the “firm belief in the reliability,
truth, or ability of someone or something.”
Webster’s dictionary says
that it is “confidence”;
a “reliance [or] resting
of the mind on the integrity,
“veracity, justice, friendship,
or other sound principle, of another person.”
Trust is related to confidence,
belief, faith, and assurance.
Experiments conducted
by Professor Dr. Michael Kosfeld,
a professor at a university
in Frankfurt, Germany,
led him to the conclusion that trust
is “a biologically-based part
of human nature.”
Kosfeld discovered that when there is
interaction between two people,
the human brain releases
a hormone that stimulates trust.
“It is, in fact,
one of the distinguishing features
of the human species,” Kosfeld states.
In everyday life, how discouraged
some are if they are not trusted.
The phrase “Don’t you trust me?”
is frequently heard with an undertone
of sadness or complaint.
Sometimes children or teenagers
ask their parents
“Don’t you trust me?” when the parents
place some restrictions on them,
perhaps in connection
with leisure-time activities.
Parents do that because they
love you young ones
and want to prevent any spiritual
or physical harm befalling you.
If you cooperate, you will see that parents
will gradually trust you ever more
and grant more liberty to you.
You can prove to them
that you are trustworthy.
In the world,
many people are not trustworthy.
Since we are living in the time of the end
and the demons are desperate
and have influenced many people,
we have to admit that
trusting in everybody is not wise.
Many trusted in religion
and were disappointed.
Others trusted in governments
or the United Nations,
but they were disappointed.
They trusted political leaders
that made all kinds of promises
but did not keep all of them.
Some politicians were
even exposed as being liars.
Proverbs 14:15 says:
“The naive person believes every word,
but the shrewd one ponders each step.”
If somebody, even in the truth,
promises us big monetary returns
if we give him money
for his planned investment,
we need to be careful
and not believe every word.
Some that spent their money
were in for a disappointment
when they learned that everything was lost.
We also should not trust everything we read
in newspapers or see on television.
There is another thing
we should not trust in—riches.
Psalm 49:6 speaks
about “those who are trusting in their wealth
and who boast about their great riches.”
Trusting in riches
often leads to disappointment.
“The one trusting in his riches will fall,”
says Proverbs 11:28.
It is not wrong to be rich;
just do not trust in riches.
Riches are a risk factor.
Many people today are dishonest and cheat.
Some business owners have installed
cameras at the workplace,
since they do not trust their employees
to put in a full day of work.
They know that some would play
video games during work hours.
But Jehovah created us
with the inclination to trust.
We can especially trust
our spiritual brothers.
True, once in a while
such trust is misplaced.
A few commit serious sins
and have to be disfellowshipped.
But that is rare.
Jehovah himself is
the best example of trusting in others.
He trusted the Logos to faithfully cooperate
with him as the “master worker”
in creating the universe,
the earth, and all the living things
on earth, including mankind.
What tremendous trust Jehovah showed
in Jesus when He sent him to the earth.
Jehovah trusted that
Jesus would remain faithful
and redeem mankind
so that His will and purpose with mankind
and the earth could be accomplished.
Jehovah trusted him so much
that he arranged for prophecies
to be written that foretold
that he would die faithfully.
This trust on the part of Jehovah
was not a risk.
It was based on the collaboration
between the two for aeons of time.
Think of the prophecy at Psalm 16:10:
“For you will not leave me in the Grave.”
Jesus had free will.
This means that theoretically
he could have sinned.
If he could not have sinned,
Satan probably would not have tried
three times to tempt Jesus to sin.
If Jesus could not have sinned,
why would he be so heavily distressed
in the garden of Gethsemane
that he was sweating blood?
Why send an angel
to comfort and strengthen him
if he could not sin or fail anyway?
No question that Jesus
felt the unfathomable load
on his shoulders to remain faithful,
since not only the salvation
of mankind depended on him
but also the vindication
of Jehovah’s sovereignty.
He did not want to disappoint Jehovah.
Jesus used his own free will
and was determined to stay loyal.
How glad we are that he did!
On the other hand,
Jesus also trusted Jehovah completely.
He trusted Jehovah that he would
resurrect him if he would die faithfully.
Actually, Jesus was publicly known
to trust in Jehovah.
People that passed by when he was
on the torture stake were saying:
“He has put his trust in God;
“let Him now rescue him if He wants him,
for he said, ‘I am God’s Son.’”
Another example of trust was Abraham.
When God told him
to kill his beloved son Isaac,
Abraham was willing to do so.
He trusted that Jehovah could resurrect him.
Hebrews 11:19 says:
“He reasoned that God was able to raise
him up even from the dead,
and he did receive him from there
in an illustrative way.”
First Corinthians 13:7 says that
love “believes all things.”
Love trusts that prophecies will come true.
It also believes what our brothers tell us.
It also helps to grant others
the benefit of the doubt
if a matter could be interpreted
in different ways.
Yes, trusting others
is an expression of love.
If you love somebody, you only assume
and think the best of him.
Another example of trust
in Jehovah was Moses.
He led the nation of Israel
out of Egypt into the desert
—a nation upwards of three million people.
And they had flocks
of cattle and sheep with them.
When he left Egypt,
did he know how to provide
these great crowds with water in the desert?
Did he know what they would be eating
after the initial foodstuffs
that they took out of Egypt ran out?
Did he know in advance that Jehovah
would miraculously provide the manna?
It doesn’t seem so.
But he trusted that Jehovah
would take care of the people.
The three friends of Daniel
were another fine example of trust.
They did not bow and worship
in front of an idol
that King Nebuchadnezzar had set up.
They were told they would be thrown
into a fiery furnace if they disobeyed.
They remained firm
and were protected by an angel,
so that the fire did not do any harm to them.
After that
“Nebuchadnezzar then declared:
“‘Praised be the God of Shadrach,
Meshach, and Abednego,
“‘who sent his angel
and rescued his servants.
“‘They trusted in him and went against
the command of the king
“‘and were willing to die rather than serve
or worship any god except their own God.’”
As we are getting ever closer
to the great tribulation,
we might be confronted with scary challenges
and tests related to nationalism.
Will we keep trusting Jehovah?
We trust we will.
Jehovah will miraculously save his
people throughout the great tribulation
and arrange for their survival.
Today, the faithful slave is put in charge
of providing spiritual food for God’s people,
who number into the millions.
The slave also shows
complete trust in Jehovah
that he will guide them with his holy spirit.
What makes it possible
for the “faithful and discreet slave”
to provide precious spiritual food?
“I will give you insight and instruct you
in the way you should go,”
says Jehovah at Psalm 32:8.
Today, Jehovah provides direction
to the slave through Jesus.
Jesus, in turn,
provides direction for his people
through “the faithful and discreet slave.”
We can therefore have full confidence
in the Scriptural insight,
understanding, and guidance.
Satan tries to sow mistrust.
Under Communist dictatorship in Romania,
secret police officers
forced a responsible brother
to walk with them
on a heavily frequented street
hoping that other brothers would see this
and wrongly conclude that this brother
works with the secret police.
Did the scheme work out?
No, it failed.
Brothers did see him but kept trusting him.
We learn that we should not quickly
lose trust in our brothers.
Satan also has the scheme
to spread rumors about faithful brothers,
including the faithful slave.
The method of spreading rumors is not new.
When Jesus was resurrected
and the tomb was empty,
the soldiers who reported it
were told to spread the rumor
that the disciples came
and stole the body at night.
Matthew 28:15 relates:
“So they took the silver pieces
and did as they were instructed,
and this story has been spread abroad
among the Jews up to this very day.”
Another rumor in the first century
was that Christians
were responsible for the great fire of Rome.
Could such an accusation be true?
Historians say that it was Nero,
the emperor, who set fire to the city.
Today, rumors are occasionally being spread
in electronic form about the faithful slave.
This has caused some concern
on the part of some brothers,
especially when the reports
are commenting on court cases
where some in the organization were accused.
Sometimes reference is made to certain quotes
and then readers think,
‘How can a quote be a rumor?’
A quote can be taken out of context.
Critical reports often
give only part of a matter
and leave out other aspects.
Often, such rumors play on the emotions.
Ask yourself: ‘Am I prone to believe rumors?
‘And even if I am, should I spread it
‘and undermine the trust
that others have in the slave
or in representatives of the branch office?’
Avoid sensationalism
by not saying something like
“Can you believe what I heard
about this matter or that matter
or this person or that person?”
referring to a statement
that may have appeared
on Facebook, YouTube, or Twitter.
The spread of rumors is like wildfire
that is hard to control.
It spreads distrust
and can undermine someone’s faith.
This is not to say that the slave is perfect
and never makes mistakes.
But Jehovah and Jesus
trust the imperfect slave
who cares for things
to the best of his ability
and with the best of motives.
Shouldn’t we then trust
the imperfect slave as well?
To appreciate the extent of Jehovah
and Jesus’ trust in the faithful slave,
reflect on what he has promised its members.
He has promised them
immortality and incorruption.
Soon, just before Armageddon,
the remaining members of the slave
will be taken to heaven.
Since 1919 of our Common Era,
the slave has been put in charge
of some belongings of Christ.
According to Matthew 24:47,
when the anointed are taken to heaven,
Jesus will at that point entrust
“all his belongings” to them.
Does this not reveal immense trust?
Revelation 4:4 describes
these resurrected anointed
as corulers with Christ.
Revelation 22:5 says they will rule,
not only for a thousand years
but “forever and ever.”
What immense trust
Jesus shows toward them!
Since Jehovah God and Jesus Christ
completely trust
“the faithful and discreet slave,”
should we not do the same?
Many servants of Jehovah in the past
showed trust in Jehovah
when confronted with obstacles or opposition.
We can trust that Jehovah will not let us
be tested beyond what we can bear
but will provide a “way out”
so we can remain faithful under trials.
So whom do you trust?
You fully trust in Jehovah,
Jesus, and the faithful slave.
To a reasonable degree, you also trust all
your fellow brothers and sisters.
The writer of Psalm 119:42
mentioned something else we need to trust in
—God’s Word.
He wrote:
“For I put my trust in your word.”
The prophecies in God’s Word
have always come true at the proper time.
Based on that, we can fully trust that
the remaining prophecies
pointing to the survival
of the great tribulation
and to the Paradise to follow
will also come true,
without the slightest possibility of failure.
Of course, we should trust
not only Jehovah, Jesus,
the faithful slave, and the Bible
but also our fellow brothers.
The apostle Paul is a fine example of this.
He wrote to Philemon
asking him to kindly receive back
the runaway slave Onesimus
who had become a brother.
Paul wrote at Philemon 21:
“I am confident that you will comply,
so I am writing you, knowing that you
will do even more than what I say.”
When we speak of trust,
we sometimes think of a little child
walking hand in hand with his father.
The child does not question
where the father will take him.
The child trusts the father.
All throughout the last days,
true Christians have faced hostility
of so many in the world.
How strengthening Jehovah’s promise is
in view of the impending attack
by Satan’s hordes!
When they attack, Jehovah’s people
will seem as defenseless.
But we do not need to quake with fear.
We trust that Jehovah, Jesus, and the angels
will fight to deliver us.
We will not shrink back in fear.
At Hebrews 10:39, Paul wrote:
“Now we are not the sort
who shrink back to destruction,
but the sort who have faith
for the preserving of our lives.”
Today and after Armageddon, all can say,
according to Psalm 26:1 and 52:8:
“I have trusted [in Jehovah]
without wavering.”
“My trust is in God’s loyal love,
forever and ever.”
Therefore, keep trusting in Jehovah
and those who are proving loyal to him.