Have you ever made a bad decision?
Maybe a better question would be,
Do you remember
the last bad decision that you made?
Most of our decisions
don’t impact our lives greatly.
A young brother
mentioned to me some time ago
when he looked at my tie,
“You have some work to do, Brother Hyatt.”
Well, maybe that was a bad decision.
But some decisions
impact our sacred service
and our relationship with Jehovah,
and that’s highlighted in today’s text.
When viewed in their context,
we quickly discern
that the words of today’s text
were not given as commendation
or even as reassurance
but were given
in the context of corrective counsel.
Now, who was being counseled?
King Asa,
the great-great-grandson of King David,
the third king of the kingdom of Judah.
He ruled for 41 years,
and he has the distinction of being known
as one of the faithful kings of Judah.
So with that in mind,
the question arises,
Why would a faithful king
need corrective counsel?
To answer the question,
let’s turn in our Bibles
to 2 Chronicles 16:7:
“At that time Hanani the seer
“came to King Asa of Judah
and said to him:
“‘Because you relied on the king of Syria
and did not rely on Jehovah your God,’”
so there was the bottom line
—the root of the problem,
“‘the army of the king of Syria
has escaped out of your hand.’”
And then Hanani reminds Asa
of an earlier event.
He asks:
“Were not the Ethiopians and the Libyans
“a very great army
with many chariots and horsemen?
“But because you relied on Jehovah,
he gave them into your hand.”
Well, sometime earlier,
Asa and the nation of Judah
were confronted
by Zerah the Ethiopian
and 1,000,000 troops.
How did Asa handle that crisis?
Well, he humbly prayed to Jehovah
and put himself and the nation
in Jehovah’s hands.
And Jehovah was favorably impressed
with that approach,
and he gave Judah the victory.
Now, in this case,
when King Baasha came against Judah,
rather than relying on Jehovah,
Asa bribed Ben-hadad.
So it was Baasha who came from Israel.
He bribed King Ben-hadad,
and it seemed to be successful.
Ben-hadad came against Baasha;
Baasha withdrew from Judah.
All was well
—except that Jehovah wasn’t pleased.
Asa left Jehovah out of the equation.
So with that in mind,
in verse 9 we have the counsel, don’t we?
“For the eyes of Jehovah
are roving about through all the earth
“to show his strength in behalf of those
“whose heart is complete toward him.
“You have acted foolishly in this matter;
from now on there will be wars against you.”
So there was the reminder and the counsel.
Why when confronted with 1,000,000
did Asa depend on Jehovah?
But when confronted by King Baasha of Israel,
he depended on himself.
Isn’t it true that when we face a situation
—a problem—
and a decision must be made
but the situation
is so much bigger than we are,
we turn to Jehovah
and we beg for his help
and for solace
and comfort and direction?
It may be a catastrophic illness
that we know isn’t going
to be resolved in this system.
It could be the death
of someone close to us.
Or perhaps a family member
or close friend is disfellowshipped.
We have no control over the situation,
and we lean on Jehovah.
But other decisions may seem
to be more within our grasp
—for example,
the selection of a marriage mate
or the choice of a career.
Maybe we came to work here.
And to help with construction,
we might have sold
our home and cut our ties.
And now a project is nearing completion,
and we have to make decisions.
Will we go back to where we came from?
We weren’t pioneering before we came.
But now after spending
some time here at Bethel,
we’re thinking about spiritual goals.
Can we pioneer?
Should we stay in this country?
Is it possible
we could move to another country?
If we’re not careful
as we make these decisions,
we could leave Jehovah
out of the equation.
So here’s a question,
How do we include Jehovah in the equation?
Well, there are three things that we can do.
The first is research.
What does Jehovah tell us in his Word
that has application
to the situation we’re facing?
What has “the faithful and discreet slave”
told us in the publications?
Has there been an article or some direction
that would be helpful to us?
A second ingredient is that of prayer,
talking with Jehovah
about the decision that we’re making.
And keeping in mind that we don’t expect
Jehovah to do our thinking for us,
but he will help us and direct us
so that we can make a good decision.
And finally,
here in the Bethel setting
and in the congregations,
we have a wealth
of experienced, faithful brothers and sisters
who would be more than happy
to help us benefit
from their experience in life.
So if we do these three things
—our research, prayer,
and talk with experienced, faithful ones—
then we can make a good decision.
Now, here’s the question,
What is a good decision?
Wouldn’t you agree
that ultimately a good decision
is one that Jehovah can bless?
And often we have a number of options,
and it’s not necessarily a question
of making a wrong or right decision
—but what decision.
What can we do that will enhance
our relationship with Jehovah
and give him something to bless?
Now, there’s one other point in the account
that can be very encouraging to us.
If you look back at 2 Chronicles 15
and the “b” portion of verse 17.
It says:
“Nevertheless, Asa’s heart
was complete all his life.”
That’s interesting, isn’t it?
Now, in our text for today,
we’re told that Jehovah is searching
for “those whose heart
is complete toward him.”
Ultimately, Jehovah viewed Asa
as one “whose heart [was] complete.”
It’s comforting to know
that Jehovah did not measure the man
because of one faulty decision;
He looked at the whole picture.
And evidently, Asa’s good qualities
and his zeal for pure worship
outweighed the bad decision
that he made in this case.
So when we make bad decisions
—and we will from time to time—
then we take comfort in knowing
that Jehovah will continue
to work with us.
And ultimately, what we want
is for Jehovah
to look at each of us and to say,
“His or her heart is complete with me.”