This month I’d like to talk about the efforts
Jehovah’s organization is making
to produce literature, publications,
articles that are as accurate as possible.
We’re going to talk about accuracy
—accuracy of statement.
Now, first, what’s the responsibility
of the writer of the article?
When a writer submits
an article for publication,
he is expected to supply references
from reputable sources
to back up the facts
that he’s included in his article.
And our Research Department
will use those references
to check the accuracy of everything.
Reliable, respected sources.
What do we mean by a reliable source?
Well, first of all, we go with encyclopedias,
books, magazines, and then newspapers
—basically in that order.
We prefer encyclopedias over books,
books over magazines,
and magazines over newspapers
—generally because newspaper editors
have a hard time checking their facts.
They have a very limited time
in which to check their facts.
Even encyclopedias and books get updated,
so we have to go
with the latest edition of those.
We have to make sure
that our sources are reliable.
Now, when a writer quotes an expert,
our researchers will ask:
“Who’s this expert?
“What’s his reputation?
“Is he working for a particular organization?
“Does this organization have an agenda?
Is it a special-interest group?”
If we find that the goals
of the organization are questionable,
we won’t use the quote
—even if it’s a really good quote.
Now, suppose that a writer
wants to quote something from a book.
In the reference material,
he’ll supply a photocopy
of the quote in the book,
but very often he’ll give us
two or three pages before the quote
and two or three pages after as well.
And that way,
our researchers can examine the quote
in context to make sure
that what we’re saying in print
is really what the author
of the quote had in mind.
For example,
an evolutionist might make a statement
which on the surface
appears to confirm his support of creation.
Or perhaps an atheist will make a statement
that seems to indicate
that he believes in God.
But when you examine
the quote in context,
you realize that that isn’t what
the author had in mind at all.
We would never
deliberately distort a quotation.
We try very hard to use all
of our quotations in context.
Now, it’s important to keep up
with the very latest research.
Something that was stated years ago
as a fact may have been disproved.
And the reason why is obvious.
Someone may spend his entire life
researching a very limited point in history
—a very small point in history—
and, of course,
if he spends so much time researching,
he’s going to uncover things.
And so it’s not surprising
that from time to time
we have to adjust our view
of some historical points.
We have to check, check, check.
And later on in this discussion,
we’re going to consider some examples of it.
It’ll be fun; you’ll love it!
Now, someone might ask,
‘Why is it necessary to be so picky,
to be so fussy, about accuracy?’
And in answer,
I’d like to give an experience
that I heard about a few years ago.
In Northern Europe,
there was a man
who accepted a Bible study
from Jehovah’s Witnesses.
And when he was asked
what motivated him
to want to study, he said:
“I read an article
in your Awake! magazine on trees.
“Now, I happen to be
a bit of an expert on trees.
“And after I read the article,
I said to myself:
“‘That article was so well-documented.
“‘It was so precise.
“‘Any organization that is that careful
when writing about trees
is going to be just as careful
when teaching me the Bible.’”
And on that basis,
he accepted a Bible study.
Now, an area where great care
needs to be taken
is when we’re quoting statistics.
A newspaper may report on a disaster
in a certain country
and say that 10,000 people
were killed in the disaster.
Immediately,
our researchers are going to ask,
“Where did they get that statistic?”
They might phone the newspaper
and ask for the source.
And if the reporter
can’t confirm the statistic,
our researchers will go to another source
—a more official source—
to get the correct statistic.
Care is also taken
when quoting personalities of the past.
Now, suppose we want to quote
something that Napoleon Bonaparte said
—the French general.
Well, being French,
Napoleon spoke French.
So if we’re quoting it in English,
that means that somebody translated
the quote from French into English.
But did they translate the quote correctly?
Our researchers will probably go
to the target language
and research the quote
in French or in another language.
And more often than not,
they find that what is presented in English
doesn’t accurately represent
what the individual said at all.
Now, as we age,
our memory can play tricks on us.
And our researchers are aware of that.
Suppose that an elderly brother
writes in his life story
that he was baptized
at a circuit assembly on a certain date.
Our researchers may look at the date.
They may check the date,
and suppose they find that the date
the brother gave fell on a Tuesday.
Now, what are the chances that there was
a circuit assembly on a Tuesday?
There may have been,
but they’re going to check.
Is the brother’s memory failing him?
If they can’t confirm the date,
they may ask someone to help the brother
to remember the date
more correctly, more accurately.
Perhaps someone was baptized
at the same circuit assembly as he was,
and perhaps that person
has an accurate note of the date.
Our translators also go to great lengths
to present accurate information
to the brothers and sisters.
Some time ago,
the Awake! magazine published an article
on a very rare species of butterfly.
Now, with all animals and insects,
we provide our translators
with the Latin name
of the animal or the insect.
And so our translators had the Latin name.
But in one large country,
they were unable to find
the name in the vernacular.
So, what did they do?
They phoned the country’s leading university,
and they were transferred
to the Biology Department,
and there an expert gave them
the name in the vernacular
of that particular butterfly.
But then he said:
“Why is it that you’re worrying so much
“about the correct name of this butterfly?
“If you got it wrong,
there are only two of us
in the whole country
who would’ve known the difference.”
Well, that opened the way
to give a witness to this expert.
Well, now, how well would you do
in spotting a statement that is slightly off
and making it more accurate?
Would you like to find out?
Of course you would!
It’ll be fun.
So let’s take a quiz that I’ll call
You Be the Editor.
We’re going to put
a number of statements on the screen,
and there’s a problem
with each one of them.
Now your job
is to figure out what’s wrong,
why it is wrong,
and then suggest how to fix it.
It’s going to be fun.
Here’s the first statement:
“According
to the Smithsonian Knowledge Encyclopedia,
“the Egyptian Sphinx
was constructed around 2550 B.C.E.”
“The Egyptian Sphinx
Well, the problem
is with the date 2550 B.C.E.
The global Flood occurred
about 200 years after that date.
So, what are the chances
that the Sphinx survived the Flood?
Unless, of course, you think
that’s how the Sphinx lost his nose.
Now, these dates
are good for you school children
to keep in mind
when you’re writing reports.
Sometimes you copy something
from an encyclopedia,
and it gives a certain date.
But think about the date of the Flood,
2370 B.C.E.,
so that what you put in your report
is as accurate as possible.
Now let’s go on to the next one:
“In 29 C.E.,
“Jesus was baptized by a close relative,
John the Baptizer.”
Well, 29 C.E., that looks right.
And we know that Jesus
was baptized by John; that’s right.
So the problem must be
“close relative,” and it is.
Now, both of Jesus’ parents
were of the tribe of Judah,
and their parents were of the tribe of Judah.
But, what about John’s parents,
Zechariah and Elizabeth?
They were both of the tribe of Levi.
So Elizabeth and Mary
couldn’t have been sisters.
Could they have been cousins?
Maybe.
We can’t even confirm that.
And if they were, that would make
Jesus and John second cousins.
Well, is a second cousin a “close relative”?
Some would say yes;
some would say no.
So it’s safer just to say,
“In 29 C.E.,
Jesus was baptized by a relative,
John the Baptizer.”
Here’s one.
Let’s see if you can spot
the error in this one:
“While most of the early Christians
“were held in little esteem in the community,
“a few enjoyed an elevated social status.
For example, Luke was a respected physician.”
Well, the word we need
to look at is “respected.”
We respect our doctors today,
and our doctors have
a very, very fine education.
But was that the case in the first century?
A reference work says this
about first-century physicians:
“Many doctors were freed Greek slaves,
“hence the social standing
of doctors was quite low.
“Because recovery rates were so low,
many people were skeptical
or even scornful of doctors.”
Note this statement from the first century:
“Until recently, Diaulus was a doctor;
“now he is an undertaker.
“He is still doing as an undertaker,
what he used to do as a doctor.”
Not very flattering, is it?
Well, in this case, we’d probably have to use
a different example.
Here’s one:
“In 325 C.E.,
“the Roman Emperor Constantine
“established Christianity
“as the official religion
of the Roman Empire.”
Well, 325 C.E., that looks right.
And Constantine, that looks right.
But look at the word “official”
—“official religion.”
Constantine never established Christianity
as the official religion
of the Roman Empire.
In 313 B.C.E.,
he did make it legal to be a Christian,
but paganism was still
one of the official religions.
Apostate Christianity
didn’t become the official religion
until 391 C.E.
This one is tricky.
See how you do with this one:
“Imagine the apostle Paul
“during his first imprisonment in Rome,
“writing his letter to the Colossians
from a dark prison cell.”
Well, if you look in the back
of the New World Translation,
you’ll find that Paul did write his letter
to the Colossians while in Rome,
and he was imprisoned at the time.
So, what’s the problem?
“Dark prison cell.”
Where was Paul
during his first imprisonment?
In his own rented house.
So the statement “dark prison cell,”
it’s very dramatic, but it’s all wrong.
Here’s an old one:
“While Paul generally preached
“to people of the nations,
“Peter was sent to the Jews.
“Contrary to popular belief,
Peter was never in Rome.”
Some scholars used to make that statement,
and they made it 60 years ago:
“Peter was never in Rome.”
But can we really say that?
Can we be that dogmatic?
Can we say that he didn’t even spend
vacation time or have a short visit in Rome?
No, we cannot.
So it would be more accurate to state:
“There is no record
that Peter ever lived in Rome.”
Here’s one:
“We can have confidence in the Bible
—it is mankind’s oldest book.”
“Mankind’s oldest book.”
Years ago, some scholars believed
that texts written
by Adam, Noah, and others
survived the Flood
and became part of the Bible.
And if that were true,
then we could say that the Bible
is mankind’s oldest book.
Now, here’s a quote
from Insight on the Scriptures,
our Bible encyclopedia.
It says:
“There is no way to establish definitely
“that some of the histories
mentioned in the book of Genesis
were committed to writing
before the Flood.”
So, today we might call the Bible
one of mankind’s oldest books
or the world’s oldest modern book,
as we do in one of our videos.
Here’s the last one:
“In 1517,
“Martin Luther nailed his 95 theses
on the door of a church
in Wittenberg, Germany.”
Well, we’ve highlighted “95,”
but there are questions
about the entire statement.
Some modern scholars have done
a tremendous, exhaustive study
of the life of Martin Luther,
and they claim
that he couldn’t have compiled
all 95 of his theses by 1517.
Others go so far as to claim
that it never happened
—that he never did nail his theses
on the door of the church.
Still others are just as adamant
that it’s all true
—that it all happened.
So there’s no consensus.
We would have to modify the statement
—“some believe” or “it is believed”—
in order to make it more accurate
and to acknowledge the fact
that there are differences of opinion.
Well, how did you do on the quiz?
If you’re like me, you’ve probably made
some of those statements yourself at times.
The statements were based
on the best research we had at the time.
But this is to illustrate
the fact that times change;
research facilities improve.
A scholar does exhaustive research
on one point of history,
and he uncovers things
that were previously unknown.
So we have to keep up.
We have to check, check, check.
And when credible research
reveals that we have to adjust
or tweak a statement
that we made in the past,
we do so without hesitation.
Our goal is to provide information
that is as accurate as possible
because we know that you
brothers and sisters use this information.
You quote it in the field ministry.
You use it in your public talks.
So we want to make sure
that our brothers are fed
with the most accurate
spiritual food possible.
We’re imperfect, of course,
and we are going to make mistakes.
And when we do,
we have to correct them.
Our goal is to do the best we can
in all our imperfection.
Well, how does it make you feel?
I know how it makes me feel.
I’m grateful that Jehovah’s organization
takes accuracy so seriously.
It gives me confidence.
And, you know, I’m reminded
of the description of another researcher,
as recorded at Ecclesiastes 12:9, 10.
You know who this is.
Ecclesiastes 12:9, 10:
“Not only had the congregator become wise
“but he continually taught
the people what he knew,
“and he pondered
“and made a thorough search
“in order to compile many proverbs.
“The congregator sought
to find delightful words
and to record accurate words of truth.”