A discussion of riches
often centers on the danger
of making material wealth
the main thing in our life.
Our text today is about riches,
but the focus is on how we use
the things that we possess.
Let’s go back to our text at Luke 16:9
and read it once again.
It says:
“Also, I say to you:
“Make friends for yourselves
by means of the unrighteous riches,
“so that when such fail,
they may receive you
into the everlasting dwelling places.”
There are certain aspects of this text
that some have found difficult to understand.
For example,
why would a Christian even be in possession
of unrighteous riches?
Who are referred to by the pronoun “they”?
Also, what application
is there in this illustration for us?
To clarify matters,
it will help us to look at the context.
Verses 1 through 8
of Luke chapter 16
contain the illustration
of the steward and the unrighteous riches.
Verses 9 to 13
provide the application of the illustration.
And that application includes the principles
that ‘the person faithful in least
is faithful in much’
and also that we “cannot slave for God
and for Riches.”
To learn how we can benefit
from this teaching of Jesus,
let’s consider three things.
First of all,
we will examine the illustration.
Second, we will identify the elements.
And third, we’ll make the application.
So first of all,
let’s examine the illustration.
If we look at Luke 16:1,
it talks about a steward.
If we look at the footnote,
it says this could be a “house manager.”
So it is someone who’s entrusted
with a good deal of responsibility.
But it says that he is accused
of handling his master’s “goods wastefully.”
Now, the wording of that verse
allows for the possibility
that the steward was slandered.
It’s possible the charges were false.
But Jesus doesn’t focus
on the reason for the steward’s dismissal.
Rather,
he gives attention
to the steward’s reaction.
Verses 2 through 7
show us the reasoning of the steward
(knowing that he’s going to be fired).
He says:
‘I’m not strong enough to dig.
‘I’m ashamed to beg.
So how am I going to make a living?’
So he decides to befriend ones
who owe things to his master.
One debtor owes 100 measures of olive oil,
so the steward reduces that debt
to 50 measures.
That’s a reduction
of nearly 300 (1,100 L) gallons of olive oil.
Another debtor owes his master
100 large measures of wheat.
He reduces that to 80.
That’s a reduction
of 4,000 (3,700 L) quarts of wheat.
That’s a substantial reduction in the debt.
Then if we look at verse 8,
the master,
on finding out what the steward has done,
calls him “unrighteous,”
and yet he commends him
for acting “with practical wisdom.”
So here Jesus is not condoning
or endorsing the steward’s methods,
nor is he encouraging
crafty business practices.
Jesus simply draws attention
to the need to be farsighted
and to use practical wisdom.
Now let’s identify the elements.
We come to our text, verse 9,
where it tells us
to ‘use our unrighteous riches
to make friends.’
Jesus doesn’t explain in detail
why he refers to the riches as unrighteous.
However, the New International Version
gives us a hint
when it calls the unrighteous riches
“worldly wealth.”
In other words,
the unrighteous riches
represent material resources
under the control of sinful humans.
Riches often serve selfish ends,
and they may be gained
through crafty or even illegal
business practices.
Then Jesus states a reality.
He says “when such fail.”
Yes, the value of material wealth is limited,
and it’s temporary.
It can be eaten away by inflation.
Consider the value
of one U.S. dollar 50 years ago.
If you had 100 dollars (U.S.) in 1969,
you would need 692 dollars today
to have the same purchasing power.
In 1969,
a gallon (4 L) of gas cost 32 cents.
A loaf of bread cost 23 cents.
Yes, riches fail.
And they will definitely fail in the future.
Zephaniah 1:18 says:
“Neither their silver nor their gold
will be able to save them
in the day of Jehovah’s fury.”
During the great tribulation,
we’re not going to be judged
based on the size of our bank account.
Rather, we’re going to be judged
based on our storehouse of spiritual riches
that we have accumulated.
And that leads to the meaning
of the latter part of verse 9;
it says that “they may receive you
into the everlasting dwelling places.”
What or who
is referred to by the word “they”?
Is it the riches?
Certainly not.
They’re temporary; they’re going to fail.
We have to go back to earlier in the verse
to find the antecedent.
And it is the word “friends.”
So who are these friends?
Please open your Bibles to John 3:16.
There are
only two possibilities of individuals
who can give us
everlasting dwelling places,
and they’re identified here in this verse.
John 3:16—it says:
“For God loved the world so much
“that he gave his only-begotten Son,
“so that everyone exercising faith in him
“might not be destroyed
but have everlasting life.”
Yes, only God, Jehovah,
and his Son, Jesus Christ,
can usher us
into everlasting dwelling places,
whether that be the heavenly Kingdom
or the Paradise earth.
Now, let’s make application
of this illustration.
How do we use
the material things of this world
to make friends with Jehovah and Jesus?
Everything we own actually belongs to them.
However, each one of us
has a measure of money and material assets
that we are free to use as we please.
So to make friends with Jehovah and Jesus,
we have to use those things in a way
that brings their approval.
Our contributions
don’t have to be in the form of cash.
In Jesus’ illustration,
the debt was olive oil and wheat.
The unrighteous riches
might even be coconuts.
A brother in southern India
owns a coconut farm.
He contributed a large number of coconuts
to the local remote translation office.
He reasoned, “The office is going
to have to spend money and buy coconuts.”
So his supplying the coconuts directly
would help his contribution go further
than it would if he sold the coconuts
and gave the office the cash.
That is practical wisdom.
Now, if we go back to Luke chapter 16,
let’s look at verse 10.
Here it’s interesting that the principle
‘the person faithful in what is least
will be faithful in much’
was given in the context
of our use of material riches.
So we cannot take
this responsibility lightly.
Notice what it says in verse 11.
It says: “Therefore,
if you have not proved yourselves faithful
“in connection with the unrighteous riches,
who will entrust you with what is true?”
Yes, the way we use
our monetary riches or goods
will affect the extent
to which the things that are true,
such as Kingdom interests,
are entrusted to us.
Therefore,
let’s remember the key point
of Jesus’ illustration
of the unrighteous steward.
No matter how much or how little
of this world’s goods
we have under our control,
we want to use them
to strengthen our relationship
with our best Friends,
Jehovah and Jesus.